Belê temaşevanên me yên hêja, beşek me ya nû, jarek a dî
destpêkir.
Yes, our dear viewers, a new segment of ours has started
once again.
Îro jî em mêvanê gundê Keferdelê ne. Evder Keferdelê Jêrîn
e.
Today, we are guests of the village of Keferdelê. This is
Lower Keferdelê.
Emê îro mêvanê vî gundî bin.
We will be guests of this village today.
Yê ehlen û sehlen. Hatina we, ser serê me û ser çavê me.
Yes, welcome. Your arrival is upon our heads and upon our
eyes [you are very welcome].
Gund gundê we ye, bajar bajarê we ye. Em li viderê, em
viderê zeytûna dajon.
The village is your village, the city is your city. We are
here, we are cultivating olives here.
Me ajot, xelas kir şûnda, xizmetê xwestin, em çê derman
derman kin.
We plowed, after finishing, they needed care, we went to
treat [spray] them.
Me'ne we gopka, bajarê... bajarê zeytûna ye, ê zîraatê ye.
Meaning that bud [pest], the city... it is the city of
olives, of agriculture.
Zîraat çi dixwaze? Zîraat xidmê dixwaze.
What does agriculture require? Agriculture requires service.
Zîraat noka, me ajot, berî gopak b'peqe.
Agriculture now, we plowed, before the bud bursts.
Gopak peqî a, ortaq em qamişê nabin, hem derman tora li bin
naxin.
If the bud bursts, partner, we won't be able to catch up, we
won't put medicine under it.
Bira wê gopka b'peqe, emê derman kin, derb bikin, îşê derman
xalis... wê gopka ê rind b'peqe.
Let that bud burst, we will treat it, spray it, the medicine
work is finished... that bud will burst well.
Paşê, emê dermanî dil nêkin, ortaq bese.
Then, we won't do the internal medicine, partner, it's
enough.
Uuu... û viderê, vê erdê zeytûn in.
And... and here, this land is olives.
Kizbera me çandiye. Me hebelbereke çandî. Me kemûn çandine.
We planted coriander. We planted Nigella seeds. We planted
cumin.
Me colban çandine. Me genim çandî. Me ceh çandî. Yanê tiştê
hana.
We planted vetch. We planted wheat. We planted barley.
Things like that.
Erdê viderê bavê min, erdê viderê li cem me taq waye.
The land here, my dear, the land here with us, the water
layer is scarce.
Medîna ne serxê ne, taqa xetêj dışwe [diçe?].
The city isn't on the line, the line's capacity goes
[fails].
Em bi qeder imkan em pê dorka av didin. Zemanê berê kanî
hebûn.
We water it by turns as much as possible. In the old times,
there were springs.
Kanî hebûn. Av... av dherikî. Teqriben vî gundî...
There were springs. Water... water flowed. Approximately
this village...
vî gundî wekî, li deşta vî gundî wekî bîst kaniya hebû.
this village like, in the plain of this village there were
like twenty springs.
Kanî hebû, çavirçîmat têda hana dibû. U av tim pênc înç, şeş
înç dherikîn.
There were springs, watercress would be like that in it. And
water flowed constantly five inches, six inches.
Ev av bîrê viderê meselen bîst miter, bîst pênc miter av
derdikeve.
This water, the wells here, for example, twenty meters,
twenty-five meters, water comes out.
Avê xwa înç nîvek, înç rûbek... di te zêde daxî zêde av tê.
Its water is an inch and a half, an inch and a quarter... if
you go down deeper, more water comes.
Vî gunda berî giştika, mala... mala Resûl hatin.
Before everyone in this village, the house of... the house
of Resûl came.
Dû mala Resûl ra mala Mehmed Elî hatin. Dû mala Mehmed Elî
ra mala Kolo hatin.
After the house of Resûl, the house of Mehmed Elî came.
After the house of Mehmed Elî, the house of Kolo came.
Dû mala Kolo ra mala Xoce hatin. Yanê hana gund ortaq ava
bû.
After the house of Kolo, the house of Xoce came. Like that,
the village was established, partner.
Ehlen û sehlen bi hatina we. Ez Ebo Stêf e, ji Keferdelê
Jêrîn e.
Welcome to your arrival. I am Ebo Stêf, from Lower
Keferdelê.
Ewa li me viderê cot dajon.
Here we are plowing.
U heywanî ye jî, bes em kîja dabeş kin? Me'ne pez e.
And it is livestock too, but which one should we deal with?
Meaning sheep.
U ta'mê pêstena li ano. Bibîne sibê da pez berdan, tiştî
nêle.
And the hardship is there. Look, releasing the sheep in the
morning, leaving nothing.
Berê dewar gi pir bûn. Gi dewar bûn. Her malekê dewarok
hebû. Noka jî yek tune.
Before, the cattle were all many. All were cattle. Every
house had some cattle. Now, there isn't a single one.
Tu l'malê dermanekî bidî, dermanê wan nabînî. Wa gi direktor
in.
If you give a medicine at home, you won't find their
medicine. They are all tractors.
Direktorêkî sed şêst pênc kin noka merxûbe cem me. Şêst û
dudo, şêst û sê, çikî merxûbe.
A tractor of one hundred sixty-five is now popular with us.
Sixty-two, sixty-three, a bit popular.
Çikî Farsin cem me, kûk ne merxûbe.
The Ferguson ones with us, aren't very popular.
No, cot... cot tim cot e. Cot û tim ew cot e. Ferqê wî qet
tune, kûk tune.
No, plowing... plowing is always plowing. Plowing and it's
always that plowing. There is no difference at all, not
much.
U xura jî cem me erdê reş e, gi erdê reş e viderê.
And the soil with us is black earth, it's all black earth
here.
Yanê çiqas qiraç teht dar tune ne, kêm e. Teht cem me kêm e.
Pirranî gi deşt e, gi deşt e.
Meaning, there aren't many rocky cliffs or trees, it's
little. Rocks are scarce with us. The majority is all plain,
all plain.
No, cot viderê her wextê xwe heye. Her teqriben meha nîvekê,
du meha, gusnekî dajon. Biskok dajon.
No, plowing here has its own time. Every approximately month
and a half, two months, we plow a round. We plow a bit.
U cotî kelfetûra başqe ye, û cotê ewê kûta başqe ye. Her
tişt wextê xwe heye.
And plowing with the cultivator is different, and that
plowing of the stomp is different. Everything has its time.
Ê kûtê n'be berî giha dajon. Paşê jî bi kelfetûra. Deqa
govînê...
The stomp one isn't done, we plow before the grass. Then
with the cultivator. The moment of the manure...
Berî vê, virokî çol bû ye. Va sarta gi çol bû ye yanê berî
vê.
Before this, this place was wilderness. This whole area was
wilderness, meaning before this.
Hinek hatin, vekirin, wergo gotin kûk dî. Elem el kirin, erd
betûn gi den bûn.
Some came, opened it, like that they said... People worked
it by hand, the land became solid.
Zeytûn çandin. Yanê întar derxistin.
They planted olives. Meaning they brought out production.
Cîl kî din hat, ewa çû, wa cîlê, wa mûsim axa. Wana çandin,
xêr wan xwar.
Another generation came, that one went, that generation,
that season's Agha. They planted, they ate their bounty.
Wa vê gundê me noka, eina qebûl... belkî deh hejdeh malê
bîrê xwa tine bûn.
In this village of ours now, accepted... maybe ten, eighteen
houses didn't have wells.
Wekî din gund gi bîr... hewşê da kolana.
Otherwise, the village all wells... dug in the yard.
U avê xwa kûk nê vexwarin. Li vê tengera hanê here, bi bîst
mala heta tola gund, avê xwa hoda kûk nê vexwarin.
And its water isn't good to drink. Go to this narrow area
here, with twenty houses up to the end of the village, their
water there isn't good to drink.
Avê xwa kûk nê vexwarin. Kls... te'l heye, te'l.
Their water isn't good to drink. Lime... it has bitterness,
bitterness.
Te'l, Silêmanî av tê derdikeve. Kibrît yanê.
Bitter, Suleimani water comes out. Sulfur, meaning.
Hewa... hewa bû sebeb nexweşî jî li gund çêbû.
The air... the air was the reason sickness happened in the
village too.
Bîr noka hedîs li gund pir in. Toximê gund, alî xerbî, avê
xwa ekterî xwa nê vexwarin.
Modern wells are many in the village now. The seed of the
village, the west side, the majority don't drink their
water.
Va alî, her hoda çû, avê xwa şarintir dibe yanê, kilsê xwa
kêm e. Sihhiyen xweş e.
That side, however far it went, its water becomes sweeter
meaning, its lime is low. Health-wise it is good.
Xelîl zote, jimêj... jimêj lê dixê.
Khalil is a player, since long ago... since long ago he
plays it.
Rind alemî ye yanê Xelîl, hewcî derdikeve dewata.
He is well known meaning Khalil, needed, he goes out to
weddings.
Yanê, karê xwa wana heye, yanê karê wan heye.
Meaning, they have their work, meaning they have their work.
U welle Pîşo Melta mi lê dixistin. U dudu ra mi lê dixist.
Lawê min Xelîl, noka paşê...
And by God, Pîşo and Melta and I were playing. And with two
I was playing. My son Khalil, now later...
Alemê... pêşta hatim birayê delal.
The world... I have come forward [in time], dear brother.
Ew berê cîhaz û mîhaz tunebûn, di gund da def bû...
In the past, there were no devices and such, in the village
there was the drum...
Û zirne bû, hema...
And the zurna [horn], just...
E dinê noka, fennî xwa pir e.
But the world now, its technology is plentiful.
Fennî xwa zêde pêşda çûye.
Their technology has advanced too much.
Berê tim def bû û zirne bû, zêde ti nebu wekî din.
Before, it was always the drum and zurna, there wasn't much
else.
Şirîn bû? Na, na şirîn bû.
Was it sweet? No, it wasn't sweet.
Bes noka pêşta çûye.
But now it has advanced.
Na, ne wekî berê ye.
No, it is not like the past.
Li dawetê, kû bûn? Li derê bûn?
The weddings, where were they? Were they outdoors?
Dawet li derê bûn, bêder bûn, fira dor bûn.
Weddings were outdoors, on the threshing floors, they were
wide circles.
Milet gî kom dibû, heft rû, heyşt rû li defê dixistin.
The whole nation gathered, seven rows, eight rows danced to
the drum.
Bûk li espê dikirin.
They put the bride on a horse.
Weyniyek li serê şda pirç dikir.
Yes, yes.
She covered her head with a veil.
Berê bûk ji cilê espê dikirin.
In the past, they put the bride on the horse's saddle cloth.
Yanî du heywan... digerandin...
Meaning two animals... they walked them around...
Dur gund ra digerandin.
They walked them around the village.
Def bû, zirne bû, tiştê dîlan bû, qetê diçûne ev der.
It was drum, zurna, dance matters, they went all the way
over there.
E... yanî qeşmer şê dikirin.
Uh... meaning they performed clown acts [jokers].
Tiştê tewrê, heta lawik û zêbe va çêdikirin, qeşmer yanî...
Strange things, they even performed ballads and chants,
meaning clowns...
Pê dikenin.
They laughed at it.
Meşhûr Ayş bû, ê berê bûn.
Famous was Ayş, they were of the past.
Ayşo Îbê bû, Cebelî bû...
It was Ayşo Îbê, it was Cebelî...
Mem bû...
It was Mem...
Klamên te berê bûn.
Your songs were of the past.
Noka...
Now...
E... keça zer û keça sor heye?
Uh... is there the "blonde girl" and "red girl" [modern pop
lyrics]?
Elmuhim yanî ê berê, klamên giran bûn.
The important thing is... those of the past, the songs were
heavy [meaningful].
[Instrumental Music Playing]
Serê berê...
The beginning of the past...
Berê pirsgirêk... noka, gal malê... berê dar hebûn.
In the past, problems... now, lots of wealth... before there
were trees [feuds/strength].
Di darê sê darê me da... go darê we bikir.
In the tree, our three trees... said buy your tree [idiom
about strength/feuds].
Kefardelê jorîn begî bûn.
Upper Kefardel were Lords [Beys].
Malê Hemdo bûn. Darê wan bûn.
It was the House of Hemdo. It was their turn [power].
Ee, gundogî berê...
Uh, the villagers of the past...
Cîyê xwa gî, Kefardelê jêrîn, em gî fiqare bûn, ji gund
dernakevin, şivan û...
All their places, Lower Kefardel, we were all poor, not
leaving the village, shepherds and...
De li ber runiştinê.
Just sitting around.
Daweta berê...
The wedding of the past...
Yekî gundgî xelat bişanda, ew gund gî bûye xelatê tenê da...
If a villager sent a gift, that whole village became
involved in that single gift...
Her gundekî dikir ser malekê.
Every village was assigned to a household.
Heyro xwendina ê tenê.
Singing songs alone.
Sê roj, çar roj li defê dixistin.
Three days, four days they played the drum.
Heftan ki li defê dixistin.
Even a week they played the drum.
Bûk las pa dikirin.
They put the bride on the horse.
Hewa xwendina gî ser mêrikî da bûn, gî ser radibûn rûniştin.
The atmosphere of singing was all on the men, everyone stood
up and sat down based on it.
Û saha bû, fereh bû, çawir bû, çîman bû, der bû, wî bû
tûnî...
And it was joy, it was happiness, it was loud, it was
meadow, it was outside, it was distinct...
Em pirs dikin, yanî dibîsin, ez pir geriyame.
We ask, meaning we hear, I have traveled a lot.
Tirkiyê ra... de hevdah sala li Tirkiyê bûm. Yanî kuderê em
pirs dikin...
In Turkey... I was in Turkey for seventeen years. Meaning
wherever we ask...
Serekê klaman Mem e.
The leader of songs is Mem.
Memê Alan.
Mem and Zin [Memê Alan].
Yanî nîv saetkê...
Meaning for half an hour...
E dawetika cimeatê rûniştandina pê dana.
At a wedding, holding the seated gathering with it.
Dûra Dewrêşê Evdî bû.
Then it was Dewrêşê Evdî.
Ayş bû...
It was Ayş...
Cebelî bû...
It was Cebelî...
Mem bû...
It was Mem...
Oh klamên... klamên te berê bûn.
Oh songs... your songs were of the past.
Noka...
Now...
Keçê... keçê zer û keça sor heye?
Girls... is there the blonde girl and the red girl?
Elmuhim yanî noka ê berê... klamên giran bûn.
The important thing is, meaning now versus the past... the
songs were heavy.
Ê noka kesê wanan noka ti dîtin nîne.
Those of today, no one sees any substance in them now.
Yekî bê, du şoreja bike, tîne ye.
Someone comes, says two words, it's nothing.
Cemîl Horo rehmetî...
The late Cemîl Horo...
Rehme li miriyê we be, yanî berê însaniyetê ke bû.
Mercy on your dead, meaning in the past, humanity was
something.
Galkî... galkî bi hatin e... neba keda te nan nedixwar.
Much... much welcoming... if there wasn't your labor
[invitation], you didn't eat bread.
Yê noka belayê xwe re bêje tîne ye.
Those of today, tell them about their own troubles, it's
nothing.
Ihtiram... teqdir... kêm bûye.
Respect... appreciation... has decreased.
Ihtiramê berê pir bûn, ihtiramê berê pir bûn.
Respect in the past was great, respect in the past was
great.
Cem me berê Xelê... Xelûçka rehmetî, muxtarê gund bû.
With us before, Uncle... the late Xelûçka, he was the
village headman.
Mesûlkê gund bû. Xwedê rehma xalikê, rehma li miriyê we be
jî.
He was responsible for the village. God have mercy on the
uncle, mercy on your dead too.
Yanî... milet gî îdare dikir.
Meaning... he managed the whole people.
Dewrêk bahata pirs kira, go filan meriya kanî?
If a patrol came and asked, saying "where is this person?"
Bi xwîna xwe dikirî... ezim.
He would buy it with his blood... [saying] "I am him."
Mirov tulo... her sekel... kuderê bila were.
A person like that... every shape... wherever let it come.
[Instrumental Music Playing]