Teqriben geha, ne bes hinekî...
It almost arrived, no but a little...
Teqriben geha, ne bes hinekî kanê, lê bêjer nistina hewş û
vederê girtina, bes ew hewş nebû şixul wek din, giş liberin.
It almost arrived, no but [we needed] a bit more, say
regarding the courtyard sitting area and the closing of the
outside, but if not for that courtyard, the rest of the work
is all done.
Darê şkilarê tînin o vê?
Are they bringing the form wood over here?
Em jar pilotî ne, şkargulê tîne, ciqutol tîne, ni haseb.
We are poor/wretched, he brings [unintelligible], he brings
[unintelligible], it depends.
Kefê min jê ra hat lo.
I really liked it, man.
O fişek berda welleh.
He shot a bullet, by God.
Elîkum... Merheba...
[Salam] Alaykum... Hello...
...qelebalix...
...crowded...
Erê... ew tizbîka, ew tizbîka ne çê dibe. Dindikê gindiye.
Yes... those prayer beads, those prayer beads are not good.
The beads are rotten.
Welleh ne wekî din e, pir xweş e. Ez ê noha paqij... seke
haşkiye.
By God, it's not like the others, it is very nice. I will
clean it now... look it is dry.
...qutkê min ê rojê, ji êvîran a rojê, ji giştika rojê...
...my daily portion [of sorrow], from the evenings of the
day, from everything of the day...
Saetekî ya xweş be, canê we sax be...
May you have a happy hour, may your souls be healthy...
Erê hevalno, merheba ji we ra, hûn çewan in, inşallah rind û
rehet in.
Yes friends, hello to you, how are you, God willing you are
good and comfortable.
Erê îro vîdyokî xweş kîbor, em hatine sevî çêkin, li gundê
Zivingê.
Yes, today [we have] a nice, grand video, we came to make a
tour in the village of Zivingê.
Em hatine gundê Zivingê, di Canme'tekê, em ketin malê Ebû
Newras.
We came to the village of Zivingê, through Canme'teke, we
entered the house of Abu Nawras.
Erê ka Bimarê bin, em derbasî vî gundî bin, vî gundî kîbor.
Let's pass Bimarê [village], let's pass into this village,
this grand village.
Teb'en gund cî namaz in e, adet çil mal e, çil û pênc mal in
e.
Of course, the village is not small, there are usually forty
houses, forty-five houses.
Ka Bimarê bin em derbasî gund bin.
Let's pass Bimarê and enter the village.
Hevalno, ma ho... du çê nebû kefiyê, ne gundê Qesima, gundê
kîderê ye ez nizanim.
Friends, I wonder... [unintelligible] happen, isn't it
Qesima village, I don't know where that village is.
Ewî hember me jî ez nizanim kîjan gund e, gundê Qesima ye,
kîderê ye ez nizanim.
That one opposite us, I don't know which village it is
either, is it Qesima village, where is it, I don't know.
Erê hevalno, awwal marra di heyata xwe da têm vî gundî,
gundê Zivingê.
Yes friends, for the first time in my life I am coming to
this village, Zivingê village.
Sebre rêka xwe ne zibt e, qorçox e.
Wait, the road isn't solid, it is bumpy [muddy/rutted].
Seke mokînê xidra tên vî gundî firotin.
Look, vegetable cars [trucks] come to this village to sell.
Qorçox û çetîn e.
It is bumpy and difficult.
Nîdal birayê min, ev gundê te ye ha.
Nidal my brother, this is your village here.
Silavên me ji te ra hene heta Cîyê Tle.
Our greetings to you all the way to Jayetle.
Gundê Zivingê jê mahrûm xe...
Zivingê village is deprived of... [audio fades].
Û inşallah me telebê te jî, û xinca te jî, em ê cî bi cî
bikin inşallah.
And God willing, your request, and your wish, we will
fulfill them God willing.
Mago fuqara begundo... çû dikin fuqara.
I said, the poor villagers... what do the poor do.
Miletê me cebar e, cebar.
Our people are resilient [survivors], resilient.
Mako miletê me cebar e...
I said our people are resilient...
Vî derî hewş e ne?
This place is a courtyard, isn't it?
Rêka çetîn e.
The road is difficult.
Erê.
Yes.
Hevalno qisir efû kin, malek he dher neket... yanî qene rêk
çetîn e.
Friends, forgive the shortcomings, a house hasn't appeared
yet... I mean, the road is difficult.
Em pir nikanin tekevin dera.
We can't go into [deep] places much.
Em tirkê, em jêr û jor o wela nizanim, rêk e.
We leave it, we [go] down and up, by God I don't know, it's
the road.
Erê hevalno, me nikanî xwe mokînê berda, yanî rêka vî derî
pir çetîn e, ê batanş ke.
Yes friends, we couldn't take the car down, I mean the road
here is very difficult, [it needs] a high-clearance vehicle.
Zatir da mal tinen hoda.
It seems the houses are down there.
Mago zatir da mal tinen hoda.
I said it seems the houses are down there.
Tolî ye, vî derî tolî ye.
It's empty, this place is empty.
Erê hevalî min go, vî malê jî bigir.
Yes, my friend said, film this house too.
Erê... Xalû, merheba ji te ra.
Yes... Uncle, hello to you.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Xalû... vî gundî... ser vî gundî me ra xeber de. Vî gundî
çiqas mal e?
Uncle... this village... tell us about this village. How
many houses are in this village?
Pêncî mal... çil û pênc, pêncî mal heye.
Fifty houses... forty-five, fifty houses are there.
Pêncî mal.
Fifty houses.
Xalû... sekanê xwe geha ye?
Uncle... are its residents original [from here]?
Teqriben geha, ne bes hinekî kanê, lê bêjer nistina hewş û
vederê girtina, bes ew hewş nebû şixul wek din, giş liberin.
Almost all, no but a few [are missing], say regarding the
courtyard sitting area and the closing of the outside, but
if not for that courtyard, the rest of the work is all done.
Eywa.
I see.
Teyib Xalû, navê te çi?
Okay Uncle, what is your name?
Ebû Mihemed.
Abu Muhammad.
Ebû Mihemed? Ser serê min, ser çavê min.
Abu Muhammad? On my head, on my eyes [you are
welcome/respected].
Xalû, vî gundî kevnar e emrê vî gundî?
Uncle, is this village ancient, the age of this village?
Emrê vî gundî kes nizane tines.
Nobody knows the age of this village at all.
Pir kevn e?
Is it very old?
Pir kevn e, heta rebebîm, yanî emrê vî gundî bi pênc sedî,
şeş sedî kes nizane tines.
Very old, until [unintelligible], I mean nobody knows the
age of this village, maybe five hundred, six hundred
[years].
Kes bêle tines?
Nobody has a record/memory of it?
Na.
No.
Hawa ê em zanin çar pênc sed sal...
So what we know is four or five hundred years...
Ê em noka, em jî vî gundî, ê aîlê esasî em in.
And us now, we are also from this village, we are the
foundational family.
Eywa.
I see.
Werdê Mala Heyso.
Descendants of the House of Heyso.
Yanî kes nizane tines.
I mean nobody knows at all.
Pir kevnar e.
It is very ancient.
Pir kevn. Ne navê meselen hene dibên mala Hanî Kêlê hene,
mala Mendû hene.
Very old. There aren't names, for example, they say the
House of Hani Kele is here, the House of Mendu is here.
Eywa.
I see.
Evna paşê hatine yanî.
Those came later, I mean.
Bes esas bixwe, Mala Heyso ye.
But the foundation itself is the House of Heyso.
Xalû xêlê, nav lê kirin, xêr Zivingê, manê çiye Ziving?
Uncle, the tribe/people, the naming of it, why Zivingê, what
is the meaning of Ziving?
Ê hind dibên, yanî... şkest bin, şkestê xwe pir bin digotin
Zivingê.
Some say, I mean... [because] the caves/shelters, because
there were many caves they called it Zivingê.
Hind dibên Darik heye, vîr em bi Kurmancî dibên teawî.
Some say there is Darik [Gate?], here in Kurmanji we call it
shelter.
De orta wanê bi nûbî we ye.
In the middle of them [unintelligible].
Û...
And...
Hawa di gûnê hîn, di gûna Tirka da nav lê kiribûn Cûcik
Ziving.
So in the days of... in the days of the Turks they named it
"Küçük Ziving" [Small Ziving].
Cûcik Ziving?
Küçük Ziving?
Cûcik Ziving.
Küçük Ziving.
Paşê, manasê xwe çi Cûcik Ziving?
Later, what is the meaning of Küçük Ziving?
Işte cûcik yanî, cûcik.
Well, "cücük" [small/chick], I mean, small.
Yanî gundekî cûcik e yanî?
I mean, it's a small village?
Gundekî cûcik e, gotin Cûcik Ziving.
It's a small village, they said "Küçük Ziving".
Tirkî Cûcik Ziving e.
In Turkish it is Küçük Ziving.
Eywa.
Exactly.
Û bi Kurmancî Ziving e.
And in Kurmanji it is Ziving.
Ziving e.
It is Ziving.
Ewa nîkê em hana zanin.
That is what we know now.
Ne min go, ewilî navê Tirkî li ser bû, Zivingê?
No I said, was the Turkish name on it first, Zivingê?
Na, navê Kurmancî li ser bû.
No, the Kurmanji name was on it.
Navê Kurmancî.
The Kurmanji name.
Navê Kurmancî li ser bû, paşê di gûna Tirka da digotin Cûcik
Ziving.
The Kurmanji name was on it, later in the days of the Turks
they called it Küçük Ziving.
Cûcik Ziving.
Küçük Ziving.
Eme bi eslê xwe Zivinga Şkesta.
But in its origin, it is "Zivinga Şkesta" [Ziving of the
Caves].
Zivinga Şkesta.
Berî berê sê mal bûn.
Long ago, there were three households.
Sê aîle bûn, sê mal bûn.
There were three families, three households.
Wele pir hewşek av nûr têda, ez dibînim pir xweş e, pir mija
ye.
By God, there is a courtyard with fresh water in it, I see
it is very nice, very foggy/misty.
Hîn, hîn.. ê kêm e, kêm e, xirab kirin.
Still, still... it is low, it is low, they ruined it.
Xalo, û mago sersê vê sedê heşûnyê... sedê heşûnyê... wextê
ku av berdanê?
Uncle, and you said regarding this dam... the dam... when
they released the water?
Av kete... bîdayê wextê çêkirin çêkirin e... bîdayê av rind
kete...
The water entered... at the beginning when they were
building it... in the beginning the water came in well...
Û paşê jî, bi xwe, sed qul bî û av têçû.
And then, on its own, the dam had a hole and the water
leaked out.
De jê berdan.
So they released it [from there].
De jê berdan, hukmetê jî...
So they released it, the government also...
Yanî niha hûn ji ber vê avê, gundê xwe bar dikin?
Meaning, now because of this water, you are moving your
village?
Gund bar kirin, xelas kirin.
The village has moved, it's finished.
Hûn pê neêşiyan? Dilê we pê neêşiya?
Were you not hurt by it? Did your hearts not ache?
Qatixeyrandin, tirk...
They made us migrate, the Turks...
Ha, bu rind bî wele, fedaye we jî bidîto, nava?
Ha, if it was good, by God, you would have seen the
sacrifice/shame too, right?
Ekîd e feda...
For sure, it is a shame/sadness...
Baxçên ro, dar û tiştên ro...
[Leaving] the gardens, the trees and things...
Fedî, avê kuderê hebe, fedî heye.
Shame/sadness, wherever there is water [covering land],
there is sadness.
Xalo jî dibêje li vê gundî, av tenê, bîrên avê tenê... derin
ji kuderê tînin avê?
The Uncle also says in this village, water only, only water
wells... where do they go to bring water?
Em ji Qopla tînin, ji Qirgûlê tînin, ji Qutê tînin, haseb...
We bring it from Qopla, from Qirgûlê, from Qutê, it
depends...
Yanî dûr e jî, sîh têl bi şasê doreqê tirk neqla tînin nav
vê gundî.
Meaning it is far too, thirty [distance unit] by Turkish
tractor chassis, they transport it into this village.
Yanî debar li vê gundî çetin e, heta avê vexwarnê jî çetin
e.
Meaning livelihood in this village is hard, even drinking
water is hard [to get].
Meîşet çetin e.
Livelihood is hard.
Erê, Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê hemrê ki dirêj ke Xalo.
Yes, may God be pleased with you, may God give you a long
life, Uncle.
Xwedê ji we razî be, serî we sax be.
May God be pleased with you, may you be healthy.
Serî serî me tu jî û miletê gundî Zivingê giştek jî, silavên
me ji giyan ra hene.
Upon our heads [You are welcome], you and all the people of
Ziving village, our greetings to everyone.
Silav ji we giyan ra, ehlen we sehlen.
Greetings to all of you, welcome.
Silavên te gihîştinê, em spas dikin.
Your greetings have reached them, we thank you.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Saeta te xweş Xalo, Xwedê hemrê ki dirêj ke.
Have a good time Uncle, may God give you a long life.
Hemû dûr û nêzîk, silav ji giyan ra hene.
To everyone far and near, greetings to all of them.
Maşallah axê wele pir şêrîn e, her kes alimê gundê xwe...
Mashallah, the soil/land is very sweet, everyone is
accustomed to their own village...
No, emn sebra min li vê gundî nayê bi seraha.
No, honestly, I do not have patience [cannot stay] in this
village.
Lê noka miletê vî gundî, segwanê camêrn, gund sebra xwe li
camêrn nayê.
But now the people of this village, they are brave/patient
men, the village cannot lose patience with the men.
Her kes alimê gundê xwe, cîhê mezin bîye.
Everyone is accustomed to their village, the place where
they grew up.
Cîhê zarokatiya mezin bîye, başqe ye.
The place where their childhood grew up is different.
Lê axê wele şêrîn e, axê gundî mêra şêrîn e.
But the land, by God, is sweet, the land of the village of
brave men is sweet.
Meran cinet e yan cehnem e. Wele.
To men, [whether] it is heaven or hell. By God.
We go ne go gunda çi hiştine?
Whether you say it or not, what have the villages left?
Maşallah, va.
Mashallah, look.
Erê hejîr in, simaq in, zeytûn in, behîv in.
Yes, they are figs, sumac, olives, almonds.
De hiştine, ewê rêya xwe darbas dikin.
So they left them, they are passing their way [through
time].
Darên camêr de tên.
The trees of the brave men are coming along.
Lê, cimaeta mala Naso. Ne?
Look, the group of the Naso family. Right?
Mala Naso li ewê jî hene, Emar o.
Naso's family is on that side too, Emar [and them].
Ne mala Naso ji Emar o ji hene?
Is Naso's family not from Emar's side too?
Na ew kider, mala Çeqmaqo hene.
No where is that, Chaqmaqo family is there.
Çeqmaqo ji hene? Li Emar o ji hene, mala Naso, silavên me ji
giyan ra hene, mala Naso.
Chaqmaqo is there too? From Emar's side too, Naso family,
our greetings to all of them, Naso family.
Kî ne, mala Xalid, Se'da, Sîrkan...
Who are they? Khalid's family, Se'da, Sirkan...
Silav, rîz ji giyan ra.
Greetings and respect to all of them.
Arif o...
Arif...
Sîrî...
Siri...
Her yekî kuderê...
Wherever each one is...
Kakê Nidal, emê herin malbata, wa o, emê bimeşin herin. Ne?
Brother Nidal, we will go to the family... over there, we
will walk and go. Right?
Lê.
Look.
Lê, emê bimeşin, herin, heybo...
Look, we will walk, go, oh my...
Ev wek taqe ye, waye na?
This is like an arch/window, isn't it?
Mala Pîta Manan e.
It is the house of Pita Manan.
Mala Pîta Manan e yavo?
Is it the house of Pita Manan, folks?
Silavên me, xalê Manan re jî hene.
Our greetings to Uncle Manan as well.
Rêka xwe têda bimeşin.
Walk your way through it.
Evna hewşa Birokî Tana? Hewşa Birokî Tana, Kakê Nidal?
Is this the courtyard of Biroki Tana? Biroki Tana's
courtyard, Brother Nidal?
Evna geh Birokî Tana ye, Meyrê Tana ye.
This is sometimes Biroki Tana's, Meyre Tana's.
Çi tebîatek xweş e, cew xweş e.
What a nice nature, the weather is nice.
Hûnê, navê Zinar no?
Look, the name is Zinar (Rock/Cliff), right?
Çîçike rêka xwe çetin e, ne?
The road is a little difficult, isn't it?
Dûvre, dûvre heye, rêk bes wele kevir e.
Straight, it is straight, the road is just, by God, rocky.
Heye çîçike kevir e, çetin e.
Yes, it is a little rocky, it is difficult.
Mola wî pê gindibigir.
Capture/Film his Mosque in the village.
Mola berê ke?
The old Mosque?
Mola înê, mola înê bigir.
The Friday Mosque, capture the Friday Mosque.
Erê evwa mola înê ye.
Yes, this is the Friday Mosque.
Qupî xwe dikir, divrê ye?
It had its dome, is it around here?
Xweli cîh, cîh kî bilind lê kê çûye? Cîh bilind girtî hewşa
xwe.
The soil/place, which high place did it go to? It occupied a
high place, its courtyard.
Wele gund gih xwe wite.
By God, the village has completely disappeared/emptied.
Cîh bilind e, rind e.
The place is high, it is good.
Erê, hewa Apê Kemîl?
Yes, is this Uncle Kemil['s house]?
Hewa jî Apê Mehmûd.
And this is Uncle Mehmud.
Apê Mehmûd.
Uncle Mehmud.
We hewa jî bavê...
And this is the father of...
O, em gihîştin ber malbata wa o.
Oh, we have arrived at their family's home.
Hê, çi cî ye lo.
Hey, what a place, man.
Yekinda bibe, nava kelim no çog xwaçêke.
If one [falls], inside these rocks, it will break his knee
nicely.
Mago Selam Aleykum.
Uncle/Sir, Peace be upon you.
Begêm silav li xwarzê.
Sir, greetings to the nephew.
Merheba.
Hello.
Halê, halê we çawa ye, baş e?
How is, how is your condition, is it good?
Tu bi xêr hatî, ehlen we sehlen.
You are welcome, welcome.
Ehlen xwarzê, ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome nephew, welcome.
Çawa ye, işê te çawa ye?
How is it, how is your work?
Bixwedê elhemdulîlah, em bi wucûdê şebaba pir kefxweş dibin.
By God, praise be to God, we become very happy with the
presence of the youth.
Em jî te dîtî, em pir kefxweş bûn.
We also saw you, we became very happy.
Ê seyîda, te jî wext xweş bî û înşallah...
Oh Sayyid, may your time be good too and God willing...
Înşallah aqûbet li gund bi, heriyê wela te xerîbiyê tu çûne,
her wela te xerîbiyê hene.
God willing, the fate will be in the village, everywhere, by
God, where you went in exile, everywhere, by God, there is
exile.
Em gih hevdu bibînin.
May we see each other.
Înşallah emê bibînin, bibînin, daka were em derbas bin, emê
germ in, em biçin hundur.
God willing we will see, we will see, mother come let's
pass, we are hot, let's go inside.
Heva Dara Şemsê, sersiya dibîne ma li vira din.
This is the Shams Tree (or Sun Tree), look at its top, we
are here.
Keremkin.
Welcome (Please come in).
De ba hewşek te xortî.
So, a courtyard of yours, young man.
Hewa min e.
This is mine.
Em ji ber vê rokê revîn hatin vir.
We ran from this sun/heat and came here.
Mamê û da pîrê û em li vir man, hîştin em çûn.
Uncles and grandmothers and we stayed here, they left us and
we went/stayed.
Heva, evê kitêba Quranê.
This, this is the book of the Quran.
Heşê rib milî, evê çêkir serka.
[Unclear, possibly regarding binding], he made this on top.
Heva ebcav rûpî cûda şûten.
This... [unclear phrase about washing/cleaning parts
separately].
Berê, cût qatir av dikirin.
Before, they used to water the mule pairs [plowing].
Heva jî, ewê nîr e, gindî ye.
This too, that is the yoke, it is from the village.
Ma digo benî gind pê... gaho da cot dikirin.
We used to say... they plowed with the oxen.
Pê digirtin le.
They held/caught [the oxen] with it, look.
Heva jî hawa.
And this is like this.
Hevna sûretê dikim min heva.
I am making a picture of this one.
Sûretê dikim heva jî, şebek e.
I am making a picture, this is also a net/mesh holder.
Hevna darê tezbîk e, evwa tezbîk e, li çiyê dibê. Dendikê
gindî ye.
These are rosary tree [beads], this is a rosary, it grows in
the mountain. It is wild melon seeds.
Tînin qul dikirin, û wana pê çêkirin.
They bring them and make holes in them, and make [rosaries]
with them.
Kê çêkiriye ev xaltîkê?
Who made this, Auntie?
Babê min, Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, wî çêkir.
My father, may God have mercy on him, he made it.
Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke.
May God have mercy on him.
Heva jî me pê pella diçinî, dask e. Daskê pella ne.
And this, we harvested leaves/herbs with it, it is a sickle.
Sickles for leaves.
Me pê pella diçinî.
We harvested leaves with it.
Erê.
Yes.
Heva jî dîsa, şebekê çêkiriye, heva qalûn e.
This again, made of mesh/net, this is a pipe.
Heva e cixare.
This is for cigarettes/smoking.
Ê titûn, titûn dikê çî vira.
The tobacco, he puts the tobacco inside here.
Û êr vedixin, û vira jî emzikê dikin devê xwe, vedixwin.
And they light the fire, and here they put the mouthpiece in
their mouth, and smoke.
Pê vedixwin, heva qelûn e.
They smoke with it, this is a pipe.
Way berê ne. Erê.
It is from the old times. Yes.
Heva tiştê berê kevn e.
This is an old thing from the past.
Heva jî cerê qurbetê.
And this is the jar of exile/strangeness.
Cerê qurbetê berê digotin.
They used to call it the jar of exile.
Berê digotin cerê qurbetê, cerê din tenabîm, heva cerê...
Before they called it the jar of exile, other jars were not
available, this jar...
Ê or vedixist, pê biçûya çûle, biçûya kûr, nadimire.
One would put water in it, if going to the wilderness, going
deep [far away], it does not spill.
Bê le nadixist. Na.
It wouldn't spill without reason. No.
Vêda dûr genda, qezêza.
Over there far away... [unclear, possibly place name or
material].
Lê qezêza, hewa belûr e.
Look at the glass, this is glass/crystal.
Lê, hewa cerê qurbetê ye.
Look, this is the jar of exile.
Heva jî çû ye.
And this is a stick.
Tedî dino hindirî xo sîleh tunebî.
You saw inside, he didn't have a weapon.
Heva me dî dino paş qopî xo, yek bata...
This, we saw behind the door/corner, if someone came...
Gota nes naker, heramî çî, bivît difaê xwe dikir.
Saying don't make noise, if a thief or whatever [came], he
would defend himself with it.
Pevî çûyî me difaê dikir.
With this stick we defended.
Şûynê, hef sîlahê berê.
Look, this is the weapon of the past.
Hef sîlahê me bî.
This was our weapon.
Erê.
Yes.
Heva sîlahê me bî.
This was our weapon.
Ez dibêm qey te pê li mêrê xwe dixist.
I thought maybe you hit your husband with it.
Na, mêr distîne.
No, the husband takes it.
Pê tepe li hinda dixist, bes o qisêr e, henek dikim.
He would hit others with it, but it is short/broken, I am
joking.
Em kêf dikin xaltîk.
We are having fun/joking, Auntie.
Na qisêr e wela, yare.
No it is short really, friend.
Heva jî şta perde, ewê me wena çêkirine, êd me ne. Heva jî
cerê qoyzaxê.
And this is for the curtain, the ones we made, ours. And
this is the jar of... [unclear type].
Heva kevçiyê behrê.
This is the sea spoon.
Heva yekê...
This is one...
Apê min e, heve yê bavê min e. Rehmî Melîna ne, hewna
kevçiyê behrê ne.
It's my uncle's, this is my father's. Late Melina's
[belongings], these are sea spoons.
Heva jî serqezîz e.
And this is a mirror [head-mirror].
Serqezîzê gundî ye. Qilpî qezîzê, qezîz şikî min ser
nexistine.
It is the village mirror. The frame of the mirror, the glass
broke, I didn't put it back on.
Erê.
Yes.
Heva, ne kesî.
This, no one [has it].
Heva veda darê... heva...
This, over there the tree of... this...
Boyîj heye veda, Dara Ta'wî ye. Berê digotin Dara Ta'wî, ana
sûr dibîn, me ta'wî dixwarin.
There is "Boyij" over there, it is the Hackberry tree.
Before they called it Hackberry tree, they become red, we
ate the hackberries.
Heva Boyîk e.
This is the "Boyik" [fruit/berry].
Heva hejîr e, wa veda fistiq e.
This is a fig, and over there is pistachio.
Maşallah tirit tijî xotik e.
Mashallah, it is full of your things.
Lê hevna jî, min... ê zeytûnê bîn min sol moşle kirin,
zeytûnê xo ne anîn, min ê zetî lê xistin.
Look, these too, I... there were olives, I pickled them this
year, I didn't bring my olives, I put the oil ones in.
Xotikê, gaws şele kir ne?
[Unclear]... you pickled them well?
Zeytûn maye xwar.
The olives remained down [there].
Heva jî çilê mîrê.
And this is the rolling stone/grinder.
Heva fîşek e.
This is the "cartridge" [cylindrical stone roller].
Fîşekî dew...
The roller for...
Me tîna sibê dewî xo dikirê, ovê hinek dikirê, me hûro lê
dixist, me dikêya.
We would bring it in the morning, put our seeds/ingredients
in it, put some water, we would crush it, we would grind it.
Rûn biser diket, tehmî wî dewî pir xweş dibê. Pir xweş bî.
The oil/fat would rise to the top, the taste of that yogurt
drink would be very good. It was very good.
Na wekî xasale, na wekî din e. Pir xweş e tehmî dewî. Ez sal
bi sal...
Not like the mixer/machine, not like the other things. The
taste of the drink is very good. I, year by year...
Ez ê noka paqij e, seke, hişk bîye. Salik din eke, doxê de
berî dew bikêm, ez ê têkim ovê.
I [kept] it clean now, look, it has dried. Next year, if I
put yogurt drink in the churn, I will put it in water.
Ê nerm bibe...
So it becomes soft...
Ez ê dewî xo têda bikem.
I will make my yogurt drink in it.
Ê ti nîz tehmal dikê xaltîk?
So you don't tolerate the new ones, Auntie?
Erê, sal bi sal ez dikim.
Yes, I do it year by year.
Ez ê çûkim, şta min... tiştî berê ez hez dikim.
I will go... I like the things of the past.
Erê can xotikê tişt pir xweş e.
Yes dear Auntie, the things are very nice.
Heva teşî ye.
This is a spindle.
Tê dîtina hirî berê, waî adî li kol cem min, ez çanokim.
You saw the wool before, [unclear phrase], I don't know.
Hêre û mû.
Wool and hair.
Me tîna şeh hebî. Şehê mişkîn, wer digotin şehê mişkîn.
We brought... there was a comb. The breaking comb [carding
comb], they called it the breaking comb.
Erê pê çû...
Yes with it... [unclear].
Me hana dişkînî, dişkînî, dişkînî... wekî por dibî.
We would break/card it like this, break it, break it... it
became like hair.
Paşê divtil, me dirist.
Then it was rolled/twisted, we made it.
Hem mû û herye b'hevdû dişkînî.
We broke/carded both hair and wool together.
Me dirist, paşê divtilî, me dibir hêre sofî tenê jî dirist.
We made it, then twisted it, we took just the wool thread
and made it too.
Vayê sûr, bo wes, sofî hêrî ye.
The red ones, for [unclear], is wool thread.
Me dirist, me takro, ber d'bûwe dikir. Me dikir destê...
We made it, we made it single [strand], put it to the
loom/knitting. We made gloves...
Meldar d'ina, m' hurî dida destê, me ba dikir, m' teşî dida
na, m' gok d'hiltîna... firk firk m' dikir bi destan.
I brought the carder, I put wool in my hand, I carded it, I
put the spindle there, I picked up the ball... I spun it by
hand, spin spin.
Meldar d'ina, me gur d'hiltîna... şeî m'şkîn hebû... şeî ew
pê dikirin... dugotn krkît.
I brought the carder, we picked up the bundle... there was a
broken comb... the comb they used... it was called a krkît
(beater).
Krkît hebû, bevş hebû, paştabn hebû, sergurt hebû, me ke
wana çêdikir, firk firk me dikir.
There was a beater, a heddle rod, a back beam, a top beam,
we made them like that, spin spin we did.
Hewa jî ver d'bîn leçek, ba dî tera, xweş d'rûyt... a em ke
leçek m' çêdikirin.
We took them to the stream, to the other side, washed them
well... ah, we did it in the stream.
Haba ke naxî genda, m' leçek çêdikir. Manê ve nexweşe xero
nebe, lê?
I didn't put it in the pond, I did it in the stream. That's
bad if it's not running water, isn't it?
M' gişta wana bi desta dikir, her tiştek bi desta bû. E noka
vê tişta tinî. M' nan li ser dikir.
I did all of those by hand, everything was by hand. Now
these things don't exist. I made bread on it.
Te hînd dikin, ê noka?
Do they learn it, the ones now?
Erê lê, hînd dikim. Hewa jî dûx e... hewa jî dûx em pê
dikin.
Yes dear, I teach. That is also a thread... that is also a
thread we use.
Lê hewa jî dûx e, ha.
Yes, that is also a thread, ha.
Lê, em dikin lê, hîd v'hîde.
Yes, we do it dear, slowly slowly.
Xaltîk tiştê turasî hez dikî?
Auntie, do you like heritage things?
Ez hez dikim. Qîmeta zane.
I like them. He knows the value.
Seke me çûna b'dar xistî.
Look, we threw the churn onto the tree.
Dê nîm ardê, rutûbet bibe. Rutûbet bibe lê, xera bibe lê.
It will get half on the ground, it will get damp. It will
get damp dear, it will get ruined dear.
Hîn tiştî xaltîkê pir zî dibî di harbê da, d'zi birin. Şûr
hebûn, mar hebûn, m'dîna bî ser vira mar k'hebû... oho...
mezin bî.
Many of Auntie's things were lost in the war, thieves took
them. There were swords, there were snakes, I saw a snake on
top of here... oho... it was big.
Ewe di zman têda, e textî çêkirbû, çû warin bîn. Dizin
birin. Şûr dîsa birin.
It was in the tradition, the bed was made... Thieves took
it. They took the swords too.
Xaltîk xelfetî te çi dikir?
Auntie, what did your husband's family do?
E... Lawkê min jî na we qolûna û marikî... û çêkir... lawkê
m' çêkir. Lawkê m' noka hewal Almanya ye.
Uh... My son made those columns and snakes... and made... my
son made it. My son is now a friend in Germany.
Xudê seheta we jî xweş... Xudê înşala pir... hewa bin... we
xweş bin... hûn jî ew bikin înşala.
God give you good health too... God willing many... be
that... you be happy... you do that too God willing.
Seheta we xweş xaltî, Xudê rehmê li dê û bavê te bike, Xudê
seheta we xweş bike.
Good health to you Auntie, God have mercy on your mother and
father, God give you good health.
Xudê de şîta û qçkê zî be hefdigî ne.
May God protect you and the children together.
Seheta we jî xweş.
Good health to you too.
Noka tu vê sibê nahê... te çû dikir te?
Now you didn't come this morning... what were you doing?
Wile min xwedê hişt...
By God I left...
Ê Xaltîk silav ke, te çi d'şîne ji qçkaro?
So Auntie, send greetings, what do you send to the kids?
Qçkê Xaltîkê 's taban li derva hene... Silav dikim ji
giştkaro, û merhaba ji giştkaro, ehlen we sehlen.
Auntie's kids are naturally outside... I greet everyone, and
hello to everyone, welcome.
Ji qçkê d'Mero jî, û ji cîranê ro jî, ji giştkaro. Seheta we
giya xweş be, canê we sax be.
To the kids of Mero too, and to the neighbors too, to
everyone. May you all have good health, may your souls be
healthy.
Dûr, nîzîk, ji meshewdê miro jî... Nîdalê ro jî... ji hevalê
kî û cîran, hewa, dûr, nîzîk, ji giştkaro.
Far, near, from our viewers... to Nidal too... to friends
and neighbors, those far and near, to everyone.
Ahlen we sehlen, seheta we xweş be.
Welcome, may your health be good.
Îkolê têda ye? Îkolê... kelak ta ye. Tew cma' bikî te xwa.
Is the Ikol inside? The Ikol... is boiling. You and the
group do your own.
...darna ba'dya... hele w'otir me... firçone.
...trees afterwards... look further us... brush.
Heqolî me hol v'darno bigira. Hews şûj da tew ma... holê me
ye.
Let our field catch these trees. The courtyard gave a
needle... is our room.
Axolo em t'j'hewşê derkevite derê çolê. O wara vê malnanû jî
derxe.
Uncle, let's go out from the courtyard to the door of the
wild. And come film these homes too.
Gundê Zivingê be.
Let it be the village of Ziving.
Lê, gundê Zivingê.
Yes, village of Ziving.
Hember me jî çayê heware.
Opposite us is Mount Hawar.
Çiyayê Hawarê... haaa. Ava gundê dikê ye.
Mount Hawar... haaa. This is the village of Dike.
Gelo te gotinek ma?
Do you have any words left?
Bêje yaw...
Say it man...
M' kişiya orê, m' kişiya...
I filmed there, I filmed...
Brokî min Nîdal, apê min noka xatira xwe ji we bixwazin, em
ji mala Xolû ne.
My brother Nidal, my uncle now wants to say goodbye to you,
we are at Xolu's house.
Xolû te çi silavê d'şîne ji şebabê xora?
Xolu, what greetings do you send to your youth?
Em pir silava d'şînin ji şebabê ro, giya ro, xwedê canê sax
bide, şebabî, xerîbî, e giştiko.
We send many greetings to our youth, all of them, God give
health, youth, strangers, everyone.
Ne bes î me tenê, ê cîrana, ehbaba, ê giya.
Not just ours only, the neighbors, loved ones, everyone.
Seheta we giya xweş be û xwedê înşala îşê giya rastî bike û
p'orrn bike. Û înşala emê hev bibînin.
Health to you all and God willing may God make everyone's
work straight and successful. And God willing we will see
each other.
Xol gotina te hene?
Xol do you have words?
Silav rîz ji giya ro.
Greetings and respect to everyone.
Silavê min ji giya ro.
My greetings to everyone.
Gotina min, ehlen sehlen. Nîdal merhaba ji te ro yorim.
My words, welcome. Nidal hello to you my dear.
Te şan seheta te xweş, em dîndarê te ne. Û Fêrûza merhaba ji
te ro jî.
You are beautiful, your health be good, we are indebted to
you. And Feruza hello to you too.
Û Fatma Hûrî merhaba ji we giştkaro yorim. Ez ji we razî me,
xwedê pêxember ji we razî be.
And Fatma Huri hello to all of you my dear. I am pleased
with you, may God and the Prophet be pleased with you.
Wile yê me jî... sûretê me kişand...
By God ours too... took our picture...
Kakê Nîdal, ez destê bavê te, serê dêka xwe maç kim, û destê
giya maç kim.
Brother Nidal, I kiss your father's hand, my mother's head,
and kiss everyone's hand.
Ez netirsim qçkê m' destî maç kim.
I'm not afraid to kiss my child's hand.
Qurban qurban, ber genda vo, ber genda vo.
Sacrifice sacrifice, wait wait.
Hane l'm' qçkê m', destî maç kim. Seheta we xweş, û xwedê ji
we razî be.
Here is my child, I kiss the hand. Good health to you, and
may God be pleased with you.
B'merabun dîsa vîdyo kî din xweş, kîbar, emê înşala nîzîk da
daxin. Înşala bi xêrî werin...
With greeting again another video, nice, elegant, we will
upload soon God willing. God willing come in goodness...
Bi xatira we, gula gula, biminne bixêr.
Goodbye, bye bye, stay in goodness.
Gula gula, ma rûmetin boş. Çavê qîza xwe giya maç dikim, ê
lawê xwe. Seheta we giya xweş.
Bye bye, our respect is plenty. I kiss the eyes of all my
daughters, of my sons. Health to you all.
Silav ji giya ro... Giya ro, giya ro, ummeta Mehemed giştî
kiro silav.
Greetings to everyone... Everyone, everyone, to the whole
nation of Muhammed greetings.
Erê hevalno, vî derê jî Sedê Aşûnê ye.
Yes friends, this place is the Ashune Dam.
Berê sed livi darê bî, çêkirin, xolû go av tê çû, go hiştin.
Temam nekirin.
Before, a dam was in this place, they made it, Xolu said
water came, said they left it. They didn't finish.
Û yanî av rind ketibî îsaleke. Avo vira dibên Sedê Aşûnê.
And meaning water fell well this year. This here they call
the Dam of Ashune.
Erê hevalno seke wa dî ye. Avê darê sed bî. Me go vî darê
sed bî, seke... ew sê dilik o.
Yes friends look it is visible. This tree is a hundred. I
said this tree is a hundred, look... it has three trunks.
B'şûne jî g' kirne bîstan. Bîstan jî necehî ye. Lê nîvê
kûrtê da ye, tm rûbê xwe heye.
Behind they made into gardens. Gardens are successful. But
it is in the middle of the hollow, always has its moisture.
Ê av divir da hatibû, vê milkano, vê darno, vê g'... g' av
bibû. P'rrn bî.
The water had come here, these properties, these trees,
all... all became water. It was a lot.
Walahî heta noka gundiyan av neçû av.
By God until now the water didn't go to the villagers.
Av o jî hafê me, gundê Aşûnê ye. Erê. De gundê Aşûnê, Sedê
Aşûnê.
This is our side, village of Ashune. Yes. The village of
Ashune, the Dam of Ashune.
Ekîd bile bile ye selef wati vî gundî, jinek bî, nav lê
kirin gundê Aşûnê.
Surely there is a story, a flood came to this village, it
was a woman, they named it village of Ashune.
Erê hevalno, av o jî gundê Aşûnê ye, em êl dikşînin gundê
Aşûnê.
Yes friends, this too is village of Ashune, we are filming
village of Ashune.
Gundê Aşûnê malbat j'ma na, xwasna, bes esker lexto ke...
wana ji nav ro çêkim. Mila divir da nemîne.
Village of Ashune families are not from us, in-laws, but
soldiers hit... I will make them from inside. So folks don't
stay here.
Wey, rêka xwe jî qaçax e, toz e.
Oh, its road is smuggling, it is dust.
Inşala her gundek ser gundekî ra. Seke hewşên jî kevnar o.
Af rêko derê ke... e he.
God willing every village on top of another village. Look,
the courtyards are ancient too. This road goes out... uh
huh.
Qa te 'etarê bacan û... qane xidre mera bû minê xûr bû
firotan a vê gundî.
As if you were a seller of eggplants and... if we had
vegetables I would have surely sold to this village.
Lê difrût wela. Bazar a derdikevim.
But he sells by God. I'm going out to the market.
İnşalla we ye.
Hopefully it is so.
Ev rêkû darê serçê çiye?
What is this road going up to the peak?
Wele miştin serçê. Yeh!
By God, it is full of ascents. Oh!
Wele miştin serçê.
By God, it is full of ascents.
Avo lo qusrê 'off' ke no vê gundok... Mol Batman... no bı
grablı min...
Hey man, turn off the deficit... look at this village...
Mall of Batman... don't mess with me...
Wele herra çel pênca.
By God, it is going at forty-five.
Mago emê darin 'Mol' qene em dinav gund de haş û nêra herin.
I said we are going to the 'Mall', at least let's stroll
through the village.
Te belkim heno rûnê em şandin.
Maybe they sent us some oil.
La nî dûre... cam mêva hativır dûre mago melo...
No it's far... guests came here, it's far, I said man...
Am vêji amo lextokê biserxin.
We will also push this one a bit.
Ehe! Dê ev rêkoyna hîn darê jor.
Ehe! Look, this road still goes up.
Ma rarê heta jor çiye?
Man, what is this all the way up?
E devrê rêka be ma rarê.
Let this be the road, man.
Ooo Delû bık lıvır ji heye. Aça babi rêk dıvro. Xo berdin.
Ooo, Delû is here too. Man, look at the road here. Let go.
Eh heyy! Norê!
Oh hey! Norê!
Ecêb darê hewşê lê darê ke wele mezin.
Strange courtyard trees, but trees that are huge, by God.
Şikle em ters şor a qe nizonim, em tam tam darin.
It seems we are going the wrong way, I don't know, we are
going blindly.
Ta bermîl ka bome... no ve gundî tûl kıro... milete gış
xewrobo.
Since the barrel fell on us... look at this village... all
the people were ruined.
Gê bûşî mazotê hebo, me dı nov gundro tûl kıro, taxorkıl
fılmono.
If there was plenty of diesel, we would have toured inside
the village, round and round like in films.
Gê berahfîno. Qırqıra giyoyê boto çıbî.
Look at the wide view. What was that crunch of the grass.
Ehh. Avo ev darê kıvreko?
Ehh. Hey man, which way is this road?
Tebîetık xweş... a welî min... lê bısewrîne hêê.
A nice nature... oh my guardian... film it, hey.
Ooo hewşê kevn kîlû goyşî.
Ooo old courtyards, clay and lime.
Are avol no, me vîdyo xwe xîtam kiribî. Me vîdo xîtam
kiribî...
Yes guys, we had finished our video. We had finished the
video...
...em me go em gundê Aşûnê ji bisewirînin, erê.
...we said let's film Aşûnê village too, yes.
O Zivingê li ko em ji wê gundî hatin. Seda Aşûnê ji evaye
jêrî me ye. Dabhênerrin?
And Ziving is there, we came from that village. The Aşûnê
dam is this one below us. Do you see it?
Af sedda. Û lı vî darê jî... berê xerabe lı vî darê pir bûn.
This dam. And on this side too... previously the ruins on
this side were many.
Ho gile gı xoniyê kevin. Berê milet gı lı vir rûniştibî
gile... çûqso hewşene.
Look all are old houses. Previously the people who lived
here all... look how they are courtyards.
Gı hewşê kevinorin, xerabiye û takro hatine lı vir girtine.
They are all old courtyards, ruins, and then they came and
occupied here.
Vro jî cama xezanê avê heye, hafe gind. Munazema çêkiriye.
Today there is a water tank inside the village. An
organization built it.
Mileti vê gundî avê vedxwin gundê Aşûnê. Zater hember me ji
gundê Karrê ye.
The people of this village drink water, Aşûnê village.
Anyway, opposite us is the village of Karrê.
Maşalla. Dinê germ e, tım cîhaz merê dimre. Cîhaz her dı
deqe cîhazê me difasle.
Mashallah. The weather is hot, the device always dies on us.
The device turns off every two minutes.
We manem tım dıkin acele. Dêmîş nabe. Anca şemsîkê vero
çêkim.
That's why we are always rushing. It doesn't work out.
Unless I make a sunshade for it.
Wadiyê mentiqa me çiqso xweş e, tebîetê vir, cuxrafyê vir
pirr xweş e.
The valley of our area is so nice, the nature here, the
geography here is very nice.
Ehh hê. Maşalla maşalla.
Ehh he. Mashallah mashallah.
Ooo.
Av o av o... ev ji Be'dînî ye... lwah şemsî ew dikin.
That one, that one... he is also from Ba'dîna... they use
solar panels.
Ew jî çakî gundê me ye, roj Be'dîno tê viro gundê Aşûnê,
lwah şemsî drakbîne.
He is also from the good people of our village, he comes
from Ba'dîna here to Aşûnê village, installs solar panels.
Seta gund xweş e. Yanî kahraba hîn negihiştiyê vî gundî.
The situation of the village is good. Meaning electricity
hasn't reached this village yet.
Cama nahya Rajo Efrîn, kahraba gi daraye...
Actually, in the Rajo district of Afrin, electricity is
everywhere...
Bes gundnê huna cîçke dûr in, ji nahyo va dûr in... hın
kahraba demdîd nekirine.
But villages like this are a bit far, far from the
district... they haven't extended electricity yet.
Yawaş yawaş... her gi gund bi gund xlas dikin darin gundî
din.
Slowly slowly... they finish village by village and go to
the other village.
Rêya pîda dîsa kahraba ê nîzami bighê darê gine.
Hopefully regular electricity will reach everywhere again.
Cama kahraba me bîst û çar seeta heye, rinde.
Actually our electricity is 24 hours, it's good.
Em beradê xwe vêdixin, televizyonê xwe vêdixin.
We turn on our fridges, turn on our TVs.
Heye lwah şemsî gundî ji ana îstîmal dike birû... bê vore
kahrabê dewletê vê dixê.
There are solar panels the villagers use now... without
needing the state electricity they turn it on.
Evi hember me ji gundê Karrê ye.
This opposite us is the village of Karrê.
Bi xatirê ta gundê Aşûnê, gundê Zivingê... bi xatirê we gula
gula.
For the sake of Aşûnê village, Zivingê village... goodbye to
you, flowers flowers.
Erê avol no, taben em gihiştin toliyê vîdyo xwe.
Yes guys, anyway we reached the end of our video.
Me vîdo li wî gundê Zivingê xîtam kiribî.
We had finished the video at Zivingê village.
Takro me go vî gund o... mıla guni vî gundi natê istima...
zılmi vî gundo divırdo gundê Aşûnê.
Then we said this village... it's a pity for this village
not to be included... it's unfair to this village here,
Aşûnê village.
Ka bimarê bin vîdyo ki dîn xweş kîbor, emê werin inşalla
nîzik da emê daxin.
Let it be a nice distinct video for us, we will come
hopefully soon we will upload.