Sta hacorê me bîra hewşê kir, em tê bê biniya xwe, bîra xwe
tê dikin da.
You reminded us of the stone courtyard, we will come to its
bottom, we remember it well.
Zirnora înê, zirnora înê kevir dibin, zirnora înê...
Zinarê Înê (The Rock of Friday), the stones of Zinarê Înê,
Zinarê Înê...
Bra dibin zirnora înê, himm.
Brothers, they call it Zinarê Înê, hmm.
E çokatî ma herdûk jî wekî hev e cemaet, noko dê bînimo?
Well, both our knees are the same [in bad shape], folks,
shall we see it now?
Heta noko kelak min e, min ne dî.
Until now, it is my side [that hurts], I haven't seen it.
Biniya gund e.
It is the bottom of the village.
Ba'ce bînin.
Bring the others.
Çû te'eciban b'brê Mihemed, te'eciban.
Look at the wonders, brother Muhammad, the wonders.
Heta teq ji destî te sax be.
As long as the strength in your hand is healthy.
Bi mera ben, noko...
Stay with us, now...
Em çûna xwe jî çêkin.
Let us make our way.
Dî xornê ra Fatme mera qehwekê çêke l'ser êr.
Tell the nephew to have Fatma make us a coffee on the fire.
Qehwe l'ser êr.
Coffee on the fire.
Ekî zikratê şevê b'pir l'vire hene.
Surely, there are many night memories here.
Erê cemaet...
Yes, folks...
Wekî we dî ye, hûru vîde ma, em li orta gundê Emo ne.
As you saw, here in this video of ours, we are in the middle
of Emo village.
Abû orta gundê Emo ye.
This is the middle of Emo village.
Cemaet, ev jî heye, ev kevro.
Folks, there is also this, this stone.
Emrê vê kevrî 350 sal, 400 sal heye vê kevro.
The age of this stone is 350 years, there are 400 years to
this stone.
Waxtê ne di berê de, vir de genim dikutan, şa'bê vê gundî.
In the times of the past, they used to pound wheat in here,
the people of this village.
Şa'bê gundê Emo vir de genim dikutan.
The people of Emo village used to pound wheat here.
Avo pir kavnor e.
This is very ancient.
Emrê xwe 350 sal, 400 sal heye.
Its age is 350 years, 400 years.
Ev jî mala xalkê min e.
This is also my maternal uncle's house.
Ev hewşo...
This courtyard...
Avo mala Êniş taye.
This is the house of Enish.
Abû Hanan, emê li gundê Emo ne, sehke ev hewşo te ye.
Abu Hanan, we are in Emo village, look, this is your
courtyard.
Hacarê me bîra gundê kir, em tên biniya xwe b'hewşê
derdikin, hewşê gundê.
You reminded us of the village, we come down to appear at
the courtyard, the village courtyard.
Heta wina em pê xweş dibin. Em tên hewşê dibînin sankî me
gundiyan dîtine.
We are happy with that much. When we come and see the
courtyard, it's as if we have seen the villagers.
Ev hewşo waye, emê noko hewşê were teswîr kin.
This is his courtyard, we will now film the courtyard for
you.
Reber were.
Reber, come.
Erê Abû Hanan, emê li hewşê werin rûniştinê, avo hewşo waye,
emê hewşê neho dekomin ji bove.
Yes Abu Hanan, we have come to sit in the courtyard, this is
his courtyard, this courtyard is now [shown] for you.
Sta hacorê me bîra hewşê kir, em tê bê biniya xwe pê dikin
der.
You reminded us of the stone courtyard, we come to its
bottom and we show it.
Avo hewşo wayîş te, ooo, emê li gundê Emo ne.
This is his courtyard too, oh, we are in Emo village.
Xellîk nayim, xellîk nayim.
Stay lying down, stay lying down.
Xellîk nayim.
Stay lying down.
We b'ra dengê bigrim kine berke.
Brother, let me record the sound, make it short.
Bes.
Enough.
Erê cemaet, avo hewşo Qulê Henîfe.
Yes folks, this is the courtyard of Qule Henife.
Mistefa, avo hewşo way.
Mustafa, this is his courtyard.
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Hewşo Qulê Henîfe.
The courtyard of Qule Henife.
Erê me cemaet, wekî we dî ye, biderê gundorê me rxên e.
Yes our group, as you saw, outside, our village surroundings
are slopes.
Mantiqa xwe xweş e. Emî derên noko qelê... Zinarê Înê.
Its area is nice. We are going now to the castle... Zinarê
Înê (The Rock of Friday).
Mewqe'ekî pir xweş e.
It is a very nice location.
Wa dî ye, în hev jî waxtê hêşîniyê te were, pir xweş e
biderê.
You see, this place too, when the greenery comes, it is very
nice outside.
Avo binê gundê Emo vêra dibên.
They call this the bottom of Emo village.
Minnetê gundê Emo kesê l'der va, l'mantiqê xwe sêr kin, biko
we bîrê kirî.
The favor of Emo village [is upon] anyone who went abroad,
look at your region, so you may remember.
Erê cemaet...
Yes folks...
Wekî we dî ye, hûru bide me, em li orta gundê Emo ne.
As you saw, here in this video, we are in the middle of Emo
village.
Avo orta gundê Emo ye.
This is the middle of Emo village.
Cemaet, emê jî heye, hav kevro.
Folks, we also have this, these stones.
Emrê vê kevri 350 sal, 400 sal heye vê kevro.
The age of this stone is 350 years, there are 400 years to
this stone.
Waxtê ne, di berê de, vir de genim dikutan, şa'bê vê gundî.
In the times of the past, they used to pound wheat in here,
the people of this village.
Şa'bê gundê Emo vir de genim dikutan.
The people of Emo village used to pound wheat here.
Avo pir kavnor e.
This is very ancient.
Emrê xwe 350 sal, 400 sal heye.
Its age is 350 years, 400 years.
Ev jî mala xalkê min e.
This is also my maternal uncle's house.
Ev hewşo...
This courtyard...
Avo mala Êniş taye.
This is the house of Enish.
Abû Hanan, emî li gundê Emo ne, sehke ev hewşo te ye.
Abu Hanan, we are in Emo village, look, this is your
courtyard.
Hacarê me bîra gundê kir, em tên biniya xwe b'hewşê
derdikin.
You reminded us of the village, we come down to appear at
the courtyard.
Silav û rêz û hurmetê me ji muşahîdînê me, mutabî'înê me
gişta kar heye.
Our greetings, respect, and honor to our viewers, there is
work [hello] to all our followers.
Û wekî gotî, inşallah emê l'her derkî hebin, û inşallah emê
her derkî ji muwatinê xwa ra, dostê me ra, yê me mutaba'e
dike...
And as was said, God willing we will be everywhere, and God
willing everywhere for our citizens, for our friends, for
those who follow us...
Emê xizmet kin, emê bînin her mantiqok ji mantiqê Efrîn.
We will serve, we will bring [show] every region of the
Afrin region.
Eger yê me mutaba'e dike, yê bîra mantiqê Efrîn kirî,
inşallah emê çiqas mantiqê Efrîn heye, emê gî bera
bisewirînin û emê xizmet kin.
If one follows us, one who misses the Afrin region, God
willing, however much of the Afrin region there is, we will
film it all for them and we will serve.
Ehlen we sehlen b'muwatinê wara û b'laykê wa û mutaba'eyê
wa.
Welcome to the citizens there, and [thanks] for their likes
and their following.
Bes yoş, siwalekî ji te pirskim.
Just wait, I will ask you a question.
Keremke.
Go ahead.
Tu heq sêr dikî, te... min nezanî çoketî te wekî min e?
You look right, you... I didn't know, are your knees like
mine?
Yan ta dikin, te jî çoket wekî min hew kirî?
Or do you... have your knees also given up like mine?
Çokatî me herdûk jî wekî hev e cemaet, noko dê bînimo?
Both our knees are the same [bad], folks, shall we see it
now?
Heta noko kelak min e, min ne dî.
Until now, it is my side [that hurts], I haven't seen it
[the top].
Wekî min e?
Is it like mine?
Ye gidi dil bavdo ra, ger ne dor bin, sed bavdo ra lo
dinasînin.
Oh boy, hearts are giving up, if they are not around, a
hundred giving up won't recognize him.
Te dî?
Did you see?
Sehkin, saatêk e kelakê niştme, min nezanî kir... çoketî xwe
wekî min e.
Look, I've been holding my side for an hour sitting, I
didn't know... his knees are like mine.
Û dilî me û mutabî'înê me bûn ji va bera dorê.
And our hearts and our followers were [happy] because of
these surroundings.
Erê welle. Inşallah em tîn xizmet mutabî'înê xwa kin.
Yes, by God. God willing we can serve our followers.
Heke hemu kûntir nî jî wekî av kûntir xortik.
Even if all are older, even like this young guy.
Bi mera bin, noko vîdyoya nû xweş emê wara çêkin.
Let's go.
Stay with us, now we will make a nice new video for you.
Temam.
Okay.
Erê havalê me, me berê wara gotî, emkê noko şikat ne, kavnor
wa.
Yes our friends, we told you before, we are now at the
caves, ancient ones.
Av şikat no, emrê xwe kavnor ne.
These caves, their age is ancient.
Gellek ro diçî banê do ye, rêber nîzîk bike lextê.
It goes up a lot to the top, Reber bring it closer a bit.
Wa dî ye, hav şikat no emrê xwe... çar pênc sed sal zêdetir
heye.
You see, these caves... their age is more than four, five
hundred years.
Berê xelkê tê da dixevt, di se û da ne, salûn ne, gi tiştê
da heye. Noko bi me ra bin.
In the past people worked in them, there are clocks/niches
inside, salons, there is everything inside. Now stay with
us.
Şoxlê em kanibin têkevine, wara lexteno diçî şikatê
bikişînim. Bilind e lenû.
The work [is hard], if we can enter, I will go a bit to film
the cave for you. It is high, man.
Bi me ra bin cemaet.
Stay with us, folks.
Av... avo çûye biniya gundê Emo, Zinarê Înê vêra dibên.
This... this goes to the bottom of Emo village, they call
this Zinarê Înê (The Rock of Friday).
Were emman çi re jur were teswîr ke.
Come, let's go up, come film.
Erê havalê me...
Yes our friends...
Em rehet bîn. Em gihiştin binî gundê, noko emê helşine çe.
Let us rest. We reached the bottom of the village, now we
will climb up.
Bilind e, şola ez kanibim helkişme çe wara teswîr kim, pir
mewqa'kî xweş e çî gundê tar e.
It is high, if I can climb up to film for you, it is a very
nice location, it is the dark/shady side of the village.
Bini do jiyane, rêber were, roh bini bisewrîne.
Down there is life, Reber come, go film the bottom.
Of of of, bilind e bilind e, wû wû wû.
Oh oh oh, it is high, high, whoa whoa whoa.
Di bini do jiyane.
Down there is life.
Reber were le.
Reber come here.
Avo cî çi ye welle nizanim.
What this place is, by God I don't know.
Binî do.
Look down.
Welle cemaet vir fere heye, bes em nêwîrîn têkevinê
biserahetî.
By God folks, it is wide here, but we don't dare enter it
honestly.
Emê nêwîrîn têkevinê.
We don't dare enter.
Av havo yek li vir e, yek li darên odê jî...
Look here, there is one here, one at the trees of the room
too...
Belkî biçî, avderê qul bin.
Maybe it goes, that place might be holes [connected].
Were havo vî jî havo bike.
Come, do this one like this too.
Cemaet wekî we dî ye, yek di vir de jî heye, pir kûr e û pir
awa...
Folks as you saw, there is one here too, it is very deep and
very...
Gi dirinde... ni tişt ne çikirina nizanim.
All [kinds of] beasts... or whatever things they do, I don't
know.
Ev jî kavnor o, pir e. Diçî havro qul ne... çûye... a
nêwîrim têkevime yane, şevreşe.
This is also ancient, very. It goes, they are connected
holes... it goes... I don't dare enter, you know, it is
pitch black.
Tiş miş tê hebe?
Do you have anything [light]?
Mero tirsi na eyb e.
Don't be afraid, it's not a shame.
Bi mera ben noko ezê helkişim jor mehawle kem.
Stay with us, now I will climb up and try.
Dua jî mera bikin, leynî pir cî ginde çatine, pir bilind e.
Pray for us too, because the place is very steep/difficult,
it is very high.
Dua ji mera bikin, ez pêgîn me çe wara teswîr kim.
Pray for us, [so] I reach the top to film for you.
Reber were ez helkişim jor.
Reber come, I will climb up.
Dilî m'le dixe, dilî m'le dixe.
My heart is beating, my heart is beating.
Uff ye şkatek kûr e.
Oof, it is a deep cave.
Welle kûr e belkî didi bav dorê qul ne Abû Semîr, pir fere
ye.
By God it is deep, maybe two... the surroundings are holes
Abu Samir, it is very wide.
E.
Is it deep?
Yes.
Reber ko avo bike helkişim jor.
Reber, do that [point camera], I will climb up.
Cemaet dua ji mera bikin o, ez helkişim jor xoxatiriyekem.
Folks pray for us, I will climb up and say goodbye.
Ma'nî xatirê wa da, mera dua bikin, şole ti qaza çê nebin,
pir pîs e ciyê xwe.
Meaning with your leave, pray for us, that no accidents
happen, its place is very bad [dangerous].
Bi mera bin.
Stay with us.
Erê cemaet.
Yes folks.
Wekî we dî ye, Abû Semîr l'ko.
As you saw, Abu Samir is there.
Ev jî hevalê min e, Reber e.
This is also my friend, Reber.
Ev jî...
This too...
Cemaet vî derê berê av gitê da diçû, xelk dihat vî derê ber
avê.
Folks, in this place, in the past water used to go through
it all, people came here for the water.
Qîçikê me jî le ko daron one, i mar o sifre çê dikin.
Our kids are also there by the trees, they are preparing the
table [picnic] for us.
Em hel wer, emê fitûrê sibe bixwin.
We came up, we will eat breakfast.
Ez rehet bûm, rehet bûm nefesa min helkişiya.
I rested, I rested, my breath came back.
Avo telê bini gund e.
This is the hill of the bottom of the village.
Seke berê go av têr diçû, noko ge avê ma'serê... meqbezo.
Look where the water used to go through, now it is the water
of the press... the dam/catchment.
O gundê me ro l'dar û da mayî... dûr mayî.
Oh, our village stayed way over there... stayed far.
Cokî bilind e, a kê weru noko têk hav mê.
It is a high place, I will now enter it for you.
Havo yek l'vî derê şikat.
Here, there is one cave in this place.
Û ê din jî d'banê do ne, jor do ne.
And the others are at the top, high up.
Ard jî şil e.
The ground is also wet.
Maro keş xwa be.
May snakes be far [from us].
Erê havalê me.
Yes our friends.
Havo yek l'binê heye.
Here, there is one at the bottom.
Te dî ye? Yek kûr e.
Did you see? One is deep.
Eger tîrîk mera heba ezê biçûma.
If we had a light/flashlight, I would have gone.
Tîrîk mera tune.
We don't have a light.
Welle a nêwîrim, a nêwîrim tê herim.
By God I don't dare, I don't dare go in.
Bi tirs e, dilî m'le dixe.
It is scary, my heart is beating.
Off.
Oof.
Havo.
Here it is.
Weleh ne dîti şkatek veto çûyî dana.
By God, I have never seen a cave go down like this.
Hadî berê...
Come on, before...
Berê kafirno xelk, xelk çawa li vir dijî?
Oh you infidels [expression of amazement], how, how did
people live here before?
Bilind e, eleva kulekê hîna ne gihiştime jûr.
It is high, look at that hole, I haven't even reached the
top/inside yet.
Bi mir û bi helek gihîştime jûr.
With death and destruction [great difficulty], I reached the
top.
Erê hevalê me...
Yes, our friends...
Êêlşîm gihiştim jûr.
I finally managed to climb inside.
Xweçkê me yê roqetê lê konê, ooo bilind e.
Our tripod [camera gear], I'll set it here, oh it is high.
Erê binê çiqas bilind bilind.
Yes, look how high, high it is.
Heva hîna ne gihiştime... devê...
This... I still haven't reached... the mouth [entrance]...
Seke ser vê tehtê, îşaret hene, ooo vê jirniko.
Look at this rock, there are signs, oh [look at] this basin.
Wekî wadiyê.
Like a valley.
Li vê derê cemaet, av heye. Jirn.
Here folks, there is water. A basin.
Pir bilind e, hena nîvî me.
It is very high, here is half of us [halfway up].
Xweçkê me jî roqetê lê kone, ha bine.
I'll place our tripod here, look.
Dûr e, îro derê me ro çoyî dikişînin.
It is far, today we are filming our going/path.
Çiqas bilind e.
How high it is.
Pir bilind e. Gelî server gî çûyî nivîs kirine, nizanim.
It is very high. Folks, look how they have written all over
the top, I don't know.
Îşaret mîşaret nîn e çû ne.
There are no signs or anything left.
Xelkê...
The people...
Ser tehtê...
On the rock...
Ne min ra got...
Didn't I say...
Hezî çi didom e.
Whatever I continue [exploring].
Heva wekî... 'amûdekî ye di vê ortê da.
This is like... a column in the middle here.
Min got heva wekî 'amûdekî ye.
I said this is like a column.
Viro jî çiye nivîs kirine nizanim.
I don't know what they have written here either.
Reş... Reşo ye, Reşo ye navê xwe.
Rash... It's Rasho, Rasho is his name.
Heva kişan sal e? Salê hezar û neh sed û nod û neha.
Which year is this? The year one thousand nine hundred and
ninety-nine.
Xelkê pir tişt nivîs kiriye.
People have written a lot of things.
Ooo ser vê zimûrê jî nivîs kirine.
Oh, they have written on this ledge/corner too.
Pir kevnar e.
It is very ancient.
Hene, yek din hafê me ye.
Look, there is another one facing us.
Weleh bi tirs e, hela hilkişim.
By God, it is scary, let me climb up.
Hilkişandina hilkişim, heke çû... noka dakevim.
Climbing up, I will climb, if go... [but] how will I descend
now.
Qey ne de'an a jimar a bikin.
You all should pray for us.
Basmilah...
In the name of God...
Maşallah.
Mashallah [God has willed it].
Xelkê ro dize qif da nivîs kiriye.
People have written names in two rows/layers.
Gi nav ser nivîs kirine, pir kesayetî gihiştî vê derê.
They have written names all over it, many personalities have
reached this place.
Bine, ro sed dûr jûr nivîs kirine.
Look, they have written a hundred lengths up.
Kef qelemê darê nivîs kirine.
They wrote with wood pens/charcoal.
Devanê navê xwe nivîs kirine, hene, Xoşnav, Mirdne, ne diyar
e.
They wrote their names around here, look, Khoshnav, Mirdne,
it's not clear.
Pir pir pir...
Very, very, very...
Ser vira jî heger... wekî jirnikê...
On here too if... like a basin...
Darê çêkirine.
They made it out of wood [or refers to trees].
Gelî...
Folks...
Vê derê we nav nivîs kirine Ehmed, nizanim çîk.
Here they wrote names, Ahmed, I don't know what else.
Viro jî dixwaze... dora heywana... awî damê çêkirine.
Here too it looks like... for animals... they made that
barn/stable area.
Dîlîstin vê derê.
They played [or stayed] in this place.
Eh cemaet, yek di virdê jî heye, şola noka dê vêk çî kevim.
Uh folks, there is another one over here, now I will try to
enter this one.
We were teswîr kim we.
I will film it for you.
Hore hevalê min...
Here are my friends...
Ev jî ciyê din e.
This is another place.
Enîwrim dakevim.
I dare to go down.
Ha bine, pir e ewa.
Look, it is abundant/a lot, that.
Ev jî ciyê din e.
This is another place too.
Ha vo d'çî zerûrî înî de? Çi benî da?
What necessity brought them here? What stuck them here?
Kûr e, enîkim dakevim e. Hevo... başqey wa dî din e.
It is deep, I don't dare to go down. This... is different
from the others.
Wile vê derê jî kûl on e, kûr e.
By God, there are holes here too, it is deep.
Uff, nefes li min qut bî.
Oof, my breath is cut off.
Ciyê xwe jî pir pîs e.
The place itself is very dirty.
Ez zanim, çû ber heldikşîn çi vê şkatê, ez nizanim.
I know, how they climbed up to this cave, I don't know.
Ez zanim gûra, ez sivik im, bi zor zor hildikşim.
I know I am like a wolf, I am light, [but] I am climbing
with great difficulty.
Iş dokatina...
The work/problem is descending...
Do'a wel dî me bin.
May your parents' prayers be with us.
Bi me ra bin noka.
Stay with us now.
Hore hevalê me.
Here friends.
Ez ji vê banê dakatim, emrim tirsora.
I climbed up from this roof, I died of fear.
Dadî nefesa min çû qedî be.
Mom, my breath is gone, finished.
Bilind e, bilind e.
It's high, it's high.
Ha ta vda zicir fima heta dakevim.
Until here I struggled/suffered until I descend.
Ebine, oboo!
Look at that, oh boy!
Rabine me... ano doxre li hofê xwe girtiye.
Look at us... they took the straight path opposite them.
Pir bilind e.
It is very high.
Uff.
Oof.
Oy, tobe car din hilnakşime derê wina.
Oh, I repent, I will never climb places like this again.
Dinê jî şil e.
The world [ground] is wet too.
Dinê jî şil e, baran ewrî.
The ground is wet too, rain and clouds.
Wez bine.
Look at me.
Oooh.
Boş, ewa pol vêr jiy, awê xwe nivîs kirine.
Empty, that side over there too, they have written their
stuff.
Ser vê ta'tno.
On these rocks.
Qorana nigê min diçirifin.
By the Quran, my legs are trembling.
Vro kirine çi, Ebû...
What did they do here, Abu...
Fir Ehmed e, çîk e, ez nizanim.
For Ahmed, or whatever, I don't know.
Hêşta bixwînim, kesê nexwendî bixwînim, seke min nexwendî.
If I could read it yet, read for the unread [illiterate],
look I didn't read it.
Ha noka çûxso ew bîma.
Now [I wish] I was...
Poşman bîma.
I regret it.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Hêê.
Hey [calling out].
Hooo!
Hooo, were were, tu mûşahîdînê xwa bîne, were.
Hooo, come come, bring your viewers, come.
Ma emê çawa hûnê bikin, were çû emê bikin, were.
How are we going to do it, come, what are we going to do,
come.
Emî hatin, hatin!
We came, we came!
Yalla, yalla, bide 'ecele kin, 'ecele kin.
Come on, come on, hurry up, hurry up.
Tamam.
Okay.
Erê hevalê me, ban medike, dibê werin.
Yes my friends, he is calling us, saying come.
Çoyê vexwin, bi me ra bin, heta em dagerin jêr.
Drink tea, stay with us, until we go back down.
Qusûrê me efû kin, helkişîm tê... ji tirsora.
Forgive our faults, I climbed up... out of fear.
Erê hevalê me.
Yes, our friends.
Helkişim jûr weleh el'ezîm.
I climbed up, by God the Almighty.
Dilê min sekinî.
My heart stopped.
Me'ne xatire we da helkişim jûr, wexo kir xeteriyê.
Meaning for your sake I climbed up, I put myself in danger.
Weleh el'ezîm ne yûm ban, ne cam ne ban û helnekişim, pir
çetîn e.
By God the Almighty, neither for a day nor a glass nor a
roof would I climb, it is very difficult.
Barê rêk çû hebî, çû hildikşîn çi vê şkatê, ez nizanim.
Before there might have been a path, how they climbed into
this cave, I don't know.
Heta ez zanim emrê min, yanî gor emrê min, û gor yanî ez...
kes wekî min tines e...
As far as I know of my age, meaning according to my age, and
according... meaning I... there is no one like me...
Ez zû zû hilkişîme çiya.
I climb mountains very quickly.
Hilkişandin, te hilkişê qolayî ye.
Climbing, climbing up is easy.
Baş coxit kê dakeve, hele were dakeve, çû dakeve.
But when you have to descend, hey come descend, how to
descend.
Erşî me yê tek.
Our belongings are single/alone.
Bi me re bin, were em cema...
Stay with us, come let's join the group...
Malê me, em sekin hela çi dikin.
Our family, let's see what they are doing.
Erê milet, ez gihiştim cem mala me. Hemdillah ji Xwedê ra.
Yes people, I reached my family. Praise be to God.
Hemdillah ji Xwedê ra, hêşta muxamerato...
Praise be to God, yet the adventures...
Dike xolêk hêşta, tike natirse.
It creates a spin/dizziness still, it doesn't get scared a
bit.
Em sekin hela, malê me.
Let's see now, our family.
Êhê hê hê hê hê.
Ehey hey hey hey hey [Cheering].
Çi maro dikin havna?
What are you doing here to us?
Êêêê.
Eyyyy.
Çi kêf e lo?
What joy is this?
Hela 'Em Semîr, 'Em Semîr dididîso, de 'Em Semîr.
Hey Uncle Samir, Uncle Samir is seeing it, come on Uncle
Samir.
Ser serê min, 'Em Semîr û dêka Semîr, ser serê min.
On my head [You are welcome], Uncle Samir and Samir's
mother, on my head.
Wallah.
By God.
Viro jî Fatmê me çoyê çêdike.
Here too our Fatima is making tea.
Oooh.
Ebû Semîr te nago Hemdilha 'es-selamê, min xol xeteriyê
xist.
Abu Samir, you didn't say "Praise God for safety", I put
myself in danger.
Ser çava.
You are welcome [On my eyes].
Nêzî virdê be.
Get close to here.
Bi Quran egemrî me kincim e girt, harrî bî.
By the Quran, my life... was caught, it became muddy/ruined.
Baqir meke na, qirmik e, em kê çoyê çêkin, çoyê.
Don't shout no, it's wood/twigs, we are going to make tea,
tea.
Ah.
Ev jî... Ebû Semîr ê min e, sedelqê min e, ev jî... oho
ezingo tîne, saet xweş Ebû Semîr, saet xweş.
This is... my Abu Samir, my faithful friend, this is... oho
he brings firewood, well done Abu Samir, well done.
Merî kal bî... Merî kal bî, 'eyb milet.
Man has gotten old... Man has gotten old, it's a shame [in
front of] the people.
Dilê te ciwan bî ye, tu kal bî ye ha.
Your heart is young, [even if] you have gotten old, ha.
Xelk... Xelk qîmetê zane, em me dişînin qirmiko.
People... People know the value, we are sending ourselves
for twigs/wood.
Bes şolê qirmikê me ecibîne.
Just as long as they like our twig work.
E b'ecibînin. Çû te eciban dvirê, Mihemed te eciban.
They will like it. Why are you surprised here, Muhammad, you
are surprised.
Saeto taxo ji destê te sax be.
May your hour/time be good, bless your hands.
Ye de war dke...
Come on, put it down...
Ha, ez ê war dkim.
Here, I am putting it down.
Tamam hişta... bes mûşahdînî te ji b'ecibînin qirmikê.
Okay now... just as long as your viewers like the twigs.
E b'ecibînin, qabîl e, hecî heta qabîl, na d'bê her kes payê
xwe bînin.
They will like it, it is acceptable, Hajj untill acceptable,
not everyone has to bring their share.
Reşikî Eweş hebî, Şêx Reşîdê Be'dîno, mla 'ilmî muşadînî me
têda hebe.
There was a Black Ewash, Sheikh Rashid of Ba'din, let this
information be for our viewers.
Temî... dêka ginde... d'şand êzingo.
He ordered... the village mother... sent for firewood.
Ê Heyderê Zeynêbê, rasti Heyderê Zeynêbê lici ho... fiqêra
nikenî l'gre.
And Haydar of Zeyneb, truthfully Haydar of Zeyneb where...
poor guy don't laugh at him.
Halyo te'ban bî.
His situation was tired/bad.
Heyderê Zeynêbê ber 'alimo... gû Şêx Reşîd...
Haydar of Zeyneb before the scholar... said Sheikh Rashid...
Gû tzanî ez çû bkim pêş... êzingo xlos be.
Said do you know what I should do before... the firewood
runs out.
Gû ez d'jimro raw'stim Heyderê Zeynêbê w.
Said I challenge him, that Haydar of Zeyneb.
Heyderê Zeynêbê gû... Şêx Reşîd, tê hejde kevir, têkê kiziya
xwe, bibê herrê... ji dêka xoro, Heyderê Hebeşro.
Haydar of Zeyneb said... Sheikh Rashid, put eighteen stones,
tie your braid (kizî), take it go... from his
bush/mother(?), for Haydar of Habash.
Rabî Şêx Reşîd... hejde kevir krin, kizî, wilê xos br çû ji
dêka xoro îvorî.
Sheikh Rashid stood up... put eighteen stones, the braid,
and strictly went up and crossed over from his bush/cliff.
Ê Heyderê Hebeş gû, "Wero gû, la Şêx Reşîd, hevo çiye hevo?"
And Haydar of Habash said, "Come man, hey Sheikh Rashid,
what is this?"
Logo hşta... kêm nabe v'çoyê. Ezeng min kinê ro krno.
He said now... it won't be less than this. I prepared the
firewood.
Hmmm.
Me'ne... Me'ne tjmr'o zîbe m'kevr ştarno, kevirê cî
ştarnosin.
Meaning... Meaning the challenge was won, we broke the rock,
we break the rocks of the place.
Rabî Heyderê Zeynêbê... b'wê exlaqî... b'wê fenê... Şêx
Reşîd j'ezingo xlos krin.
Haydar of Zeyneb stood up... with that morality... with that
art... he saved Sheikh Rashid from the firewood [task].
War war, hûn kc m'tîn bbşînin... êzingo qurmiko.
Come come, you [plural] sit down... the firewood of twigs.
Helklî holmê çûm qurmiko, vê corê bes mlo mûşadînê me
b'ecbîne.
Anyhow I went for twigs, this time just so our viewers like
it.
Mlo Efrîn se şeş mlo qena ecbîne. Xora mdken, t'bê Ebû Semîr
kal bî ye, dşînin qurmiko.
So Afrin 36 [channel name?] likes it. They are making fun of
me, saying Abu Samir has gotten old, they send him for
twigs.
Dîsa j'ra tênê, avo ûştê xotrî mûşadînê me... ma'ne noka
kos'ek çow...
Again for you alone, this is for the sake of our viewers...
meaning now a glass of tea...
Em bera l'ser çêkin... xzmet... mûşadînê xwe bteb'înê xwo
bkin.
Let's make it on it [the fire]... service... do it for our
viewers and followers.
Saet xweş, dest sax bin Ebû Semîr, êşd.
Well done, bless your hands Abu Samir, live long.
Tamam, vir jî çoyê me d'kelê.
Okay, here our tea is boiling too.
Berê d'gotin...
Before they used to say...
Ha... Ew Ebû Semîr qirfik... hele ê wî lone... aqe n'ecbînin
wana.
Ha... That Abu Samir's twigs... look at those ones... they
won't like those.
To, ohoo.
Aqe wane na ecibînin, wane xwa dinyan.
They won't like those ones, those are very [old/bad?].
Xay, m' helklî hol, şonsê meriyo têna bîse.
Okay, anyhow, man's luck is just unfortunate.
Wilehî çû bike têna ye.
By God, whatever you do, it is unfortunate.
Wile Ebû Semîr...
By God Abu Samir...
B'tar û î nan e, qeh we noka bin.
With bread and this food, look at it now.
Tehur û reş xo krî, qaderê te reş e.
You made yourself obscure and black [dirty], your fate is
black.
Ê, qe kê bêxem xayo.
Yeah, well nevermind, okay.
Êwa, sûr biftilîn.
Yeah, turn around.
Saeto te xweş, û Xwedê te razî be.
May your hour be good, and may God be pleased with you.
Goze...
The pot [of tea]...
Ê çoyê jî çêbibe, bê qehwe jî çêbibe.
And the tea will be ready, let the coffee be ready too.
Saet xweş, saet xweş.
Well done, well done.
Saetî... ê çoyê çêdike jî xweş.
The hour... of the one making tea is also good.
Ê we giyo sax bin.
May you all be healthy.
Aw jî xzmet d'ke, û l'darona jî ftûr çêdikin, bê xde.
She serves too, and they make breakfast on the trees [in
nature], by God.
Noko no, amê mletî xwo gştkî 'ezîmet kin, dost û ehbabê xwo.
Right now, we are inviting all our people, our friends and
loved ones.
Û her yek... inşallah wekê gotî, çîçkê hû jî me ji bîr
mekin.
And everyone... God willing as said, don't forget us with a
small thing too [likes/support].
Qene be...
At least...
Da'm kin, na we?
Support us, right?
Ma da'm kin, vê qanatî da'm kin, em jî we da'm kin
b'cografya xwo, b'torîxa xwo.
Support us, support this channel, and we will support you
with our geography, with our history.
Û bavê Semîr... dbê silav û rêz, dîsa j'mûteba'înê tora. Ebû
Az...
And the father of Samir [himself]... sends greetings and
respect, again to all the followers. Abu Az...
Saet xweş Ebû Semîr. Kefû.
Well done Abu Samir. Kudos.
Saet xweş Ebû Azad.
Well done Abu Azad.
Eşî çayê dikelîne, çayê ser êr.
She is still boiling the tea, tea over the fire.
Her dilê we têra ye, emkê baxin, me nehsakın, bê darêjî çi
hazır kirine me ro.
If you still have the patience, look, don't judge us, look
at what they have prepared for us outdoors.
Rojî... me tıştî ew nîno, şevî mevî me nîno.
During the day... we don't have that [fancy] stuff, we don't
have dinner [vibes].
Em sibe derketin, me go emkê tıştê hemlê mal dexin, em kê
l'çolê bixon.
We went out in the morning, we said we would take whatever
is in the house, we will eat it in the countryside.
Ev fıturê mal e teb'en.
This is, of course, a home breakfast.
Me goşt moşt xorî nîno.
We aren't meat eaters [right now].
Me go tıştê on o, ê sibe l'çolê pir xweş e.
We said things like this, in the morning in the countryside,
are very good.
Evna mukelez ne.
These are appetizers.
Zeytûn...
Olives...
Zeyt, zeytûn.
Oil, olives.
Felafel, atûn. Eva germî çiye?
Falafel, black olives. What is this hot dish?
Germiya pincar a.
It is chard stew.
Eva germî gihiye? Pincar. Germiya pincar.
Is this stew done? Chard. Chard stew.
Ev atûnê me ne.
These are our black olives.
Ev jî dıbsî bîber a ye.
And this is pepper paste.
Zehmet ter a.
It is very spicy.
Moustî kemandî.
Curd balls.
Ev jî vir da mukelezatê me ne, fûl ne.
And over here are our appetizers, fava beans.
Eww, ya selam.
Oh, wow.
Dest xweş bin.
Health to your hands.
Samir.
Eww, sıfra roş û muşahîdînê te roşî.
Ooh, a bright table and bright [good] for your viewers too.
Saet xweş, saet xweş bî Şem-Semîr.
Bon appetit, bon appetit Sham-Samir.
Bi me ra ben, noka...
Join us, now...
Em çayê xwe jî çêkin.
We will make our tea too.
De ne germık e.
Come on, warm it up.
Wana çûye?
Where did they go?
Layka lêxin.
Hit the like button.
Layka lêxin? Ê eşt.
Hit the like button? Yes, exactly.
Ê lêxin, ê lêxin. Teqsîre nakin, cimatê me teqsîrê nakin.
Yes hit it, yes hit it. They won't fall short, our community
won't fall short.
Heta me jî lıkay..
Even us, the likes...
Dikin ê, iştîrak jî dikin.
They do it, yes, they subscribe too.
Maşallah ro germık e o.
Mashallah, the sun is warm.
Ma'ne, mutabeînê me...
Meaning, our followers...
Azîmet fıtur ke.
Invite [them] to breakfast.
Çaxê me nemînın.
Don't hold it against us.
Her yek zanê, çi tam... xwarinê l'çolê heye.
Everyone knows what a taste... food in the countryside has.
Em jî we teklîf dikin, em dibên hûn jî bîrin, bi me ra, bi
cimatê me ra muşarekê kin.
We invite you too, we say you should be here too,
participate with us, with our group.
Bi me ra xwarikın, bixon fıturî sıbê li ber zıravkê, li binê
gundiyê me.
Eat with us, eat the morning breakfast in the breeze, below
our village.
Her bijî Ebu Semîr, her bijî.
Long live Abu Samir, long live.
Ser ser û ser çava. Ellah razî bî wellah. Xwedê te
biwafqîne.
You are welcome [on my head and eyes]. God bless you,
really. May God grant you success.
Qenatê te pêş xîne.
May [He] advance your channel.
Û Xwedê, mutabeînê te û muşarekînê te...
And God, [may He increase] your followers and subscribers...
Bi bîst hezar ke.
To twenty thousand.
Û mutabeînê te jî mustehel ne, û tû jî mustehel e.
And your followers deserve it, and you deserve it.
Em hêvîdikin tu û mutabeînê xwe, hemû heval, l'ber vira
xwarikın.
We hope that you and your followers, all friends, eat here
together.
Û Xwedê te biwafqîne.
And may God grant you success.
Saet xweş. Her bijî Jıwaro.
Bon appetit. Long live Jwaro.
Bi me ra bin, emkê fıtur buxin. Dılî we têra ye, bîrin kerem
kin fıturî sıbê hev ra buxin.
Join us, we will eat breakfast. If you have the patience,
come, please, let's eat morning breakfast together.
Teb'en tıştî çayê me yû nîye, me şevî nîno yî.
Of course, our tea items aren't here [yet], we don't have
the dinner stuff.
Me go werû mılê ona be.
We said let it be just like that.
Wellah radî bin, xelkê mû radî bin.
By God, be satisfied, our people be satisfied.
Bi me ra bin heta çayê me çê dibe.
Stay with us until our tea is ready.
Mışkîlat tınne. Muwatınê xwa ra, tu dostê xwa ra, muşahidînê
xwa ra, rehet be... adî ye.
No problem. With your citizens, your friends, your viewers,
be comfortable... it's normal.
Êkê muğameratê xo lêxî êşta.
He will embark on his adventures now.
Vêkê bike qurpawa.
Make that one snap [open].
Cimat sıfra me cahêz bî viderê.
Friends, our table is ready here.
Sıfra me cahêz bî.
Our table is ready.
Bûrin, bûrin.
Come, come.
Dılî we kê têra ye, bûrin, emo ezîmet... fıturî sıbê dıkın.
Whoever has the patience, come, we are inviting... doing
morning breakfast.
Lı biniya gundê emo.
Below our village.
Hem ber zırarê yine.
We are also in the breeze/shade.
Bûrin, em bi hevra nanê xwe buxin.
Come, let's eat our bread [meal] together.
Ez jî em nanê xwe buxum.
I will eat my meal too.
Erê hevalê me, hev jî du xwarinê ra ye.
Yes friends, this is after the meal.
Fatma me ra qehwe ke, çêdike l'ser êr.
Fatma is making coffee for us, making it on the fire.
Qehwe ser êr, berê me wara gotîye, pır xweş çêdıbe, û rexwe
xwo zêde ye.
Coffee on the fire, as we said before, turns out very good,
and its foam is abundant.
L'çolê pır xweş e.
It is very good in the countryside.
Kerem kın, bîrin, dılî we têra ye, emkê vexwin.
Please, come, if you have the patience, we will drink.
Emo ezîmet dikin fîlcanek qehwe l'ber ovê. Biniya gundê emo.
We invite you for a cup of coffee by the water. Below our
village.
Ha kû, ooo, şixûl meriyet e.
Looking good, ooh, it's quality work.
Bınî qehwe rate viderê.
The coffee grounds came here.
Ooo.
Ooh.
Bêlê xweş çêbiye.
Yes, it turned out good.
Ha esîda.
Here is the "Asida" (thick coffee).
Bismillahirrehmanirrehîm.
In the name of God, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Saet xweş fîdan, saet xweş cîran.
Bon appetit Fidan, bon appetit neighbor.
Saet xweş, hûn ser sera hatin m'ezzet.
Bon appetit, you are most welcome [on our heads], dear.
Bas ma qehwe worte... divê qehwe worte vexe, divê rake
fîncanê, divê 'tızengîn' divê, rast e?
But when coffee comes... one must drink the coffee, one must
lift the cup, it must 'ring' [clink], right?
Da zengîn bibe, welle, he zengîn bibe.
Let it be rich/ring, by God, let it ring.
Em her dikin zengîn welle.
We always make it ring, by God.
Êjî worte bıbın?
Should they become that too?
Mula her e.
It's always [like that].
Mula êjî zengîn bıbın.
Let them become rich/ring too.
Ne wa dibên?
Isn't that what they say?
Bûrin cimat, werın vexun qehwe, b'me ra.
Come friends, come drink coffee with us.
Ono, ser vê çawirê, bes çawir hındık e qa, boronê lê
nekirîye.
There, on this grass, but the grass is sparse, it hasn't
rained on it.
Bes o, hışk e.
It's enough, it's dry.
Ooo!
Ooh!
Nihad!
Semîr, m'dî, Nazlı çibo kine da!
Samir, I saw, Nazli went into the [mud/water]!
Semîr! Semîr wer!
Samir! Samir come!
Nihad rone, wera!
Nihad stop, come!
Nazlı çî makîne da derke!
Nazli get out of the machine [likely referring to a vehicle
or pump]!
Nihad, roke!
Nihad, lift it!
Nihad de.
Nihad come on.
Cewze.
Walnut.
Vidarê... Fatma me yî sırbıgo dıke.
Over here... Fatma is gathering watercress [sırbıgo] for us.
Fatma, ma yî sırbıgo dıke.
Fatma is gathering watercress for us.
Haho het bındırêkirî, sırbıgo dıke.
Look, she rolled up [her sleeves/pants], she is gathering
watercress.
Fatma çi dıkey?
Fatma what are you doing?
Ez sırbıgo dıkım, sırbıgo.
I am gathering watercress, watercress.
Ma'ne em, pê cîpê s'poçke.
Meaning we [will eat/cook it], with stems and all.
Ere, hoy sırbıgo dıke vidarê. Sırbıgê avê ne.
Yes, she is gathering watercress over here. They are water
watercress.
Ê dorî.
Yes, wild ones.
Ev Semîr jî, ro lıko, ew jî qırmıkên xwe beraf dıke.
And Samir here, look at him, he is also rolling up his
sleeves/pants.
Ooo.
Ooh.
Lêx, lêx, zû dê, serî xonî xole.
Hit it, hit it, hurry up, [unclear: lift the head/top].
Ooo wadi ye, ev Semîr... qırmıkên beraf dıke.
Ooh it's a valley, this Samir... is rolling up his sleeves.
Rêber, saet xweş, saet.
Reber, bon appetit, health.
Elhemdu lillah, iştîya xweş.
Praise be to God, good appetite.
Welle elhemdu lillah.
By God, praise be to God.
Elhemdu lillah.
Praise be to God.
Ebû Semîr?
Abu Samir?
Elê, sehlê.
Hello, welcome.
Ha kerî me.
Here is our flock.
Ho darê jî, fîlcanê xwe qehwe jî duşun, emkê herın, noka
emkê ber mal herın.
And here, he is washing his coffee cup, we will go, now we
will go home.
Bi me ra bın, noka emê cısır jî wera darxın, cısrê asinî.
Stay with us, now we will show you the bridge, the iron
bridge.
Emê lextanê xweş lı wır jî çêkın.
We will create some nice shots there too.
Erê hevalê me, em noka hatın ber kupriyê, ev o kupriya
biniya avê, ayn hecerê, gundê me.
Yes friends, we have now come to the bridge, this bridge
below the water, Ayn Hajar, our village.
Rêber, lê bigre.
Reber, hold it.
Ev o pır kavnar e, vê kupriyê.
It is very ancient, this bridge.
Kuprik kavnar e.
An ancient bridge.
Ekîd zikrayatê şabo bi pır lı vra hene.
Surely the guys have many memories here.
Şabo, berê dıhatın vıdarê, vıdarê av têra dıhat. Cımat.
The guys, they used to come here, water used to flow here.
Friends.
Vıdarê berê av dıvra dıhat.
Water used to flow through here.
Mılat gıj Efrîn, ji Heleb, daro dıhatın xora vıdarê ziyaro.
People from all of Afrin, from Aleppo, from outside, used to
come here for visits/picnics.
Seke vê şînê, bes av hışk bîye, av namoy.
Look at this greenery, but the water has dried up, no water
remains.
Wînê xo tê warkın, ho!
They are recording themselves, look!
Ew na l'şîn ser kupriyê.
Those are on the green on the bridge.
Wînê xo tê warkın, m'aran.
They are recording themselves, hey guys.
Inşelle wûru rok germık e, derketiye.
God willing, today the sun is warm, it has come out.
Hevo reka Êsê ne, dıçû Heleb, dıçû gıdarê Şamê.
This is the Ese road, it used to go to Aleppo, it used to go
towards Damascus.
Em ro l'daro nebîn, cımat, bini vê çoyiyo no.
We are outside today, friends, under these trees.
Gundê me jî lıko l'jûr e.
And our village is there, up above.
Erê hevalê me, me wûru vîdyo xo xılos kır. Rıhla me xılos.
Emkê herın, ber mal herın.
Yes friends, today we finished our video. Our trip is
finished. We will go, go towards home.
Dınê sar dıbe qortıq.
The world [weather] is getting a bit cold.
Ma go, bîr nekin, dîsa layk û iştîrak me ro pêdınê.
We said, don't forget, give us a like and subscription
again.
Û xwestekê ke hene, me ro yazmîş kın.
And if there are any requests, write to us.
Tıştê em kanın, emê telebê wa, ew bıkın.
The things we can do, we will do your requests.
Ê em nıkanın jî, wekî dın, wînê qusırî me efkın.
And what we can't do, otherwise, forgive our shortcomings.
Bîr mekın layk û iştîrak, me ro pêdınê, û b'me ro bın
vîdyokî dın, xweş, hejar.
Don't forget like and subscription, give it to us, and be
with us for another video, good, humble.
Çavê wamo j'dıkım. Her bîjîn.
I kiss your eyes. Long live.
Wextê kaxizê destê min da, delîlê destê min da, ez çûme
mehkemê.
When the paper was in my hand, the evidence was in my hand,
I went to court.
Kete mehkemê, min nîşan da.
It went to court, I showed it.
Wexta te nîşan da, hakim çi got?
When you showed it, what did the judge say?
Got welle ev, ev senet e, ev tapo ye.
He said, by God, this, this is a deed, this is a title deed.
Ev ne kaxizek e, ev senet e.
This is not just a paper, this is a deed.
Ev senetê hikûmetê ye.
This is a government deed.