Arê hevalno, em îdarê, mala xwedê ava, xwelû...
Hey friends, today, may God build your homes, uncle...
Vê darê hewa şarha gund ye.
Here the weather is the village breeze.
Bawke, emê dakevin.
Father/Man, we are going down.
Emê nêzîkî bavin a.
We are getting closer.
Gista...
All of it...
Malê pê de be, bê raş e.
Step on the gas, let it go fast.
Cîcika me ye weke berê bibê, weş berê rintir jî bibê.
Our place is like before, in fact, it is even better than
before.
İnşallah, inşallah.
God willing, God willing.
Elhemdulîlah yanî nêm pir jî berê çêtir e.
Praise be to God, meaning the grace is much better than
before.
Milet gava gerî mala xwe.
When the nation returned to their homes.
Hewa sar bûye.
The weather has become cold.
Çetina cefayê gund, digerê çolê gi biçinin?
The difficulty of the village suffering, are they going to
harvest the whole field?
Bismillah.
In the name of God.
Gava xelî me? Erê?
Is the mud stuck? Yes?
Yanî camêr, miletê Ewropa tem vistan e.
Meaning man, the people of Europe are all [in] winter.
Ne rû rû ye, na vistan vistan e.
It's neither fully sunny/clear, nor fully winter.
Cama, xilas, avîn avîn e, mha kî dinê hejîrê bibin.
But here, that's it, summer is summer, a month form now the
figs will be ready.
Arê hevalno, hûn rû dîsan bi xêr hatin, vîdyokî xweş û
kîbar.
Hey friends, welcome back again, a nice and neat video.
Li vî darî, di biniya gundê Olkana.
Here, at the bottom of Alkana village.
Teben, hevalê dima jî me xwestine, ser telebê muşahîdînê me.
Of course, our friends asked for this, upon the request of
our viewers.
Gundê Olkana emkê vira bi sewrînin.
We will film the village of Alkana here.
Noh li vî darî jî, hember me gundê Hecîba heye.
Look, right here, opposite us is the village of Hajikan
(Hecîba).
Emî li mefreqê ne, emkê nuka dakevinê.
We are at the intersection, we will go down now.
Keremke.
Go ahead.
Spêde wa bi xêr hevalê me, hûn çawani, îşalla hûn baş bin.
Good morning friends, how are you, God willing you are well.
Sihet xweş, şalê hûn gî rind û rehet bin.
Good health, I hope you are all good and comfortable.
Arê îro dîsam ware hatin, vîdyokî xweş û kîbar.
Yes, today we came back, a nice and neat video.
Emkê ware darbazi gundî Olkana bin.
We will pass through to the village of Alkana for you.
Bi me ra bin, em darbasî gund bin, vîdyokî xweş kîbar em
çêkin.
Stay with us, let's enter the village, let's make a nice and
neat video.
Arê hevalno, teben mentîqê vir pir xweş e.
Yes friends, of course the area here is very nice.
Gundê Olkana.
Alkana village.
Hevalê min, lê bigir, nêzîk bike û hemberê jî gundê Hecîba
bigir.
My friend, capture it, zoom in, and also capture the village
of Hajikan opposite us.
Maşallah, cografî pir xweş e.
Mashallah, the geography is very nice.
Ev e cinet e.
This is paradise.
Hevalno, like û iştîrak me ra bide ne, hindik ma em deh
hezarî bigrin.
Friends, give us a like and subscription, little is left for
us to reach ten thousand.
Arê hevalno, hûr û dîsan bi xêr hatin, vîdyokî xweş kîbar.
Yes friends, welcome back again, a nice and neat video.
Li vî darê, di biniya gundê Olkana.
Here, at the bottom of Alkana village.
Teben, hevalê dima jî me xwestine, ser telebê muşahîdînê me.
Of course, our friends asked for this, upon the request of
our viewers.
Gundê Olkana emkê vira bi sewrînin.
We will film the village of Alkana here.
Noh li vî darî jî, hember me gundê Hecîba heye.
Look, right here, opposite us is the village of Hajikan
(Hecîba).
Emî li mefreqê ne, emkê nuka dakevinê.
We are at the intersection, we will go down now.
Arê hevalno, ev der jî, wira socha gund e.
Yes friends, this place, here is the center/street of the
village.
Di vir da jî derî vekeya, sehke her gundekî derîyek jî tê da
heye.
It opens a door through here too, look every village has a
door/gate in it.
Cam e, xozanê avê, derîb... yanî tiştek kevnar ne.
Glass/Window, water cisterns, paths... meaning they are
ancient things.
Bes nuka iste'mal nakin.
But they don't use them now.
Hewşê kevnar vir da pirin hevalno, gel vê hewşana.
Ancient courtyards are plenty around here friends, look at
these courtyards.
Hingî dîrok in, dîroka gundê kevnar in.
They are history, the history of the ancient village.
Dê de, hevalê min war çîçke nêzîk bike.
Come on, my friend come and zoom in a little bit.
Ha bin e.
Look at it.
Hîn gi dîrok tê da ne.
Still history is inside them.
Vê na va?
Look at this?
Berê gi dîrok bî, çû bî...
The stone that was history, was wood...
Ha vana dîrok ne, qolto pizrîn e, kevnar ne.
Look these are history, crumbling arches, they are ancient.
Walla gundekî kevnar e vir a.
I swear this is an ancient village here.
Arê vira orta gund e.
Yes here is the middle of the village.
Ehe.
Aha.
Afyapî, çiqas emrê wê kevnar e.
This structure, how ancient its age is.
Pişta xwe li dîwar dike.
She leans her back on the wall.
Arê emî li socha gund in.
Yes we are in the village square/street.
Xoltîk jî li simaqê tê, diçû simaq çinî.
Auntie is coming from [gathering] sumac, she went to pick
sumac.
Arê, bîye, xoltîk simaq bîye?
Yes, is it coming, Auntie is sumac coming [growing]?
Walla na bîyo, diçinin.
I swear no dear, they are picking it.
Diçinin na? Were ke bê çayî da îşte, hîn ne wext e.
They pick it, right? Come let's have tea then, it's not time
yet.
Wa da ber gundî xelkê Ereb ne, ev da man e, pak diçinin.
Those down below the village are Arab folk, they stayed
here, they pick it all clean.
Arê hevalno, vî derê...
Yes friends, this place...
Miş xoltîkê pirs kir, xoltîk dibê vî dîrokano kirnî ye.
I asked the Auntie, Auntie says this history is made [here].
Dibê berê çi mezin tina bî, vî dîrokano dikirnê.
She says before there were no large things [machinery], they
made these histories.
E noko jî ne betûn der çêbî ye, e av kirin, laxwe kirin.
And now that concrete has come out, they watered it down,
they canceled it.
Pir kevnar e.
It is very ancient.
Arê.
Yes.
Arê evê di şiqopê bar e. Maşallah.
Yes this is on the edge of the overhang. Mashallah.
Xoltîk, wela bin vir heye ne ke?
Auntie, there is really a foundation down here, right?
Bê, nemû wara qewm bûn wara.
Yes, no folks stayed here.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Wela...
I swear...
Hevalno bin e, berê qanter ma ona dikirin çiyav da, tedî ye?
Friends look, before they made arches like this in the
mountains, you see?
Hewşê kevnar hew no ne, ha.
Ancient courtyards are just like this, look.
Metirka ye, qolnbînî gund e.
It's abandoned, it's the pillar of the village.
Sê kî dîrok li pîşê min jî bûn.
Three histories [generations/eras] were before me too.
Xanî, xanî barbono gir dibin. Sûk a.
Houses, ruined houses become hills. It's a market/center.
Hevalî min were, o vir jî bigre, ha tedî ye?
My friend come, capture here too, look do you see?
Arê.
Yes.
E qene torîx ser hebe, ma e torîx zanî bo? Torîx li ser
tune.
If only there was a date on it, do we know the date? There
is no date on it.
Ecêb e torîx nekirine. Pir kevnar e.
It's strange they didn't put a date. It is very ancient.
Wa dî ye?
Did you see that?
Berê hewş go o no bîn.
Before, courtyards used to be like this.
Bê.
Yes.
Berê tinebîn bî, îşte, feqîre bîn bî.
Before there was nothing, you know, there was poverty.
Lê pere tinebîn.
There was no money.
Erê.
Yes.
Hemû genimê xwe, û mîj, û hejîrê xwe dikirin mol, ewa mûne
ye, xilas.
They would put all their wheat, and lentils, and figs in the
home, that was the provisions (mouneh), that's it.
U diçûn palîyo, diçûn...
And they went to harvest labor, they went...
Mîk berê go ax boxê dikirtin.
Before, like, they would do "Agas" and "Begs" [feudal
lords].
Bere gi de axê bî ne xoltîk?
Was it all Agas back then Auntie?
Bê, boxê dikirtin.
Yes, they acted as Begs.
E ez zanim vî derê çend kev in hene, kîlekî wan.
I know there are a few stones here, beside them.
Bê, boxê dikirtin îşte berê. Hembno gî boxê bîm, tegro biro
kirin.
Yes, they acted as Begs back then. They were all Begs, they
chased them away.
Em xirab kirin.
They destroyed us.
Kirin çiman.
They turned them into pastures/ruins.
Xoltîk tu xweş vê gundî ye?
Auntie are you originally from this village?
Her vê malê me.
This is my very house.
Yanî tî nefs eslî taş vê gundî ye?
Meaning you are originally native to this village?
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Ser serî min, ser çavê min ta. Bereke emr çax se xoltîk?
Upon my head, upon my eye [Respectfully]. A blessing, how
much is the age Auntie?
Emrî ye ta, emr, çend e?
Your age, age, how much is it?
Yemkin heftê ye.
Maybe it is seventy.
Maşallah, maşallah, hîn ti wekî piskilêt o ye, hîn ti sar
paye maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah, you are still like a bicycle
[fast/active], you are still on your feet mashallah.
Arê.
Yes.
Maşallah çî vir çax so hene ke?
Mashallah what things are here huh?
Yekî gi roş heleb o nî vir girt.
One black [snake/thing] caught here.
YPG?
Oh my God.
Ere, m halabonî girtin, irim bîn noqe xoy.
Yes, they caught/took the Aleppo [pine/area], they were
grapes inside.
YPG bî?
Was it YPG?
Ê.
Yeah.
Erê.
Yes.
Noq nî girtin.
They took/dug inside it.
Îrim?
Grape [vines]?
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Eywa.
I see.
Lê berê gi çû bû, em darin bêrûtê dar û dişxilîn, bare xarg
jî dihat liv derno dişxilî.
But back then it was gone, we go to Beirut and work, back
then people came here to work.
Erê min dişxûland.
Yes I worked.
Aha.
Dako hevalno mar bin, em sê lexto jî nov gund çêkin, waha
mala xolû jî.
Okay friends stay with us, let's make three shots inside the
village, and there is the uncle's house too.
Arê hevalno, emî derin mala xolû.
Yes friends, we are going to the uncle's house.
Vê darê hewa şarha gund ye.
Here the weather is the village breeze.
Aha.
Ha wo molo me ye.
Look that is our house.
Ha wo molo wa ye xolû?
Look that is your house uncle?
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Kîjan malbata we ye?
Which family are you?
Malbata xo... no harebine.
The family of... looking that way [referring to location].
Mala xo lî derê one ye.
Their house is over there.
Dûre.
It's far.
No, no, ha wo ber bê hecîba ye.
No, no, look that is facing toward Hajikan.
Ber bê hecîba ye.
Facing toward Hajikan.
Migo xolû dibê mala xorzî te ye.
I said uncle says it's your nephew's house.
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Migo xolû dibê mala xorzî te ye.
I said uncle says it's your nephew's house.
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Ev ci horata wa ye teben.
Yes.
This is your [family] line of course.
E wo horata ma ye.
That is our line.
Aha.
Çi boyî yene cemaatê xolû?
What wind [fate] brought this group uncle?
Em de boyî yene cemaatê.
We came with this group.
Xolû wala hewşê kevnar pir camêr da hene.
Uncle I swear there are many ancient courtyards in it man.
Arê hevalno, vê hewşnû jî wa dî ye?
Yes friends, did you see these courtyards too?
Çoqso hewşê kevnar tê da hene, torîxa xo jî mêj da ne, du sê
sed sol ne, pênc sed sol ne, em nizanin.
There are so many ancient courtyards in it, their history is
from long ago, two-three hundred years, five hundred years,
we don't know.
Çerx e Xalû?
Yes.
How is it, Uncle?
Welleh, wey pos bûye, pos bûye.
By God, it has become rubble, it has become rubble.
Ava wa?
This one here?
Na ey pos bûye.
No, it has become rubble.
Ka wer, hevalî min mirwar...
Come here, my friend...
Erê, xoka me Xedîca, merivî me yî mişkir bî, sefha bî nûvî
gindî ye, kî ye bi xoo ye, ez nizanim.
Yes, our aunt Khadija, she was a thankful relative of ours,
this is a page from the inside of the village, whoever wants
it, I don't know.
Erê, mala Xalû ev e, mala Weşma Qostî.
Yes, this is Uncle's house, the house of Washma Qosti.
Hewş kevnar e, bes kes tê tine.
The courtyard is ancient, but there is no one in it.
Hezar û neh sed û şêst û dudu.
One thousand nine hundred and sixty-two.
Tarîxê vê hewşê ya tîgirtin, yop e.
The date of this courtyard's construction, it is paved
stone.
Yopî qe pir kevnar e.
The paved stone path is very ancient.
Erê.
Yes.
Heva teb'an mala Bateway, tebîetê vir wane ye.
This is naturally the Bateway house, the nature here is like
this.
Erê.
Yes.
Ev nikanin pir jûr bigrin, yanî jûr ew tê danin.
They cannot build very high up, meaning they place the rooms
[low].
Heva zeytûnê xone, ev heva.
These are eating olives, these right here.
Evna zeytûnê xone?
Are these eating olives?
Ev simaqe jî yê xone?
Is this sumac for eating too?
Simaq jî yê xone.
The sumac is also for eating.
Zeytûn heta vê toximî zade kevin e wane.
The olives, even this seed, are very old like this.
E simaqê kî diçinin lê?
Who harvests the sumac here?
Ew Xorzêkî Gindor bira.
That nephew of Gindor took it.
Xorzêkî Gindor?
Gindor's nephew?
Wele î qurt û sûr dibe, î tirş dibe.
By God, it becomes condensed and red, it becomes sour.
Mm.
Erê, teb'an hewş e do kes tine.
Yes, naturally there is no one in the courtyard.
Ma hewş jî kes tê tine be, xerabe dibe.
If there is no one in a courtyard, it becomes a ruin.
A va serinc e.
And this is a cistern.
A va serinc e, wela av tê heye.
This is a cistern, by God there is water in it.
Mm.
Av tê heye.
There is water in it.
Li hewşo da hişta, heftokê tê da rûni manin, xera dibe.
Left in the courtyard, if a week passes without staying in
it, it gets ruined.
Bes meriv were heftokê tê da bişixul, ê dîsa gicî be wekî
berê.
But if a person comes and works in it for a week, it will
become lively again like before.
Bile şol nake.
But it doesn't work.
Erê, avo paş hewşê ye.
Yes, this is the back of the courtyard.
Avelim zeytûnê gindî jî bigre, wana dûr çêkirime.
Let me film the village olives too, I have framed them from
afar.
Xalû av li heye, vira jam we xalk bîrê lê dixin?
Uncle, is there water? Do people dig wells here now?
Bi Xwedê lê xistine, bes ava vir zeîf e.
By God, they have dug, but the water here is weak.
Heye bes zeîf e ne?
It exists but it's weak, right?
Heye, zeîf e.
It exists, it's weak.
Çiqas metre dar dikeve?
How many meters down does it hit?
Di heftê û pênc heta heştê da.
In seventy-five to eighty.
Wele maşalla hindik...
Well mashallah, that little...
Ê bes hindik o.
Yes, just that little.
Yanî têra wekî xertûmê dînamo...
Meaning enough for like a dynamo hose...
E wa têr e.
Yes, that is enough.
E nîmet e ke.
That is a blessing then.
Ev jî yê mala Birokî ye?
Is this also Biroki's house?
A vî li hewal li wê kî çîbî.
Yes, this one beside the one that was made.
A va mala Birokî ta ye.
This is Biroki's house of yours.
Ka wer em yawaş yawaş bimeşin.
Come, let's walk slowly.
Xalû gundî we pir bûn, yan mal bûn?
Uncle, were your villagers many, or were they households?
Gundî me? No, geh hatin e.
Our village? No, they came rarely/few.
Du mal nahatin e.
Not even two households came.
Em gel hûne li hal e bîn, ez jî li wul bî me hatim, em çûn
teb xowa bitin hatin.
We are with you in this situation, I also came from there,
we went and came naturally by ourselves.
Wele milet pir vegeriya Xalû.
By God, the people have returned a lot, Uncle.
Milet geh vegeriya, du mal gundî me man e.
The people have returned somewhat, two households of our
village remain.
Ew jî hewa rinde.
Even that is good.
E hewa rinde, Xwedê heye.
Yes that is good, God exists.
Wele cemaet, vê îdê em çûn, maşalla zehmet bî wek berê.
By God guys, this Eid we went, mashallah it was crowded like
before.
Pîroz gundî...
Blessed village...
Behdîno.
Behdino.
Ahlen we sehlen, Behdîno.
Welcome, Behdino.
Ser serê me.
Upon our heads (You are welcome).
Erê Xalû, xokê mero yê mişkirî, de em nizanin...
Yes Uncle, our thankful aunt, well we don't know...
Mero gû malbata me bi sebrînin, de evna haretê xone.
They said our family should be patient, so these are their
surroundings.
Sadik e bî ye? Pî ye?
Was it Sadik? His foot?
A vola li vî derî jî, teb'an em xalû mero hat, nav gund em
gerrîn.
Here in this place too, naturally Uncle came, we walked
inside the village.
Vêr dibên Ebasî sem, emî li ber malbata gind in e.
They call this the Abas of Sam (or similar name), we are in
front of the village families.
Saeto gind xweş, mero rehet kir.
The village hour is pleasant, it made one relaxed.
E wey xweş.
Yes, it is pleasant.
O tey xweş.
And yours is pleasant.
Ev xertûmê jî yê xorzî te ye.
Is this hose also your nephew's?
Yê xorzî te ye, avê didê malbato.
It is your nephew's, giving water to the family.
Erê de av wena hebe nîmet e.
Yes, if there is water like this, it is a blessing.
Xalû te çi silavê dişînî ji milet ra?
Uncle, what greetings do you send to the people?
Lawo milet da inşalla bi xêr û selamet bê, û her kes vegere
gundê xwe, û inşalla...
Son, may the people come in goodness and safety, God
willing, and everyone return to their village, and God
willing...
Û Elhemdule şên bikin.
And Alhamdulillah, make it lively.
Elhemdule şên bikin, û weke berê bibe.
Alhamdulillah make it lively, and may it become like before.
Çîçik maye weke berê bibe, û ê ji berê rintir jî bibe.
Just a little remains for it to become like before, and it
will become even better than before.
Inşalla, inşalla.
God willing, God willing.
Elhemdule yanî em pir ji berê çêtir e, ana milet geh vegerî
mala xwe, elhemdule.
Alhamdulillah, meaning we are much better than before, now
people have returned somewhat to their homes, Alhamdulillah.
Yo şaş e çê bibe.
It will be made right.
Inşalla, inşalla.
God willing, God willing.
Sabir, sabir gerek e.
Patience, patience is needed.
Na we Xalû.
Not like that, Uncle.
Erê wela.
Yes, by God.
Erê a vona hewa tebîetê vê gindî ye.
Yes, this is the nature of this village here.
Gindî Olkana.
Alkana village.
Wela Xalû gotin namiro kirin dilê mi pê şewitî, welahil
ezîm.
By God, Uncle, the words they spoke burned my heart with
pain, by God the Almighty.
Xedîca Bekir, Xwedê rehma xwo lê ke, ciyê xwo cinet be.
Khadija Bakr, may God have mercy on her, may her place be
paradise.
Ser serî me, ser çavî me, birakê gind e, malbatê gind e, ser
serî min e, ser çavê min e.
Upon our heads, upon our eyes, the brothers of the village,
the families of the village, upon my head, upon my eyes.
Xwedê rehma xwo lê ke, û ciyê xwo ji cinet be.
May God have mercy on her, and may her place be paradise.
Wela Xalû gotin nemiro ardû, ne pirr tesîr bîm pê.
By God, Uncle, the news of the death came, I was very
affected by it.
Erê wela, ka wer heva wulin wer.
Yes, by God, come here, come this way.
Ba vî derî jî teswîr kem.
Let me film this place too.
Gundikî pir xweşikî bor e.
It is a very beautiful village over there.
A velim avê ro rind derxîne.
Let me bring out this [shot] well.
A velim ma berê wera wago, hem ber ma gundî hebû ye, ma
gavodînî wera wago.
Look, as I told you before, it was a village of
livestock/herdsmen, as I told you earlier.
Gind pir ne mezin e, çûçik e.
The village is not very big, it is small.
Heva teb'an seh e.
This is naturally a courtyard/clearing.
Avê yolî bû.
The water was coming this way.
La Îlahe Îlallah.
There is no God but Allah.
A gilê, hişta avê, av difûre derê, li cîranê balo dikin avê.
Look guys, the water is still here, water is spurting out,
the neighbors look after the water.
Aman, aman.
Oh my, oh my.
Erê tebîetê vir pir xweş e.
Yes, the nature here is very pleasant.
Awa gikirna vî derê, derî veke çiye.
This place they made, open the door, what is it.
Cuxrafî vir pir xweş e.
The geography here is very pleasant.
Bes serê xo qit e qit.
Just its peak is very steep/isolated.
Va kora kê xo qit e.
Look where it is isolated.
Xalû hênik e vî ser sîkê?
Uncle, is it cool on this shade/corner?
Ahlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Erê wela, ciyê Xalû hênik e.
Yes by God, Uncle's place is cool.
Lê wela, ew ma jî nêtê me sikiniye, me go hinekî dilopiyê
bibînim.
Oh by God, our internet has stopped too, I said let me see a
little signal (droplets).
Dibê gundî Xelîl didin... mar û par û...
They say Khalil village gives... snakes and shares and...
[unclear idiom or context about connection].
Înternet?
Internet?
Aaa, sikiniye.
Yea, it has stopped.
Lê hişta bi du sê ro, la qeçkê ma telefon dikin, darî hişta,
gerek dibe.
But still for two or three days, our girls call, trees
still... it is needed.
Ê qeçka mal dar vo jiyan e, la...
The daughter of the house lives abroad, oh...
Heleb jiyan e, Efrîn jiyan e.
Living in Aleppo, living in Afrin.
E tu çi silavê dişînî ji qeçka ro, qeçkê xo ra?
And what greetings do you send to the girls, to your
daughter?
La de Xwedê silavo, aş... qeçkê xo giya dikim, saeto xo
xweş.
Oh may God [give] greetings... I [send] to all my girls, may
their time be pleasant.
Ya giya xweş, o wa jî xweş.
Everyone's pleasant, and yours is pleasant too.
O tey xweş Xalû.
And yours is pleasant, Uncle.
Lê hişta... ahlen wa sehlen.
But still... welcome.
Maşalla tebîetê vê gindî pir xweş e Xalû.
Mashallah the nature of this village is very pleasant,
Uncle.
Lê rind e, rind e ko ni bar e.
Oh it is good, it is good that it's not a burden.
Gindî ma na zota ye wagû... gundekî... sae çap e.
Our village is not rough like... a village... the hour is
left/wrong [idiom].
Gû gundekî rind e ka.
Saying it is a good village, indeed.
E rind e, erê.
Yes it's good, yes.
Bes ne mezin e, teqrîben sed mal heye?
But it is not big, are there approximately a hundred houses?
Teyna dikim mino firs nekir.
I suspect I didn't count/opportunity.
De em biçin.
Let us go.
Me got, hewşo ma, me qahwe...
We said, our courtyard, we [drank] coffee...
No şikune lê, me wa ne...
No it's broken/done, we are not...
Mişkla, mero nizane, rêko nizane, mero wekî yê, xerîb xarîb.
The problem is, one doesn't know, doesn't know the road, one
is like, strange stranger.
Em nizanin şar'ê xo çûne.
We don't know where its streets went.
Eqa yê Xalû jî bi emr mezin e, qa ya bixora tim nagerrînim.
And Uncle is old in age, I won't drag him around with me all
the time.
Şab bike ka bo...
Look at this...
A vona, hêşta vê gundê, rêka xwe çîçkê ona çetin e, zanî?
Look at this, still this village, its road is a little
difficult now, you know?
Hene kim xo şar'o ra bardim.
So that I don't drop myself off the street/path.
Pir mal hene dar naketin wela, minê qusûrî efû ken.
There are many houses I didn't get into/film, by God,
forgive my shortcoming.
Gelek meselen, mal o gi di jêrdana.
Many for example, the houses are all downwards.
Mero hare ro jêr jî...
If one goes down too...
Wela maşalla pir gundekî kevnar e.
By God, mashallah it is a very ancient village.
Seke vê yopê jî kevnar e, pir kevnar e.
Look at this paved path, it is also ancient, very ancient.
Dibînî?
Do you see?
Olkana û Gundê Hembo, hemû wekî li ser hev dikeve.
Alkana and Hambo Village, they all seem to fall on top of
each other [same line].
Ew Gundê Xelîl bû.
That was Khalil Village.
A volîm dilav to poş vo jî li gind bigir.
Let me capture the back part of the village too.
Ev gundana tebayê nehiyê Mabata ne.
These villages are subordinate to the Mabata sub-district.
Erê.
Yes.
Deh kîlometre pêva dûr e, ji Mabatê va.
It is ten kilometers far away, from Mabata.
De baş e dayê, ev karê ku tu dikî çiqas wextê te digire?
Alright mother, how much of your time does this work that
you are doing take?
Welle kurê min, ev kar hinekî bi zahmat e.
Well my son, this work is a little difficult.
Car heye em mehekê pê va mijûl dibin heta ku xelas dibe.
Sometimes we are busy with it for a month until it is
finished.
Heke karê me yê din hebe, hêj zêdetir dikişîne.
If we have other work, it takes even longer.
Yanî sebra we gelekî fireh e maşallah.
That means your patience is very immense, mashallah.
Ee, mecburî ye. Heke sebir tunebe, ev kar naçe serî.
Yes, it is out of necessity. If there is no patience, this
work will not succeed.
Te got ev têşî ye, ne? Tu çawa vê badidî?
You said this is a spindle, right? How do you spin this?
Ahan, binêre. Em herî pêşî hiryê tînin.
Aha, look. First of all, we bring the wool.
Em hiryê dikin rîs, paşê em dikin ben.
We turn the wool into thread, then we make it into yarn.
Rengên wan jî gelek xweşik in. Hûn van rengan çawa çêdikin?
Their colors are also very beautiful. How do you make these
colors?
Berê me bi giyayên çiyê reng dikir.
Before, we used to color them with mountain herbs.
Lê niha em boyaxê ji bajar dikirin, hazir tînin.
But now we buy the dye from the city, we bring it ready-
made.
Ciyawazî heye di navbera ya berê û ya niha da?
Is there a difference between the old kind and the current
one?
Belê, helbet. Rengê giyayê xwezayî saxlemtir e.
Yes, certainly. The color of the natural herb is healthier.
Ew qet ranabe, heta sed salî jî dimîne.
It never fades, it stays even for a hundred years.
Maşallah. Ev çanda me ya kevnar e, divê em biparêzin.
Mashallah. This is our ancient culture, we must protect it.
Rast e. Lê keçên niha zêde hez ji vî karî nakin.
That’s true. But the girls of today do not like this work
much.
Dibên destê me diêşe, pişta me diêşe.
They say our hands hurt, our backs hurt.
(Dikenê) Rast e, hinekî nazik bûne.
(Laughs) It is true, they have become a little delicate.
De fermo, em hinekî bêhna xwe vedin. Çay jî hazir e.
Come please, let us rest a little. The tea is ready too.
Zor spas dayê, te zahmat kişand.
Thank you very much mother, you went to trouble.
Na kurê min, çi zahmetî? Kêfa me bi mêvana tê.
No my son, what trouble? We are happy with guests.
Av û hewayê gundê we jî gelekî xweş e.
The water and air of your village are also very nice.
Meriv li vir pîr nabe.
One does not get old here.
Welle hewa xweş e, lê jiyan hinekî zor e zivistanê.
Well the air is nice, but life is a little hard in the
winter.
Rê tê girtin ji ber berfê.
The road gets closed because of the snow.
Rast e, zivistana vir dijwar e.
That is true, the winter here is harsh.
Kerem ke, ev çaya kekotî ye.
Help yourself, this is thyme tea.
Dest xweş. Bêhna wê gelek xweş tê.
Health to your hands. It smells very good.
Noşî can be.
Bon appetit (May it be health to your soul).
Dayê, tu ji kengî va li vî gundî dijî?
Mother, how long have you lived in this village?
Ez li vir hatime dinê, li vir mezin bûm.
I was born here, I grew up here.
Bav û kalên me hemû li vir bûn.
Our fathers and grandfathers were all here.
Tu qet neçûyî bajar ji bo jiyanê?
Did you never go to the city to live?
Na, ez nikarim li bajar bijîm.
No, I cannot live in the city.
Li bajar bêhna min teng dibe.
In the city, I feel suffocated (my breath gets tight).
Çima? Ji ber qerebalixê?
Why? Because of the crowd?
Belê, hem qerebalix e hem jî dikan û xanî li ser hev in.
Yes, both it is crowded and the shops and houses are on top
of each other.
Li vir em azad in, çavê me vekirî ye.
Here we are free, our eyes are open (we have a view).
Rast e, mirov li vir hîs dike ku zindî ye.
True, one feels that they are alive here.
Ka em hinekî behsa wan hekîban bikin dîsa.
Let us talk a little about those saddlebags again.
Ev nexşên li ser wan, wateya wan çi ye?
These patterns on them, what is their meaning?
Her nexşek çîrokek e kurê min.
Every pattern is a story, my son.
Ev nexşê hanê, ev nîşana çiyayên me ye.
This pattern here, this is the sign of our mountains.
Û ev jî nîşana çemê me ye ku di gund ra derbas dibe.
And this is the sign of our river that passes through the
village.
Gelek balkêş e. Yanî hûn xwezayê dinexişînin ser xalîçan.
Very interesting. Meaning you embroider nature onto the
carpets.
Belê. Tiştê em dibînin, em wî çêdikin.
Yes. The thing we see, we create that.
Gelo ev huner derbasî nifşên nû dibe?
Is this art passing to the new generations?
Welle kêm e. Hêvîya me ew e ku wenda nebe.
Well, it is scarce. Our hope is that it does not get lost.
Em jî hêvîdar in.
We are hopeful too.
Heke hûn bixwazin, ez dikarim nîşanî we bidim ka em çawa nan
dipêjin jî.
If you want, I can show you how we bake bread too.
Welle dê gelek baş be. Nanê tenûrê ye?
Well that would be very good. Is it tannour bread?
Belê, nanê tenûrê ye. Me hevîr kiriye, hazir e.
Yes, it is tannour bread. We have made the dough, it is
ready.
De ka em herin binêrin.
Come let's go and see.
(Dengê meşê û guhertina cih) Em niha hatin ber tenûrê.
(Sound of walking and location change) We have now come to
the tannour.
Germiyek gelek xurt jê tê.
A very strong heat is coming from it.
Belê, divê tenûr baş germ bibe daku nan xweş be.
Yes, the tannour must get hot well so that the bread is
good.
Keça min, ka wî hevîrî bide min.
My daughter, give me that dough.
Destê te neşewite dayê?
Won't your hand get burned, mother?
Na, em hîn bûne. Çermê destê me stûr bûye.
No, we are used to it. The skin of our hands has become
thick.
(Temaşe dike) Tu çawa wisa zû li dîwarê tenûrê dixî?
(Watching) How do you slap it on the tannour wall so
quickly?
Ev tecrûbe ye. Salên dirêj e em vî karî dikin.
This is experience. It is for long years that we do this
work.
Bêhna nanê teze mirov serxweş dike.
The smell of fresh bread intoxicates a person.
Kerem ke, ev nan ji bo te ye. Germ e, hay jê hebe.
Here you go, this bread is for you. It is hot, be careful.
Gelek spas. (Dixwe) Welle tama wî nayê gotin.
Many thanks. (Eats) Honestly, its taste cannot be described.
Li bajêr nanê wisa tune ye.
In the city, there is no bread like this.
Nanê bajêr hemû bi makîne ye. Ev bi dest û dil e.
The city bread is all by machine. This is by hand and heart.
Rast e. Dilê dayikê tê de ye.
That's true. The mother's heart is in it.
Xwedê rizqê hemûyan bide.
May God grant sustenance to everyone.
Amin. Dayê, zarokên te çend in?
Amen. Mother, how many children do you have?
Pênc kur û sê keçên min hene.
I have five sons and three daughters.
Hemû zewicîn e, çûne malên xwe.
All are married, they have gone to their own homes.
Hemû li vî gundî ne?
Are they all in this village?
Hinek li vir in, hinek li Duhokê ne.
Some are here, some are in Duhok.
Tên serdana te?
Do they come to visit you?
Belê, her Înî û Şemî tên. Mala me tijî dibe.
Yes, every Friday and Saturday they come. Our house gets
full.
Xwedê wan bihêle. Kêfa te bi neviyan tê?
May God keep them. Do you enjoy the grandchildren?
Ooo, neviyên min canê min in. Ez ji wan pirtir hez dikim.
Oh, my grandchildren are my soul. I love them more.
Dibêjin "Gûz şîrîn e, kakil şîrîntir e."
They say "The walnut is sweet, the kernel is sweeter."
Aynen wisa ye. Ew kakil in.
It is exactly like that. They are the kernels.
De baş e dayê, emê niha berê xwe bidin bexçê we yê hinarê.
Alright mother, we will now head towards your pomegranate
orchard.
Min bihîst hinarên vî gundî navdar in.
I heard the pomegranates of this village are famous.
Belê, hinarên me tirş û şîrîn in. Avdar in.
Yes, our pomegranates are sweet and sour. They are juicy.
(Dimeşin) Rêya bexçe dûr e?
(Walking) Is the way to the orchard far?
Na, li jêra gund e. Pênc deqe ye.
No, it is at the bottom of the village. It is five minutes.
Xweza li vir gelekî xweşik e di payîzê de.
Nature is very beautiful here in the autumn.
Payîz xweş e, lê darên me pelên xwe diweşînin.
Autumn is nice, but our trees shed their leaves.
Ev darên çi ne?
What trees are these?
Ev gûz in, û ewê jêr jî sêv in.
These are walnuts, and those further down are apples.
Berhemê îsal çawa bû?
How was the harvest this year?
Şikir, ne xirab bû. Lê av kêm bû îsal.
Thanks (to God), it wasn't bad. But water was scarce this
year.
Kêmbûna avê tesîr li fêkî kir?
Did the lack of water affect the fruit?
Belê, hinekî biçûk man.
Yes, they stayed a little small.
Lê tama wan?
But their taste?
Tama wan şêrîn e, pirsgirêk tune.
Their taste is sweet, there is no problem.
Me got hinar. Em gihîştin?
We mentioned pomegranates. Have we arrived?
Ahan, ev in darên hinarê. Binêre çawa sor bûne.
Aha, these are the pomegranate trees. Look how red they have
become.
Maşallah, wekî laliyan dibiriqin.
Mashallah, they are shining like rubies.
Ez dikarim yekî jê bikim?
Can I pick one?
Kerem ke, hemû para te ye.
Help yourself, it is all your share.
(Hinar vedike) Rengê hundirê wê jî ecêb e.
(Opens pomegranate) Its color inside is also amazing.
Dayê, tu ji van hinarên tirşava jî çêdikî?
Mother, do you make pomegranate molasses from these too?
Belê, em her sal dema hinarên mezin çêdikin.
Yes, we make it every year during the big pomegranate
season.
Em dikelînin heta dibe wek dimsê.
We boil it until it becomes like molasses.
Ew gelek bi feyde ye bo nexweşiyan.
That is very beneficial for sicknesses.
Bo dil baş e, bo mîdeyê baş e.
It is good for the heart, good for the stomach.
Destên we sax bin. Hûn xizmetek mezin dikin.
May your hands be healthy. You are doing a great service.
Berî em xelas bikin, gotinek te ya dawî heye?
Before we finish, do you have a last word?
Ez silavan li hemû temaşevanan dikim.
I send greetings to all the viewers.
Bila werin gund, deriyê me ji hemûyan re vekirî ye.
Let them come to the village, our door is open to everyone.
Gelek spas dayê, bimîne di xweşiyê de.
Thank you very much mother, stay in happiness.
Eve gundê Fêrxarabê ye. Cihê kevin e, hemî cihê kevin e,
gundê xarabî ne.
This is the village of Ferxarab. It is an old place, they
are all old places, ruined villages.
Baş e, nexweş nîne.
It is good, it isn't bad.
Waşê, ka neçûye...
[Inaudible], it hasn't gone...
Baadînî, Baadînî...
Badini [dialect], Badini...
Tirş, tirş, tirş.
Sour, sour, sour.
Korê me yê, gundiyê me yê Baadînî, ka tirş e hevalno.
Our son, our Badini villager, look friends, it is sour.
Hevalno, simaq, bi rastî xaltîkê, simaq çiniye.
Friends, sumac, truly Auntie, she has picked the sumac.
Gelo hinek sor biye, hinek jî hêşîn e.
Indeed some has turned red, and some is green.
Ha vê tebhet, çîçikê... germê dikeve ser bigrin ê sor bibe.
Like this naturally, the bits... when the heat hits it, they
will turn red.
Se ke, hewa sor biye.
Look, this has turned red.
Cefayî gundî... Têkare çolê giyê biçine?
The suffering of the villager... Are they harvesting the
wild plants?
[Unintelligible]
Giyê bi meqesê diçinin, diçinin û tên mal jî, vê belena giyê
jê dikin, ha.
They cut the plants with scissors, they cut them and come
home too, they remove this wild part, look.
Cefayî xwe heye simaqê, tebhet gundiyê me Baadînî, ticaretê
tirşê gişt gundiyê Baadînî dikin, ha.
Sumac has its suffering, naturally our Badini villagers, all
the Badini villagers do the sour [sumac] trade, look.
[Unintelligible]
Sivik e jî, sivik e simaq.
It is light too, sumac is light.
Xwedê Badînî biren biren.
May God take the Badinis, take them.
Tenê di germa... neçinin, sibe, xelk diçine yara.
They don't just pick in the heat... in the morning, people
pick it, dear.
Diziya pir dikin.
They steal a lot.
Eve me'neya malbiniya xweziyanabû.
This means the domesticity was desirable.
Biniya xweziyan çi ku serê Ebû Hesen nîne.
What desire is there when Abu Hassan is not around.
Erê.
Yes.
Sebaqê bigre, lê bigre.
Hold the basket, hold it there.
[Unintelligible] hewşê Ebdule...
[Unintelligible] courtyard of Abdullah...
Wele kevnar ne.
By God, they are ancient.
Oho, çi çîçekin xaltîkê çûne. Ha vê...
Oho, look at the flowers Auntie went to. Look at this...
Hevalno, ha vê sarnic e.
Friends, look, this is a cistern.
Se kine, sarnic e.
Look, it is a cistern.
A vê xwe hênik be.
This must be cool.
Maşallah, baba, maşallah sê metro kûr e.
Mashallah, man, mashallah it is three meters deep.
Ha vê tebhet hana, vêr tben...
Look this is naturally here, they call this...
Çawa ye? Ez ê sotelekê bifeletînim ha.
How is it? I will drop a stone/pebble, look.
Gihiştê.
It reached [the bottom].
We de lûyî me, we de ber sarnicê.
Come here, come to the cistern.
Se ke, hewa karê zemanê berê ye ho.
Look, this is work from the old times.
Bê şambê, bê têkelê, me'nî gemar nebe.
Without cement, without mixture, meaning so it wouldn't be
dirty.
Lê?
really?
Hevalno, wesen, se kin ava hênik e. Bîsmîllah.
Friends, wait, look the water is cool. Bismillah.
Bîsmîllah. Ke bixwe lûyî min, êş?
Bismillah. Here drink, my dear, okay?
Maşallah, ayn buz buz.
Mashallah, just like ice, ice.
Erdê gewr e, hin vaxa... vaxa.
The ground is whiteish, look here... look.
Erdê gewr e û kûr e, hênik e, lûyî min veke, ha, avî berda.
The ground is whiteish and deep, it is cool, look my dear,
look, the water flowed.
E, boş kine.
Eh, empty it.
Erê hevalno, vederê hewş, hewşa pir kevnar di vederê Sûriyê
da hene.
Yes friends, here is a courtyard, there are very ancient
courtyards here in Syria.
Bes pir jî xarab bûye.
But it is also very ruined.
Vê darbe lê ketine, voo...
This blow struck it, whoa...
Wele kevnar e, emrê xwo çiqas e?
By God it is ancient, how much is its age?
1325.
Emrê vê hewşê 1325 e.
The age of this courtyard is 1325.
Yazî jî ser heye, mişkîne, xwendina me tne mişkîla.
There is writing on it too, it's a problem, our reading is
not there [to read it], it's a problem.
Yazî bi Erebî ne, lefzê xwo jî bi Tirkî, bi Ermenî ye.
The writing is in Arabic, but the pronunciation is in
Turkish, in Armenian.
Ermenî ye, ne?
It is Armenian, isn't it?
Yazî bi Erebî ye, bes lefzê gundî bi Ermenî ye.
The writing is in Arabic, but the language of the village is
Armenian.
Ha, wunû. Pir kevnar e emrê gund.
Aha, like that. The age of the village is very ancient.
Hevalno, ev dî hewş xirab bûne, zîlzokê wisa kirine, darbe
lê ketine, çûbûne, zanim.
Friends, look the courtyards are ruined, the earthquake did
like this, blows struck them, they are gone, I know.
Na, heram e vê hewş no.
No, it is a pity/sin for these courtyards.
Hewşê kevnar, ji cîranê mara naxweş.
Ancient courtyards, from the neighbors [unintelligible].
Ev tebeqe jî kevnar, ev jî heşfîlik e.
This floor is also ancient, this is also 'heşfîlik' [stone
type/measurement].
Heşfîlik?
He.
Yes.
Wele min pê bîst e heşfîlik.
By God, I heard it is twenty 'heşfîlik'.
Ew jî kevn e, ew jî poz vî de hedimiye.
That is also old, that nose/corner over there has collapsed.
Ew jî kevnar e? Ha welle em ê vê hewşê jî bigrin, pir kevnar
e ev jî.
Is that also ancient? Look, by God, we will film this
courtyard too, this is very ancient too.
Binêre, sehne kirine, hewşê berê çawa çêkirine.
Look, they made a view, how they built the courtyards of the
past.
Binêre, sehne kirine.
Look, they made a view.
Ev...
This...
Ayet.
Verse [Quranic].
Eywa. Yabê, ow na dinêrin vederê, tê be wan sehne kirine,
sehne.
Yes. Man, oh look here, you'd say they made a scene/view, a
scene.
Ho, belê sehne tê dîtin, bes ew şikestiye.
Oh, yes the view is visible, but that is broken.
Mm, sehne kirine wekî menzer.
Mm, they made a scene like a view.
Vê gundê teqrîben bîst mal hatine, bîst mal hatine. Ê din jî
nehatine, yanî sê rûbêkê hewşa xirabane.
Approximately twenty families have come to this village,
twenty families have come. The others haven't come, meaning
three-quarters of the courtyards are ruined.
Wa dî ye?
Is that right?
Vê hewşnê kevin, tarîxa xwo pênc sed sal ne, şeş sed sal ne.
These old courtyards, their history is five hundred years,
six hundred years.
Nagihêjine wana xirab bibin?
Shouldn't they reach ruin [given the age]?
Wero sê sehne kirine.
Look, they made three scenes/views.
Ev jî sê sehne kirine wekî wana menzerî çêdikirin.
They made three scenes here too, like how they used to make
views.
Bes sehne jê ketine.
But the scenes have fallen off.
Ev şi'arê...
This emblem/slogan...
Ev şi'arê gundiyê, aceb hewa çi ye?
This is the emblem of the villagers, I wonder what this is?
Heva Allah, şûra Xwedê, Allah yani.
This is Allah, the wall of God, Allah basically.
Navê Xwedê yê nivîskirine.
They wrote the name of God.
Allah.
Erê. Her malek Kurmanca, her malek Kurmanca ayet tê da hene,
hewşê kevnar.
Yes. Every Kurmanji house, every Kurmanji house has verses
in it, the ancient courtyards.
Yanî hewşê pir ke, pir kevin, se ke ayetê Quranê dînane ser,
navê Allah.
Meaning very ancient, very old courtyards, look they put
Quranic verses on it, the name of Allah.
Têkev hindir yo, her malek Kurmanca deha kitêb Quranê be di
mala gundê da ne.
Enter inside, every Kurmanji house has ten Quran books in
the village houses.
Lê.
Yes.
Heva jî de aceb çi kirine hevo?
What did they do with this one, I wonder?
Kuncê re canoyê, kevirî demanê berê ne.
The corner... stones from the old times.
Eywa.
Yes.
Hev jî bigre.
Film this too.
Erê hevalno, wa dî ye hevo çi ye? Ev te derxan çi ye?
Yes friends, look what is this? What is this sticking out?
Se ke, hev kevir no, berê derece bûn, derece. Derecê
kevirnî.
Look, these stones, they were stairs in the past, stairs.
Stone stairs.
Di ser va radihildikişîn, gelo çi kirine?
They used to climb up on these, presumably what did they do?
Xweletî mir divê derece kevirnî bîn. Berê derece tune bîn,
wana kevir dikirne weter radihildikişîn.
My aunt says they must have been stone stairs. In the past
there were no stairs, they placed stones like that to climb
up.
Pir kevnar e emrê vê hewşê.
The age of this courtyard is very ancient.
Arê hevalno, îşteha gelo merhele ji çolê dikin, merhele
silav tînin vira.
Yes friends, so look, the stage [of work] they do from the
field, the stage of greetings [welcome] they bring here.
Paşê ro, vê belena dûrê va jê dikin.
Afterwards, they remove this wide part from it.
Wa bo merhele didiyê.
That was the second stage.
Te zanî? Û paşê ro, mesela jimûnê ro ke, hîlînin, ehîlînin,
paşê hewa gi dibê tana.
You know? And afterwards, for example regarding the amount,
they keep it, they keep it, then all of this becomes a bale
[pressed tobacco].
Dike tana, bi erzone difroşin.
It becomes a bale, they sell it cheaply.
Arê, dikin tana, dikin tana. Iye haye mesela me'nî firotanê,
pav ser hev difroşe.
Yes, they make bales, they make bales. There is for example
regarding the selling, they sell it all together on top of
each other.
Bi ser va erzan e, bes ta ke tana pir biha ye.
As a whole it is cheap, but if you make it a bale it is very
expensive.
Ta ke tana, kiloyê xwo teqrîben sed weraqê Tirk e.
If you make a bale, its kilo is approximately one hundred
Turkish lira.
Te zanî? Yanî serê xwo qena be nîvê dikeve ser.
You know? Meaning its capital/cost at least adds half on
top.
Dikin tana û paşê dêrîn û dibin qurtax difroşin.
They make bales and then winnow/process and take it to
Qurtax to sell.
Xalo, sê sed bi heştê weraq bû, tana bi sedî.
Uncle, it was three hundred and eighty lira, the bale for a
hundred.
I serê xoltîk?
Is that right, auntie?
Na, tana.
No, the bale.
Tana bi heştê?
The bale for eighty?
Tana bi sedî.
The bale for a hundred.
Tana, se ke, ev tirs bi tana be kîlo bi sed weraqê Tirk e.
The bale, look, if this sour [sumac] is in a bale, the kilo
is one hundred Turkish lira.
Teqrîben du dolar û nîv o. Kîloyê ginde du dolar û nîv e.
Approximately two and a half dollars. A kilo of it is two
and a half dollars.
Arê, bes ta hana bifroşe erzan e. Pêncî weraqê Tirk.
Yes, but if you sell it like this it is cheap. Fifty Turkish
lira.
Se ke? Cefayî xwo heye, cefayî xwo pir e.
Look? It has its suffering/toil, its suffering is great.
Lê.
Yes.
Arê hevalno, hewşê kevnar xaletî me dibê erd hezî gwa be ye.
Yes friends, ancient courtyard, my aunt says if only the
floor was earthen/mud.
Gelo, ga erd hezî ye.
Indeed, look the floor is earthen.
Migo belkî bi tiştin din hedime ye, go erd hezî wabî cixwa
zîlzol e.
I said maybe it collapsed from other things, she said if the
floor was earthen [it absorbs] the earthquake.
Erd hezî nîne.
It is not earthen floor.
Se ke, xonî duqurî, i pir zîlzolê de hedimîn.
Look, the two-story mud houses, they collapse a lot in the
earthquake.
Hewşnê pir kevnar ne.
They are very ancient courtyards.
Voo...
Whoa...
Sok me te çûyê ewê, Cenûb Efrîqa.
Look, you have gone to that one, South Africa.
Xaniyê kevnar ne.
They are ancient houses.
Voo...
Whoa...
I divorda no te eîşandin?
Does nobody live in here?
Na te eîşandin, ya rebbî kî we re hedimîne, ecêb e.
No, nobody lives, Oh Lord who collapsed this on you, it's
strange.
Af vorda no te eîşandin, kûk?
Nobody lives here, man?
Ke çi dide be eîşe?
Who is going to live here?
Wan çiqas...
How much did they...
Mere newêrî hilşê ser ge.
One doesn't dare [enter], it might collapse on top.
Tiştekî verî çime to.
Something [unintelligible] cement.
Arê hevalno wa vê hewşo dî ye? Emrê vê hewşê jî pir kevnar
e.
Yes friends, did you see this courtyard? The age of this
courtyard is also very ancient.
E tebî yozî mivo xwînê tê, seke derebzûnî gund e.
Of course [unintelligible] reading comes, look at the
railing of the village.
Heva derebzûne gundî ye.
This is the village railing.
Berê çû çê dikirin.
How they used to make it in the past.
Wa dî ye derebzûnî gund e.
Did you see, the village railing.
Pir pir pir hewşê kevnar e.
Very very very ancient courtyard.
Hev sarnicê gund e.
This is the village cistern.
Hev jî hesinê kirine viderê.
They put iron here too.
Şîş tê da tinene çiye?
Are there no bars inside or what?
Qa bere şîş tina bîn, hemo yek kirine viderê, didu, sê şîş.
It seems in the past there were no bars, but they put one
here, two, three bars.
Vê balkonê gi sê şîş kirine, hovo qilqê xwo belin e, hovo
şîş têr darxistine û vê hesno.
They put three bars on this whole balcony, look they spread
its hook, look they put bars through it and this iron.
[Walking sounds]
Eceb viro behr tê?
I wonder if the sea [wind] comes here?
Arê hevalno vê hewşno, yapî gundê gi duqurî ne, mitirka,
bine?
Yes friends, these courtyards, the construction of the
village is all two-story, [unintelligible], look?
Bes qenterma ye, qenterma ye, çiy gundê pir hênik e. Sok me
bay radayî.
But it is an archway, it is an archway, the place of the
village is very cool. Look at the open wind.
Xudanê xwo rehmetî bîn, ne?
Its owners are deceased, aren't they?
Xudanê xwo ne li vir in.
Its owners are not here.
Evno xudan rehmetî bîne?
Are the owners of these deceased?
Gele çû qenterma çêkirine?
Look how they built the archway?
Qolinga, bine?
With pillars, look?
Oho...
Arê.
Yes.
Wa dî ye? Hevo bere hewşê kevn go hano bîn, bine?
Did you see? This is how old courtyards used to be, look?
Qopî textikî nî. Ha.
Wooden door/shutter. Look.
Wekî awe.
Like that.
Wele hênik e. Sok me bay radayî.
By God it is cool. Look at the open wind.
Hev jî pencera xwo textikî ye.
This one's window is also wooden.
Berê heva hano dikirin, ber.
In the past they used to do it like this, look.
Oho hesno hano dikirine, me'nî qope venade, bine?
Look they did the iron like this, meaning the door wouldn't
open, look?
Ha.
Look.
Molê giyo ha bîn.
All the houses were like this.
Pir, av ji hewa xon e.
Very, this is also a house/room like this.
00 - 43:44 ===
May God have mercy on the villagers, the place...
Weleh serincê vî derê pir xweş e.
By God, the cistern of this place is very nice.
Havelû sêke, were devê gundî bigir.
Look at the courtyard, come film the entrance of the
village.
Obû! Havolû sêke, ev 'emrê vê serincê jî pir kevnar e.
Wow! Look at the courtyard, the age of this cistern is also
very ancient.
Sêke devî gundî kîver e.
Look where the entrance of the village is.
Yanê, hewa kever e, û hev jî ban e.
Meaning, this is rock, and this is the roof.
Binê, ban e. Kîder e.
Look, it is the roof. Where it is.
Wadî çû jî kever xwarî?
How is it supported by the rock?
Dadî, ban, vê banê, ji kever xwarî. Eger îf çêkirna...
So, the roof, this roof, is supported by the rock. If they
made it...
Binê.
Look.
Cihê adamim bên, ji kever xwarî, ma'nê xwe pir dibrê o.
The place where I say, it is supported by the rock, it
carries a lot of meaning.
Ê fehmon, ez zanim bê edebim çi.
Yeah understanding, I know what I am saying.
Havo pir me'nê xwe heye.
This has a lot of meaning.
Cihê ban ji kever bixwe, me'nê xwe pir e.
Where the roof eats from the rock, its meaning is great.
Ê baqil î, zanî.
Yeah you are smart, you know.
Wara havalî malê bigir.
Come film the courtyard of the house.
War havalî malê bigir, evro.
Come film the courtyard of the house, today.
Havolno berê havna dereca bûn. Berê dereca bûn, sêke.
Friends, before these were stairs. Before they were stairs,
look.
Divir ra wekî seqif kêfa kirine, taxt kirine, pêncere.
From here they made it like a ceiling for pleasure, made it
a wooden platform, a window.
Divir ra hildikişin jor, wê pêncerê vedikin, hildikişin jor.
Taxt e.
From here they climb up, open that window, climb up. It is a
wooden platform.
Eywa, hev jî cihê qemrî ye, jî çi ye.
Yes, this is also a place for doves, or whatever it is.
Taq e, da me'netê gundî jî hem nizanin.
It is a niche, the meaning of the village they also don't
know.
Ê mezin nizanin ev çi ye.
The elders don't know what this is.
Fermû.
Welcome.
Havolno viro binê.
Friends, look here.
Bas ge seqat e ho, ka kever kê bikevin, binê.
But this is very damaged, the rocks might fall, look.
Havo berê hişta, berê zemandeg ho nebî. Buxarîka çêdikirin.
This before... in the past times it wasn't like this. They
would make a fireplace.
Xora orîxo veda xistin.
They would put down their bedding.
Orû diniştin.
And sit there.
Çurçunaka wel didan.
They would have a snack together.
Genimê xwe, hejîrê xwe, mûnetê xwe didanîn, û qortax...
Putting down their wheat, their figs, their supplies, and
safe...
Bixwarê vêx û xora çurçunak awil da.
Near the fireplace and having a snack first.
Hav saetê jî, kevnar e 'emrê vê saetê.
This clock too, the age of this clock is ancient.
Gelek.
Very.
Ya heram tiştek pêva niştine.
Or nothing haram has settled on it.
Tamam tişt nîne.
Okay there is nothing.
Bû... Qederê rehma xwedê li gindiyo ke.
Wow... May God's mercy be on the villagers.
Ji layê xaltîkê ra, hewşê gundê ra derxîne.
From Auntie's side, take a video of the village courtyard.
Teben vê malbatê hem sedfe hatin, xaltîkê semaq çêdikir.
Of course, we came to this family by chance, Auntie was
making sumac.
Qeçkê xaltîkê gişt li Ewrûpa ne. Hemî wurtu hewş e wane.
Auntie's children are all in Europe. This whole area is
their courtyard.
Havolî mehan dûr çê er ma bigir, ji şaba bora.
Film our courtyard from afar, take it, from the wind
direction.
Bikim bîra gundî xo kirine, bîra hewşê xo kirine.
Let me make them remember their village, remember their
courtyard.
Eşyo gav xira ne bûn çi? Daxîne, daxîne.
Did these things not break or what? Put it down, put it
down.
Na na mar heye saetxweş.
No no there is a snake, thanks.
O qewekê derê kê, ma ne xweş e?
Take a shot of that corner, isn't it nice?
Xwedê çi terazî be.
God, what a scale.
Berê qenyê çiye?
What is the date of it?
Ayfrîn sê sed şêst û şeş.
[Brand] 366.
Sê sed şêst û şeş.
366.
Hav ro ye qirisî lê.
This sun has struck it.
Dinya germ bû, havalno dinya germ bû.
The weather got hot, friends the weather got hot.
Ooo qeçikî tirsê çêdikin, bin qep e.
Oh the kids are getting scared, under the arch.
Bin dişqep e.
Under the archway.
Arê havalno, teben em gihîştin talyê vîdyoyê.
Yes friends, of course we reached the end of the video.
Vê derê jî em Hofê Kerke? Jûrin û jêrin e.
This place is also Hofe Kerke? Upper and Lower.
Havî hamber ma Dêmîlya ye. Be'dîno gundê Qûpê.
This opposite us is Demilya. Then the village of Qupe.
Berbannê.
Berbanne.
Vire gundiyona.
Here are the villages.
Viro Sêviyote? Gûliya.
Here is Seviyote? Guliya.
Gundê Kêlî bû.
It was the village of Keli.
Mentiqe gi xoynta jma vo.
The region is very beautiful from here.
Gundê Qeda, hember ma ye, gundê Qeda.
The village of Qeda, is opposite us, the village of Qeda.
Em gihîştin talyê vîdyoyê, havalno.
We reached the end of the video, friends.
Bi mere bûn, dês û vîdyokî xweş kîbar.
Stay with us, a nice beautiful video.
Û te'lîqê yazmîş kin. Û hûn kî derê dixwazin?
And write comments. And which place do you want?
Ma ro qenatê ma bidê hazirî gîn.
Make our channel ready for us.
Şeş heft simarê ma mo.
Six seven [numbers] remain for us.
Çavê we maç dikim, saetê we xweş. Yalla bay bay.
I kiss your eyes, thanks to you. Yalla bye bye.