Li nav Mabatê jî bazar heye, milet ferqî bazarê...
There is a market in Maabatli too, people [know] the
difference of the market...
Bi Qenter mebîn...
Don't look at [the name] Qenter...
Hey ranê çawa qoçê kevirê kîçikê da ro...
Hey, look how he hit that small stone on the side...
Ev jî doston o, nav gund xidra digerîne...
This is also [unclear], driving the vegetables through the
village...
Yê rewala meş... tişto tû nebî...
The walker... things you are not...
Yê rewala tû nebî, min sala 2007an da me dewat kiriye...
You walker, you weren't [born/around], I got married in the
year 2007...
Tû nebî...
You weren't [there]...
Merheba ji were hevalno, dîsa vîdyoyek nû, vîdyoyek xweş,
kîbar.
Hello to you friends, again a new video, a nice, neat video.
Teb'en vîdyoya me jî îro, em li gundê Qenterê ne.
Of course, our video today, we are in the village of
Qentere.
Gundê Qenterê jî tabî'ê Mabatê ye.
The village of Qentere belongs to [the district of]
Maabatli.
Arê, birayê me yê ji me re xwestî, Ferhad Ebdo Henan.
Yes, our brother who requested this from us, Ferhad Abdo
Hannan.
Silavê me ji gundiyan re hene, heta ciyê gindî.
We have greetings for the villagers, to the place of the
village.
Gundî teb'en ji me xwest, em gundê gindî teswîr kin, û pir
kesan ji me xwestî.
The villager of course asked us, to film the villager's
village, and many people requested it from us.
Silavê me ji miletê vî gundî re hene, gundê Qenterê.
Our greetings go to the people of this village, the village
of Qentere.
Gundekî pir xweş, kîbar e.
A very nice, neat village.
Bi me re bin, leqtanên xweş, nav gund emê werin û teswîr
kin.
Stay with us, nice shots, inside the village we will come
and film.
Sipas dikim.
Thank you.
Sibê we bi xêr hevalno, başin, çawane, îşalla hûn
sihetxweşin, şolê we giran rehet in.
Good morning friends, are you well, how are you, God willing
you are healthy, your heavy work is easy.
Arê vîdyo me yê îro li gundê Qenterê em kaçekê kin.
Yes, our video today, we will take a tour in the village of
Qentere.
Bîr nekin marê like û îştîrakê pê dan, û vîdyo me heta
dawiyê seyr kin, û saeta we giyan xweş.
Don't forget to give us a like and subscription, and watch
our video until the end, and have a good time.
Arê hevalno.
Yes friends.
Teb'en noka jî emê me'lûmat jî ser vî gundî bibin, emê ji
milet jî pirsin.
Of course, now we will get information about this village,
we will ask the people too.
Gundekî pir xweş e, tebîeta gund. Gelek hember me ereba
qwînte.
A very nice village, the nature of the village. The car
struggles a lot against the slope opposite us.
Ereba ma'milê gundî ba dîn o.
The car's dealing with the village [roads] is crazy.
Berbanê gundê qûpe, dûrçêr me gih xwîlt e.
The slopes of the village are steep, we have hit/entered the
inclines.
Heke ne em çok sukin, çok sukindan e gih xwînte.
If not, we fall very silent, from the silence...
[unintelligible metaphor about the car noise].
Tebîetek pir xweş e, pir kîbar e.
A very nice nature, very neat.
Hevalê min jî zêr jî bigre.
My friend, take [film] the gold/yellow [crops] too.
Teb'en emê hilkişin vî derê, vî derê ana mewqihê cîkê bilind
e.
Of course we will climb this part, this part right here is a
high location.
Min got darbkem destpê bikin, yanî ji ser Mabatê va nêzîk e.
I said let me start, meaning it is near from [the direction
of] Maabatli.
Maşallah, maşallah, çi coğrafya.
Mashallah, mashallah, what a geography.
Çi tebîet e.
What a nature.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Teb'en Qentera Mabatê dikeve ser Hawarê.
Of course the Qentere of Maabatli is located above Hawar.
Arê hevalno, emê noka pêşî dikanê ne.
Yes friends, we are now in front of the shop.
Maşallah li nav vî gundî şênayî ye, gundekî pir xweş, kîbar
e, milet heye.
Mashallah inside this village it is lively, a very nice,
neat village, there are people.
Teb'en hinek heye, hinek tune ye... Ê warin inşallah giyê
biftilin warin malê xwe.
Of course some are here, some are not... Those who are away,
God willing, will all return to their homes.
Hûr û bazarê jî li Mabatê...
[Unclear] and the market too in Maabatli...
[Unintelligible conversation]
Arê hevalno, em cem xuletiyê min e. Magû em jê pirsin vî
gundo, çiqas hewş tê da ye?
Yes friends, we are with my relative (in-law). I said let's
ask him about this village, how many courtyards [households]
are in it?
Pismam, magû merheba ji te re dîsa.
Cousin, I said hello to you again.
Vî gundo çiqas hewş e? Mal?
How many courtyards is this village? Houses?
Welle, teqrîben sed û pêncî mal e.
Well, approximately one hundred and fifty houses.
Sed û pêncî mal. Seydê, çima nav lê kirin Qenterê?
One hundred and fifty houses. Sir, why did they name it
Qentere?
Welle, ji vê berê, malê xwedê pir gi qenter me bîn.
Well, from before, [at] the house of God [mosque?], we saw
many arches.
Gi qenter me bîn?
We saw many arches?
Gi qenter me bîn.
We saw many arches.
Ji ber wê nav lê kirin Qenterê.
Because of that they named it Qentere.
Nav lê kirin Qenterê.
They named it Qentere.
Me'lûmatek xweş e.
That is nice information.
Arê hevalno, vî gundo sed û pêncî mal e.
Yes friends, this village is one hundred and fifty houses.
Hewş.
Courtyards.
Û nav lê kirin Qenterê, dibê bere gi qenter me bîn, kevnor
bîn.
And they named it Qentere, he says before we saw many
arches, they were ancient.
Wê me'ne nav lê kirin Qenterê.
That is the meaning of naming it Qentere.
Gundî xweş e, gundekî bilind e, ana ser tili e.
The village is nice, a high village, right now it is on a
hill.
Mentiqe dûrçêr me gih xwîlt e, gelek çiyayê awarê gih dar
xwîntin.
The area is full of slopes we entered, many mountains of
Hawar [are visible/covered in trees].
Heta bi Efrînê, heta bi Cebel Ehlam gih xwîntê.
Even up to Afrin, up to Mount Ahlam [Dream Mountain], all is
visible.
Mentiqek pir bilind e.
It is a very high area.
Û inşallah noka emê hêca din jî werin û teswîr kin.
And God willing now we will go to other places and film.
Bi me re bin, leqtanên xweş, nav gundî Qenterê.
Stay with us, nice shots, inside the village of Qentere.
Silavê me ji birayê me Ferhad re hene, Ferhad Ebdo Henan.
Our greetings go to our brother Ferhad, Ferhad Abdo Hannan.
Silav rês û hurmetê gundê Qenterê ji te re.
Greetings, respect and honor of the village of Qentere to
you.
Û ji miletê Qenterê tevayî re.
And to the people of Qentere as a whole.
Arê hevalno, li vî derê me dest pê kir. Emê silavê divê
hûretê re tê kabine.
Yes friends, we started at this place. We will [send]
greetings... [unintelligible].
Maşallah gundekî pir xweş, kîbar e.
Mashallah a very nice, neat village.
Li nav Mabatê jî bazar heye, millet pir çûbû bazarê.
In Maabatli there is a market too, people went to the market
a lot.
Wa darê gûzê, hember me ye. Oh ho, çok sukind xwîntê.
Look at the walnut trees, opposite us. Oh ho, very [unclear]
visible.
Berdan henderî gund pir nîn e.
There isn't much produce around the village.
Hewş nê, hûr xwîntin.
The courtyards, [unclear] visible.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Ehe.
Aha.
Milet pir gund jê me xwestin e.
The people requested the village from us a lot.
Û inşallah emê gundê giya darxin.
And God willing we will present everyone's village.
Bi sebrê giyê bibe.
With patience it will all happen.
Welle gundî xurmez in e, dibê sed û pêncî mal e, mezin e.
Well the village is nicely arranged, he says it is one
hundred and fifty houses, it is big.
Teb'en kareba hatî vî gundî jî, kareba jî heye, kareba
hîkmet.
Of course electricity has come to this village too, there is
electricity, government electricity.
Rind e, ya xweş e, kê gundê giya bela kin karebê.
It is good, it is nice, may they distribute electricity to
everyone's village.
Jiyan bê karebê nabe.
Life is not possible without electricity.
Û avê gundî jî, avê şebekê ne.
And the village water too, it is network [mains] water.
Yani gundekî xizmetguzarî tê de heye.
Meaning it is a village that has services in it.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Rêk Ereb a ye.
The road is for vehicles.
Dibiro darên gûzê, mala Hesen, mala kê...
Look at the walnut trees, Hesen's house, whose house...
Ezê vî hewşê no bigre.
I will capture this courtyard now.
Welle hewşê kevnar bîrdana, berê gimek bas bîn şûbî.
Well the ancient courtyards remind [us], before [unclear] it
was...
Weke xalo gotî, ji dil gi qenter me dîtin wo.
Like the uncle said, truly we saw all the arches [there].
Hewş no.
The courtyards.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Wey, wa yeno mala ewê...
Wow, look at the house of that...
Hewş ro jêr girtin e.
The courtyard is held [built] downwards.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Sake vî hewşê wa norendin, hotatî ye?
Look at this courtyard, how beautifully it's painted, is it
Hotati [style]?
Wan ên li derbayî gund, û dûrê jî gi dar, darê sindiyan e û
hişînayî ye heye, wan rinde pir rind e.
Those at the passage of the village, and the distance is all
trees, Oak trees and greenery is there, those are nice, very
nice.
Xoro runê çawa qoçê kevirê kîçikê da ro.
Just look how he hit that small stone on the side.
Maşallah baranek dan lêke, çewîrê derkeve qirtox.
Mashallah if it rains a bit, the mud will come out [and
make] potholes.
Berî vê lêkir, wekî du saeta lêkir, ê 'ertî ye, 'ertî ye.
Before this happened, like two hours it rained, it is muddy,
it is muddy.
Yek dan lêke çewîrê derkeve.
One [rain] hits, the mud comes out.
Qurban texdî bime, konê dinê ger.
Sacrifice for the chassis, the world's [unclear] turn.
Erê welle.
Yes indeed.
Maşallah o.
Mashallah.
Bro meqbeze gi qenter me ye, gi xerabi ye.
Bro, the junction is all arches, all ruins.
Ka heta tole herin.
Let's go until the end.
Gundê Qenterê yê pir xweş e, kîbar e.
The village of Qentere is very nice, neat.
Gundê kurmancan gelek xweş in. Mila li ser bilind bin.
Kurdish villages are very nice. Let them be on the heights.
Mirov erdnîgariya xwe, boka xwe, axa xwe bernade.
One does not give up their geography, their origin, their
soil.
Heta pişê herin û paşê emê biftilin yolî din. Yolî din hîç
vir xweştir e.
Until we go forward and then we will turn on the other road.
The other road is much nicer than here.
Lê yolî din, Mabatê dergime bixwîntê.
But the other road, [the way to] Maabatli is not visible.
Nav gundê Qenterê ne.
We are inside the village of Qentere.
Gundekî şênayî ye.
A lively village.
Dengê mirîşka.
The sound of chickens.
Jiyanê gundewarî tiştek cûda ye hevalno.
The rural life is something different friends.
Heta, hinek milet noka li Ewrûpa ne, li xerîbiyê ne.
Even, some people are now in Europe, in foreign lands.
Hesreta vê axê ne, hesreta vî gundî ne, hesreta vî hewayî
ne.
They long for this soil, long for this village, long for
this air.
Hesreta vî kuçê ne.
They long for these streets.
Kuçê gundê miro, ji bajara Parîsê, ji bajara Berlînê, ji
bajara Londonê, xweştir e.
The street of one's village is nicer than the city of Paris,
than the city of Berlin, than the city of London.
Welatê miro pir şîrîn e.
One's country is very sweet.
Çiqas hûn herin, çiqas hûn bikin...
However much you go, however much you do...
Bajarê xelkê nabin yê miro.
Other people's cities do not become yours.
Warê xelkê nabe warê miro.
Other people's land does not become one's land.
Her, her tim mirov hesreta axa xwe ye.
Always, always one longs for their own soil.
Hesreta cî û warê xwe ye.
Longing for their place and land.
Rast e, em têda dijîn, em têda fêr bûn e.
It's true, we live in it, we are used to it.
Belkî em qîmetê nizanim, lê hûn qîmetê dizanin.
Maybe we don't know the value, but you know the value.
Yên li xerîbiyê.
Those in foreign lands.
Hûn qîmetê vê axê, hûn qîmetê vî kevirî, hûn qîmetê vê darê
dizanin.
You know the value of this soil, you know the value of this
stone, you know the value of this tree.
Welle, hinek milet hene dibên: "Xwezî em rojekê bihatana, me
bêhna axa xwe bikirana."
Well, there are some people who say: "I wish we could come
for one day, and smell our soil."
"Me serek li gundê xwe, me serek li welatê xwe xista."
"[I wish] we could pay a visit to our village, pay a visit
to our country."
Welle welat şîrîn e.
Indeed, the country is sweet.
Çi bêjim, welat şîrîn e.
What can I say, the country is sweet.
Çiqas mirov bibêje, kêm e.
However much one says, it is [too] little.
Heta tole herin, hê heye.
Let's go to the end, there is still [more].
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Rêk jêr da hinekî pir çetîn e, nukur don dakam, me zel vî da
ranû biftilin.
The road downwards is a bit very difficult, [unclear], we
will turn here.
Wî hewşê jêr bigre, yanî rêk jêr da pir çetîn e.
Film that courtyard below, meaning the road downwards is
very difficult.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Cewê sibê çiqas xweş e. Teb'en, saet deh û nîv ne.
How nice the morning atmosphere is. Of course, it is ten
thirty.
E, darê saet deh û yeko...
Er, around eleven o'clock...
Cewê sibê pir xweş e gund da.
The morning atmosphere is very nice in the village.
Sake, hisî serçote, hisî çûko, cew hênik e, sibê.
Look, the feeling of [unclear], the feeling of birds, the
weather is cool, in the morning.
Mîro dibê dinê germ dibê, milet...
One says the world gets hot, people...
Gidik ev e hindirî o dar o, sibê ana xelk hereket e.
That's how it is inside the trees, in the morning right now
people are active.
Karê dikin, daren şixulê xwe...
They do work, go to their jobs...
Şixul gi sibê dibe.
All work happens in the morning.
Emê diveda katîn, o rêkê çetîn e.
We will cut through here, that road is difficult.
Rêkê çetîn e.
The road is difficult.
O...
Oh...
Rêya Hewşa Qibê... Gundê Welîklî...
The road to Hewşa Qibê... The village of Welîklî...
Emê herin Hewşa Nejar, bigrin Hewşa Nejar.
We will go to Hewşa Nejar, take [the road] to Hewşa Nejar.
Awa rêka wê dikre.
This is how its road enters.
Emê herin lê bigerin, awirekî lê bidin... Nêzîk bû ka.
We will go look around, take a glance at it... Let's see how
close it is.
Wele nêzîk bûke, mela...
Well, it was close, mullah...
Çavê xwe li hewşê kin... Maşalla, maşalla.
Take a look at the courtyard... Mashallah, Mashallah.
Xwedê rizqê hemûya bide şînê, Xwedê bide xatira dê û bavê
min.
May God grant provision to everyone, may God grant it for
the sake of my parents.
Bo, hîn yekî [rê] li gelî da girtiye.
Wow, one person has taken the [road] through the valley.
Emê vê nanê jor jî... we hewşê nanê jor bigrin. Rêka xwe...
hinekî bi fitil û diyalî derbas dibe.
We will take this upper side... take the upper side of the
courtyard. The road... passes through with some twists and
turns.
Haa haa... gundikî... Gundikê jêr, Gundikê jêr e.
Aha, aha... the village... Lower Gundik, it is Lower Gundik.
[Unintelligible song lyrics playing]
Awa, ev rêya orta gund e.
Here, this is the road in the middle of the village.
[Unintelligible song lyrics playing]
Bye bye, bye bye, bye bye.
Saetê we xweş.
Good health to you.
Ewa, orta gund e.
Here, this is the middle of the village.
Hêdî hêdî...
Slowly, slowly...
Awa li vê derê jî, me got em li orta gund in, bi rastî
xezana avê, maşalla, pir kevnar e...
Here at this place too, as we said we are in the middle of
the village, truly the water cistern, Mashallah, is very
ancient...
Awa xezana avê, yê gundiya.
Here is the water cistern, belonging to the villagers.
Awa ev malên li wê aliyê jêr, giya vegir e.
Here, these houses on the lower side, it covers all of them.
Bê derxe.
Come out.
Silav û rêz... maşalla.
Greetings and respect... Mashallah.
Xezana avê ya gund e?
Is this the village water cistern?
Belê.
Yes.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Lê hema, ji 'idê da nav tî ye.
But, since the Eid [holiday], the inside has been thirsty
[empty].
Tî ye?
It's thirsty [empty]?
Belê.
Yes.
Ava gund, ava şebekê nayê?
The village water, the network water doesn't come?
Tê, qetmê ye.
It comes, it is cut off [rationed/broken].
Qetme ye, na?
It's cut off, isn't it?
Belê.
Yes.
Awa ev qentera, ya orta gund e?
Here, is this archway the one in the middle of the village?
Awa...
Here...
Pir kevn e, wisa diyar e.
It is very old, it seems so.
Zemanê Fransawî ye.
It is from the French era.
Zemanê Fransawî ye?
It is from the French era?
Belê.
Yes.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Navê wê çiye? Qentera çi ye?
What is its name? Archway of what?
Digotinê Qentera Koko Doro Zenterê.
They used to call it the Archway of Koko Doro Zenterê.
Qentera Koko Doro Zenterê?
Archway of Koko Doro Zenterê?
Belê.
Yes.
Zenter tê çi wateyê? Hûn zanin?
What does Zenter mean? Do you know?
Zenter... wekî dibêjin Geliyê Cernê.
Zenter... is like when they say the Cernê Valley.
Geliyê Cernê, Zenter e?
The Cernê Valley is Zenter?
Belê.
Yes.
Gelo Zenter tê çi wateyê? Anku...
But what does Zenter mean? Meaning...
De wate, wate...
The meaning, the meaning...
Yanê wek Geliyê Cernê ye, ew jî Zenter e?
So it is like the Cernê Valley, that is also Zenter?
Na, Zenter tune ye.
No, there is no Zenter [anymore/as a place].
Tune ye?
There isn't?
Na.
No.
Ee heye, dibêjin gundê Zenterê heye, li Efrînê.
Uh, there is, they say there is a village called Zenterê, in
Afrin.
Gundê Zenterê li Efrînê heye belê.
The village of Zenterê in Afrin exists, yes.
Gundê Zenterê heye, belê.
The village of Zenterê exists, yes.
Lê li vir Zenter tune ye.
But here, there is no Zenter.
Li vir Zenter tune ye?
There is no Zenter here?
Na.
No.
Ee, lê dibêjin Qentera Koko Doro Zenterê.
Uh, but they call it the Archway of Koko Doro Zenterê.
Gundê Zenterê li Efrînê heye belê.
The village of Zenterê in Afrin exists, yes.
Gundê Zenterê heye, belê.
The village of Zenterê exists, yes.
Lê li vir Zenter tune ye.
But here, there is no Zenter.
Li vir Zenter tune ye?
There is no Zenter here?
Na.
No.
Ee, lê dibêjin Qentera Koko Doro Zenterê.
Uh, but they call it the Archway of Koko Doro Zenterê.
Gundê Zenterê li Efrînê heye belê.
The village of Zenterê in Afrin exists, yes.
Gundê Zenterê heye, belê.
The village of Zenterê exists, yes.
Lê li vir Zenter tune ye.
But here, there is no Zenter.
Li vir Zenter tune ye?
There is no Zenter here?
Na.
No.
Ee, lê dibêjin Qentera Koko Doro Zenterê.
Uh, but they call it the Archway of Koko Doro Zenterê.
Koko Doro Zenterê, bavê Zenterê bû.
Koko Doro Zenterê, he was the father of Zenterê.
Bavê Zenterê bû?
He was the father of Zenterê?
Belê.
Yes.
Qentera Koko Doro Zenterê.
The Archway of Koko Doro Zenterê.
Belê.
Yes.
Awa, li vir, ez yekem car e dibihîzim, dibêje bavê Zenterê
bû li vê mantiqê.
So, here, it's the first time I'm hearing this, he says he
was the father of Zenterê in this area.
Belê.
Yes.
Yanî, nav, milet pir datînin, ne?
Meaning, the people give many names, right?
Zenterê heşînşî bixwe, diçû daxwazê, ka...
Zenterê himself, [unintelligible - heşînşî?], would go to
request, where...
Ew Zenterê jî mufîd e ji nexweşiyê re.
That Zenterê [referring to a plant/herb called
Zenter/Centaury] is also useful for illnesses.
Geliyê Cernê heta noka heye.
The Cernê Valley still exists until now.
Geliyê Cernê?
The Cernê Valley?
Li vira.
Here.
Vê re dibên Geliyê Cernê?
They call this place the Cernê Valley?
A, vê geliyê din, noka heta noka Zenter hîn nayê.
Ah, this other valley, now until now Zenter still doesn't
come [grow?].
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Te got me çi derman e, Zenter hîn nayê.
You asked us what medicine it is, Zenter still doesn't come.
Wele, emê werin mecalê xwe bidin. Kes me têne, eger berî we
giya wara me. Zenter, Geliyê Cernê...
Well, we will come and give it a chance. No one brings us,
if before you came to us... Zenter, the Cernê Valley...
Heke bixwe bibînin, bixwe...
If they see for themselves, themselves...
Geliyê Cernê, vê rê dibê?
The Cernê Valley, do they call this way that?
Paş Qenterê bo.
Behind the Archway.
Keremkin, saetê we xweş. Em hatin te jî aciz kirin da, Xwedê
ji te razî be.
You are welcome, good health to you. We came and bothered
you, may God be pleased with you.
Ser serî, hûn bi xêr hatin, ser seran.
Upon my head [You are welcome], you are welcome, upon heads.
Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê destê xwe ser we bigre, miletê
me, Kurmancê me, Xwedê ji we razî be.
May God be pleased with you, may God place His hand over
you, our people, our Kurds, may God be pleased with you.
Ser serê me, hûn bi xêr hatin. Em jî qenatê Efrîn 3636, em
li her derê ki hazir in û em xizmetî we dikin.
Upon our heads, you are welcome. We, the channel Afrin 3636,
we are present everywhere and we serve you.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Ez benî, birakê min, Ferhad ji me xwest, em hatin vê gundî û
miletê vê gundî ji me xwest, silavê me jî li vê rê hene,
ortê gundê Qenterê.
My dear sir, my brother Ferhad asked us, we came to this
village and the people of this village asked us, our
greetings are also on this path, the middle of the village
of the Archway.
Li saetê gundê xweş, da... ev Qenterê, de êsta her kesî tê
em istiqbal dikin. Ser serî û ser çavên me.
In the good hours of the village... this Archway, so now
whoever comes we welcome them. Upon our heads and upon our
eyes.
Xwedê ji we, ji we razî be. Wele, me dihelqand, mobata da
çêkirin, bes na ji... yanî...
May God be pleased with you, with you. Well, we
created/tried, we did the "Mobata" [affection/visit?], but
not from... meaning...
Rind ji dilê min da ew nebî yanî...
It wasn't really fully from my heart [satisfied]...
Te fena hesî?
You felt like that?
Na fena hesî, mezin bî û me dihelqa çêkirin, me... hemû we
na me çêkirin.
Not felt like that, it was big and we made the
circle/episode, we... we didn't make all of those.
He texfîf?
Huh, light/brief?
Pir hûrgilî hebûn, me hîn têda çênekirin.
There were many details, we haven't done them in it yet.
Înşallah...
God willing...
Înşallah emê rind di Mobata da çêkin.
God willing we will do a good one in Mobata.
Saetê we xweş. De ka me re bin, em cewla xwe temam bikin.
Good health to you. Come let's go, let us finish our tour.
Maşalla, miletê vê gundî, maşalla zarên giya xweş e.
Mashallah, the people of this village, Mashallah all the
children are beautiful/good.
Erê wele, maşalla, vê darê te jêr şawoke.
Yes indeed, Mashallah, look at this tree below.
Wele, miletî, ana zarxweş e.
Well, the people, really have beautiful children.
Em keda daran, dibê û aman werin, aman werin.
We [appreciate] the labor of the trees, it says oh come, oh
come.
Saetê giya xweş. Qîmetê nîvanê xwe zanin vê gundê.
Good health to all. They know the value of their halves
[partners/neighbors] in this village.
Awa no ka, ve tatlîcê, no ka emê dakevin, xwaro lê binerin
çi cewekî xweş e. Ooho.
Here now, this slope, now we will go down, look down at it,
what a beautiful atmosphere. Oho.
Maşalla. Binerin la.
Mashallah. Look man.
Ya selam, ya selam, ya selam.
Oh my, oh my, oh my.
Wa hesî çûko krî, wa hesî çûko krî.
Look how small he made the terrace, look how small he made
the terrace.
Sa ke, Mabata kevn derma.
Look, old Mabeta has appeared.
Wuh, ez nizanim zixab şûnê giya bigirim.
Wow, I don't know where to film the grass of the gravel
slope.
Ebe vana Maşallah, Maşallah.
Look at these, Mashallah, Mashallah.
E her gundekî, ser gundekî ra... Maşallah.
Oh, every village, on top of a village... Mashallah.
E wer, wer, wer. Babê te taliyê sa ke la.
Come, come, come. Dude, look at the back, man.
Vê nerindane Mabata.
From these views of Mabeta.
Maşallah. Ehh.
Mashallah. Ehh.
Mentiqa ge xweyî tê.
The whole region shows itself.
E vana hem ber ma. Maşallah.
And these are all in front of us. Mashallah.
Maşallah, hewale min çîçkî nîzîk bike. Maşallah.
Mashallah, my friend zoom in a little bit. Mashallah.
Avo ge Mabata ye. Maşallah, Maşallah.
That is all Mabeta. Mashallah, Mashallah.
Terbana, terba Mabata niçine a... mîrat...
The road, the road to Mabeta doesn't go... oh damn...
Kuro terbana... ha... Xwedê rehma xwe lê ji yad ke.
Boy, the road... ha... May God bestow His mercy upon him.
Gundekî pir xweş e kîbar e.
It is a very nice and cute village.
Bara aşiq vî gundî no dibe.
Brother, one cannot help but fall in love with this village.
Maşallah, Maşallah.
Mashallah, Mashallah.
Xwezika bi hatê vî gundî xweş û xweş.
I wish for the coming to this nice and pleasant village.
Tam avrêko jî... avrêko derê ave...
Exactly this crossroad too... the crossroad goes to that...
Derê gundê Hesen, derê... Ereba...
It goes to Hesen village, goes to... Ereba...
Derê gundê Birîmce, derê ge dera.
It goes to Birîmce village, it goes everywhere.
Rê û didimîlo, ma'milo, ridat keve.
The road and the transaction, man, falls onto the path.
Dirac ro jî diseta derdikeve.
It also comes out to the Durak path.
Mentiqa me pir mezin û xweş e.
Our region is very big and beautiful.
Gi avra qela.
It's all [white soil].
E vana malna ciya bisawirînin.
Come, let's film these houses and places.
Maşallah. Au vayê jêr û jûr.
Mashallah. Oh look, below and above.
Ave hew şino...
That greenery...
Çi cenn e ket baxekî do. Maşallah.
What a paradise, like falling into a garden. Mashallah.
Gundekî pir xweş e kîbar e.
It is a very nice and cute village.
Ehh.
E vana me gund rind nîzîk bike wina milo xweş derkeve.
Film the village closely so it comes out nice, man.
Hinekan e wina di jêr da ne, me nekanî teswîr kira.
Some are down there like that, we couldn't film them.
Emê li hember bikşînin milo fên ware.
We will film from the opposite side so they appear clearly.
Merheba hevalno.
Hello friends.
Kî tê derxê ve derê kîder e ye.
Who can guess where this place is.
Talîqa da yozmîş kin.
Write it in the comments.
Erê hevalno, teb'en em çûn gundê Qenterê me sewirand.
Yes friends, of course we went to Qenterê village, we filmed
it.
Vîdyo me jî wane bî, înşallah vîdyo me jî bi ecibînin.
Our video was like that, hopefully you will like our video
too.
Silavê min ji miletê gundê Qenterê tevavî ra hene, ser serê
min, ser çavê min.
My greetings to all the people of Qenterê village, on my
head, on my eyes.
Erê hevalno ve derê jî, me go aji derêm Efrîn...
Yes friends, this place too, I said I will enter Afrin...
Me vîdyo xwe xilaskir. Vîdu wano derket.
We finished our video. The video came out like that.
Şaşbîn maşbîn jî hene wina qusûrê efû kin.
There are mistakes and such, forgive the faults.
Vîdyo me jî ekterî gaff e wina.
Our video is mostly gaffes like that.
Li viro jî hem ser rêka Efrîn e, viro meqbez e, teb'en
meqbeza zeytûna ye.
Here is also on the Afrin road, here is a press, of course
an olive press.
Ve derê jî xolû xur e tebîetek xweş çêkiriye.
This place is raw nature, it has made a beautiful nature.
Çox sewîq zov aye.
It is a very deep ravine.
Mentiqê me Efrîn hene, ekteriyetê ne ve derê gelek qetata
çêdikin.
Our Afrin region, mostly in this place they make many clips.
Teswîra çêdikin. Maşallah tebîetek pir xweş û kîbar e.
They do filming. Mashallah it is a very nice and cute
nature.
E vana wilo were.
Come like this.
Pir kîbar çêkiriye. Maşallah, Maşallah.
It is made very cute. Mashallah, Mashallah.
Ehh. Wadiye?
Ehh. Is it a valley?
Ya ne şkefî dilê xwe re çêkiriye.
Meaning, the caves have made themselves to their heart's
content.
Heta poşî çêkiriye.
It has even made mist.
Le tiştê ten bîgzovatin viro bi destê av de digirin.
But things... big ravines here... hold with water.
Leqtetan çêdikin. Min çakê bikik wina ve derê...
They make clips. I [wore] a jacket like this here...
Maşallah, çi dor e, kî... avo dorî tî e ye.
Mashallah, what a view, who... this is the view of Tiyê.
Ya ewel merre ez dorî tî dibînim hona... ana reşê xwo
berdadin.
It is the first time I see the view of Tiyê here... they
have cast their blackness.
Erê wele, pir tebîetek pir xweş e.
Yes indeed, it is a very beautiful nature.
Erê hevalno, li ve derê Ez û Mezet jî.
Yes friends, here Me and Mezet too.
Em leqtek xwa no di ber da re çêkin.
We are making a clip like this in front of it.
Ne meroq meromon e.
It is not a worry of people.
Wina nabê tişto tinebî.
Don't say there was nothing.
Tinebî, min salê du hezar heftê da min dewet kiriye.
There wasn't, in the year 2017 I got married.
Tinebî, hema def û cîhaz a û xop xiş û xelas.
There wasn't [anything], just drums and trousseau and rush
and finished.
Erê hevalno li ve derê jî em gihîştin talyê vîdyo xwe.
Yes friends, here we reached the end of our video.
Bîr nekin layk û îştîrak me ra bo vîdyo me din.
Don't forget to give us a like and subscription for our
video.
Loyi min... tu dibê çi? Bêje.
My son... what do you say? Say it.
Milo çû kin?
What should uncle do?
Layk, îştîrak.
Like, subscribe.
Xuşk wa bibê.
Say it nicely.
Layk, îştîrak.
Like, subscribe.
Ewa pîçî xwe jî wa bike. Ewa. Ha... ev jî baqil e.
Yeah do your hand like that too. Yeah. Ha... this one is
smart too.
Tim... dibê... erê... dibê... ez divê heke ware derkevim,
yek naxla radbe dernakeve.
Always... he says... yes... he says... I want if I come out,
he gets up suddenly [but] doesn't come out.
Erê hevalno em gihîştin talyê vîdyo xwas.
Yes friends we reached the end of the nice video.
Heta gîha xweş xwedê ji gîha razî be.
Until good [times], may God be pleased with all.
Bîr nekin te'lîqne xweş kîbar me ra binivîsînin.
Don't forget to write nice cute comments for us.
Û vîdyo dî vero jî înşallah emê herin gundin din ji me
xwestine emê herin.
And for the next video, God willing, we will go to other
villages you asked from us, we will go.
Sînka ji me xwestine. Gundê Alke ji me xwestine.
They asked for Sînka from us. They asked for Alke village
from us.
Piro xwestiye gund. Gundin jî hene welekîn dûr in.
Many asked for the village. There are villages but they are
far.
Dîsa hû hûr mewidê me textir heye.
Again slowly slowly our appointment is closer.
Me go em Qenterê ser rêka min e ez teswîr kim û ez derbas
Efrîn bim.
We said Qenterê is on my way, I will film it and pass to
Afrin.
Ma'nî ez herim... axir celce exelas kim.
Meaning I go... finish the last session.
Bi me ra bin, leqtok xweş kîbar, vîdyoke xweş. Bay.
Be with us, nice cute clips, a nice video. Bye.