Belê temaşevanên hêja, programa Gundên Me îro desta spêkê,
bi şewq û nû de, emê seredana gundê Burc Ebdalo yê bikin.
Yes dear viewers, today in the program "Our Villages", early
in the morning, with enthusiasm and anew, we will visit the
village of Burj Abdalo.
Di vî gundî de, emê biratiya Misilman û Êzdiyan bibînin
pêşberî we.
In this village, we will see the brotherhood of Muslims and
Yezidis before you.
Eleykum selam, ehlen we sehlen, ser çavan.
Peace be upon you, welcome, you are welcome.
Burc Ebdalo bi xwe gundekî kevnar e, yanî kevn e.
Burj Abdalo itself is an ancient village, meaning it is old.
Yanî burcek li orta gund hebû, jêre digotin Burc Ebdalo.
Meaning there was a tower in the middle of the village, they
called it Burj Abdalo (Abdalo's Tower).
Însanekî hew, derwêş hat, li wî burcî hewî. Navê wî Ebdal
bû.
A person... a dervish came, he stayed in that tower. His
name was Ebdal.
Ser wî navî, nav lê kirin Burc... ser wî burcî, ew meriyê li
wir dihewiya, lê kirin Burc Ebdalo.
On that name, they named it Burc... on that tower, that
person who stayed there, they named it Burj Abdalo.
Ekîd gundê Burc Ebdalo mesela bêje... Kurmanc tê hene, Êzdî
tê hene, Misilman tê hene.
Certainly, the village of Burj Abdalo, for example let's
say... there are Kurds in it, there are Yezidis in it, there
are Muslims in it.
U... yanî em hevre, teayeşê me, em rind hevre ne, u em
miriyê hev, em darda ser hev tê, nexweşiyê de, şînê de...
And... meaning we are together, our coexistence, we are good
together, and our dead [funerals], we visit each other, in
sickness, in mourning...
u wekî gotî... îdê me, em danê îdê xwe bi hevre dikin, hew
tên îdê xwe mara dikin, îdê wan, em yanî muşareke dikin bi
hevre.
and as said... our Eid, we celebrate our Eid together, they
just come and congratulate our Eid, their Eid, we meaning
participate together.
U... yanî gund Burc Ebdalo bi xwe gundekî... yanî zîraî ye,
zîraetê de dijî miletê xwe.
And... meaning the village of Burj Abdalo itself is a
village... meaning agricultural, its people live by
agriculture.
Yanî em bên îro mesela baxça, bi henara, bi ermûta, sêva,
fewakê yanî bi şeklê am.
Meaning if we come today, for example orchards, with
pomegranates, with pears, apples, fruits meaning in a
general form.
U aliyekî din, mesela genim diçînin, nîska, noka.
And on the other side, for example they plant wheat,
lentils, chickpeas.
Yanî ev tiştê karê me... karê gund zîraet e, yê dereca yekê
yanî.
Meaning these things are our work... the work of the village
is agriculture, of the first degree.
Yê didiwa jî, yanî dewar jî heye cem milet yanî.
The second one too, meaning there is livestock too with the
people.
Heye wekî hezar dewarî di gund de heye yanî.
There are about a thousand heads of livestock in the
village.
U yanî va di... di merheleya bab û kala de bi zîraetê u
dewar de dijîn yanî.
And meaning this in... in the stage of ancestors, they live
by agriculture and livestock.
Yanî ez tera bêjim, êma zîraetê me berê ê yekê, êtîmadê me,
hên ser avê Efrîn e, nehra Efrîn e.
Meaning I will tell you, the basis of our agriculture, the
first part, our reliance, is on the water of Afrin, the
Afrin river.
U ê didiwa jî, cem me bîr hene. Yanî bi bîrê xwe, mesela
baxçê xwe pê av didin.
And the second one too, we have wells. Meaning with their
wells, for example they water their orchards.
Zîraetê xwe, mesela genim e, dendik in, nok in, nîsk... yanî
tiştê zîraetê bi şeklê am.
Their agriculture, for example wheat, grains, chickpeas,
lentils... meaning agricultural things in a general form.
U va salê nîzik da de jî, zîraet nû acer ketine cem me.
And in these recent years too, new agriculture has entered
among us.
Wekî patata, mesela yensûn, esfer... ev berê me va zîraeta
me nizanîn, evna acer de hatine cem me, berî vê pênc sala
şeş sala yanî.
Like potatoes, for example anise, safflower... this before
we didn't know this agriculture, these have newly come to
us, before this five years, six years.
Şa'bê me jî... bi yardimê hev dike, alîkariya hev dike.
Our people too... help each other, assist each other.
Yanî îro însanek wefat bibe mesela... ev miletê karê xwakî
ber dide, gi tê de, mesela yardimê... wê aîlê ge wefat cem
çêbûyî.
Meaning today if a person passes away for example... these
people drop their own work, all come in, for example help...
that family where the death occurred.
Bi vî şeklî yanî gi mutawin in tev hev, u pir îşekî xweş e,
rind e.
In this way meaning all are cooperative with each other, and
it is a very nice work, it is good.
Daxê îro tê bibînî, wela cîranê te... hawa kî mesela kî vira
çêbû tê yardim kî, derb kî, musaede kî, pir tiştekî rind e
yanî.
That today you see, by God your neighbor... like for example
something happened here, help, ... assist, it is a very good
thing.
Cem me ev tişta, em pê meşhûr in elhemdulelah, gundê Burc
Ebdalo.
Among us these things, we are famous for it praise be to
God, the village of Burj Abdalo.
(Muzîk)
(Music)
Ehlen we sehlen ya şebab. Bircê...
Welcome, guys. The village of Burj...
Ne pir kevn e.
It is not very old.
Yanî sê sed sal hana heye.
It is about three hundred years old.
Em jî bi xwe, heft-heşt sal heye em neburcine.
As for us, we haven't been to Burj for seven or eight years.
Wextê em hatinî Bircê, emrê min texrîben şeş-heft sal, heşt-
deh sal ez hebûm yanî.
When we came to Burj, I was approximately six or seven,
maybe eight or ten years old.
Noka emrê min bûye heştê û... du-sê kin.
Now my age is eighty... eighty-two or three.
Ew wextê em hatinî, avakirina Bircê yanî...
That time when we came, the building of Burj...
...texrîben heftê sal biye.
...has been approximately seventy years.
Di zeman da war hebûn war...
In the past, there were camps...
Berê war çêdikirin, kon çêdikirin...
They used to make camps, pitch tents...
Hews çêdikirin, tiştê dikirin tê de diketinî.
They built enclosures, did things to settle in.
Ew cîh me lê girtî berê giş war bûn.
The place we occupied was all camps before.
Berê gund tim di cîyada nebûn.
Before, villages weren't always in specific places.
Nava herra pêşiyê, kevir tûnê, war hene, cîh malalê heye.
In the front lands, there are no stones, there are camps,
there are places for households.
Herra vê jorê cîh malalê heye.
In the upper lands, there are places for households.
Herra ha va şimal, Qişlê... Qişlê cîh malalê heye.
In the lands to the north, Qishle... in Qishle there are
places for households.
Kurd berê giş tim di cîyada bûn.
Before, Kurds were always in the mountains.
Navê Bircê meselî bi Burcekî...
The name Burj comes from a tower [Burc]...
Navê xa... berî sê sed sal...
Its name... three hundred years ago...
Burcek lê bû, hîn milet li wir tûnne bû.
There was a tower on it, there were no people there yet.
Yek tiştekî kevn yanî wek qentermokî kevn hebû.
There was an old thing, like an old archway.
Ser du taqa bû.
It was two stories high.
Noka jî Birc bi çi meselen... yanî Birca zîraetî ye.
Even now, what Burj is about... it is an agricultural Burj.
Dar û ber e, mişmiş in, sêv in...
It has trees and vegetation, apricots, apples...
Zerraq in...
Yellow plums...
Yanî debara wan bi zîraetî ye.
I mean, their livelihood depends on agriculture.
Yerli bûnî li vê derê Mala Mela Osmên hebû, Mela Osman.
The natives here included the family of Mela Osman.
Mela Osman li vê derê kevn bû.
Mela Osman was established here long ago.
Û Mala Hesenê Osmên, ew jî texrîben malek kevn bû.
And the family of Hesenê Osmên, that was also an old family.
Gotin Mala Kuleh... Kuleh jî...
They said the Kuleh family... Kuleh as well...
Li vê derê li Qişlê bû.
Was here in Qishle.
Paşê daketin jêr...
Later they came down...
Ava kirin, çêkirin... dinya pêş de hat, çê bû, xelas bû.
They built, they constructed... the world moved forward, it
was built, it was done.
Wele eded sukanê Bircê, yanî tê bêjî du sed mal heye.
Well, the population count of Burj, you could say there are
two hundred houses.
Texrîben jê sed û çel mal Êzîdî ne. Em Êzîdî ne.
Approximately one hundred and forty houses are Yezidi. We
are Yezidis.
Urf û adetê me bi hevdra yanî...
Our customs and traditions are together...
Hetanî miriyê me, tirbê me, nav hev dene, em veşêrin.
Even our dead, our graves, are amongst each other, we bury
them.
Û tefrîqe nav me da tûnne ye.
And there is no discrimination amongst us.
Yanî urf û adetê me...
Meaning our customs and traditions...
Em xas miletê Êzdî...
We, specifically the Yezidi people...
Em xas miletê rehmin e û wîjdan û rehm...
We are specifically a merciful people, with conscience and
mercy...
Insanetî cem me heye.
There is humanity in us.
Berê, berî şêst-heftê salekî...
In the past, sixty or seventy years ago...
Cîranê me giş Îslam bûn, keko.
Our neighbors were all Muslims, brother.
Wextê me... ku tiştek serjê kira meselen...
When we... if we slaughtered something, for example...
Nedixwarin.
They wouldn't eat it.
Bes bapîrkê me digot, yavrim...
But our grandfather used to say, my child...
Digot ku çi serjê bikin, çi de'wehê bikin, pa ne cîranê
xwin, Îslam kin, bila serjê kin.
He said whatever you slaughter, whatever feast you make,
since they are your neighbors, they are Muslims, let them
slaughter it.
Jiboy ku bixwin. Heke bibînin û nexwin, gunekar bibin. Gunî
xuy wa stuyê we.
So that they can eat. If they see it and don't eat, they
will commit a sin. Their sin will be on your neck.
Me jiber wînî, me banê dikir, me çav dikir, me banê wan
dikir, serjê dikirin, me dida boy ku bixwin yanî.
Because of that, we called them, we watched out, we called
them to slaughter, and we gave it so they could eat.
Em... miletê rehmin e û insanetî ye û dîmuqratî ne. Rebbê
alemin, rebbê alemê ye.
We... are a merciful people, with humanity and democracy.
The Lord of the worlds is the Lord of the world.
Wele berê, berê kevin de berê...
Well, in the past, in the old days...
Têdî hudud tûnne bûn.
There were no borders anymore.
Welat tûnne bûn.
There were no [separate] countries.
Bi xwe eslê me, em bi xwe Xaltî ne.
As for our origin, we are Xaltî [tribe].
Botane... Jizîra Bota...
It is Botan... Cizîra Botan...
Cîhê Mem û Zînê...
The place of Mem and Zin...
Wele em ewilî... li Xerbê... li Îsko em ewilî yerli bûn. Li
Îsko.
Well, we were first... in the West... in Isko [Iska village]
we were natives first. In Isko.
Bes elê Bircê... eve keko.
But the people of Burj... this is it, brother.
(Muzîk)
(Music)
Belê temaşevanên hêja, ji gundê biratî û yekîtiyê...
Yes, dear viewers, from the village of brotherhood and
unity...
...ji gundê hezkirinê, gundê Burc Ebdalo em giştin dawiya vê
beşê jî.
...from the village of love, the village of Burj Abdalo, we
have reached the end of this episode as well.
Di demek nêzîk de li benda me bin.
Stay tuned for us soon.
Di beşek nû de, ji gundên me yê Efrînê.
In a new episode, from our villages in Afrin.
(Muzîk)
(Music)