Merheba hevalno, dîsa em îro hatin vîdyoyekî xweş û kîbar.
Hello friends, today we came again with a nice and lovely
video.
Vîdyoyî me jî, em îro... emkê herin derbasî gundê Eltaniya
bin.
As for our video, today we... we are going to visit the
village of Eltaniya.
Miletî gundê Eltaniya ji me xwestî.
The people of Eltaniya village asked us to.
Bi me ra bin heta dawî vîdyo, vîdyokî xweş û kîbar, emê nav
gundê Eltaniya wara çêkin.
Stay with us until the end of the video, we will make a nice
and lovely video for you in the village of Eltaniya.
Meze gotin tanê?
Did they tell you the appetizers?
Silav û bixêr hatin, hevalno hun çunin, îşê we çwaye, sihet
çwaye, inşalla hun gerr û rihet ne.
Hello and welcome, friends how are you, how is your work,
how is your health, I hope you are well and comfortable.
Erê, li projê me jî heye Mefrûşat Ivo, kekê me Husam ra, bi
xwe ji Dêrswanê ye.
Yes, we also have a project, Ivo Furniture, with our brother
Husam, he is originally from Dêrswan.
Ji doza vê ra tawasol be, reqemê genda em didin ser şaşê, û
'unwanê genda Lohne, kêlek Koln, li Almanya teb'en.
To contact regarding this, we put their number on the
screen, and their address is Lohne, next to Cologne, in
Germany of course.
Û bîr nekin, noka emkê derbaz gund bin.
And don't forget, now we will enter the village.
Vîdyoyekî xweş û kîbar wara çêkin, wara layk û îştîrakê
pêdinê, û saetê we xweş.
We will make a nice and lovely video for you, give it a like
and subscription, and may you be well.
Saet xweş he ma'zet.
Thank you for the effort.
Erê hevalno, bi me ra bin, noka nav gundê Eltaniya, amkê
vîdyokî xweş wara çêkin.
Yes friends, stay with us, now inside the village of
Eltaniya, we will make a nice video for you.
Gundekî pirr kîbar e, cografî gund pirr xweş e. Emê noka
wara kîbar teswîr kin.
It is a very lovely village, the village geography is very
nice. We will now film it nicely for you.
Silavê min miletî vî gundî ra hene, gundê Eltaniya.
My greetings to the people of this village, the village of
Eltaniya.
Teb'en ciyê me jî jêr jî, deşta Tirkiyê gih xuya dike.
Of course, our location shows the lower part too, the plain
of Turkey is all visible.
Oo, Qerebaba, gile, Yûlçate ma Yûlçate, gih ma va xuya
dikin, o bajar xuya dikin.
Oh, Qara Baba, the hill, Yolçatı and Yolçatı, they are all
visible, and the city is visible.
Deştek pirr bilind e. Erê mewqiyê xwe pirr xweş e.
It is a very high plain. Yes, its location is very nice.
Ee, hevalno teb'en îro, qîzê xaltîka min û xaltîka me hwno
hatine, cem Heleb hatine.
Uh, friends, of course today, my aunt's daughters and our
aunt have come, they came from Aleppo.
'Aciz dibin, go emkê tero derkevin gund teswîr, gora?
They get upset, saying "are we going to go out just to film
the village, really?"
E me got em xora derxin, bila çîçikê wan xora gundo bibînin.
So we said let's take them out, let them see the village a
little bit.
Ka bi me ra bin, leqtek xweş nav gund, emê...
So stay with us, a nice shot inside the village, we will...
Layk û îştîrakê bîr nekin.
Don't forget like and subscribe.
Erê, layê min dibê layk û îştîrakê bîr nekin.
Yes, my son says don't forget like and subscribe.
Erê hevalno, me dest pê kir vî derî.
Yes friends, we started from this place.
Mewqiyê xwe pirr xweş e, kîbar e. Di nav çiyayê da ye, ciyê
xwe bilind e.
Its location is very nice, lovely. It is in the mountains,
its place is high.
Vî derî mekteb, çoqsi pêva dûr e.
This place is the school, it's quite far from it.
Berê xwe bidin va dera.
Look at this place.
Gundê Eltaniya.
The village of Eltaniya.
Maşalla gundekî xweş û kîbar e.
Mashallah, it is a nice and lovely village.
Gundê Eltaniya me got şêst mal e, heta şêst pênc maloyî
gundê Eltaniya.
The village of Eltaniya, we said, has sixty houses, up to
sixty-five houses in the village of Eltaniya.
Tabi'e nahiyê Raco ye.
It belongs to the district of Raju.
Maşalla cografiyê xwe pirr xweş e, kîbar e.
Mashallah, its geography is very nice, lovely.
Gundekî xweş e, wana nav çiyayê da, ciyê xwe bilind e.
It is a nice village, there in the mountains, its place is
high.
Gundekî pirr xweş e.
It is a very nice village.
Livî derî jî milet zeytûna dadişînin, qorta zeytûn ber
çûndinê ne yani, xales dibin zeytûn.
In this place, people are also shaking down olives, the
olive harvest is about to end, meaning the olives are
finishing.
Silavê me miletî vî gundî ra hene, çûçik mezin.
Our greetings to the people of this village, small and big.
Çi nîzîk dibe, çi dûr dibe, çavê giya maç dikim.
Whether near or far, I kiss everyone's eyes.
Emê noka wara nav gund gî derxin. Inşalla.
We will now show you the whole village inside. God willing.
Wele vî alî jî hewşek ra û... jûr girtiye, ewa hewş e na?
By God, on this side, a courtyard has... blocked the top,
that is a courtyard, isn't it?
Ee, hewş e hewş e.
Yes, it is a courtyard, it is a courtyard.
Ok e ewa?
Is that okay?
Wele ewa yekî... heceme wele.
By God, that is someone... a Hajj, by God.
Hecemo, çaxma xe Hecemo ne?
Hecemo, aren't they Hecemo's things?
Maşalla, ciyê xwe rind e.
Mashallah, his place is good.
Gundê Hec Xelîl rûtî wîr girtiye.
Hec Xelil village has taken the view from there.
Emê wara mat'am kin, yekî wara zîna kin.
We will make a restaurant for you, make something like that
for you.
Wele cîkî xweş e mat'am.
By God, it's a nice place for a restaurant.
Saetê we xweş, Xwedê rizqê we bide.
May you be well, may God give you sustenance.
Rind e, rind e, saetê we xweş. Maşalla mewqiyê xwe pirr
kîbar e.
It is good, it is good, may you be well. Mashallah, its
location is very lovely.
Noka parçê... parçê din emkê divira herin na, di jûr ra?
Now the other... part, are we going from here, or through
the top?
E xulasa tu wira here.
Uh, basically you go that way.
Rêk nava gund da naçe.
The road doesn't go through the village.
Saetê we xweş, xalê we Xwedê ji we ra zîde.
May you be well, may God increase your well-being.
Maşalla ro germek jî derketiyê.
Mashallah, a warm sun has also come out.
Qasek me vistan tinê cema. Me go qasek me vistan tinê.
Just now we only brought dresses. We said we only brought
dresses.
Emkê pêncêr bikin, we ren pêncar derketî o.
We are going to pick greens, look the greens have come out.
Me go pêncar derketî.
We said greens have come out.
Hevalno, vî derî jî... qîzê xaltîka min hew noka ji Heleb
hatine.
Friends, in this place too... my aunt's daughters have just
come from Aleppo.
Da pêncar Heleb tinê, çû o dibên pêncêr ketine, tûlke tûlke.
There are no greens in Aleppo, look they say greens have
fallen (are available), mallow, mallow.
Me go tûlke dikin.
We said they are picking mallow.
Em elimî ne dikin.
We are used to doing it.
Lîme jî dikin, lîme jî dikin, pêncer, lîme we na dikin?
They are also doing "lîme", they are also doing "lîme",
greens, aren't you doing "lîme"?
Ewa çiye ewa?
What is that?
Ha? Gayo ye?
Huh? Is it "Gayo"?
Bi desta hal dikê, ehe, o ya hal kir.
She solves/handles it with her hands, uh-huh, she handled
it.
Wele hinek pak e, delîl we te re ye, werin.
By God, it is a bit clean, the guide is with you, come.
Deştê miletî gundoka çikorî bikin? Pêncar e... tişta korî o
gund.
Look what the village people are doing? It is greens... the
things of that village.
Hevalno, par gund hene, milet cîcike te'f... ce'fer soy e,
nûjen derkevin.
Friends, some villages exist, people a little... it is Jafar
lineage (?), new generations are coming out.
Nizanim, em qenaatê çin e jî.
I don't know, whatever our conviction is.
Miletî gundo, hele saetê miletî gundo bin.
The village people, just look at the condition of the
village people.
Tetewur, pirr gund hene tetewur têda tinen e.
Development, there are many villages that have no
development in them.
Yani hîn milet hinda kaye, çav girtî ye, çav girtî ye.
Meaning the people are still somewhat, eyes closed, eyes
closed (unaware/undeveloped).
Em dibên şara'ê re herin hefte jûr.
We say let's go up the street for a week (?).
Maşalla wadî, çi gundekî xweş û kîbar e.
Mashallah the valley, what a nice and lovely village.
Bê şem si le vê parçî de herin.
Maybe we should go from this part.
Bê şem parçî din wara qeyt kin.
Maybe we record the other part for you.
Hevalno, maşalla, mewqiek pirr xweş e, bilind e.
Friends, mashallah, it is a very nice location, it is high.
Hêê! Heta çavê me ra ferq dike.
Hêê! Even to our eyes, it makes a difference.
Em bi ho de naçun vê mal no oho. Hewalim wara em hata daran
herin.
We didn't go that way to these houses, oho. My friend, come
let's go up to the trees.
Wadiye? Hewalim vê hewşuno nîzik bike.
Is it a valley? My friend, zoom in on these courtyards.
Serxaniyê ov gul biye.
The roof has become water and flowers (?).
Êvarê çîçike xerbî lê kir...
In the evening a little western wind hit it...
Mûk nîne, notla virçiq çêbûye.
It is not dust, it has become like slush.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Ma qeçax li jêr sekinîn?
Did the smugglers stop down there?
Ewrekî reş hatibû ser me, lê xwedê hebe bayekî hênik lêxist
û ewrekî spî anî.
A black cloud had come over us, but God willing, a cool
breeze hit it and brought a white cloud.
Haya mûk nîne, notla virçiq çêbûye.
Look, it is not dust, it has become like slush.
Ma go ez heta vira hatim...
Since I came all the way here...
Zere hemûnda ma pise çi bikim.
[Unclear] what should I do.
Yekî mîhên xwe şa bane girtî.
Someone has kept his sheep [sheltered/hidden].
Avalim ware ew vedê malana jî derxîne.
My friend, come, bring out the cattle of these houses too.
Seke rêka xwe çîçkê viro ave.
Look, his path is a bit that way.
Emê noka herin géçî wî du jî.
We will now go to that side too.
Maşallah gundekî xoş e welle.
Mashallah, it is a nice village, by God.
Wollo...
By God...
Deşt... mer go xuyinte.
The plain... man says look at it.
Binê wan jî av, jî nêçîr kirin e.
Their bottoms are water, and hunting was done.
Mo go... milo çîçke Helebî xwaro bigehin, acizî ne.
I said... let the Aleppo [pistachios/people] reach down a
bit, they are annoyed.
Bê sê çar roj cem mane, em neçûne teswîrê.
It has been three or four days with us, we haven't gone
filming.
Guhur emkê wa ro derkevin.
[Changes] we will go out like this.
Ma go mişxoro em herin.
I said never mind, let's go.
Gundê Altonya.
Altonya Village.
Lê xoro pincer dikin.
Look, they are making windows for themselves.
De... m'ezzet ji vîdyo çêdike j qicikoro.
Look... [someone] is making a video from the small one.
Tiştî wekî pincer xoş tune.
There is nothing as nice as a window.
Pincer jî... tabîatê tirsa şwîn da, wana blêmîn kê, vuk vi
şe ser.
A window too... [due to] the nature of fear in the place,
block them, throw [something] on it.
Daw kî sor ber o çêke, dawi mî ye.
Make a red skirt in front of it, it is a ewe's skirt.
Pir xoş e.
It is very nice.
Dewazen em wa ro şehen kin bes Ewropa pir e.
We want to charge it like this, but Europe is full [too
much].
Ceme hesol boron naketi, der naketi.
A community like this, rain doesn't fall, doesn't go out.
Zat bilindî ye heye qiral.
Anyway, it is a high place, king.
Rutubê xwe heye.
It has its humidity.
Wey tûrê xwe tije kir o.
Oh, he has filled his bag.
Keyf keyf o we.
It is pure pleasure.
Welle evna qort o jidî mino qetin gind o.
By God, these holes... cut me from the village.
Kê timir derkevin gind o.
Who will go out of the village completely?
Wamon cema be'dîno, gayo tne û hevno jî hotin vir bigehin
ketine.
Those folks afterwards, cows came and summer also came
here... they fell.
Pincer... tirse dikim qorto timir o gindo bigerin.
Window... I fear looking for holes in the village.
[Unintelligible speech while walking]
Ka were... hevalî min nqto kê wani jî bigir.
Come... my friend, take a shot of those too.
O darx ji miletî gind ro... miletî gind ro rind teswîr ke.
And the trees for the village people... film the village
people well.
Milo miletî gind kêf xoş bibê.
So the village people become happy.
Taben silavê min j miletî gindê Altonya re hene.
Of course, I have greetings for the people of Altonya
village.
Çunkî mezin û ççik giyo maş dikim.
Because big and small, I kiss [greet] them all.
Gindekî pir xoş e, ma ecibondî.
It is a very nice village, I liked it.
Deşt gi xuyinte maşallah.
The whole plain is visible, mashallah.
Bilind e.
It is high.
Ve hevalno, ela glî ev bane dikim qenotê bi pincer ketî, lê
were were.
Friends, well I am saying this roof fell with a window...
but come come.
Tne dibê yoş yoş.
It only says slowly slowly.
[Music and driving scene starts]
Erê hevalno, li vê derê jî...
Yes friends, here also...
Em gundê Altonya ne, mala Elî Saleh.
We are in Altonya village, at Ali Saleh's house.
Em l mala mixtêr in.
We are at the Mukhtar's house.
Emmî rast xaltîkê hatin, xaltîkî aw zehra diqawirîne.
We ran into Auntie, Auntie is roasting that grain.
Xaltîk ê naşewtin ano?
Auntie, don't they burn?
Na na, baş e, baş e.
No no, it's good, it's good.
Oo destê min şewtî, xaltîk hun çû dikin?
Oh my hand burned, Auntie how do you do it?
Welle çat in e.
By God it is tough.
Wa were xaltîk were were.
Come Auntie come come.
Welle ew destê min şewtî, gelek lapik hebin.
By God that burned my hand, there should be gloves.
E welle, welle bila nebin gundo ye.
Oh well, by God let there not be, it's the village.
Ûy destê min şewtî.
Ouch my hand burned.
Agir dibore ra pir çê?
Does the fire pass through it well?
Tenê tav da guma lapik heban, em çû dikin lê?
Just in the sun, I wish there were gloves, what can we do?
Ê karê we ye, ne wa ye xaltîk?
It's your work, isn't it Auntie?
Erê ma... weşta manî û zalimê çûye.
Yes... the time of fatigue and oppression has gone.
Em vê xweşîyê b ser 'êr' nokin û ser lêzer dikim.
We don't do this pleasure on fire, I do it on the 'laser'
[electric/gas stove].
Dê bike xet nake.
Do it, it doesn't matter.
Ya ew karê jinan e, vike were.
Yeah that's women's work, do it come.
Ez jî him m'ezet biqawirîne, ez jî aw bikim.
Let me also... let her roast the appetizer, I will do that.
Hinke j xolû ra şîvê hozir bikin heta tê.
Prepare some dinner for Uncle until he comes.
Çûye çolê ne xaltî?
Did he go to the field, Auntie?
Noko çûye walt...?
Now he went to...?
A çûye Rajo.
Ah, he went to Rajo.
A bibê cemaetê badîna hatin, tero şîv hozir kirin.
Ah, say the Behdini group came, prepared dinner for you.
Ê ma zehro bes were qawrandin, neje hez nokim.
But roasting wheat... just come roasting, I don't like it
much.
Bes xove... ade bixum.
But raw... let me eat.
Noko xove serîkî tûyî me, ezê xalos kim.
Now raw, a bag of [mulberry/snacks], I will finish it.
Bes biqawirin, di çalmisin, eji hez nokim.
But roasted, they get chewy, I don't like it.
Bî me...
Give me...
Şîvê ser êr xoş in e.
Dinner on fire is nice.
Zehra xoş e.
The wheat is nice.
Şûniyê buxo, dirimkê xoş e.
Eat the [snack], it's nice.
Mhm... Ya ya... daw dikê wekî msaq... çêdike?
Mhm... Yeah yeah... does it give a taste like msaq [dish]...
make?
Xaltîk wiy gund o, wiy tim o na na ser êr daro şîvê dikin.
Auntie, in this village, all of them no no, they make dinner
on wood fire.
No welle, hûr û lêzer ma oniyen.
No by God, small ones and 'lasers' we brought.
Em ser lêzer dikin.
We do it on 'laser'.
Ser lêzer?
On 'laser'?
Ser taqa şemsiyê.
On solar energy.
Misa kir... dinya 'ewr e, no meşê... zeytê do nerdin.
Like if... the world is cloudy, it doesn't work... don't put
it in oil/diesel.
Ê na ser êr rind e, malê wa bi çêva nîzik e, qijik heş pir
ne.
No, on fire is good, your houses are close to each other,
small twigs are plenty.
Qiş pir e, gi tişt pir e, bes... wano behosoyî ye.
Twigs are plenty, everything is plenty, but... that is
laziness.
Wele... ew biye korî xulomî.
By God... that has become servant's work.
Wele ye xulomî ye.
By God it is servant's work.
Lê xulomî ye, berê giyo wano dikir, ser nan ser êr dikirin.
But it is servant's work, before everyone did that, made
bread on fire.
Rûbrû nan dikirin, diçûn şeleko...
Made bread face-to-face, went to the Shalako...
Ê le korî behasoyî hatî, xêr merke cefêb...
Eh but the work of laziness has come, don't welcome
[trouble]...
No canim.
No my dear.
Ser lêzer gînîb ser don do...
On laser... [unclear].
Ê xoltîk, nehona tam didê, tama dûy lê bigre xoş e.
Eh Auntie, doesn't it give taste now? If it gets the smoky
taste it's good.
Şîvê xo em gîn ser lêzer dikin welle, ser gazê.
We make our dinner all on laser by God, on gas.
E gerek tolyero jî te cewzî çoyê dinê, nov êr.
And need [something] too, put walnut tea in it, on fire.
Yekir ker çim...? Gî çûne zeytûn o.
One did...? All went to the olives.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Ez ji te razî be xoltîk.
I be pleased with you too Auntie.
Xwedê canê sağ bide we de jî.
God give a healthy soul to you too.
Sax bî.
Be healthy.
Hîn ji kî derêş bide we de.
Give you long life too.
Xozloda gindo, mereke çû korî bike, hêê...
Pleasure in the village, a man does what work, eh...
Korî çûle ye, mole, meroke bike gundo.
Work of the field, home, a man does in the village.
A le korî mole emkê çû ke.
Ah but housework what can we do.
Erê.
Yes.
Xoltîk berê rind bî, lê noko rind e?
Auntie was it good before, or is it good now?
Berê jî ma rind bî noko jî...
Before was good too, now too...
Lê ciyayê me berê rind bî, bes... da em çûn em ftilîn,
şta... çîçkê tap têde he bî, sate bî.
But our place was good before, but... when we went and
returned, well... there was a bit of fever in it, it was an
hour?
Xwedê heye.
God exists.
Elhemdila j Xwedê ra dîsa tewîd bî.
Praise be to God it settled again.
Elhemdila j Xwedê ra.
Praise be to God.
Hem de milet jî tê û...
And the people come too and...
Ono bereket...
That blessing...
Elhemdila canê giyo jî sax e, me...
Praise be to God everyone's soul is healthy, we...
Yane tizirar jî ne kir wano, elhemdila.
Meaning no harm was done like that, praise God.
Elhemdila j Xwedê ra, ehim şî siheta însên e.
Praise be to God, the main thing is human health.
Elhemdila, ehm şî sihet e.
Praise God, main thing is health.
Satê ta xoş xoltîk.
Health to you Auntie.
Xwedê ji te razî be, welle em kêfxweş bûn.
God be pleased with you, by God we were happy.
Xwedê ji te razî be xoltîk, welle em kê...
God be pleased with you Auntie, by God we are ha...
Ev heyatek xweş li vir e. Amê lî ser pişta xaniyê... Ebdalo
ne? Ser pişta xaniyê Ebdalo.
There is a nice courtyard here. We are on the roof of the
house of... Abdullah, is it? On the roof of Abdullah's
house.
Ev jî mala Muxtêr e.
And this is the Mukhtar's house.
Wa dî çi gindekî xweş ê kîbar e.
Look, what a nice and cute village it is.
Nav gind, qelem e... Se ke, qelem jî, hema li vî alî dûrçavê
bigre, hovolî me, dûrçavê bigre.
Inside the village, it's like a pencil [drawing]... Look,
even the pencil, just take the zoom [camera] to this side,
my friend, take the zoom.
Maşallah...
Mashallah...
E...
Yeah...
Teb'en terbiyê vî gindî jî, li gorî minî camêr, li gorî minî
can... bi nû ve dar nê sîndiyan e.
Of course, the upbringing of this village, according to my
dear friend, according to my dear soul... they have newly
planted oaks.
Hema binî camêr vaye.
It is right under the kind man.
Rind e.
It is good.
Nîzîk e em pê va.
We are close to it.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Wa dî, hewna, yakî hewş roj li jûr girtiye.
Look, over there, someone has trapped the sun inside the
courtyard [it is very sunny/bright].
Se ke, darê qelmê... darê polîtê di hewşê da, darê tehtek
hewşek te hebe û darê sîngiyan jî di hewşê te da.
Look, the pencil trees... the poplar trees in the courtyard,
you have a wooden bed/throne in the courtyard and oak trees
in your courtyard too.
Teb'en yakî wekî met'emkê li jûr digere, ser pişta... ew
jûr, ma vexwîno te...
Of course, one would walk inside like it's a restaurant, on
the roof... that room, oh reader...
Yakî jî ro, li kolî kurtê jûr girtiye, wa dî ye?
Someone else has trapped the sun in the short room today, do
you see?
Se ke, hema qelem jî dûr ma. Qelem jî dûr ma, ço.
Look, even the pencil stayed far away. The pencil stayed far
away, it's gone.
Qanê kewar kabe, emê biçin xwarê kewar ka... kewar kîn tinne
ne... dar naketin e.
If the beehive is there, let's go down to the beehive... the
beehives aren't there... looking at the trees.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
E vaye nûişta vekin, ez bawer tim wa dibêm...
Now, open a new business, I believe I always say this to
you...
Yanî her... noko bê gindî da qe nebe, qe nebe, bîst merî li
vî gindî çûyne Ewropa.
I mean every... inside this village now, at least, at least
twenty people from this village have gone to Europe.
Qiçkê vî gindî, her yakî meselen qe nebe deh-donzdeh hezar
dolaran rêke, sermalekê xwo bavêjin...
The children of this village, if each one sends, for
example, at least ten or twelve thousand dollars, invests
some capital...
...nav gindê xwo da, ewq xwo vekin, meşrûek xwo vekin, me'nî
milletê gund pê sebeb bibe.
...inside their own village, open something for themselves,
open a project, meaning the people of the village will
benefit from it.
Meşrûek xwo cûck vekin, warşê xeyatê, sa çi dibe, ez tim
dibêm...
Open a small project for themselves, a sewing workshop,
whatever happens, I always say...
Mecenê mirîşka, mezre'ê çêla...
A chicken farm, a cow farm...
Yanî her tişkî tikanî vekî...
I mean, whatever thing you can open...
Te her tişkî kanî vekî, teb'en tacirî vekir jî, tewasulê te
jî bi Efrîn re hebe teb'en.
You can open anything, of course, if you open a trade, you
should have a connection with Afrin as well, of course.
No, pirr koca me warşê xeyatê li ginda vekirî...
Look, many of our elderly have opened sewing workshops in
the villages...
Bes bi Efrîn re tewasulê qan e. Bîda'a ji Efrîn tînin li
vêra cawêz dikin didirûn, û paşê ro, bi mokîna bar dikin
dibin Efrîn, cawêz.
But where is the connection with Afrin? They bring the goods
from Afrin, prepare and sew them here, and then load them
onto machines/cars and take them to Afrin, ready-made.
Yanî ez temena... hûn jî her gindekî da, ez bawer dibêm.
I mean I hope... you also, in every village, I believe I say
this.
Her gindekî, milletê wî gindî, xwo re meşrûek xwo veke.
Şixil heye, şixil pirr e.
In every village, the people of that village should open a
project for themselves. There is work, there is plenty of
work.
Vekin, me'nî milletê gind pê bişixile. Em gind dabeziyane ta
Efrîn da meşrî'a va dikin.
Open it, so the people of the village can work in it. We
have come down from the village all the way to Afrin to open
projects.
Lo teyb, di gind da jî veke.
Okay fine, open one in the village too.
Di gind da jî veke, qane millet, noko yak şabab manim,
meselen... hene millet, eya bişixile, evê kar heye bişixile.
Meselen tim korî çûle jî tînî.
Open one in the village too, so the people, like a young man
left [unemployed], for example... there are people who want
to work, there is this work to do. For example, it's not
always field work.
Cûd tim tînî, vedan tim tînî.
Plowing isn't always there, pruning isn't always there.
Xeyat be, çi tiştek be, efedê bibîne, millet efedê bibîne.
Let it be a tailor, let it be anything, so they see a
benefit, so the people see a benefit.
Meselen, qe nebe deh mal, pênc mal, şeş mal, meselen sêwî di
wî gindî da hene, fiqare ne.
For example, at least ten homes, five homes, six homes, for
example there are orphans in that village, they are poor.
Teb'en hemû ginda digerrin, em zanin wez'ê xelkê.
Of course, we travel to all the villages, we know the
situation of the people.
Em wez'ê xelkê giyo zanin. Ê sêwî, ê fiqare, ê qiçik li
cem...
We know everyone's situation. The orphan, the poor, the
little one with...
Lê?
Right?
Yanî însanî fiqare heye ginda da pirr e.
I mean, there are poor humans, there are many in the
villages.
E bişixilin, qiçkê xwo têda bişixilin, e fêdê bibînin.
Let them work, let their children work in it, let them see a
benefit.
Ze'net rind e, ze'net rind e.
Craftsmanship is good, craftsmanship is good.
Çi kewnê kîbar in ewanî. Çi kewnê kîbar e.
What cute partridges those are. What a cute partridge.
Xêr na, qançka kerr xwo nê, hawî ne, ma nêrim ber pêis?
No good, the female is deaf [doesn't move], look, she's
calm, should I release the male on her?
Kiçik, kiçik, kiçik...
[Calling the bird] Kichik, kichik, kichik...
Çoqsone ke kîbar in wadî ye?
Look how cute they are, you see?
Xwe ro le... hema j' pêpe bar dide, j' moxê.
Look at him... just holding back from the kick, from the
head.
Hema xwo re nav qelema xwo diçêrin gile.
They are just grazing inside their pen, man.
Têr xwarin, wehasîyîn e. Ne ere ne ne, ne darr in.
They ate their fill, they are wild. They aren't
domesticated, they aren't trees [stationary].
'Elimîn e. E bûxin, têr xwarin e, wehasin tim wa ne.
They are used to it. Let them eat, they are full, they are
always wild like this.
Gindê nav qelmo da xweş bûn e.
The village inside the pen became nice.
Wa bira polîto kiri? Polîto?
Look brother, did he do the pillars? The pillars?
Hema ji qopiyê xwo te derxist, te polîto jî bike.
Since you took it out of your copy [design], you should do
the pillars too.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Lê, bes ev polît hew ne rind ne kemîlî ne.
Right, but these pillars here are not completed nicely.
Migo hew ne rind ne kemîlî ne. Wa rîn lî sêr kem.
I said these here are not completed nicely. Come let's look
at them.
Hin heşîn in e, kîçax lûniyê xwo sûr bî, bikun kemîlî ne.
Some are green/blue, when their color becomes red, they will
be complete.
Lê, hew ne xweş in e, buxe, ev bê temînatê xwo pirr e.
Right, these are nice, eat, this has a lot of vitamins.
Erê saeta xaltîka xweş, çû çîçek da me'zetê.
Yes, good health to the auntie, he went and [messed] with
the flowers out of spite.
Welle keyfa re gî me da qemiş a min gene.
By God, I don't enjoy it when people touch my fabric/stuff.
No, heram e. Çû çîçek da... ewa me'zetê çîçekê wuna hez ke.
Teb'en mi jî çîçek hez dikim.
No, it's forbidden. He went [to] the flowers... she loves
the flowers obsessively. Of course, I love flowers too.
Mi berê pirr dihewandin, e celkî min noko dest b'vê korî
kirî, û mi berdayî jê.
I used to keep/grow many before, but my tote bag [my
business/life] has now started this work, and I let go of
it.
Dest ji me giyo berdaye.
He has let go of all of us.
Erê welle. Mi berê çîçek, hewşê min tiji bî. Te çi nu'ê
daxoziyê li mala min mewcûd bî. E noko m'da jê berdayî, e
nanî na buşm jê ro.
Yes, by God. I used to have flowers, my courtyard was full.
Whatever type you desired was present in my house. Eh, now I
gave up on it, I don't even smell them anymore.
Gule gule.
Goodbye.
Gule gule, saeta wa xweş. Emê noko hangeçê din jî. Ko
bimerre bin emê hangeçê din.
Goodbye, good health to you. We are now going to pass
through. Let them stop so we can pass.
Erê hevalo, ma polît çênekirin? Welle çûqas polît m' şirîn
bî.
Yes friend, did we not make the pillars? By God, that pillar
[construction] was so sweet to me.
Em poşman bûn, ma pirr nekirin.
We regretted that we didn't do more.
Însan zanin, her rûkê ginda darbas ke, bimolî dinyê dike.
People know, every root [corner] of the village you pass
through, is worth the wealth of the world.
Se ke cewê ginda, ana sehî, sehî.
Look at the atmosphere of the villages, it is healthy,
healthy.
Ne kelem der, ne biçêva nîzîk e, sehî ye, bokî pok te.
Not prickly out there, not close to the eyes, it is healthy,
a clean wind comes.
Yane naxoşî, merov ro çi naxoşî hebe, vonê rabû der, were
ginda... yanî boyê ginda pok e. Ne wekî boyê bajar e. Bajar
ro...
I mean illness, whatever illness a person has, get up and
come out, come to the villages... I mean the wind/air of the
villages is clean. Not like the air of the city. The city...
Binî modûte û binî dûyê şatmonê mokîno, hemdî merov lehev
dikeve.
Under the exhaust and under the smoke of the car exhaust
pipes, a person just collapses.
Gind o, pirr xweş e. Se ke hesê dîko, çûko tê. Pirr kîbar e.
The village is very nice. Look/Listen, the sound of
roosters, birds is coming. It is very cute.
Bes xêl ginda qehwê sibê xweş e, ez zanim. Şim xweş e qehwê
sibê.
But the people of the village, the morning coffee is good, I
know. It smells good, the morning coffee.
Cihê yona xuseten cîran ban hevdu dikin, pîşî qopyorî didin,
qehwe vedixwin.
Their places, especially neighbors call each other, giving
each other the updates/gossip, drinking coffee.
Hevalî me gind rind teswîr ke ho, m'lo kes nebê male me
firtiye.
My friend, film the village well, so no one says we missed a
house.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Xwedê ezîm her gindekî a darime... her gindek jî ser gindekî
ro.
God is great, every village I pass... and every village is
above another village.
O xoltîka amber me me'rre dike, an kûre. Vê xoltîkê nîzîk
bike.
Oh, the auntie opposite us is waving, looking. Zoom in on
this auntie.
Ho liko.
Here, look.
Nîzîk bike, gile xoltîkî me'rre dike. Saeto gindiyê xweş.
Zoom in, look the auntie is waving. Good health to the
villagers.
Rêk hebe? Emê biçin cem.
Is there a road? We will go to them.
Xwedê 'emrekî dirêj bide.
May God give [her] a long life.
Evul nû te'lîqê mero pirr e yê mişkan. O em tên gindî wa we
ro sewrin wa bîro gindî xwo kirî. Em zîkriyatê wa tînin bîrê
wa.
First now, our comments are many from the mice [critics].
Oh, we come to the village to film for you, remind you of
your village. We bring your memories to your mind.
Eceb rêk di virra hebe?
I wonder if there is a road through here?
Kule em se kin hela.
Let's see now.
Em xwo di virra lêxin.
Let's hit the road through here.
Teb'en mogo gind ne mezin e, şêst-pênc mal e ne.
Of course, I said the village isn't big, it's sixty-five
houses, right.
Yo, di virra jî heye, rêk.
Yes, there is one through here too, a road.
Evul nû wele wê hewşê onû tadiye? Xwedanî gindî ro li jûr
girtiye.
First now, by God, do you see that courtyard there? The
owner of the village has trapped the sun inside.
Mi jmêrek pirz kir, wê hewşê jûr dibê xwedanî ginda li
Ewropa ye, yekî met'amek têda veke.
I made a calculation, that upper courtyard, they say the
owner of the village [house] is in Europe, someone could
open a restaurant in it.
Saeto gindê xweş. Se ke, ona met'emkê di wir da veke.
Good health to the nice village. Look, open a restaurant in
there like that.
Mewqi'ê xwo jî pirr bilind e, mantiqa pirr xunde, milletê
kora re... îstîrahek xwo cûcik li wir bibe, çîçke bêhnê xwo
derbê, ona cewê xwo tegeyîrat çêbibin.
Its location is also very high, a very calm area, for the
working people... have a small rest there, let out a bit of
breath/stress, so their atmosphere changes.
Tiştê ona ginda da çêbe, pirr kîbar e.
For things like that to happen in the villages, it is very
classy.
Welle, bibî gind bibî cîranê kî xweş û xweş.
By God, if it happens, the village becomes a neighbor of
beauty and joy.
Se ke, rêk a, di vêra bazdin şêr.
Look, it's a road, lions run through here.
Di vêra hebe? Ecem.
Is there one through here? I wonder.
Kerê te çiqas yekî nomsiz e?
Your donkey is such a dishonorable/cheeky one?
Qey axî... qey te tm cê didiyê?
Do you... do you always give him barley/feed?
Nuh.
No.
Qey awa, te tm cê didiyê?
Is that so, you always give him feed?
[Inaudible - likely "Awa koy didimê"]
[Inaudible - likely "Yes I give him chaff/feed"]
Ko ye? Xey wana zap nabe le.
Where? That one can't be held back/controlled then.
Novika te gêrka xiş kirî.
He has scratched the roller of your... [inaudible part].
Grêda grêda dore vegirêda. O nivîkê te birîn kirî. De.
Tie it, tie it, tie the surrounding. Oh, your waist is hurt.
Come on.
Waş birader.
Whoa brother.
Oh, çi ciyekî xweş e.
Oh, what a nice place.
Arê havalno, li vî derî hem noka noka toli gundê, heyê ne?
Li al'kî ji diskinim, serî tûlkê dibînim, dibê me dîne.
Feqîro. Segê me carna qet tûlek me nedî ye.
Yes friends, here we are now, just inside the village, isn't
it? I stop on one side, I see the puppy's head, saying he
saw us. Poor thing. Our dog sometimes we haven't seen a
puppy at all.
Yabo! Ewil tebxe ye, yan kevn e? Sûlçêkin, me nexwariye.
Oh man! Is this the first batch [of milk], or is it old? You
make colostrum, we haven't eaten it.
Avo ewil tebxe ye, Muaze dibê ewil tebxe ye, hêsol.
This is the first batch, Muaze says it's the first batch,
colostrum.
La ne cem me tîne, ne cem me gund o lê...
No, it doesn't come to us, it's not at our village but...
Yeş yeş.
Whoa whoa.
Weh sî kahrê kirî. Eşt.
Wow look what the kid (baby goat) did. Shh.
Her bijî. Te dî zangel lê xist. Yanî go dugri ye.
Long live. You saw it hit the bell. Meaning it is correct.
Avo ewil tebxe ye, em hêsol em kê bixon cema, be'dîno me go
pir da tine ye.
This is the first batch, we will eat colostrum together,
afterwards we said there isn't much in it.
Pir da tine, ne biye, ne biye.
There isn't much, it hasn't happened, it hasn't happened.
Vê digindana xeribî xo pir e, xeribî xo pir e, heye.
In this village, there is a lot of strangeness [or exile],
there is a lot of strangeness, there is.
Nu miletê vî gundî kêf dikin, maşallah.
Now the people of this village are enjoying themselves,
mashallah.
Guhê pez jî boro pak e, yanî tişt dar tine, gabol e.
The sheep's ear is also very clean, meaning there is no
thing [dirt/tick] on it, it's smooth.
Aa maşallah pak e. Em ê hêsol bixon bilê mîna.
Ah mashallah it's clean. We will eat colostrum, oh my.
Jin çox car pênc car hez dikin, a dern ki der dibê biskin,
da dern di ki dibê biskin.
Women like it four times five times, wherever they go out
they have to break it, wherever they go they have to break
it.
Pa ne êzing xo brav ken, wadiye, ha? Tij mole xo derket,
hemo haje bra fke. Tadîye hajê hişk. Manî şîvê.
But they don't gather their wood, isn't it, ha? She came out
of her house, gather all the stuff. You saw the dry stuff.
Meaning dinner.
Tadîye? Ko em jin kero hinke brav kin.
You saw? Where are the women to gather some?
Wele hene, wef dere hene.
Well there are, around here there are.
Evo sorda me çîye?
What is this red thing of ours?
Wela kivark e.
Well it's a mushroom.
Ne sorda me. Kivark o? Tine ne kivark o.
Not our red thing. Is it a mushroom? No it's not a mushroom.
Maşallah. Çi çavê ki xweş e.
Mashallah. What a nice spring.
Arê havalno noka em konê bin, me rêk pirs kir, am konê bin
am kan wê hewşê wan o jûr.
Yes friends, now we are down below, we asked the way, we are
down below, we will go to that yard of theirs up there.
Emê laxta nûj bervo were çêkin, wînê xor binîm çi menzer e.
We will make a new shot towards there, see for yourselves
what a view it is.
Tadî milet tişta, milet hano ye.
You saw the people are thing, people are like this.
Feqe, metemeke ljur bigre, her wur ehsen berke ye. Deştê
Tirkiyê yoli ding xuy tê.
Look, take a shot up there, everywhere is the best place.
The plain of Turkey, the road comes clearly.
Akî noko her mûr laxtan were çêkim. Bi min ra bin, mewqîyê
sekin.
Okay now I will make shots everywhere for you. Stay with me,
look at the location.
Arê havalno, live dere me, em derketin dervayî gund.
Yes friends, here we are, we went outside the village.
Bes sê çor mol, ow li ko li jêr, di gelî da ne, ez nizanim
kîjan gund e ve derê.
But three or four houses, oh where down there, they are in
the valley, I don't know which village is this place.
Gund hewş wano girtine, ez nizanim.
The village has closed their yards, I don't know.
Ev rono kî derê wela ez nizanim, cara nehatime vî gundî.
That side where is it, well I don't know, I haven't come to
this village before.
Muaze te navê vî gundî jêr?
Muaze, [do you know] the name of this village down there?
Na.
No.
Boyono?
Maybe Boyono?
Kî derê vî gundo. Hevalno merivê mişkin vî gundo kî derê,
wele ewil merra dibînim.
Where is this village. Friends, people who know where this
village is, well first time seeing it.
Çend mol in.
It's a few houses.
Taban xeraba ba, hember min e weleko.
Of course if it was ruined, opposite me over there.
Wadiye? Xeraba ba, li ko hember min e, gundê Xeraba ba,
misewra hinde.
Is that so? If it was Xeraba, where opposite me, Xeraba
village, it's visible there.
Mîdan Mekbeze misewra hinde?
Midan Makbaze is visible there?
Gundekî livra jî heye misewra hinde, bes hav çend mol na min
ne sewirandine, vanê binî ver.
A village here is also visible there, but these few houses I
haven't filmed, these ones down here.
Sê çor mol ne, û binî vo jî teqriben heft heyşt mol ne.
Hejbla. Yek, dido, sê, çar, pênc, şeş, heft, heyşt.
Three four houses, and below them approximately seven eight
houses. Count them. One, two, three, four, five, six, seven,
eight.
Heyşt mol jî li gelî ne. Maşallah çi cane li bin ra.
Eight houses are in the valley. Mashallah how beautiful down
there.
Wadî çoyê xo çik galin. Ha?
You see their creek how ... huh?
Ew ne panêr e koy?
Isn't that cheese...?
Hevalno yê zimişkin mera vî gundo kî derê, em nizanin.
Friends, those who know tell us where this village is, we
don't know.
Wadî deşta Tirkiyê ka me bixuytê deşta Sûrkê.
You see the plain of Turkey, let the Surke plain appear.
Deşta Mîdan Mekbeze ne. Maşallah.
The plain of Midan Makbaze. Mashallah.
Wele hînokê, ji jêr va dihilkişe zîreka poporê, ew rêka
poporê darê Mîdan Mekbeze wê rêko.
Well there, from below climbs the switchback, that road goes
to Midan Makbaze that road.
Ew rêka durê darê... hînoke ji rêka heta vir were, tê rûkê
pêda hilkişe.
That road far away goes... there from the road until here,
comes up the slope.
Lê hela binî gelî xo çiqas kûr ne.
But look below how deep their valleys are.
Wela vî gundo, gundekî av e, axa naxwa heçî moro...
Well this village, a village of water, soil isn't eaten
whatever man...
Ew gundo zilmî di wê gelî da. Bes ciyê xo rind e ha.
Maşallah. Deşta.
That village is oppressed in that valley. But its place is
nice ha. Mashallah. The plain.
Hevalno, ew em hatin cem hewşê, hevalî me lê bigir hewşê.
Friends, we came to the yard, friend film the yard.
Te vê hewşê dîye? Rêka xo jî heye teb'en.
Did you see this yard? It has its own road of course.
Hîn her cî gund e, pir rind e kîbar e, bes çiçkê huna divê
dhesibim erd şil e.
Here every place is village, very nice and elegant, but a
little bit you have to consider the ground is wet.
Silavê min ji xudanê vê hewşê re hene. Sake metemkeke çêke,
silavê min ji gund re hene, serkeftin be, Xwedê rizqê gund
bişîne.
My greetings to the owner of this yard. Look make a shot, my
greetings to the village, good luck, may God send sustenance
to the village.
Fe'len mizwêq e. Xudanê vê hewşê fe'len mizwêq e.
Truly tasteful. The owner of this yard is truly tasteful.
Le'nî tebîetê lê hewş girtî û cuxrafî lê girtî, manazer
bicennin, wekî Ereb dibên.
Because nature has enclosed the yard and geography has
enclosed it, views are crazy, as Arabs say.
Werin lê binêrin ha. Wadîye? Çi mewqî ye? Ha. Hevalî min
were nîzik bike hind.
Come look at it ha. You see? What a location? Ha. My friend
come bring it close here.
Deşt, çiyayê Gewr, gundê Hemze Tado ne.
The plain, Mount Gewr, Hamza Tado village.
Wadîye? Vê malno, hevalî min lê bigir. Fe'len mizwêq e.
You see? These houses, my friend film it. Truly tasteful.
Hana ecabê wî maş dikim. Lê, ho.
Look I admire his wonder. Look, here.
Wekî Libnanê, Libnanê. Cîkî bilind likî, çog ew likî ye,
Libnanê daren wek Ewrûpa daren hewşo têda digirin.
Like Lebanon, Lebanon. A high place like this, since it is
like this, in Lebanon trees like Europe trees hold yards in
it.
Maşallah, ev tebîeto dest kê dikeve.
Mashallah, whose hand gets this nature.
Bervî gundî jî hano ber ciyê gewr, sibê ehsen rûniştin, çay
û qehweka xol vexe, şevkî xo çêke li hember gund.
Towards the village also look towards the white place,
morning best sitting, drink your tea and coffee, make
yourself a night opposite the village.
Rêka xo jî heye, seata gund xweş. Wadî çi cuxrafye ye.
It has its road too, the hour of the village is nice. You
see what geography.
Gundê Altunya. Maşallah maşallah. Silavê min ji miletê gundê
Altunya ra giyor e hene.
Altunya village. Mashallah mashallah. My greetings to the
people of Altunya village go there.
Çavê gîyo maş dikim, gundê Altunya, bay bay, bay bay.
I kiss their eyes, Altunya village, bye bye, bye bye.
Arê havalno, li vê derê jî teb'en emê vîdyo xo xîtam kin.
Yes friends, here also of course we will finish our video.
Silavê min ji miletê gundê Altunya Taveyî re hene, cûcik
mezin çavê gîyo maş dikim.
My greetings to the people of Altunya Taveyi village, small
big I kiss all their eyes.
Bîr nekin te'lîqa pir binivîsin, mole kê derket, bişînin ji
hevdira.
Don't forget to write many comments, whose house appeared,
send it to each other.
Gundî kêlekê, bişînin ji hevalê xora dost û ehbaba ra, miro
milet lê sêr kin.
Neighboring villagers, send to your friends, friends and
loved ones, man let people watch it.
Silavê min ji Birakî min Zûhêr ra hene, li Siwêd, bajarê
Siwêd. Ji gundê Dalgirê.
My greetings to my brother Zuher, in Sweden, the country of
Sweden. From the village of Dalgir.
Silavê min jêra hene. Birêz Zûhêr, dema te xweş, bimînin di
xêr û xweşiyê de.
My greetings to him. Mr. Zuher, have a good time, stay in
goodness and happiness.
Hevalno, şeva wa xweş, bimînin di xêr û xweşiyê da.
Friends, have a good night, stay in goodness and happiness.
Bi min ra bin, dîsa vîdyokî xweş kîbar, emê noka wera
bisewirînin, vîdyokî din.
Stay with me, again a nice elegant video, we will now film
for you, another video.
Muaze gundê em ka herinê kî derê?
Muaze, which village will we go to?
Bililko.
Gundê Bililko. Hevalno gundê Bililko jî emê kî wera
bisewirînin. Bi min ra bin, yalla bay bay.
Bililko village. Friends, Bililko village too we will film
for you. Stay with me, yalla bye bye.