Merheba vollo, win çûne inşalla rihet ne? Hûro vîdê me li
binyanê gundê Dolgirê ye.
Hello folks, how are you, hopefully you are comfortable?
Today our video is in the Dolgirê village region.
Tebe'en dost û birayê me, xûçkê me ji me xwestine.
Of course, our friends and brothers, and our sisters asked
us for this.
Dolgirê, em hatin... ewê... cûq û menaq û kûni û virê ew
bikra, teswîr kira, me kina meraqa xerîbî.
Dolgirê, we came to... uh... to film the nooks and crannies
and corners and places, to satisfy the curiosity of the
expatriates.
Mihezet, tu çi dibêjî?
Mihezet (Co-host), what do you say?
Merheba mûtabi'înê me, win çûne, îşalla çûne sihet xweş,
şalê win gi hene rihet ne.
Hello our followers, how are you, God willing your health is
good, hope you are all comfortable.
Are îro vîdê me eceb li gundê Dolgirê ye, emê wêra
bisewirînin.
Yes, today our video is surprisingly in the village of
Dolgirê, we will film for you.
Bi me ra bin, em derbasî gundê Dolgirê bin, wêra vîdyokî
xweş û kîbar em wêra çêken.
Stay with us, let's enter the village of Dolgirê, we will
make a nice and classy video for you.
Are, are vollo, tebe'en Dolgirê jî maşalla gundekî pir mezin
e, xweş e, kîbar e.
Yes, yes folks, of course Dolgirê is also mashallah a very
big village, it is nice and classy.
Evola, Dolgirê jî mezin e.
Folks, Dolgirê is also big.
Şerî’e... şerî’a gund.
The street... the village street.
Are evola, viderê bîra avê ye, nav gunda.
Yes folks, this place is the water well, inside the village.
Oo, avo bîra avê ye.
Oh, that is the water well.
Are evola viderê jî şikeftek heye, likû qopê pi xistine.
Yes folks, there is a cave here too, look they have built a
dome over it.
Avo kevnar e, dibin werda çêbiye.
That is ancient, they say it was built back then.
Berîya me heye?
Is there anyone ahead of us?
Na.
No.
Heta dawîya gund herre.
Go to the end of the village.
Evola, ewwil car e emrê min da têim vî gundî.
Folks, this is the first time in my life I am coming to this
village.
Kuro hêdî.
Boy, slow down.
Are evola, tebe'en em hatin nav Dolgirê. Li vî derî jî bin
vê darê...
Yes folks, of course we came into Dolgirê. Here also under
this tree...
Maşalla xêr û bêr jî pir e. Me gû... temam berê vîdyokî xwe
da me wagû, me gû ka... wanê emr mezin...
Mashallah the bounty and blessings are plentiful. We said...
okay before our video we said, let's see... those of old
age...
Qîmetê vana zêde bin, evna xêr û bêr di vana da ye.
Their value is high, the bounty and blessings are within
them.
Seke cemaet, evna tune bin de'ê me mirî ye. Wekî dibên
firingî ne, na firingî ne.
Look community, if these people didn't exist, our mother
would be dead (idiom: we would be lost). Like they say
"tomatoes" (new generation), no they are not tomatoes.
Em hatin jî, î li vî derî iskambîl dilîzin, xwe ra bitesele
dibin tebe'en.
We arrived, and they are playing cards here, entertaining
themselves of course.
Ka em sivola ji pirsken.
Let's ask them a question.
Xalo, kîke me ra ser gund... navê xwe bêje?
Uncle, who will tell us about the village... say your name?
Evû Henan e de...
It's Abu Hanan, come on...
Kîke ser gund bipeyîve?
Who will speak about the village?
Evû Cemîl e? Evû...
Is it Abu Jemil? Abu...
Ebu Henan, Ebu Henan.
Abu Hanan, Abu Hanan.
Ka welim war viro.
Let him come here.
Şalo qijik bî ji derbênin... deng ke, bilo deng ke, avû kî
deng ke.
Take the small shawl off him... speak, let him speak, let
that one speak.
Temam. Merheba şîtar xalo.
Okay. Hello to you uncle.
Merheba, ahlen we sehlen.
Hello, welcome.
Ser serî me.
You are upon our heads (You are very welcome/respected).
Cemaeta we pirr bi xêr ser serî me, ahlen we sehlen.
Your group is very welcome, upon our heads, welcome.
Saet xweş. Xalo, am qenatê Efrîn 366, am xora gundo teswîr
dikin. Am tiştekî kîbar pêşkêşî milet dikin.
Good times to you. Uncle, we are channel Afrin 366, we are
filming villages for ourselves. We present something classy
to the people.
Tu kanî me ra çend...
Can you [tell] us a few...
Ser çava, xoş.
With pleasure (Upon my eyes), nice.
Tu kanî çend gotina me ra ser vî gundî... tarîxa vî gundî,
çiqas sale?
Can you say a few words to us about this village... the
history of this village, how old is it?
Tarîxa xwe pirr ji mêj e. Ewwilê xwe vî gundî... Duxuy
tîbî... ciyabî (cihê bî).
Its history is very old. In its beginning, this village...
was [at] Duxuy... it was separate.
Ciya bî.
It was separate.
Hatim vî gundî, bin artê (erdê) kûlan, giçirin şikefta.
[They] came to this village, dug the bottom of the earth,
they entered the caves.
Berê di şikefta da dijîn?
Did they live in caves before?
Ketin şikefto, milet.
The people entered the caves.
Ketin şikefta.
They entered the caves.
Piştî wî her kesî mala ser girtin, kuşkê di me ji hatin.
After that, everyone built a house on top, our
pavilions/houses also came [to be built].
Berê di şikefta tîda bûn, heft mal, oylaxê (cûylaxê) wî da
bûn.
Before, they were inside the caves, seven families were in
its surroundings.
Heft oyle di şikeft ke da bûn?
Seven families were inside the caves?
Belê, oyle yek e. Ji malê ewilî mezin in, yek tîda bûn.
Yes, it is one family. From the first great house, they were
one inside.
Ê şivte (hefte) ketin vî gundî, Qere hebû, Muhemmed hebû...
So seven [people/families] entered this village, there was
Qere, there was Muhammed...
Oyle... oyle ma wekî, bira bûn, yek in.
The family... the family remained like, they were brothers,
they are one.
Yek malbata ne.
It is one family [lineage].
Yek jê mir li hefde xiste, gû gaz (gazin) mirim, kîş bî...
One of them died at seventeen, he said [unclear:
gas/complaint?] I died, he was pulled/withdrawn...
Bijîjkê (bijîşkê) gote ha, ti rûy nanî.
The doctor said ha, you don't face [unclear phrase].
Gullo bî tê qere lînê.
Gullo was there [unclear name/phrase].
Qere.
Qere lînê.
They called him Qere.
Î oylê me u wan va... Qere gi yek e.
And our family and those... Qere is all one.
Ê ma wa, mala Aqîl û, mala Ebdê û şêx, mala Bekî Elî kîye,
ya hewna gi yek in.
So it remained, the House of Aqil, and the House of Ebdê and
the Sheikh, the House of Beki Eli, all of these are one.
Wa ji, ewa başqe bî. Nû vlinim (nizanim) em çîkê hev dibin.
That too, that was separate. I don't know now what relation
we are to each other.
Teyib xalo, xê nav lê kirin Dolgirê? Ya'nî Dolgirê.
Okay uncle, why did they name it Dolgirê? Meaning Dolgirê.
Ê dar... dar gir... dar... darê reş mezin heye.
Uh tree... big tree... tree... there is a big black tree.
Dar gir.
Big tree.
Dar mezin e.
It's a big tree.
Ma'nî vê darê nav lê inan "Dar Gir".
Meaning, because of this tree, they named it "Big Tree" (Dar
Gir -> Dolgirê).
Dolgir.
Ma'nî nûvî vê darê nav lê nan Dar Gir.
Meaning, the name of this tree, they named it Big Tree.
Dar Gir, paşê bû Dolgirê.
Big Tree (Dar Gir), then it became Dolgirê.
Dor... Dor... Dorik, li wir dibên "Dedey".
Dor... Dor... Dorik, over there they call it "Dedey".
Dorik.
Dor mezin e.
It's a big cycle/tree [Context: Likely refering to the tree
size or type].
Ma'nî vê darê nav lê nan "Dar Gir".
Meaning, because of this tree they named it "Big Tree".
Bûn b'navî wê, bûn b'navî wê.
They became [known] by its name, they became by its name.
Gund b'navê darê hat naskirin.
The village became known by the name of the tree.
Dolgirê bi navê wê darê hat naskirin.
Dolgirê became known by the name of that tree.
Teyib xalo, çiqas malbat li vir da heye? Dolgirê.
Okay uncle, how many families are here? [In] Dolgirê.
Teqrîben wekî du sed û bîst û pênc hewsa heye.
Approximately like two hundred and twenty-five or so.
Sikonê (sakinê) xo ge (gi) heye, holiyan (hêlîn) ge hene?
Are its inhabitants all here, are the nests (homes) all
here?
Noker (nokar) ge hatine.
The servants/workers [people] have all come.
Ewa heşwê da ge hatin.
Those have all come in the stuffing [idiom: into the
mix/crowd].
Rind e, mala Xwedê ava be.
It's good, may God build God's house (May God bless them).
Xalo me'îşet çû? Me'îşet li viro, gundo.
Uncle, how is the livelihood? Livelihood here, in the
village.
Walla me'îşet... te'ban bî.
Wallah, livelihood... was tired (bad).
Te'ban bî.
It was bad.
Te'ban bî. Milet hat... hevna...
It was bad. The people came... these...
Î nexweş bî, î qehrî derbî, gi dimirin milet, pirr mir.
The one who was sick, the one who left in grief, the people
are all dying, many died.
Pirr mir ne?
Many died, right?
Pirr mir. Ji qehrê û siqilmişbêş (siqilmişbûnê). Kines (kes)
tune bîne, ji qehrê fikire.
Many died. From grief and distress. There was nobody, [they
died] from grief and thinking (worry).
Ji fikirê.
From worry.
Fikirê xo ne behese.
Don't let your thoughts sense it.
Ê hey jî wekî merkol (bêhna milet) gi nexweş in.
And now too, like the people's spirit/breath is all unwell.
Xwedê emrê te dirêj ke hekiyo be.
May God prolong your life, let it be so.
Elhemdulila, am hatin em fireh lemîn bûn.
Praise be to God, we came and we were relieved/happy.
Xwedê sihet û xwesî bide te.
May God give you health and happiness.
We elhemdula rind e, bes î pirr gi şar zeytûna dijîn.
And praise be to God it is good, but the majority all live
on olives.
Ser zeytûna.
On olives.
Zeytûna. Paşê dûro rez...
Olives. Then later vineyards...
Xalo tê bêjî çi, em çanda vî gundî diparêzin vî gundî wey,
dorgir e?
Uncle, what do you say, we are preserving the culture of
this village, this village, is it surrounded?
Ê şeqafet, milet belê wiyaye şeqafet çû. Çû binê erdê
wiyaye. Hûnda, ferman, giya revî.
Oh culture, indeed the people are like that, culture is
gone. It went underground like that. Lost, chaos, everything
fled.
Wela maşala berî vê vîdyok me çêkir, dimîlê ji cimeatek anha
kola hebî, a pir gundî digerim a pir bes kola nate mey wekî
we, hinek mezin maşala min go wekî cîcaka ne.
Well mashallah, before this video we made one, I wish there
was a group now that had the 'kola' (traditional hat), I
look around many villages, but the 'kola' doesn't come to us
like yours, some elders mashallah I said they are like
flowers.
Hemdilla. Keçkê me.
Praise God. Our daughters.
Me dîtî nê, a me de bibînin.
We haven't seen them, we will see them.
Serî serî de tu. Go tene, silavkê bişîne ji milet ra, kesê
me el me seyr dikin.
First of all, you. Just send a greeting to the people, our
people who are watching us.
E wela saeta we ya xweş, û hatina we ya xweş, Xwedê pêxember
ji we razî be, saeta we ya xweş, hun hatin pêşîya milet
dikin, milet ferman dibe, û pêşda derê. Kêfa me. Kêfa Xwedê
weyî gwa de saeta we ya xweş, Xwedê pêxember ji we razî be.
Well, may your time be happy, and your coming be happy, may
God and the Prophet be pleased with you, may your time be
happy, you came and lead the people, the people become
organized, and go forward. Our pleasure. God's pleasure is
that your time be happy, may God and the Prophet be pleased
with you.
Û îşdar be û wetenê Xwedê ji wan ji we razî be.
And may it be prosperous and God's homeland, may He be
pleased with them and you.
Amîn, amîn. Xalo Xwedê te bihêle.
Amen, amen. Uncle may God keep you.
Xwedê pêxember ji we razî be, û nuh ten...
May God and the Prophet be pleased with you, and now you...
Emê camê, tişkî vexwin. Saeta te xweş Xwedê te bihêle. Wela
emkê nav gund lokas teswîr kin, û emê hevdû bibînin inşela.
We will [have] a glass, drink something. Good luck to you,
may God keep you. Well, we will film locations inside the
village, and we will see each other God willing.
Ka bimeşo biner, volvo no?
Let's walk and see, the new Volvo?
Maşala xêr bêrê vê derê heye. Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te
xalo, ji mawzûdê te, xora çend poket xwo jî didin a?
Mashallah there is bounty in this place. May God give you a
long life uncle, regarding your diesel, they give you a few
packets for yourself too right?
Mawzûd û benzin e...
It is diesel and petrol...
Vir jî xora se poket xwdîn a ne, xora vî derê sarsîya
iskambîl dilîstin, xora teselat bun, wextê xwe derbas dikin.
Here they ate three packets themselves right, here they
played cards in the cool, they were comforted, passing their
time.
Binêre darê tûra şîn e, esasê gund e yanî.
Look the mulberry tree is green, it's the foundation of the
village basically.
Maşala. Emê noka herin.
Mashallah. We will go now.
Navê Şêr e...
Name is Lion...
Are avo nû teban, xwelî me meraye, avo li vê şikeftna jî
bigre kevnor in ev jî.
Yes guys, naturally, the dust is killing us, guys capture
these caves too, they are ancient.
Vê germê, motorê germ dibe.
In this heat, the engine gets hot.
Are wela dinya jî germ e.
Yes well the weather is hot too.
Îja emkê nava hespî xwe têr av bikin, emê ca hênik kin, dûr
herin.
So we will give our horse [car] plenty of water, we will
cool it down, go far.
Wela mezin e xalo gund.
Well the village is big uncle.
Gund niçika sê sed, sê sed û pêncî mal heye.
The village is roughly three hundred, three hundred and
fifty houses.
Maşala.
Mashallah.
Ebû Henan dibê te şêx, Ebû Henan li şerê va şemo dûr xwe
d'ajon.
Abu Henan tells you sheikh, Abu Henan drives far away in the
fight of this Shamo.
Eywa.
Okay.
Bas nîzamî sê sed, sê sed û pêncî mal e.
But the layout is 300, 350 houses.
Yanî ji sê sed û pêncî malî, imkin sed mal puştî ne.
Meaning out of 350 houses, maybe 100 houses are empty.
Herin de?
They left?
Na gundîya zeft kirin.
No, the villagers took over.
Ê bişî bigrin we hewar hatina.
Let them take it, you came to the rescue.
Rêk dîk e xalo?
Is the road straight uncle?
Are lo kuro... rêk e.
Yes oh boy... it is a road.
Ê gundî me xweş gund zeft kirin.
Eh, our villagers took over the village well.
Are avo nû teban weyê hember me jî Mabata ye.
Yes guys, naturally, the one opposite us is Mabata.
Li ser vê Qenterê ye. Înşala vîdîyê mal wer heye emê teswîr
kin.
It is on this Qentere. God willing there is a video of the
house we will film.
Ev jî Mabata ye ne xalo?
This is Mabata too right uncle?
Na Mabata wekî yak, Mabata mezin e.
No Mabata is like one, Mabata is big.
Emê vîdîyê mal wer heye, emkê teswîr kin nîzik da inşala.
We have a video of the house, we will film it up close God
willing.
De bila.
Let it be.
Dê nava Mabata nahyê ye.
Inside Mabata is a sub-district.
Yanî rêka xwe çîçikê çetin e ne, şareha xwe, em nikanin
dighûratê kevin...
Meaning its road is a bit difficult right, its street, we
can't get into the holes...
Xalo emrê te dare çiqas e?
Uncle how much is your age?
Emrê min ketiye darê heftê û pênc salî ro ye.
My age has reached the level of 75 years today.
Maşala.
Mashallah.
Ez bum gutinê...
I became [the subject of] saying...
Teban lê. Kevnor e.
Naturally. It is ancient.
Avo nû maşala vê gundî, mêrek dibê sê sed, sê sed û pêncî
mal e.
Guys now mashallah this village, a man says it is 300, 350
houses.
Dibêjê sê sed mal bad, ne lê mal ne. Hene geh ne mesela
hewş, xarûba ye, î haî jî li dervayî Ewropa ye.
He says 300 houses, look at the houses. There are some for
example courtyards, ruins, and these are outside in Europe.
... gund nizanin...
...village don't know...
Avo nû ev gunda pir kevnor e. Seke hewşek li vir e, kevnor
e.
Guys now this village is very ancient. Look there is a
courtyard here, it is ancient.
Şikeft têda pir in.
Caves are many in it.
Berê aba me bes bî.
In the past our fathers were enough.