Hezar û nehsed û deh û yek û duduyê, tarîxa vê rêkê...
One thousand nine hundred and ten, one and two (1912), the
date of this railway...
Milet, avore, ava Rajoe teb'an...
People, look here, this represents Rajo of course...
Vêra dibên ava Rajoe teb'an, û bişêti jê derin.
They call this Rajo's water of course, and it is drinkable
too.
Ka, kanîna li vî alî heye? Belê av dardiket.
Look, is there a spring on this side? Yes, water is coming
out.
Xelkê berê av vedixwarin.
People in the past used to drink this water.
Kêlîbû...
Kêlîbû [Village Name]...
Nokame derbasbin...
We will pass through now...
Hevalno, xelkê te xwedê, em îro li van deran, sed sal e...
sed salî û bêtir e...
Friends, for God's sake, we are in these places today, it is
a hundred years... a hundred years and more...
Yanî nakim... Em gundê Kêlîbû... mehella jêrîn de...
That is to say... We are in Kêlîbû village... in the lower
neighborhood...
Xola Xwedê re bay bay... Mehella teyî ba...
Goodbye for God's sake... The upper neighborhood...
Were, were...
Come, come...
Erê hevalê me...
Yes, our friends...
Ava vîdyokê hejar, em wara li Qutx ne, ser kupriya hesinî,
Qutx.
This poor video, we are here in Qutxa, on the iron bridge,
Qutxa.
Vêra dibên Pira Qutx.
They call this the Qutxa Bridge.
Me'rûf e. Qunaq... Bi nav vîra dibên Qunaq.
It is famous. "Qunaq" [Station/Mansion]... They call this
place by the name "Qunaq".
Mehetta hesin li vê derê bû.
The railway station was in this place.
Ebû Semîr kî ye, noka me ra hewaldê, tarîxê vê... Çûye?
Who is Abu Samir, he will now give us information, the
history of this... Where did it go?
Keramke Ebû Semîr, me ra hewaldê.
Please Abu Samir, give us the information.
Were me ra.
Come to us.
Bûrin derbas... Serê... [unintelligible]
Let's pass... On the... [unintelligible]
Were me ra.
Come to us.
Keramke Ebû Semîr.
Please go ahead, Abu Samir.
Em noka li ser kupriya Qutx... Qunaq e.
We are now on the Qutxa Bridge... It is a "Qunaq" [Station].
Qunaq... li gundê teqrîben, ê gundî be'dî noy...
The Station... in the village roughly, the village after
this...
Li nahiya Rajo dikeve.
It falls within the Rajo district.
Ev hesino, vê çêbû... Ev hesino çêbû ji mabeyna Tirkiyê...
This railway, this was built... This railway was built
between Turkey...
Û Rajo... Ji Rajo ra derbas dibe Efrîn, tê Efrîn ra derbas
dibe Heleb...
And Rajo... From Rajo it passes to Afrin, from Afrin it
passes to Aleppo...
Ji Heleb ji diçe Şamê.
From Aleppo it goes to Damascus.
Fransa wextî vêra çêkirî, hezar nehsed... deh û yek û
dudu...
When France built this here, one thousand nine hundred...
ten, and one, and two [1912]...
Deh û duduya intihâ kir.
It was finished in '12.
Hezar nehsed deh û yek û dudu, û Bûrin warin... ma'rîf
tarîxê rind te'kîd kin.
One thousand nine hundred and twelve, and come let's see...
let's confirm the known date well.
Li ser vî darî jî, o belê ye.
On this stone as well, look it is clear.
Sebra belê ye.
Wait, it is clear.
Me ra nîzik bike, tarîxê gînde, wa binêrin.
Bring it closer to us, the date is right there, look here.
Hezar, nehsed, deh û yek û dudu, tarîxê vê rêkê.
One thousand, nine hundred, ten, one and two [1912], the
date of this railway.
Dînan ser her hesinkî, teb'an li ser heye.
Look on every iron piece, of course it is written on it.
Ser vayî heye, ê pişta heye.
It's on this one, and it's on the back one.
Ebû Semîr, berê xelkê vir çi dikir, çi nedikir?
Abu Samir, what did the people here used to do or not do in
the past?
Vê derê kanîk pir mezin li vê derê heye.
Here, there is a very large spring in this place.
Bin vê kaniyê, miletê me, mentiqa me, git dihatin li bin vê
kupriyê.
Below this spring, our people, our region, all used to come
under this bridge.
Kanîk pir rind e, munasib e, avê ginde pir pak bû.
It is a very nice spring, suitable, the water there was very
clean.
Salê heta salê din ma.
From year to year it remained.
Ê miletê me dihat li vê derê, kincê xwe, vê derê istîrahetê
xwe li vê derê dibirin.
So our people used to come here, [washing] their clothes,
and taking their rest here in this place.
Cîkî pirê muheterm ê hadî ye.
It is a very respectable and quiet place.
Hindik şîn li ser vê tilî... Xora digerin, xora li dor
mentiqa xwe dinêrin.
A little greenery on this hill... They walk around, looking
around their own region.
Ê ev jî qunaq e, o mela wî zanibin, qunaq e, ji ber vêra
dibên qunaq.
And this is a "Qunaq" [Station], oh mullahs you should know,
it is a station, that is why they call it "Qunaq".
Rêkê bigre, hevalî min rêkê jî bigre.
Film the railway, my friend film the railway too.
Werne, ava rêka Rajo ye.
Look, this is the Rajo railway.
Milet, ava rêka Rajo ye. Devera darin Rajo teb'an, û peşêtir
jî darin Efrîn.
People, this is the Rajo railway. Going that way goes to
Rajo of course, and further ahead goes to Afrin.
Û bi me ra bin jî, noka emê werin biniya vir, kanîk hebû emê
teswîr kin, û bi me ra bin.
And stay with us, we will now come underneath here, there
was a spring we will film, so stay with us.
Emkê herin gundê Kêlîbû.
We will go to the village of Kêlîbû.
Hevalkî me ji me xwestî, gundê Kêlîbû, emkê vêra teswîr kin.
A friend of ours asked us, the village of Kêlîbû, we will
film there.
İnşallah leqtekî xweş, emê werin li gundê Kêlîbû temam
bikin.
God willing, a nice clip, we will come and finish at the
village of Kêlîbû.
Bi me ra bin.
Stay with us.
Erê milet, wekî way dî ye, ava biniya kupriyê ye.
Yes people, as you have seen, this is underneath the bridge.
Li vê derê... kanîna li vê derê hebû, berê av dardiket.
In this place... there used to be a spring in this place,
water used to come out before.
Xelkê berê av vedixwar. Li vê derê herim merim dişûştin.
People in the past drank the water. Here they washed flock
and wool.
Bes av nema ye, ya heram.
But there is no water left, what a pity.
Îsal baran ne katin.
This year it didn't rain.
Vê derê gi qewaq bûn, gi dar bûn.
This place was all poplars, it was all trees.
Ê lê sêrke, ê zone be.
Hey, look at it, and be aware.
Erê hevalê me, vê derê Qutx e.
Yes my friends, this place is Qutxa.
Vêra dibên Qutx.
They call this place Qutxa.
Carna dibên Qunaq.
Sometimes they call it "Qunaq".
Ava mala Şewqî, vêra dibên.
This is Shawqi's house, as they say here.
Ev mal moka, ê mala Şewqî ne.
These houses here, they are Shawqi's houses.
Heta besa mala Ekif e.
This is just Akif's house.
Ev Qutx e.
This is Qutxa.
Ev darê malê nebê ne.
These are the trees of the Nabi family.
Ebû Semîr vî xurmî bigire.
Abu Samir, film this rubble/ruin.
Ava... kêlî bû.
This... was a "Kêlî" [Headstone/Pillar/Marker].
Kêlî... Navê gund ji vê Kêlîyê hatiye.
Kêlî... The name of the village came from this "Kêlî".
Gundê Kêlîbû. Vêra dibên Kêlîbû.
The village of Kêlîbû. They call this place Kêlîbû.
Yanî kêlîk mezin li vê derê hebû.
Meaning, there was a large pillar/stone marker here.
Navê gund danîne ser wê kêliyê.
They named the village after that pillar.
Noka emê derbasbin, herin gundê Kêlîbû.
Now we will pass through, going to the village of Kêlîbû.
Berê vê derê şîn bû, hereket pir bû.
Before, this place was green, there was a lot of
movement/activity.
Kanî hebû, xalk dihatin vir kincê xwe dişûştin.
There was a spring, people used to come here to wash their
clothes.
Yanî dihatin... awê, siyaha... Efrîn va, derava, ji dûr va
dihatin vê derê.
Meaning they used to come... that, tourism... from Afrin,
from outside, from far away they came here.
Carna pir kanî hebûn.
Sometimes there were many springs.
Ava mefraqa Kêlîbû ye.
This is the Kêlîbû intersection.
Ev kanîk li vir hebû, digotin kaniya berbenê.
There was a spring here, they called it the Barbene Spring.
Li ser mefraqa gundê Kêlîbû ye.
It is at the intersection of Kêlîbû village.
O noka em ketin, mefraqa gundê Kêlîbû.
And now we have entered the intersection of Kêlîbû village.
Ava jî, ewê sêramîka, blata darok...
And this here, that ceramics, the paving tiles...
Minşare, minşare vê dibên.
A sawmill, they call this a sawmill.
Teda tirba...
Inside the tomb...
[Music starts and continues until the end of the video]
Erê hevalê me, gundekî, la bavo gundekî pir çûçik e.
Yes my friend, it is a village, oh man, it is a very small
village.
Yanî ne mezin e. Gî de şora axo hene.
Meaning it is not big. It has its own soil/story inside it.
Em nika paş gund in e. Zotir evana mal in, û paş gundî jî
zeytûn e.
We are currently behind the village. Down there are the
houses, and behind the village are olive trees.
Hem ber me jî sevî ye. Ewa sevî ye jor.
And in front of us is an orchard. That orchard up there.
Ya heram evna hewşek hene hedîmîne gîştek.
What a pity, there is a courtyard here, they have ruined
everything.
Erê hevalê me, dûr û nêz...
Yes my friend, far and near...
Hevalê me, ev darno, dar dibin qitax, hev darno qitax e.
My friend, these trees, trees become huge, these trees are
huge.
Emrê vana sed sal e, sed salî û barjor yanî.
Their age is a hundred years, a hundred years and more, that
is.
Yanî ne kêmî sedî, ser sedî re.
Meaning not less than a hundred, over a hundred.
Em va, em li Qitax ne nika. Mezin e.
We are here, we are at the Qitax [Big Trees] now. It is big.
Evana darê qitax ne. Em... qeterê kor a jî...
These are the huge trees. We... and the blind train too...
Mistefo, xaletî, vê vîdyo sêr ke, va erdê we ye ha.
Mustafa, Auntie, watch this video, this is your land here.
Xaletî me, Mistefo, milolê sêr ke, va erdê xwe ye, zeytûnê
xwe ne. Tê dî ye?
My Auntie, Mustafa, look at the mallow plants, this is your
own land, your own olives. Do you see?
Xaletî were, were manta hewşek ji xwed re verda bigre.
Auntie come, come and take a courtyard here for yourself.
Mistefo, ha we şûna bêtûn kir, dar kir.
Mustafa, look they made the place concrete, they planted
trees.
Ha erdê we yî paqij cût kirine, tê dî ye?
Look, they plowed your land cleanly, do you see?
Mehderkî top diverda wala.
A ball field is over there, by God.
Tu natê tê da nagirî, xaletî ezê werim tê da bigrim ha,
istixfil...
You don't come and occupy it, Auntie I will come and occupy
it then, I'll take advantage...
Heke pêş kim. Ezê werim hewşek xwe tê da bigrim.
If I proceed. I will come and take a courtyard for myself in
it.
Erê hevalê me, em nika mefreqê Ba'dîno ne.
Yes my friends, we are now at the Ba'dino intersection.
Ev çato gundê me ye. Ev qorma jî, darê Mekbezel daro no.
This is our village crossroad. And this trunk, the tree of
the Mekbezel trees.
Zoter Raco. Temam bike, derê Raco.
Downwards is Rajo. Finish it, the Rajo road.
Bîr mekin layk û iştiraq ji bo sefhê ten.
Don't forget like and subscription for our page.
Û bi me re bin vîdyokî din xweş û hêja, emê we re pêş kêş
biken. Se'ta we xweş.
And stay with us for another nice and valuable video, we
will present it to you. Thanks.
Eva cîyê qehwê... Berê qehwe diverda bû.
That is the place of the coffeehouse... Before, the
coffeehouse was over there.
Eva kafîterye ye... avo vedxwin çay û...
That is the cafeteria... they drink tea and...
Şûn bigir, mekbeze bigir. Xalê Qadir ro lo heye bigir.
Film the place, film the press/dump. Uncle Qadir is there,
film him.
Mehelle, mehelle ginda, mehelle ginda.
The neighborhood, village neighborhood, village
neighborhood.
Xalo Qadir, bay bay, mehellê te ye wa. Were were.
Uncle Qadir, bye bye, this is your neighborhood. Come come.