Yo, ne texîr e, texîr e nîne.
No, it’s not late, there is no delay.
Sê sal e min tebê korî dikê.
For three years, I have been following you blindly.
Avo, ji serî ba bokê min e...
Brother, from the start, it was my [steering] box...
Bok çêkir na? Berê çîçikê xerabe bî, noka teslîh kirine, gû
çêkirine.
He fixed the box, right? Before, the small part was broken,
now they repaired it, they fixed it up well.
Avo xudê ne eh... çêkirî... navê wî avo... Xalê Hisên jî
zûda rehmetî bî, sala deh hezar û pêncî... hûno?
Brother, by God... he didn't... fix it... his name,
brother... Uncle Hussein passed away a long time ago, the
year ten thousand and fifty... you know?
Avo, seke heffar e, ya lîj e, pertîj e, ev e, heffar e.
Brother, look, it's a driller, it's sludge, it's debris,
this is it, it's a driller.
Berê... ma rî nos bî... ma rî... ma rî...
Before... was it half... was it... was it...
...gol xwestî...
...wanted round...
Heştê dolarî?
Eighty dollars?
Heştê dolarî.
Eighty dollars.
Na, ewel...
No, before...
Agahî da... navê te derketî... îno... te me'rûf e bi wî
pîyê... bi wî emrê...
He gave information... your name came out... you know... you
are famous with that foot... with that age...
Xizmetê dikê.
You are doing a service.
Siheta gundîyê xweş... xora li ber e rûniştin.
Health to the villagers... sitting in front of it for
themselves.
Wextê baranê kirî, avo, am hatin cê me... bloka... cê me
hewşê...
When it rained, brother, we came to our place... the
blocks... our courtyard place...
Merheba ji we ra hevalno, hevalno... disan em hatin vîdyokî
xweş û kîbar.
Hello to you friends, friends... we have come again with a
nice and elegant video.
Erê hevalno, teben îro jî xelqa, dora gundî min e, gundî
Ba'dîna.
Yes friends, of course, today the episode, the turn is for
my village, the village of Baadina.
Em kê li wera bisewrînin gundî Ba'dîna. Teben şababê
Ba'dîna, miletê gundî Ba'dîna ji me daxwaz e îne em gundî
Ba'dîna teswîr kin.
We are going to film the village of Baadina for you there.
Of course, the youth of Baadina, the people of Baadina
village requested from us that we film the village of
Baadina.
Erê, îro cewekî xweş e û kîbar e û hêdî ye... nerm e, baran
lê dikê, bînî axê tê, xerîbîkî hûrik e.
Yes, today is a nice and elegant and calm atmosphere... it
is mild, it is raining, the smell of soil is coming, it is a
light drizzle.
Emê noka wera vîdyokî xweş û kîbar, nav gundî Ba'dîna
bisewrînin.
We will now film a nice and elegant video for you inside the
village of Baadina.
Gundî xwo, ezê pêşwe kim. Tebîet e gundî Ba'dîna çawa ye.
My own village, I will present it. How the nature of Baadina
village is.
Me'zel bîrin gotina tenê, bîrin.
Don't forget the saying either, don't forget.
Sibe we bi xêr hevalno, ma hûn çûne, şîwa çûne, sihet çûye,
şolê giyan rûni rihet ne?
Good morning friends, how are you, how are things, how is
your health, are all works going comfortably?
Erê îro jî vîdî me li gundî me ye, teben li Ba'dîna, em kê
çêkin.
Yes, today our video is in our village, naturally in
Baadina, we will make it.
Bimar bin heta dawî vîdîo, û berî hûn dikevin vîdîo zî,
laykê û îştîrakê pê dinê, û te'lîq nexweş kîbar binivîsînin
paşê têkevin vîdîo.
Stay with us until the end of the video, and before you
enter the video too, give it a like and subscription, and
write a nice elegant comment, then enter the video.
Erê û siheta we giyan xweş e.
Yes, and good health to you all.
Sihet xweş e, me'zel. Erê hevalno, teben em li vir jî dîsa
wa bîzakirinin, uh, Mefrûşat Îbo.
Good health, indeed. Yes friends, naturally we will remind
you here again about, uh, Ibo Furniture.
Birakê me Hûsam, bîr neken, li Almanya, hanê, Kêlak Koln...
unwanê geda hevajî hewe.
Our brother Husam, don't forget, in Germany, over there,
near Cologne... the address fits perfectly too.
Îmkan e vêra tewasul kin, mefrûşat gelekî malê kêne, wera
wênê bîgîne, pêşî hewşê we.
It is possible to contact there, the furniture is very good
stuff, bring the image to you, in front of your yard.
Saet'a we xweş, ko bi mera bin em derbas gundî Ba'dîna bin
jî.
Good health to you, come with us as we enter the village of
Baadina as well.
Avo lî me qorma jî nîzik bike.
Brother, zoom nicely in on me too.
Gundî Ba'dîna jî hevalno pir mezin e.
The village of Baadina, friends, is very large.
Hazar mal e ya.
It is a thousand houses.
Hazar mal e, tabiî nuhê mobata ye.
A thousand houses, naturally in the Mabata district.
Erê.
Yes.
Hînokî gelek ciz' têda çêbibin, le'nî pir mezin e.
Many parts will be made in it, because it is very large.
[Music Playing]
Erê hevalno, gundî Ba'dîna pir gundekî xweş e, kîbar e.
Yes friends, the village of Baadina is a very nice village,
it is elegant.
[Music continues with vocals]
Erê hevalno medxel destpêkir.
Yes friends, the entrance has started.
[Music continues]
Wadi ye, gerek medxelî gunda gaha nobe.
It is a valley, the entrance of the villages should be like
this.
Duxulî tike diki dikeve, gerek dar bin û wana hêşinayî hebe.
When you make the entry and enter, there must be trees and
there should be greenery like this.
Teben noka wextê pelkî dara qawîye, çilî dara weşîye.
Of course, now is the time when tree leaves turn brown, the
tree clothes [leaves] have fallen.
Yan berî tibê timê bisevrînda ge hêşinî bî. Seke darê şemsî
ge cilê xwo weşîne.
Or if you had filmed before, it would have been totally
green. Look at the sun [umbrella] trees, they have all shed
their clothes.
Xelqê kazoxaa kirine.
People have pruned them.
Medxelî gunda gerek gaha nobe.
The entrance of villages should be like this.
Vira jî meqbezek hecer çêkirine, ê neda, ê made malê
midawer.
They have built a stone quarry/press here too, not that one,
the circular material one.
Xwedê rizqê gundî bişîne.
May God send sustenance to the villagers.
Ah...
Meqbesê zeytûna, teqrîben şeş meqbes zeytûna di gundî me da
hene.
Olive presses, there are approximately six olive presses in
our village.
[Music Playing]
Oh wadi ye, wadiyê xelçû wehşatî aha dike, maşallah çû
emîdîna wadi ye. Reş, çîmentîqozî pir.
Oh it is a valley, the valley has gone wild like this,
mashallah look at the hope of the valley. Black [soil], very
romantic.
Gundî meda jî hewşê heywan dana ho.
In our village, there are animal yards/stables like this.
Erê hevalno, evû sêlafe hekê mektebê heffarê li wa mînim.
Yes friends, I will leave this flood of the Heffar school
story to them.
Vira dibên Heffarê.
They call this place Heffar.
Miletê gundî Ba'dîna zone, vî derê Heffarê ye.
The people of Baadina village know, this place is Heffar.
Evû mekteba gundî me ye.
This is our village's school.
Erê hevalno, evû mekteba Ba'dîna ye.
Yes friends, this is the school of Baadina.
Wadi ye?
Is it a valley?
Teben poc çêkirine, berê cîcikê xerabe bî, noka teslîh
kirine, gû çêkirine.
Naturally, they paved it, before the small bit was ruined,
now they repaired it, they made it well.
Sofê genda zîde kirine, heta dawîyakê ye.
They increased the street curbs too, until the very end.
Gû plot kirî ye.
It is paved well with stones.
Kirsî jî çêkirine.
They made benches too.
Wul vî derê jî, kelakê min rastê, camîk me ra çêkirin. Camî
me berê heye jû, camî me kevnar e.
And right here too, on my right side, they built a mosque
for us. We had a mosque before up there, our mosque is
ancient.
E munezemê jî, yek li vî derê zîde kir, çêkir.
And the organization, they added one in this place, they
built it.
Ev vî derê hewş pir zîde bîne.
In this place, the courtyards have become very abundant.
Teben ev diki şim jî meqbez e.
Naturally, this one facing us is also a press.
Ew jî meqbez e, Salah e, Salahê malê Midawer.
That is also a press, it is Salah's, Salah of the Midawer
family.
[Music Playing]
Erê hevalno, eve jî cem'a Mistosef e.
Yes friends, this is also the Mistosef (Clinic/Dispensary)
gathering place.
Evî jêrî me jî Mistosefê gundî me ye.
This one below us is our village's clinic.
Yanê kasek nexweş bibe, derbibe, qicik têkevî vî derê, belaş
yanê xizmet dikin.
Meaning if someone gets sick, gets injured, a child falls in
this place, they serve for free.
Saet'a wan jî xweş.
Good health to them too.
[Music Playing]
Arê hevalno, eviya hember me jî, medaqa avê ye.
Yes friends, this opposite us, is the water distribution
point.
Avê cem gundî me, jiyî gundê Giya Pirtê ye.
The water for our villagers, is from the village of Giya
Pirtê.
Bes welekin munezemê hat vira termîm kir, çêkir.
But an organization came here, renovated it, and fixed it.
E hîn lewh şemsîyê ne rakibandine.
They haven't installed the solar panels yet.
Ove me ji Giya Pirtê ye.
Our water is from Giya Pirtê.
Bîra me 400 metre kûr kirine.
They dug our well 400 meters deep.
Ov ji Giya Pirtê ye.
The water is from Giya Pirtê.
Bes hîn munezemê caiz nekiriye... termîm kirin, caiz kirin.
But the organization hasn't finished it yet... they
renovated it, they readied it.
Li ser esas lewh şemsîyê me re bînin.
On the basis that they will bring us solar panels.
De hîn mayî... nizanim.
So it is still pending... I don't know.
Va derê, dûbera bin dîwar, hefare... dîwar e bi rastî.
Here, passing below the wall, the excavation... it's a wall
actually.
Tasorê! Tasorê!
Tasorê! Tasorê! [Calling a person]
Ha?
Huh?
Ev o dîwar e.
This is that wall.
Vana jî bigir... vana jî bigir... vana heq dikim...
Record these guys too... record these guys too... I really
appreciate them...
Arê ev jî şebabê gundî me ne... Xalê Xelîl e û ev in.
Yes, these are the youth of our village... Uncle Khalil and
them.
Maro vîdeo gundî xoda çêke çawa rind e?
Man, making a video in one's own village, isn't it nice?
Bas maro eyb dike... xêr maro gundî xoda vîdeo çêdike maro
eyb dike?
But one feels shy... why should one feel shy making a video
in their own village?
Arê hevalno, ev sebîla jî...
Yes friends, this water fountain too...
Me xwest ku em olmozê berî vê, me vêra çêkir.
We wanted to make this aluminum facing for it, so we made
it.
Saeta gundî ya xweş, em dîsa di vîdeoyê xoda bezakînin.
Health to the villagers, we will mention it again in our
video.
O havo, Xwedana yê çêkirîk... navê yovo.
And this, the owner who made it... [unclear name].
Xalê Hisên jî zûda rehmetî bûye, sala du hezar û pêncda.
Uncle Hussein passed away a while ago, in the year 2005.
Xwedê rehme xolê ke, me l'vir çêkir.
May God have mercy on him, we built it here.
Me'nî miletê gund, wela milet mirin d'mirin têne ovê
vedxwen.
Meaning the village people, well people keep dying
[generations pass], they come and drink this water.
Misnî ovê... teb'an li vê derê jî me ew pêxist.
The pitcher for water... naturally, here too we paved this.
Vê derê jî me... avo pêxist. Silef me hî esînê pêxistibû.
Here too we... paved this. The path, we had paved it with
concrete before.
Tolê jî... me avo pêxist.
The rest too... we paved this.
Vana haş e, me ketik jî pêxistî, me'nî qicik nebin,
dernekevin.
This is the edge, we also paved the curb, meaning so the
kids don't fall, don't go out.
Teb'an nîzamî ne.
Naturally, it is orderly.
Arê. Xwedê rehma xol li miriyê gund ke, cihê xwo cinet be.
Yes. May God have mercy on the village's dead, may their
place be paradise.
Rind e.
It is good.
Arê hevalno, li vê derê jî em ber mezelê Şêx Reşîd in.
Yes friends, here too we are in front of the shrine of
Sheikh Rashid.
Silavê min ji birayê min Zuwêr re hene.
My greetings go to my brother Zuwêr.
Zuwêr, birayê min ji gundê Dolger e.
Zuwêr, my brother from the village of Dolger [Carpenter].
Saeta wî meryî jî xweş, Xwedê rehma xolê ke.
Bless that man too, God have mercy on him.
Li vê derê me sate karebê ji mezel re rakibandî.
Here we installed an electricity meter for the shrine.
Mezelê Şêx Reşîd.
The shrine of Sheikh Rashid.
Teb'an, lambeyên xwo tênebin, karebê xwo tênebin, şev reş
bi.
Naturally, so its lamps are there, its electricity is there,
[so] the night isn't dark.
Milet dikeve... çi şev reş bi.
People enter... why should the night be dark?
Me hat, me lamba pêxistin û me saeto karebê vêra qetimand.
We came, we turned on the lamps and we fixed the electric
meter for it.
Havalî mar...
My friend...
Arê hevalno, gelek me kareba rakiband.
Yes friends, we installed a lot of electricity.
Dê dî, me lamba l'vir xist û qate' jî me pêxist.
Look, we put a lamp here and we installed a breaker too.
Û me lambek jî vê çixê xist.
And we put a lamp in this corner too.
Me ciyê gundî jî gi şûştin.
We washed the entire villagers' place [gathering spot].
Teb'an me gi boyax jî kir.
Naturally we painted it all too.
Havalî mar lahtekî l'vir bigir.
My friend, take a shot here.
Zuwêr ji gundê Dolger e, mesrefê vê mezolî gund da...
giştek.
Zuwêr from Dolger village, he covered all the expenses of
this village shrine... everything.
Gelî sêke, çi gunda çiqas pak bûye.
Look folks, how clean the village [shrine] has become.
Berê gi toz bû, gi... dîwar xerabe bûn.
Before it was all dust, all... the walls were ruined.
E noko jî me gi pak, boyax kir, çêkir.
And now we cleaned it all, painted it, fixed it.
Me kareba jî gi rakibandin.
We installed all the electricity too.
Ka havalî mar...
Come here my friend...
Çiwan î?
How are you?
Quwet be, quwet be.
Strength to you, strength to you.
Çiwan î? Kîf î te?
How are you? How is your mood?
We çi kiriye? Mokîna...
What have you done? The machine [vehicle]...
Wele, debrajê lê xistî... me go em debrajê çêkin.
Well, the clutch was failing... we said let's fix the
clutch.
Ahan tu bînî zu...
Aha you bring it quickly...
Abû nekeriye?
He hasn't done it?
Wez korî me, ev meslehata te çiqas te dest pê kiriye? Çend
sal in di vê meslehetê?
I'm blind [asking humbly], this profession of yours, when
did you start? How many years in this profession?
Wele hîn ji mêj de ye.
Well, it's been a long time.
Yû ne? Teqrîben çend?
Yeah? Approximately how much?
Teqrîben dikeve sî sal.
Approximately it comes to 30 years.
Sî sal in tu vê karî dikî.
30 years you've been doing this work.
E teyb, sî sal in tu vê karî dikî, xêr wa dikanek, kofek
nekir, mehelek?
Okay, 30 years you do this work, why haven't you made a
shop, a place, a location?
Hîn em mesele qerfî...
We are still sort of makeshift...
Qerf bî mesele na? Imkanet tina?
Makeshift is the issue, no? No resources?
Ee, imkanet tina, imkan hebe dikim.
Yeah, no resources, if there were resources I'd do it.
Imkanê xwo tatinê, sî sal in ve karî dike, imkanê xwo
tatinê.
His resources don't allow, 30 years he does this work, his
resources don't allow.
Xelk tê li cem gunda, li pişî hewşê gunda çêdike.
People come to the village, he works in the village
courtyards.
Mehal bêser, rêkek raîsî be, hînek kîbar be.
A place on the main road, something classy.
Em, em tara dibên serkeftin be, saeta te xweş, di vî karî de
ke.
We, we wish you success, health to you, in doing this work.
Ev jî xizmet milet dike, bi vê rengî, şta mokîna teslîh
dike.
He serves the people too, in this way, like fixing machines.
Teb'an... te ev derî û pencer û tişt... te gi şixuland ne?
Naturally... this door and window and things... you worked
on all of them right?
Ev qafas û tiştê hanê... te şixuland?
This cage [wooden enclosure] and such things... you worked
on it?
Erê wela min şixuland.
Yes, by God, I worked on it.
Gelo ev ji bo xêrê ye yan te heqê xwo stand?
Is this for charity or did you take your payment?
Na wela xêr e.
No, by God, it's charity.
Xêr e na?
It's charity, right?
Xêra dê û bavê min e.
It's charity for my mother and father.
Arê, xêra dê û bavê wî ye.
Yes, charity for his mother and father.
Teb'an gundî me hinek alîkarî nekir ne? Yanî te tenê kir?
Naturally our villagers didn't help much right? Meaning you
did it alone?
Gund, kesî alîkarî nekir.
The village, no one helped.
Gund kesî alîkarî nekir.
Bes lecne alîkarî kir.
Only the committee helped.
Lecne... kî ye mesûlê lecne?
The committee... who is responsible for the committee?
Wela Şêx Reşîd e.
Well, it's Sheikh Rashid.
Şêx Reşîd, kîjan Şêx Reşîd?
Sheikh Rashid, which Sheikh Rashid?
Evê li Efrînê.
The one in Afrin.
Eha, ewa pere da?
Aha, he gave the money?
Ewa mesref kir, ewa alîkarî kir.
He covered expenses, he helped.
Gund qirûşek ne da?
The village didn't give a penny?
Gund qirûşek ne da.
The village didn't give a penny.
Heyfa gund be, gund çima qirûşek nedaye?
Shame on the village, why didn't the village give a penny?
Ma ne şerma gund e?
Isn't it a shame for the village?
Wela şerma gund e.
By God, it is a shame for the village.
Wele eyb e ji gund re.
Well, it is disgraceful for the village.
Lecne hat ji Efrînê, pere da, mesref kir.
The committee came from Afrin, gave money, covered expenses.
Gund qirûşek ne da, tenê karkerî kir.
The village didn't give a penny, they only did labor.
Karkerî kî kir?
Who did the labor?
Me kir.
We did.
We kir.
You did.
Hûn û kî?
You and who?
Ez û biraziyê xwo.
Me and my nephew.
Tu û biraziyê xwo.
You and your nephew.
Saeta we xweş, destê we sax be.
Bless you, health to your hands.
Xwedê xêra we qebûl ke.
May God accept your charity.
Cihê Şêx Reşîd cinet be.
May Sheikh Rashid's place be paradise.
El-Fatiha.
Al-Fatiha [Prayer].
Arê hevalno, rehmet li miriyê we bin.
Yes friends, mercy be upon your dead.
Eva jî tirba bavkê min e.
This is my father's grave.
Arê, eva ya bavkê min e. Hevalî min tîçikê we vira, yolî vo
nîzîk bike.
Yes, this is my father's. My friend, come this way a bit,
bring the camera closer.
Dê û bav mirin... cîda eziyet tave ye.
Mother and father died... [it is a place of suffering].
De, Xwedê rehma xol li giya ke.
So, may God have mercy on everyone.
Lo, rêka me giya, em gi kê bimrin. Yanî dinya j'kesî re
dimîne?
Look, [it's] the path of all of us, we will all die.
Meaning, does the world remain for anyone?
Oo, bî şaşt sal ne, bi rehmetî bûye.
Oh, it's been sixty years, since he passed away.
Ev jî, ev jî apê min e.
This too, this is my uncle.
Evna jî apê min in. Teb'an kesê xerîb tina, gi pismam in.
These too are my uncles. Naturally there are no strangers,
all are cousins.
Hava Xalê Cafo ye.
This is Uncle Cafo.
Heva jî... apê min Neşet e.
This too... is my uncle Neşet.
Teb'an apê min jî... b'... hîşkê hindik ji bavkê min
biçûktir e, bavkê min e mezin bû.
Naturally my uncle too... with... a little bit younger than
my father, my father was the elder.
E mezin teb'an Xwedê ye.
The great one naturally is God.
Havo jî apê min Neşet e, Xwedê rehma xolê ke, cihê xwo cinet
be.
This is my uncle Neşet, God have mercy on him, may his place
be paradise.
Arê hevalno, ev jî... Xalê Elî ye, Elî Gurpe.
Yes friends, this too... is Uncle Ali, Ali Gurpe.
Em vira dibên Xwedê rehma xolê ke.
We say here God have mercy on him.
We havalî min sûretê wî jî we vira derxe, seke...
And my friend, show his picture here too, look...
Vê noko... tiştê pir rind çêkirine.
This now... they have made very nice things.
Ler hember lê bigir.
Record it from the front.
Seke noko mûda hona derketiye.
Look now a fashion like this has come out.
Qebe dikin, paşê suretê gindî jî bi belûrê dikine çi...
They build the dome, then they put the person's photo in
crystal/glass so that what...
Ma'nî maro nas ke yanî. Sûretê gindî.
Meaning so one recognizes them. The person's photo.
Seke.
Look.
Xwedê rehma xolê ke, cihê xwo cinet be.
God have mercy on him, may his place be paradise.
Erê hevalno, em hatin cem vî hevalî, zeytê difiroşe.
Yes friends, we came to this friend, he sells oil.
Merheba ji te ra.
Hello to you.
Silav.
Hello.
Noka zeyt, new'ê ewil, bi çi derecê ye tenekê?
Now the oil, the first type, what is the price of the tin?
Wella noka bûye heştê û derna dare.
Well, now it has become eighty and thereabouts.
Heştê dolarî?
Eighty dollars?
Heştê dolarî. New'ê ewil.
Eighty dollars. First type.
Erê hevalno, new'ê ewil bi heştê dolarî ye noka.
Yes friends, the first type is eighty dollars now.
Berî vê rabe bibî gîşt bî nîzîkî sed dolarî na?
Before this rose, wasn't it all near a hundred dollars?
Bû nod û şeşan û derna.
It was ninety-six and thereabouts.
Nod û şeşan. Berî vê gişt nod û şeşan bes niha daket heştê
dolarî. New'ê ewil.
Ninety-six. Before this it was all ninety-six, but now it
dropped to eighty dollars. First type.
New'ê ewil heştê ye. Qîmê heştê derketiye.
First type is eighty. The price of eighty has come out.
Heye hereket heye? Olver heye?
Is there movement? Is there trading?
Wella noka çikî sûk sekinî ye, daketiye zeyt.
Well now the market is a bit stopped, oil has dropped.
Çiçikî daketiye?
It dropped a little?
Belê daketiye.
Yes, it dropped.
Sax zeyt babo veke, dirav şîn.
Just keep the oil man, (let) money grow.
Deka em vê carê ew dikin.
So let us do that this time.
Xwedê rizqê we bide.
May God give you sustenance.
Kesekî zeytê xwe nefiroşe. Wam vederê cema nefiroşin. Mêrnê
Efrîn mafiroşin.
Let no one sell their oil. Those around here don't sell. Men
of Afrin don't sell.
Emê dolarekî zêde werin.
We will get a dollar more.
Deka bimînin em vîdeoyê xwe temam bikin jû.
So stay, let us finish our video then.
Erê hevalno, li vir jî em camê malê Xalê Elî ne.
Yes friends, here we are guests at Uncle Ali's place.
Teben ew jî cihi tekeran lê vedike, li vir jî benzîn mazotê
ceran xwe datîne.
Of course, he also repairs tires here, and here he puts his
gasoline and diesel containers.
Xalê Elî, boyboya te qicik e boyboya te.
Uncle Ali, your pipe is small, your pipe.
Yek Libnanî ye bes.
It's just a Lebanese one.
Silava bikişîne.
Smoke it in peace.
Xwedê te biparêze.
May God protect you.
Jiyê te çend e Xalê Elî?
How old are you, Uncle Ali?
Wella heda sê... nod û du sal in.
Well, seventy... ninety-two years.
Nod û du sal in?
Ninety-two years?
Ne nod in. Ew are inşallah ew are.
It is ninety. Yes, God willing, yes.
Erê hevalno nod û du sal in. Xwedê temen dirêj bike.
Yes friends, ninety-two years. May God give long life.
Inşallah Xwedê qebûl bike.
God willing God accepts it.
Xatira te Xalê Elî.
Goodbye Uncle Ali.
Ser ser û çavan.
You are welcome.
Erê hevalno li vê derê jî em hatin dikana Xalê Evdû ne.
Yes friends, here we came to Uncle Abdo's shop.
Vê derê cîhê tekeran û zeytê...
This place is for tires and oil...
Û borî û sobe û vana vedike.
And he sells pipes and stoves and these things.
Da însan emr mezin bike çi karî bike, îşta xera pê sebeb
dibe.
When a person gets old, whatever work he does, it becomes a
cause for good.
Teker ne, zeyt ne, tiştê mokin o. Vira jî cîhê borî û sobe
ne.
Tires, oil, machine things. Here is also the place for pipes
and stoves.
Ka werin em du sê sualan ji Xalê Evdû wan jî bipirsin.
Come, let's ask Uncle Abdo and them two or three questions.
Selam aleykum Xalê Evdû.
Peace be upon you, Uncle Abdo.
Aleykum selam.
And upon you peace.
Tu çewan î baş î?
How are you, are you good?
Hun bi xêr hatin ser seran.
You are welcome, upon my head.
Are saxî Xalê Evdû?
Are you healthy, Uncle Abdo?
Baş in hemd ji Xwedê re.
We are good, praise be to God.
Xalê Evdû çi wa hereket heye?
Uncle Abdo, is there any movement (business)?
La wela hereket kêm bûye.
No, by God, movement has decreased.
Kêm bûye ne?
It has decreased, hasn't it?
Wela kêm bûye. Em rûniştî ne û bê kef in hema.
By God it has decreased. We are sitting and just bored.
Xwedê hetî bide.
May God give strength.
Heke em derî dadin, ewê milet tên. Heke em vekin, kes nayê.
If we close the door, people come. If we open, no one comes.
Xwedê hetî bide.
May God give strength.
Erê Xalê Evdû, berê û noka. Berê rind bû yan noka rind bû?
Yes Uncle Abdo, the past and now. Was the past good or is
now good?
Berê rind bû.
The past was good.
Çûna berê rind bû?
How was the past good?
Bi her tiştî da. Berê merî naspêlî bûn.
In every way. Before, people were familiar.
Hûr û kûçik û gurk jî peyda bûn.
(Now) small ones and dogs and wolves have also appeared.
Yanî merhemet di dilê milet de nema, merhemet.
Meaning mercy did not remain in the hearts of the nation,
mercy.
Merhemet.
Mercy.
Me hevdû teqdîr dikir. Mezinê me, çiqa biçûk ba bi salan, me
jê re derbas nedikir.
We appreciated each other. Our elder, however small in
years, we wouldn't cross him.
Lê belkîs, a balê xwe bide noka qîzik yekî, lawik yekî, bavê
xwe nahesibîne.
But on the contrary, look now, a girl, a boy, doesn't
respect their father.
Rast e.
It's true.
Ela noka hezkirin kêm bûye.
But now love has decreased.
Hezkirin kêm bûye.
Love has decreased.
Paşê ro îdî... qenaet hebû.
After that... there was contentment.
Em bi şikek nanê hişk qenaet dikir.
We were content with a piece of dry bread.
Yanî mirov qenaetkar bûn.
Meaning people were content.
Eger hindik hezkirin jî hebe, qenaet hebû.
Even if there was little love, there was contentment.
Yanî heta merî kaniya merî ber avê vexwara, merî meriv li
ber kaniyê nedikuşt.
Meaning even if a person drank water at someone's spring, a
person wouldn't kill the person at the spring.
Rast e.
It's true.
Lê îro pîta pûşt te radibe...
But today the treacherous ambush rises...
...Qolmaro neqedand.
...Qolmaro didn't finish.
Yekî şor wara ketine berî kî...
Someone fell into the speech before...
Bavê min şor ve ronaten kiren.
My father was explaining the speech.
Wa gazî min kir, got...
He called me, he said...
Ez bavkê te, rehma Xwedê lê... Em pir mêr bûn...
I am your father, may God have mercy on him... We were many
men...
Me tirba du kûlan... berê min, Seyda Ehmed...
We [built] the tomb of two holes... before me, Seyda
Ahmed...
...bi misîn bidin, hûnê bidin camiya. Me bi seda misînî
anîn.
...give with ewers, you will give to the mosque. We brought
hundreds of ewers.
Wê lo bavê min, me rû me rû... merê kirin sed û de...
Oh my father, we face to face... made men a hundred and
ten...
Kê da teşqû bûye.
Who has been in trouble.
Xalê Ebdo, te digot pêşûr, te çi pir cefa dîaye, win çûn
Lîbya jî ne?
Uncle Abdo, you said before, you saw a lot of suffering, did
you go to Libya too?
Na, ewa ez neçûm Lîbya, heval bûn.
No, I didn't go to Libya, it was friends.
We betûn berê pir bi teneka lê dikir, bi piya?
Did you use to pour concrete a lot with cans [buckets], on
foot?
Wele betûn bîst salan min lê kir.
Well, I poured concrete for twenty years.
Bîst salan?
Twenty years?
Bîst salan bi teneka.
Twenty years with cans.
Grupî we hebû?
Did you have a group?
Lê, grupî me hebû. Ez... Evdilkerim, Şewket, Osman...
biçûkê... Heyderê Eskelê...
Yes, we had a group. Me... Abdulkerim, Shawkat, Osman... the
little one... Haydar of Askale...
Wek gura zanim bavke me hewal da... we pir xane, pir hewş,
we betûn lê kirin, belaş, bê pere.
As far as I know, our father told the friends... you poured
concrete for many houses, many yards, for free, without
money.
Me belaş pir lê kirin.
We did a lot for free.
We belaş lê dikirin.
You did it for free.
Belaş. Bi piya, heta êvarî betûn lê dikirin, belaş lê
dikirin.
Free. On foot, we poured concrete until evening, we did it
for free.
Îsanet zexîm ka bûn?
Was the humanity strong then?
Grupî we jî hebûn 18 mêr bûn.
You also had a group, there were 18 men.
Win diçûn hewarê hevdu?
Did you go to help each other?
Yekî terê lo qezenc bo niyo? Me yê destê xwe kir û tevrê
xwe... û me yê biro bipeqînin, me digo bes dua li me bikin.
Bes dua bikin.
One would ask 'isn't there profit in it?' We put our hands
and our pickaxes... and we would blast the rock, we said
just pray for us. Just pray.
Ê noka ew tişta kêm bûye. Xêr e?
So now that thing has decreased. Why is that?
Kêm bûye. E wele... berê min... mişkêla xwe vê telefonê
derxistin... û pere jî... dewranê mezin ketin mezin...
It has decreased. Well... before me... these phones brought
out their problems... and money too... big eras turned into
big [problems]...
Mesela me mezinê mezin jî bîr kir.
For example, we forgot the greatest of the great
[elders/God].
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê jî me bîr kir, wextê me... heftê bîr kir, Xwedê jî me
bîr dike.
We forgot God too, when we... forgot the seventy, God
forgets us too.
Lê?
Really?
E manê hezkirinik, ji dil da me dikir, ne bi şûra. Ji dil
da.
It means a love, we did it from the heart, not for show.
From the heart.
Yekî ku em diçûn kalê Wirî me li ber kaniyan xew dikir. Diçû
qata Batmanê da... qijikê...
Like when we went to Old Wiri, we slept by the springs.
Going towards the Batman area... the little ones...
Em diçûn masiya... dirustî rû xew dikirin... vê xem, vê
xeyal.
We went fishing... we slept soundly... [without] this grief,
this worry.
Yanî cîranî te, xwdanlêqelîma te dikir.
Meaning your neighbor asked about you.
E lo wele birakî me ji noka...
Oh well, our brother from now...
Noka mirî ne noka.
Now they are dead now.
Noka em xwdanlêqê nakin kes.
Now we don't ask about anyone.
Erê wele. Ne yanî em bêjin... mesela... erê wext rind e.
Yes, really. It's not that we say... for example... yes, the
time is good.
Tişt mitewefir e. Makîne mitewefir in. Alet zîraî ye gite
mitewefir e.
Things are available. Machines are available. Agricultural
tools are all available.
Xalê Ebdo berê meşê diçûn Batmanê ne?
Uncle Abdo, used to walk to Batman, right?
Lê, meşê lê.
Yes, walking, yes.
Bi meşê hûn diçûn wirê û diçûn masiya... û dihatin?
You walked there and went fishing... and came back?
Erê û em dihatin lê.
Yes and we came back, yes.
Meraq e.
It's interesting.
Lê...
Yes...
Xa berê hezkirin pir bî, 'uhd bî...
In the past love was abundant, there was loyalty...
Em lê wî na dibin.
We don't see that anymore.
Ev welê, ev welî xwa bîn. Tim tim şer.
Like this, they became like this. Always fighting.
Derman û sebeb bîder o.
Remedy and cause are outside.
Saxiya te xweş Xalê Ebdo, Xwedê te razî be.
Health to you Uncle Abdo, may God be pleased with you.
Noka ma vê dikanê vekir... em esasê badînan in. Em qçikê
badînan in.
Now we opened this shop... we are essentially Badinan. We
are the small ones of the Badinan.
Ke wextê... hat xwaztin fêdal gundî me bibê...
When the time... it was wanted that the Fedal [village] be
ours...
Erê.
Yes.
E he... sud e. Em rabûn çûn çata Eyn Hacer, em xizmet miletê
xwe dikin.
Uh huh... it is profit. We got up and went to the Eyn Hacer
junction, we serve our people.
Mokîna tê dibî şîşoko we em dicodibin.
The machine comes, becomes stuck, we fix it.
Eyn Hacer dibê xwedê noka qedrê didin... megû...
Eyn Hacer says God now gives value... we said...
Miletê me... gund e, xûna me ye. Em kê xizmetê kin.
Our people... it's the village, it's our blood. We will
serve.
Heta ga em kanin... em osê rast ji badînan in.
As long as we can... we are truly from the Badinan.
Kirko... Soro... gundî hebû... em bûnê Amûdê... ji vî gundî
ra...
Kirko... Soro... there was a villager... we became Amuda
[residents]... for this village...
...pêber... bane... nişêf... î ma bî çadirik.
...slope... roof... descent... it was just a tent.
Çû Amûdê kî tivare bin çadirikê da?
Who went to Amuda to stay under a tent?
Hûrû em... xizmet vî miletî kin. Bes... li miqabil gerek
em... xizmetî wî miletî bikin.
Today we... serve this nation. But... in return we must...
serve that nation.
Na yek warê cem... em miterede kin. Navî me... ji ber e daye
badîno.
Not that one comes to us... and we hesitate. Our name... is
given from before as Badino.
Erê.
Yes.
Yanî me bi seda xizmet milet kirî.
Meaning we have served the people hundreds of times.
Ê de brê min hûrû jî... tike... ewê na rê... tike miletî
hûrû... alas hedê xwe bê.
So my brother, today too... a piece... that won't go... a
piece of the nation today... let it be within its limits.
Hûrû... ê jêr hat jûr... ê jûr çî jêr. E yanû bîye.
Today... the lower one came up... the upper one went down.
It has become like that.
Wa bî, wa bî.
It became so, it became so.
Ê de em bîn çi.
So what can we say.
Sahet xweş Xalê Ebdo, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Health to you Uncle Abdo, may God be pleased with you.
Xalê Yûsiv merheba, ştara jî.
Uncle Yusuf hello, to you too.
Ehlen.
Welcome.
Xalê Yûsiv, nav gund da, navê te derketiye ku tu merûf î bi
yopiyê, bi girtinê... ûsta ye yanî. Tu ustayêkî merûf e.
Heta vedanê da jî.
Uncle Yusuf, in the village, your name has come out that you
are famous for bone-setting, for fixing... meaning a master.
You are a famous master. Even in joint manipulation.
Tu çend sal in vê karî dikî?
How many years have you been doing this work?
Belkî sî û pênc sal hene yopiyê digirim.
Maybe it's been thirty-five years I've been setting bones.
Sî û pênc sal?
Thirty-five years?
Mm.
Maşallah, sî û pênc sal e.
Mashallah, it's thirty-five years.
Û tu heta noka jî, ez dibînim tu di şixulî?
And even until now, I see you are working?
Erê heta noka digirim.
Yes, until now I set [bones].
Xalê Yûsiv, bereket emir çend e?
Uncle Yusuf, bless you, what is the age?
Emir 77 e.
Age is 77.
Maşallah, Xwedê emirki dirêj bide.
Mashallah, may God give a long life.
Erê maşallah tişmek can te heye, ez te dibînim ji xwey tu
yopiyê digire, sirim te 'ewlî dav de salî ye.
Yes mashallah you have a lively spirit, I see you setting
bones yourself, your secret [appearance] is like the first
ten years.
Ewa... ji Xwedê de ye. Xwedê quwetê bide, Xwedê emirkî dirêj
bide.
That... is from God. God gives strength, God gives a long
life.
De ji Xwedê de ye, eqlî.
It is from God, the intellect.
Ne ji aqil e.
It is not from intellect.
Wela... yanî kabanî mera, aqilê mera be, mera ewa...
teqawîtî ye.
Really... meaning if it was up to us, our intellect, we
would be... retired.
Erê wela. Û ne aqilî mera ye, mera sist e ne?
Yes really. And it's not our intellect, isn't man weak?
Erê, erê. Bixwe...
Yes, yes. By himself...
...nislet ji Xwedê de ye... û ne jî emir e. Emrim 77 e, noka
Mildara jêr, Emo lê de, ling girt.
...the generation/lineage is from God... and it's not age
either. My age is 77, now in lower Mildara, Emo hit it, held
the leg.
Kevrê qibarê giha noka.
The big stone reached [until] now.
E mezin.
The big one.
E mezin. Bi kevra. Çar ûdam girtin.
The big one. With stones. Fixed four limbs.
Maşallah. Qa nizanim ez yopiyê digirim.
Mashallah. As if I don't know I am setting bones.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Xalê Yûsiv tû bi şor... te vedan jî dikir. Te vedanê dujî
mualime.
Uncle Yusuf, by word... you used to do twisting/joints too.
You are a master of joints too.
Mm.
Te vedan jî pir kirî ne?
You have done a lot of joint [work] too?
Vedan jî min kirî.
I have done joint [work] too.
Xalê Yûsiv tu çi silavê dişînî ji milet ra... kesê li ma sêr
dikin, kesê... çi dûr dibê û çi nîzik dibê, tu çi silavê
dişînî...
Uncle Yusuf, what greetings do you send to the people...
those watching us, those... whether far or near, what
greetings do you send...
Çû dikim?
What do I do?
Tu çi silavê dişînî ji milet ra, miletê kî li ma sêr ke, tu
dibê çi, tu çi silavê dişînî ji gundiya ra?
What greetings do you send to the people, the people who
watch us, what do you say, what greetings do you send to the
villagers?
Lo... silamê ma bighîne Qantorê jî rehet e.
Lo... my greeting reaches Qantor comfortably too.
Heke çi silavê ji he ra.
Whatever greeting to him.
Silamê me çî gundî jor aliye...
Our greeting goes to the upper village side...
Xwedê giya bi xefletî ne.
God [keeps] the grass with negligence [idiom].
Xwedê giya bi xefletî ne, saheta we giya xweş.
God [keeps] the grass with negligence, health to you all.
E te jî xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
And to you too, may God be pleased with you.
E cemaetê wa xweş e, kibar e, gerek miqabil kabo.
The congregation is so nice, noble, it needs to be
reciprocal.
E... or heye, heye. Tê ma ro, vê zêtê jî emê dê xilas ke,
emê zeytûn...
Eh... there is fire, there is. You didn't finish this oil
[segment] for us, we... olives...
Se'r... ji heştê û pênca da heta çar dolaran rabi ke. Heştê
û pênc wereqe... û heta çar dolaran rabi ke.
The price... raise it from eighty-five to four dollars.
Eighty-five papers [notes]... and raise it to four dollars.
Yanî sed û şêstî dike. Em dixwazin fêda me jî li milet bibê.
Tiştî draktorê... çi dixwazin heye. Li cem me.
Meaning it makes a hundred and sixty. We want our benefit to
be for the people too. Tractor things... whatever they want
is there. With us.
Erê.
Yes.
Erê avano... li vê derê cem Xalê Ebdo... teman me noka...
videoyê xwe da wa got. Li vê derê... draktorê mokîna... û çi
dixwazin li vê derê... binî mala wî... zêt... te çi daxwazê
miftanê draktorê... gel li vê derê cem Xalê Ebdo heye...
Yes guys... here next to Uncle Abdo... as we just... said in
our video. Here... tractor of machines... and whatever you
want here... under his house... oil... whatever you want of
tractor keys/parts... it's all here with Uncle Abdo...
Qonê, were vê derê bibê...
Turn, come here and say...
Û... li alîkî di jî Xalê Yûsiv heye, yê ku yopiyê digire...
kê hewceyê yopiyê hebe...
And... on the other side is Uncle Yusuf, who sets bones...
whoever needs bone-setting...
Tabaen her tiştek, win dixwazin li vê derê heye. Binî gund
vo. Binî mala vo.
Of course everything, whatever you want is here. At the
bottom of their village. At the bottom of their house.
Music starts.
De emê hinekî nava gund da bigerin...
So we will tour inside the village a bit...
Erê avano, tabaen gundî me da, mekteb didin he... yek
mekteba jor e, yek jî mekteba jêr e.
Yes guys, of course in our village, there are two schools...
one is the upper school, one is the lower school.
Yanî heta sofî sefî hefte heştê dixwînin li jor, paşê
dadikevin jêr, hemam dikin.
Meaning even the Sufis study 70-80 [classes?] up there, then
go down, and take a bath.
Û mehele çi dixwazin Badînan da ye. Bes torê daqa şemsî
ye... tiştê draktorê mokîna... heloq pênc şeşek gundî me dan
e. Win çi dixwazin hene.
And whatever the neighborhood wants is in Badinan. Only the
solar energy net... tractor machine parts... there are five
or six barbers in our village. Whatever you want is there.
Cîb belûrê... Seyda li de ten e.
Jeep of Balloor... Seyda lives there.
Bibê şorê ra... cem sereta bilbilê.
Take the street... towards the nightingale ridge.
Ewa... sirtê bilbilê... dorka...
That one... nightingale ridge... the circle...
Paş wera mokînê bikire... Efrîn şêst û şeş e...
Behind you buy the car... Afrin is sixty-six...
Na çîçkî, dinê sar e. Xerbîkî hûrik lê dike, milet hemû di
hewşa de ye.
No, not a little, it is cold. A light western rain is
hitting, all the people are in the courtyards.
Cew xweş bû tebî, ta qişim zehmet e gundî me.
The weather was nice naturally, until winter makes our
village difficult.
Bavê Nebo, me got sirtê Bilbilê, da dikevin gundê Qopê û
daren ser rêka Raco.
Father of Nebo, we said the ridge of Bulbul, we are entering
the village of Qopê and going onto the Raco road.
Yanî rêka Raco kîlometrek ji me va nêzîk e. 700 metre ye.
Meaning the Raco road is one kilometer near us. It is 700
meters.
Vê hewşinê jêr, axir mal ne.
These courtyards below are the last houses.
Cemê hebo jî firr.
Hebo's place also flew by.
Berê viro mekteb bî, noka kirine firne.
Before, this place was a school, now they have made it a
bakery.
Vê hewşinê bi beran ve, wey xaret in.
These courtyards facing us, oh they are ruins.
Taban xezanê avê li viro cema... li vir jî heye. Ne gund
mezin e.
Of course, the water tank is here next to... it is here too.
The village isn't big.
û xazanek li vir jî heye.
And there is a tank here too.
Wa dîna... gundî me binî çêbûye. Tebî çoyê me hafê me.
Look... our village is built at the bottom. Naturally our
stream is our protector.
Edî ew malê tekerê xwedê berê vî çoyê de xistine.
So, God has placed those scattered houses facing this
stream.
Ev o mekteba jûr e. Ev o mekteba me jûr e.
This is the upper school. This is our upper school.
Ev o lo... me çîçkê bî tûsik nîn... baranê bar da.
This one... when we were small without beards... the rain
fell.
Şolê lê ke, şolê lê ke, wela em te'nîşkî bûn.
Work on it, work on it, by God we were tired.
Ew nanê horate me ne teban.
That is the bread of our neighborhood, naturally.
Bira qûra jûr e. Mekteba jûr.
Brother, it's the upper hole. The upper school.
Eynê belek e. Navê wi ber Eynê Belek e.
It is Eynê Belek (Speckled Mirror). Its name used to be Eynê
Belek.
Taban nav gundî me kareba heye, 24 saeta kareba heye.
Of course, inside our village there is electricity, there is
electricity for 24 hours.
Ne gund mezin e, berê giya çûn gundê mezin kareba temdîd
kirin.
The village isn't big, before everyone went, the big village
extended the electricity.
Paşê ro, daren gundê çûçik.
After that day, they go to the small village.
Tabî... navê ez ê ger bim vî kûçî da.
Naturally... I will walk in this alley.
Taban li vî derî jî saydelî ye, Saydelî Hemûd e, ma'rûf e.
Of course, in this place is a pharmacy, Pharmacy Hamoud, he
is famous.
Saeta gund xweş jî xizmet dike.
He serves well during the village hours.
Wela pir naqlim, derman cem birî, heq nebirî.
By God, I don't transport much, if someone took medicine, he
didn't take payment.
Ya'nî fuqara ra pir harî dike, saeta gund xweş e.
Meaning he helps the poor a lot, the village time is good.
Ev o jî warşê berê mala wera sewirandî ye.
This is also the workshop from before, the house was filmed
for you.
Se ke cî farûce... û ewe cim lê vekirî ye.
Look, the chicken place... and that gym is opened there.
Eh Xalê Omer e, Omerê Şêx.
Uh, Uncle Omer, Omer the Sheikh.
Taban vê horetê jûr jî, ewa derê mala me jûr, rîka xezanê.
Of course, this upper neighborhood too, that is the door of
our upper house, the road to the tank.
Maşallah baraneke nerm dibare. Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, a soft rain is falling. Mashallah, mashallah.
Ev o mala xaletî min e.
This is my aunt's house.
Xwedê xelk çi hewşa digre binêrin. Wa de rizqê giya bişîne.
God, look at what courtyards the people take. Oh may He send
everyone's sustenance.
O î termîm dikin, gi çê dikin. Telbîs dikin.
Oh they are renovating, making everything. They are cladding
it.
Taban ev rêka jî derê Dumila yanî.
Of course, this road leads to Dumila.
Hewa nû xerbîkî hûrik hûrik dibare.
The weather now, a light western rain is falling lightly.
Çi cewekî xweş e, hisî çûka.
What a nice weather, the sound of birds.
Ewilî min vir de wer anî, gund gi nîzîk bikim.
First I brought it this way, to bring the whole village
closer.
Maşallah gund mezin e.
Mashallah the village is big.
E baran ê jî, min nekanî wera rind gi teswîr kira.
And the rain too, I couldn't film everything well for you.
Gerek di helîqatekî do çêkim, gund mezin e û baran e.
I need to make another episode, the village is big and it is
raining.
Ewilî min ano... yoş... lê bigir nîzîk bike.
First I... slowly... hold it, zoom in.
Maşallah, maşallah ji gundî me ra.
Mashallah, mashallah to our village.
Gundê xêr û bêrê ye. Maşallah.
A village of goodness and abundance. Mashallah.
Taban mala me rû li jûr e, binê xezanê ye.
Of course, our house faces upwards, it's below the tank.
Wadî ye, mentîqa me coxrafî ya me çiqas xweş e. Çiyayê di
cem me.
It is like this, our area, how nice our geography is. The
mountains next to us.
Perrê... perrê kîbar e. Durçerxî me gelek çaye.
The side... the side is elegant. Our surroundings are very
good.
Ev o el hewş e, Badînan men, Serkanê vêrê dibên.
This is the yard, our Badinan, they call this place Serkanê.
Vê derê jî berê hewş teng bûn, me hewş gelek fireh kirin.
Also here, the yards used to be narrow, we widened the yard
a lot.
Vê derê jî, vro jî mewqihê xwe pir rind e. Serkanê vêrê
dibên, Serkanê jor e.
Here too, today its location is very nice. They call here
Serkanê, Serkanê is above.
Seke mehder gicê kirin, gelekî dikê bi hewş bin vê derê.
Look, they made the terrace, it will be a very [nice] yard
here.
Vê derê hemûka gundî xwe şêl vira çêkin. Gundê Kanê.
Here all the villagers are building their homes here. The
village of Kanê.
Hewş pir bûn wela meşrîe pir çêdikin xelk. Ko wer em herin
jor.
The yards became many, people are making many projects. Come
let's go up.
Erê îro jî Xalê Xelîl e.
Yes, today is also Uncle Khalil.
Xalê min e, ez no divê derê xwe rûniştine. Cem Ciya Heddad.
He is my uncle, I am sitting here right now. With Ciya the
Blacksmith.
Temam Xalê Xelîl jî gundê Qadya ye.
Okay, Uncle Khalil is also from Qadya village.
Li cem evro Ciya Heddad ye vekirî xizmet dike.
He is with Ciya Heddad today, open and serving.
Saeta gundiyê xwe xweş li berê rûniştine.
Sitting happily with his villager for a while.
Lê de mîlo Badînan.
But, oh man, Badinan.
Em giş yek in.
We are all one.
Gundê Qadya de mîlo Badînan em giş tev hev dibînin.
Qadya village, man, Badinan, we see everyone together.
Lê em giş yek in, em giştin ev de.
But we are all one, we all reached here.
Ele rasî wela.
You are right, by God.
Aha nûha hesî baranê kirî.
Aha, just now it started raining.
Wextê baranê kirî, ev e em hatin cîhê me, bilûka cîhê me
hewşê jor.
When it rained, we came to our place, the block of our
place, the upper yard.
Em hatin vê derê. Baran bî.
We came here. It was rain.
Ewlî miko wer çîçik vî meşrûî jî bigire. Wadî ye...
First, come take a little [shot] of this project too. Do you
see...
Cem vê derê rind e, Badînan gelek xweş tê dîtin.
Near here is nice, Badinan is seen very beautifully.
Mewqiekî pir xweş e. Vêra jî meşrûekî hem ber mi digirin.
It is a very nice location. Here they are building a project
opposite me.
Ovo. Ewlî min lê bigir. Wadi ye?
This one. Take [a shot] of it for me first. Do you see?
Meşrûek dexmî li vê derê çêdibê hember min.
A huge project is being built here opposite me.
Yekî bînayê rakin. Wadi ye, qaîdê gund çiqas mekin kirin.
Someone is raising a building. You see, look how solid they
made the foundation of the village.
Úrtê tije kevir dikin. Seke, cama mentîqek pir xweş e.
They are filling its inside with stones. Look, man, it is a
very nice area.
Bes baran e. O bo em hatin vêra, magu em qotben virkin.
But it is rain. Oh, we came here, I said let's do the speech
here.
Lê... Ohx, milo leke, milo leke.
Man... Oh, man look, man look.
Maşalla, ev e lo, wadî ye Warşê çû cemê, ava radibin.
Mashallah, this is it, lo, the valley of Warshe went to the
river, the water is rising.
Qederê rizqê gundiyan bişewitîne. Feqîrî çûne ser mesrefan.
Fate might burn the villagers' livelihood. The poor went
into expenses.
Bend çêkirin sînaç, heta ser erdê xist. Bor çêkirin.
They made a dam wall, until it hit the ground. They made
pipes.
Erê evolno, li vê derê jî em teb'an em biro giştin mal.
Yes friends, here too, naturally we reached home today.
Em giştin talî videoya xwe. Saeta we xweş.
We reached the end of our video. Have a good time.
Her yekî li me seyr dike, her yekî te'lîqê xweş, maroyê me
zêde dike.
Everyone who watches us, everyone with a nice comment,
increases our morale.
Çavê giya maç dikim. Erê em noko gihîştin mal.
I kiss everyone's eyes. Yes, we reached home now.
Wela em hîvî bûn ku derketana. Horta hûrû çû av û dinê evor
bî.
By God we hoped to go out. But the clouds turned to rain and
the world became cloudy.
Silavê min jî ji bo zor re hene. Û ji bo Mamoste Mihemed ra.
My greetings are also for many. And for Teacher Muhammed.
Xwedanê... ewe... met'ema Nêrûz li Efrîn.
Owner of... that... Newroz restaurant in Afrin.
Silavê min ji wan re hene. Çavê wan maç dikim.
My greetings to them. I kiss their eyes.
Da me ra bin dîsa vîdeoyekî xweş kîbar. Em ê werin inşala
nîzîk da daxin.
Be with us again for a nice elegant video. We will come
inshallah soon to upload.
Huru helqê me hana bî, erê wela.
Today our episode was like this, yes by God.
Migo çîçka teẍyîrata têkime. Milo çîçka cew were ẍeyrandin.
I said I will put a little changes in it. Man, let the
atmosphere change a little.
Ma'nî melel were jî çê nebe. Erê ez li hewşa gundê me me.
Meaning, so boredom doesn't happen either. Yes I am in the
yard of our village.
Texma hewşê gundî Badînan e. Seke maşala gund çiqas kîbar e.
It looks like the yard of a Badinan village. Look mashallah
how elegant the village is.
Mewqiê ciyê me jî pir rind e. Erê.
The location of our place is also very nice. Yes.
Seke ev o gundê me ye. Ev o hewşa me ye.
Look this is our village. This is our yard.
Ev o gundê me ye. El hewşê giya me.
This is our village. The yard of all of us.
Wavyano camiyê gundî me ye, sehha gundî me ye.
And that over there is the mosque of our village, the square
of our village.