Giwa ye.
It is strong (good).
Rind e?
Is it good?
Giwa ye, elhemdulîlah.
It is strong, praise be to God.
Gana, Ebu Novê... vî gundo, malbat gelk mal in, sed û bîst
mal hene, bes gişt yek xan e.
Gana, Abu Nove... this village, the families are many
houses, there are one hundred and twenty houses, but all are
one lineage (family).
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Erê.
Yes.
Em şixul tîkî jî bikin, owro...
Let us do a little work too, here...
Ev jî malê...
And this is the house of...
Win nas dikin, van milan werin, lê milan nayên, vanê
Ewropayê bi şiklê giştî...
You know, come to these sides, but they don't come to
[these] sides, those in Europe generally...
Welle gerek giwa werin.
By God, they need to come strongly.
Gelek giwa werin, leka, leka, leka.
Come very strongly, exactly, exactly, exactly.
Dê çi bikin îna ha?
What are they going to do now, huh?
Ewa, Tu alîta heta hetikî bike, Silav reş bota.
Yes, until you make a [unclear], black greetings to you.
Saet xweş.
Good times (Thanks).
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Silav... Muban şer ne?
Greetings... [Unclear phrase] isn't it?
Na, derke, derke.
No, go out, go out.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Erê welle. Nîvisandina mi ha... her yekî Kurmanc silav lê
rolikî, li giya.
Yes, by God. My writing huh... greetings to every Kurmanji
[person] mostly, to everyone.
Divê bîra heye ku çaki çandin e.
You must remember that he planted [something].
Erê.
Yes.
Fermo, kerem ke.
Here you go, please.
Wer, wer, min wer.
Come, come, come to me.
Tu bilind î ha, ew pozê te yê çak e.
You are tall huh, that nose of yours is good.
Eywa, wextê ku derkete pişt, wê li hundir dikeve cem min e,
elhemdulîlah şukur.
Yes, when he went out behind, he comes inside to me, praise
be to God, thanks.
Welle.
Really.
Elhemdulîlah.
Praise be to God.
Mentiqek pir xweş e, kîbar e.
A very nice area, elegant.
Marşa min mirov sekinî.
My march, the man stopped.
Birayê min Neşet, marş bike.
My brother Neshet, start the march (play the music).
Erê.
Yes.
Merheba hevalno, hûn çawa ne? İnşallah hûn rind û rihet in,
hewalno, îro vîdeoya me, vîdeoyeke xweş, kîbar e.
Hello friends, how are you? God willing you are good and
comfortable, friends, today our video is a nice, elegant
video.
Taben, ev jî ser telebê birayê me Mistefa ye, serxweşbûn.
Of course, this is also upon the request of our brother
Mustafa, condolences (or greetings).
Em kê gundî gundî teswîr kin. Mezet, gotina te hene?
We will film village by village. Mezet (Girl's name), do you
have any words?
Merheba hevalno, hûn çawa ne? Hêvî dikim hûn baş bin,
sihetxweş bin. İnşallah rojên xweş û giran derbas kin.
Hello friends, how are you? I hope you are well, in good
health. God willing you pass nice and important days.
Erê vîdeoya me îro vîdeoyeke ecêb, li gundekî ecêb emê
derbas kin, gundî Çeqelê Cûmê ye.
Yes, our video today is a wonderful video, we will spend it
in a wonderful village, it is the village of Çeqelê Cûmê.
Bi me ra bin, em derbas kin, vîdeoyeke xweş, kîbar em wara
bişewirînin.
Be with us, let us spend [time], we will record a nice,
elegant video for you.
Û bîr mekin me ra layk û îştîrakê pêdin.
And don't forget to give us a like and a subscription.
Û rûpelê me piştgirî bikin, em bidehe hezarî gihînin, û
saetê we giya xweş.
And support our page, let us reach ten thousand
[subscribers], and may your time be entirely good.
Erê hevalno, me bidehe hezarî gihînin. Em gihîştine heşt
hezar fe...
Yes friends, get us to ten thousand. We have reached eight
thousand so...
Hindikî ma me bidehe hezarî gihînin.
Only a little remains for us to reach ten thousand.
Erê hevalno, noka bi me ra bin, lextanên xweş li nav gundî
Çeqelê Cûmê.
Yes friends, now be with us, nice moments inside the village
of Çeqelê Cûmê.
De werin. Ka hevalî me jî le bigir.
Come on. Take [a shot] of our friend too.
Erê.
Yes.
Wer, wer, wer, min wer.
Come, come, come, come to me.
Maşallah, gundekî xweş e.
Mashallah, it is a nice village.
Tebîeta gund xweş e, bes ew e, kêmasî ev e.
The nature of the village is nice, but that is it, the
deficiency is this.
Gemar e, gemar. Davêjin.
It is garbage, garbage. They throw it.
Teqrîben...
Approximately...
Kekê Mistefa, ev gundê we ye. Te bîra kiriye ne?
Brother Mustafa, this is your village. You miss it, don't
you?
Ev jî tirbe ne, Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke.
And these are graves, may God have mercy on them.
Heke navê yekî li ser xuya dike, bixwîne.
If someone's name appears on it, read it.
Erê.
Yes.
Kerem ke.
Go ahead.
Wer, wer, min wer.
Come, come, come to me.
Ez naxwazim nav gund, cokê bigerim, paşê em herin nava malê.
I don't want to wander inside the village, the alleys, then
we will go inside the house.
Hevalno hîşta bîr mekin me bidin 10 hezarî...
Friends, still don't forget to get us to 10,000
[subscribers]...
Hindikî ma.
Only a little remains.
Layk û îştîrak bikin. Rabê belav bikin.
Like and subscribe. Go spread it.
Ewa jî mekteb e, hevalno, ewa mekteb e.
That is the school, friends, that is the school.
Me digot em sibe zû derkevin teswîrê...
We said let's go out early morning for filming...
Lê nî em... dewi yek o duha jimar derdikevin.
But look at us... around one or two o'clock we come out.
Dewa dewi yeka jî... wekî dibêjin 'izê germê ye.
Around one o'clock too... as they say, it is the peak of the
heat.
Nîvro qeylûlê nîvro ye.
Noon, it is the siesta of noon.
Dinya pir germ e.
It is very hot.
Sibe zû jî derket, xelk di xew da ye... meriv nikane...
Even going out early morning, the people are asleep... one
cannot...
Saet heftan şeşan wextê teswîrê jî nabe wisa şewq.
At six or seven o'clock, the filming time isn't [good], the
light isn't right.
Vî kendî jî em kêm werin, bargê meran me.
Let's come to this side less, [unclear: our load/burden].
Erê hevalno, Kakê Mistefa, ez li mala xalê te me.
Yes friends, Brother Mustafa, I am at your uncle's house.
Tê naskirin bi Ebû Yûsif.
He is known as Abu Yusef.
Temam.
Isn't that right, uncle?
Exactly.
Eha, hemîna malbatê gund in, li Çeqelê Cûmê.
Uh-huh, these are the families of the village, in Çeqelê
Cûmê.
Erê, emê navê... çend tiştan ji xalû bipirsin li ser vî
gundî.
Yes, we will ask the uncle for the names... a few things
about this village.
Tiştê em zanin, tiştê em nizanin jî em qewmî şênokin
[fêrbin]...
Things we know, and things we don't know we will learn...
Erê.
Yes.
Xalû bêrî giya, merheba ji te ra.
Uncle, before everything, hello to you.
Merheba û sehla.
Hello and welcome.
Xalû vî gundî, çiqas mal e?
Uncle, this village, how many houses is it?
Welle dorê sed, sed û bîst malan... sed û deh... heta sed û
bîst malan heye.
Well, around one hundred, one hundred and twenty houses...
one hundred and ten... up to one hundred and twenty houses
there are.
Heta sed û bîst malan.
Up to one hundred and twenty houses.
Erê.
Yes.
Giwa heye? Rind e?
Is it strong (crowded)? Is it good?
Giwa tên elhemdulillah.
It is strong, praise be to God.
Gana... Ebu'l... Vê gundo... Malbat gelk mal in, sed û bîst
mal in bes gişt yek xan e.
Gana... Abu'l... This village... The families are many
houses, one hundred and twenty houses but all are one
lineage (family).
Maşallah, rind e.
Mashallah, it is good.
Erê.
Yes.
Xalû, emrê vî gundî çiqas sal e?
Uncle, the age of this village is how many years?
Welle ew jî sêsed û pêncî, heta çarsed sal heye.
Well, that too is three hundred and fifty, up to four
hundred years.
Sêsed û pêncî heta çarsed sal. Texmîn cemaet.
Three hundred and fifty to four hundred years. An estimate,
guys.
Erê texmîn e, yanî... bi deqet em nizanin. Bes texmîn e, ji
pêşiyên me, hewal dan, kalên me...
Yes, it is an estimate, meaning... accurately we don't know.
But it is an estimate, from our ancestors, news they gave,
our grandfathers...
Xalû, li vî derî jî me bihîst, dibêjin şikeft li nav vî
gundî de pir in.
Uncle, in this place too we heard, they say caves inside
this village are many.
Wala dûrê şêst şiketî ye.
Well, it is around sixty "broken" (sixty-something).
Şêst?
Sixty?
Erê.
Yes.
Ez henek... henek mesela...
I am joking... like the joke...
Ka ma şêst şiketî jî ser mol o kin, ê bi dest ve.
Well, add the "sixty broken" to the house [age], the one in
hand.
Na helê... 120 mol le?
No, wait... is it 120 houses (years)?
Na weş beryê mol bî.
No, looking good for the home.
Em misxere çêkî bikin.
Let's make a little joke.
Xalû, tu dibê vê gundî da... ededî vê gundî 120 mol ne?
Uncle, you say in this village... the number [count] of this
village is 120 houses?
Bes şêst şiket xwaye. Şiket.
But "sixty broken" is the owner. Broken.
Berê vî miletî vir de şiket o dibî. Şêst heye.
Before, for this nation here, it would be broken [tired].
Sixty exists.
Erê.
Yes.
Xalû berê milet tê da deh... Deh jî dijî lê?
Uncle, before, people in it were ten... Ten were living in
it, right?
Erê.
Yes.
Cih û kelem bû, devî, şikeft di nav cih da bûn.
It was brush and thorns, bushes, caves were inside the
place.
Nav çiyayî dibî.
It was inside the mountain.
Yanî pêşît me ha wal dan?
Meaning our ancestors explained it like that?
Ew biderê berê gî çiya bû mentiqa we.
That outside area, before, your entire region was mountains.
Gî çiya bû.
It was all mountains.
Paşê ro tetawir çêbî, kirin zeytûn, rez, ne?
Later, development happened, they made it olive groves,
vineyards, right?
Temam.
Exactly.
Xalû, vê gundê pir xoş e kîbar e. Tebîetê gundê hêşînahiyek
xwe rind e.
Uncle, this village is very nice and elegant. The nature of
the village has a beautiful greenery.
Bes çîçikê di kortê daye. Seqciyê xwe bilind ba, wekî alemî
ba.
But it is a bit inside a hollow (valley). If its level was
high, like the rest of the world.
Geliye çîçikê... geliye.
It is a valley, a little bit... it's a valley.
Çîçikê gelî daye, erê.
It is inside the valley a little bit, yes.
Gelî jî Biyê Gund... debî gelî da bû.
The valley too, Biyê Gund (Old Village name)... used to be
in the valley.
Jê dûr neketine? Me'ne Biyê Gund hatin viderê.
They didn't fall far from it? Meaning Biyê Gund came here.
Ewa. Bîra... bîra Rûmanî kep.
Yes. The well... the well of the Romans.
Berê, bîrek Rûmanî divê gelî da bî.
Before, there was a Roman well in this valley.
Vira jûr.
Up here.
Milet jî hat... berê rûnişt divê nîzîk be.
The people came... before, they settled so it would be near.
Me'ne avê.
Meaning the water.
Me'nî pî nîzîk be.
Meaning to be near it.
Belê.
Yes.
Erê, zeman da... xalû li berê zeman da...
Yes, in the time... Uncle, in the old times...
Kanîk li ku ba, meselen... bîrek li ku ba, milet diçûyê tam
nîzîkê rûdiniştin.
Wherever a spring was, for example... wherever a well was,
the nation would go and settle right near it.
Milet li wêr kom dibî, me'ne vexwarina avê... me'ne...
The people gathered there, meaning for drinking water...
meaning...
Erê.
Yes.
Xaltîk te çi silavê dişînî ji... birakî me mistefero... ji
vê xelkê li me sêr dike?
Auntie, what greetings do you send to... our brother
traveler... to these people watching us?
Seetê we xoş, silavê me ji giya ra hene. Û ehlen we sehlen.
Bless your time, we have greetings for everyone. And
welcome.
Û te'lîqê jê vî mehe ra bişînin.
And send comments for this month (video).
Maşallah. Te'lîqê jî û iştîrakê ne?
Mashallah. Comments and subscriptions too, right?
Iştîrak... iştîrak.
Subscription... subscription.
Iştîrakê yar bişînin.
Send the subscription, friend.
Erê, seet xweş xaltîk.
Yes, bless you Auntie.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Tu dişînî teqsîrê nekin e?
You are sending (saying) they shouldn't fall short?
İnşallah.
God willing.
Xalû, te çi nesîheta didê vanê milê we ren... lê milê ne
têyin? Vanê Ewropa bi şekil 'am.
Uncle, what advice do you give those running away... but not
coming (back)? Those in Europe in general.
Wala gerek gî werin.
Well, they should all come.
Gerek gî werin.
They should all come.
Leke, leke, leke.
Definitely, definitely, definitely.
E'nî çi çikiniye heta noka?
I mean, what have they picked/gained until now?
Erê. Wala hewa... hewa vê mentiqa xoş biye.
Yes. Well the air... the air of this region has been nice.
Xaltîk te dibê çi?
Auntie, what do you say?
Ez dibêm bila gî biftilin werin mola xwe.
I say let them all return and come to their home.
Maşallah. Gaştek?
Mashallah. Everyone?
Gaştek.
Everyone.
Pir hatin e, ne? Xalk pir hatî.
Many have come, right? Many people came.
Ooo.
Oh.
O giggî jî naftilin... heft neqla... heft ji vê pirr tir
qîçkê xwe naho zewicî dahrin.
Oh, and not all of them return... seven times... seven, more
than that, my daughters are now married and away.
Ez xozim qîçkêm vir da werin.
I wish my daughters would come here.
Gerek vir da werin.
They should come here.
Dûr nehrin.
They shouldn't go far.
Ne Tirkiyê ne?
Are they in Turkey?
Erê xaltîk dibê gerek qîçkê me yavaş yavaş vir da werin,
gerek wî da nerin.
Yes, Auntie says our daughters should slowly come here, they
shouldn't go there.
Wî da du sal in çûne min nedîne û yane ya bi hesreta qîçkê
xwe me.
It's been two years since they went there, I haven't seen
them, and I am longing for my daughters.
Feqîrê.
Poor thing.
Walah.
Really.
Xaltîk bereket çend in ê te?
Auntie, how much is your "blessing" (age)?
Şêst... sê qîzik sê lawik.
Sixty... three daughters, three sons.
Xwedê ji te ra bihêle, ta ke sare kirine xaltîk.
May God keep them for you, you have raised them (completed
them), Auntie.
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê gîyo mehfeze ke, û silavê me ji giyo ra hene qîçkê ta.
May God protect them all, and we have greetings for all your
daughters.
Xwedê emrê gi dirêj bik e xalû de.
May God prolong everyone's life, and Uncle's too.
Xwedê ji te ra razî be, û hatina we ser serî me, ser çavê
me.
May God be pleased with you, and your coming is upon our
heads, upon our eyes (you are very welcome).
Û hatina we molî dinê ye.
And your coming is [worth] the wealth of the world.
Û bê rûniştinam, rûniştinam molî dinê inşallah gî biftilin.
And my settling, my settling is the wealth of the world, God
willing they all return.
Wala tî xwe biftilin molê xwe.
I swear, let them just return to their own home.
İnşallah, gî hewa biftilin.
God willing, they will all return like that.
Wala vê... vê çax...
Well this... this era...
Wala ez qîçkê xwe jî gyo silav dikim.
I swear I greet all my daughters too.
Û cûcika mezinim.
And I kiss the cheeks.
Seet xweş, silavê te gihîştin, em ê mobaşer e fîkrinîn e.
Bless you, your greetings have arrived, we will show it
directly (live/uncut).
Seet xweş.
Bless you.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Erê havalno, di me'na da milet pir vegeriyatî ji Ewropa.
Yes friends, in that sense, many people have returned from
Europe.
Teqrîben sedî... neh...
Approximately percent... nine...
Ji Ewropa û ji Qulbad sedî heştê hatî.
From Europe and from the Other Side (borders), eighty
percent have come.
Sedî heştê ji Ewropa û ji Qulba va hatî xalû wa dibê.
Eighty percent from Europe and the Other Side have come,
Uncle says so.
Le 'eynî ez digerim ha dibînim.
Because as I walk around, I see it like that.
Erê heye.
Yes, it exists.
Pir ji Ewropa dera votine. Hinek hene dibên mişkile hene,
dewlet o nizanim çi, no.
Many have come out from Europe. Some say there are problems,
the state or I don't know what, no.
Yanî molî dinê gî yê te be, qîçkê te tina, tiştek nê yê te
ye.
Meaning even if all the wealth of the world is yours, if
your daughters aren't there, nothing is yours.
Way xaltîk way.
Oh Auntie, oh.
Wala tiştek nê yê te ye.
I swear nothing is yours.
Rast dibê.
She speaks the truth.
Yanî ez... tim hem tenê ez of dikişînim. Çima? Çi jinê fahm
kir?
Meaning I... constantly all alone I am sighing "of". Why?
What did this woman understand (from life)?
Tim dilxwîn e, ne?
Always heartbroken, right?
Ewa... inşallah gî.
Yes... God willing, all.
E wê werin. Dûr ta jî e şên bibin. Ban ta kin, cîdû nene...
ne lê?
They will come. Your surroundings will be populated. They
will call you, grandmother, grandma... right?
Erê erê.
Yes yes.
E dêre şên bibin. Maşallah mentiqa pir pir kîbar bî havalno.
The surroundings will be populated. Mashallah, the region
was very, very elegant friends.
Elhemdillah mentiqa rind bû, xelkê fitilî, hezar neqlî malê
xwedê ava.
Praise God, the region was beautiful, the people returned, a
thousand times may God's house be built (thank God).
Me qey ne dikir wiha be?
We didn't think it would be like this?
Me îna ne dikir, me îna ne dikir em ro kano bibînin. No no,
elhemdillah.
We didn't believe, we didn't believe we would see this day.
No no, praise be to God.
Xweşî, tengî, mirin...
Joy, hardship, death...
Û her yek tê em kêfxweş dibin. Her yek tê em kêfxweş dibin.
And for every single one who comes, we are happy. For every
single one who comes, we are happy.
Hinda meriv kêf dibê, wextê dûr meriv şên dibe, meriv kêf
dike lê.
That much one gets happy, when the surroundings get
populated, one gets happy about it.
Meriv kêf dike.
One gets happy.
Erê.
Yes.
No no, yawaş yawaş, yawaş yawaş.
No no, slowly slowly, slowly slowly.
Çîçik ma mandik ma.
A little remained, a bit of fatigue remained.
Hatina we noqo.
Your coming now.
Hatina we noqo, molî dinê dikir.
Your coming now was worth the wealth of the world.
Ser serî me, ser çavê me xaltîk.
Upon our heads, upon our eyes Auntie.
Xwedê emrê ki dirêj we de. Xwedê seata we xweş bike.
May God give you a long life. May God bless your time
(health).
Xwedê ji we razî be. Ehlen we sehlen.
May God be pleased with you. Welcome.
Allah yselmek.
May God keep you safe (Arabic).
Erê havalno, taba'en me hîn vîdyo xwe xilaz nekiriye. Me
lexta kûrê nav gund ro çêkir.
Yes friends, of course we haven't finished our video yet. We
made (filmed) the deep parts inside the village.
Em hatin cem mala xalû.
We came to Uncle's house.
Niha jî em ê gund werin û gî teswîr kin.
And now we will go around the village and film it all.
Û mekanî gundin nîzîk dûrê raben ji me xwestibûn, em ê sar
va teswîr kin.
And the places of the village, near and far, that were
requested of us, we will film upon them.
Mantiqek pirr xweş e. Wînê naha vîdî me bibînin. Heta toliye
lê sêr kin wînê bibînin.
It is a very nice region. You will see our video now. Watch
it until the end, you will see.
Silavê me jî ji wara hene, ji urta çaqala da.
And our greetings are there for them, from the middle of
Chaqala (neighborhood/clan name).
Urta çaqalî cûmê da silav wara hene.
Greetings to them from the middle of Chaqala Jume.
Û silavê me jî mubaşer.
And our greetings are direct.
Noqo qîçkê me, yanî çûne, bes ê vî jî merdê xwe gîl virin, ê
me jî merê mi gîl virin.
Now our daughters, meaning they went, but this one (here)
her husband complains about this, and ours (my husband)
complains too.
Bi rok, xo gîl virin.
With a day (someday), they will complain (want to come
back).
Xaltîk bereka 'emir çend e?
Auntie, how much is the blessing of age?
Yê min?
Mine?
Hê?
Huh?
Wala...
Well...
Şêst... dudu şêst sê me.
Sixty... sixty-two, sixty-three.
Şêst, dudu şêst sê me.
Sixty, sixty-two, sixty-three I am.
Maşallah. Lê yê ta xalû?
Mashallah. And yours, Uncle?
Ê min... şêst û heşt.
Mine... sixty-eight.
Şeş heşt sal ji xaltîkê mestir im.
Six, eight years I am older than Auntie.
Şeş salan ji mi mestir e.
He is six years older than me.
Êwa.
I see.
Xwedê emrê kî dirêj bo we de.
May God give you a long life.
Silavê xwedê li we razî be. Ehlen we sehlen.
Greetings, may God be pleased with you. Welcome.
Erê havalno, ka bi me ra bin.
Yes friends, stay with us.
Niha, em ê lextan xweş nav gund çêkin.
Now, we will make (film) nice spots inside the village.
Heta toliya vîdyo bin, ha lextê xweş hîn mane, min wara
teswîr nekirî.
Stay until the end of the video, nice spots still remain, I
haven't filmed them yet.
Heta toliye bimînin, û te'lîqê we jî pir bin.
Stay until the end, and let your comments be many.
Te'lîqê zêde bişînin.
Send many comments.
Seata we xweş.
Bless your time.
Gindê Çaqala... Çaqalî cûmê xwe ispat kin, ser vîdyo xwe.
Village of Chaqala... Chaqala Jume prove yourselves, upon
your video.
İnşallah.
God willing.
Erê, mlo pşî vîdyo kêsî nekeve.
Yes, don't let anyone fall behind the video (miss it).
Bê qelkî giyo keve.
Let everyone join in (watch).
Erê. Bineşirînin.
Yes. Share it.
İnşallah.
God willing.
De seata we xweş, bi me ra bin.
Alright bless you, stay with us.
Maşallah çi sarsikê ne ke.
Mashallah, what a cool breeze it makes.
Ehe.
Uh-huh.
Wêneyê ji vir jî bigire.
Take the picture/shot from here too.
Em kûrê...
Where are we...
Erê naha em ê sar xênî bo lextan xweş çêkin.
Yes, now we will make nice shots on the roof.
Ku birano, ev çi çak no.
Oh brothers, look at these beautiful places.
Ve war, ve war no, ve der ro.
Come here, come here guys, this way.
Erê afol no, wara em hatin ser xênî.
Yes guys, come, we came onto the roof.
Derê rind xuyn werin.
Nice places are showing up.
Haşê xoltîkê jî bigire, bira.
Film Auntie's courtyard too, brother.
Ev jî molê...
This is also the house of...
Molê Break e.
It is Break's house.
Ehe.
Uh-huh.
War.
Come.
Erê havalno, maşallah, çi tebîetek xweş e hano.
Yes friends, mashallah, what a beautiful nature is here.
Ehe.
Uh-huh.
Gind... gind Hemze Mero daye viderê.
Village... Hamza Mero's village is this way.
Kîbar e wala.
It is elegant, I swear.
Bes milê gindî xwe... onol darek bilind bô. Çîçikê gêle
doyê.
But the people of his village... it was [like] on a high
tree. It gives a little trouble/complaint (hard to reach).
Wadiye hevalî min viderna nîzîk bike, no?
The valley, my friend, bring it closer over here, no?
Ka wara molê mistefê jî nîzîk bike?
Come, zoom in on Mustafa's house too?
Şînî xoluyê likol dar vo.
Looks like Uncle is standing at the door.
Kakê Mistefa, hewşa way le waye.
Brother Mustafa, their courtyard is right there.
Sipî hewşa waye.
Their courtyard is white.
Î hewşê çêdikin.
They are fixing the courtyard.
Lê bine Kakê Mistefa, lê bine.
Stay low Brother Mustafa, stay low.
Miletî Çaqala, gindî xwe sêr kin, maşallah.
Nation of Chaqala, look at your village, mashallah.
Mantiqê me cennet e, cennet.
Our region is paradise, paradise.
Tebîetek pir xweş e.
It is a very beautiful nature.
Ya selam.
Oh peace (Wow).
Havalî min wawa viderna jî bigir.
My friend, film over here like this too.
Ya selam.
Oh peace (Wow).
Havolno, taba'en... re... rêka vê darê jûr, em nikarin pirr
elkşin, lere rêka xwe çetin dibê molnê jûr.
Friends, of course... the... the road to up here, we can't
climb much, because its road becomes difficult for the upper
houses.
Bes em hatin sa viderê vo me kişand, me go ma'nî gi xuyn
werin.
But we came up to here and filmed, we said so that all the
meanings (views) show up.
Kakê Mistefa.
Brother Mustafa.
Mol Betê xwe sêr ke.
Look at Bate's house.
Havolî min ko lexta kanê jî bigir?
My friend, capture the shot of the spring too?
Ez silav dikim qîza xwe ji vir heta Stenbolê!
I greet my daughter from here to Istanbul!
Ez dibêjim ew dengê xaltîkê ye.
I say that is Auntie's voice.
Qîza xwe Stenbolê silav dike.
She greets her daughter in Istanbul.
Xalo maşallah gundî gellek xweş e. Tişta cîcag ji erdhê
xwayê, cîcag, anha îdî kurm te tê.
Uncle, mashallah the village is very nice. The plants from
the ground, the plants, now the worms are getting into them.
Tişta me ye, ev bîber e. Bîberê romanî ye. Ê davi gele dabe,
pel hofe gunde. Milet me'nî bîber jê dikin.
These are ours, these are peppers. They are Roman peppers.
The end [of the plant] gives a lot, [unintelligible] in the
village. The people pick peppers from it.
Yanî bêhna wê tê.
Meaning, you can smell its scent.
Belê bêhna wê tê.
Yes, you can smell its scent.
Disa xweş e, disa xweş e. Gindî van disa xweş e maşallah.
It is still nice, still nice. Their village is still nice,
mashallah.
Xwedê bereketê bixe tê.
May God put blessings in it.
Ev der mala kî ye?
Whose house is this place?
Ev mala xalkê me ne. Mala birakî me ne.
This is our maternal uncle's house. It is our brother's
house.
Deriyan bigre.
Close the doors.
Der xin, mala me tike, mala brêka, vro...
Take it out, our house [unintelligible], the brother's
house, go...
Ko were, ewê. Lê bigre.
Come here, that one. Film it.
Hevalno te'lîqata pirr li min dikin, dibêjin "Erebê
bifiroşe". Înşallah dube dube ezê herim gida ro.
Friends, you make a lot of comments about me, saying "Sell
the car". God willing, slowly slowly I will go to the
[scrap/market].
Bes çi şikê... lê? Çi şikê, hûn kêkî li min sebir bikin.
Bawer bikin, ev rûhê makîna min lê xist.
But what... hey? What, you guys just have a little patience
with me. Believe me, this is the soul of the machine I
started.
Eva jî min nûyî nûyî... ev jî... tişta hacer min nûyî û disa
mirov marşî lê naye, are wele.
This one, I just recently... this one too... the thing is
stone/rock (solid) for me recently, and still, one cannot
start the ignition on it, yes indeed.
Birê Mustafa ev jî mala xaltîka te ye?
Brother Mustafa, is this also your aunt's house?
Erê. Ev jî mala xaltîka Benevş e.
Yes. This is also Aunt Benevş's house.
Xaltîka Benevş?
Aunt Benevş?
Erê.
Yes.
Ser çava da. Xaltîk, destê te radimûsim.
Upon my eyes (You are welcome). Auntie, I kiss your hand.
Are...
Yes...
Xaltîka te Benevş.
Your Aunt Benevş.
Are, mala xaltîka Benevş.
Yes, Aunt Benevş's house.
Wele vê dorna şêrîn kirine xalo, serserê me da.
By God, uncle has made this surrounding area
sweet/beautiful, upon our heads (welcome).
Are...
Yes...
Ka wer vir jî bigre. Lê bigre.
Come take (film) here too. Film it.
Are, mala xaltîkê.
Yes, the aunt's house.
Ser çava. Tu çawan î?
Upon my eyes (Welcome). How are you?
Tu bi xêr hatî, keyf û halê te?
Welcome, how is your mood and health?
Derbas be, derbas be. Ha...
Enter, enter. Ha...
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Tu Mustafê ro dibe çi?
What relation are you to Mustafa?
Ahlan wa sahlan, xalê min e Mustafa.
Welcome, Mustafa is my uncle.
Xalê te ye?
He is your uncle?
Hmm.
Xaltî tamm? Mustafa, Zêrî...
The aunt exactly? Mustafa, Zêrî...
Ewa...
That one...
A, ahlan wa sahlan, xaltîka min.
Ah, welcome, my aunt.
Xaltîka te, tirhatê te bi kîvê ye? Silav rêj bo te.
Your aunt, where is your [unintelligible/lineage]? Many
greetings to you.
Saet xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Thanks (good hour), may God be pleased with you.
Silav mubaşer ne.
The greetings are direct (live).
Mubaşer e ne?
They are live, right?
Lê eyb nekin, derbas ke, are.
Don't be shy, let him pass, yes.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
May God be pleased with you all.
Na, teswîr bike.
No, film it.
Are hevalno, le em hatin vê derê jî, xaltîka min vana dîtin,
vro...
Yes friends, we came here too, my aunt saw them, go...
Li ser makînê gindî jî li paşiyê nivîsandibû "Efrîn 336".
On the car, the villager had also written on the back "Afrin
336".
Min jî makîna xwe danî, min jî nivîsandibû Efrîn 336. Min
nîşretî Youtube dîtibû, xaltîka min jî nivîsandibû.
I also parked my car, I had also written Afrin 336. I had
seen the sign on YouTube, my aunt had written it too.
Bes îşare pê tune bûyi.
But there was no signal/sign on it.
Are. Ka bimar bin, li vir bigir.
Yes. Check this out, film here.
Du birxût hekandine tenê.
Only two screws are hooked on.
Du birxût hene?
Are there two screws?
Somun tê tune.
There is no nut in it.
Ewa, divê du somun di tekerê makîna me da tune ye.
Yes, so there are no two nuts in the wheel of our car.
Are ez 'aşqê abim.
Yes, I am in love with this.
Sen'etê... [Unintelligible].
The industry/craft... [Unintelligible].
Wa re, wa re, wa re, xaltîka jî ana teswîr ke şabû bûn.
Come, come, come, film the aunt too, they are happy.
Birê Mustafa, xaltîka Benevş...
Brother Mustafa, Aunt Benevş...
Xaltîka Benevş... Mustafê ro dibe çi? Ha?
Aunt Benevş... what is she to Mustafa? Huh?
Xaltîka xwa ye.
She is his aunt.
Are, are, tu dibê çi Mustafê ro?
Yes, yes, what do you say to Mustafa?
Zêrî.
Sister-in-law/Wife (Zêrî).
Zêrî?
Tu vîra çi silavê dişînî?
What greetings do you send here?
Tu dibêyî çi? Bi navê Xwedê tik...
What are you saying? In the name of God... [unintelligible].
Ewa ne, tu silavê çi vîr dişînî?
That's right, what greetings do you send here?
A, ez dişînim le wele tu zêrî naza nî, birakî min...
Ah, I am sending them, but by God you don't know Zêrî
(Gold), my brother...
Zêrî kî ye ermê?
Who is Zêrî, man?
Na ezanim.
I don't know.
Silavê jêra bişîne.
Send greetings to her/him.
Tu silavê dişînî jêra?
Do you send greetings to her?
Hmm, lê ez şînim lê wele tu zêrî nazanî birakî min. Hmm,
lawê xalkê min e.
Hmm, I am Blue (mourning/sad), but by God you don't know
Zêrî (Gold), my brother. Hmm, he is my maternal uncle's son.
Are. Silavên te gihîştinê, el te sêrke.
Yes. Your greetings reached her, she is watching you.
Înşallah, îşê we çêbe, em çi dikin, çi nakin, ça... çi tne.
God willing, may your work go well, what we do, what we
don't do, how... whatever.
Qîçikê malê me ne, we şad bûn vî derê.
They are the kids of our house, you made this place happy.
Heta we xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be û silav kaşmer giya silav
ke.
As long as you are well, may God be pleased with you and
greet everyone everywhere.
Saet xweş xaltîk silavên te gihîştinê.
Thanks (Good hour) auntie, your greetings reached them.
Qîçikê min jî silav ke.
Greet my kids too.
Qîçikê xaltîkê silav ji we ra hene giya ra.
The aunt's kids, there are greetings for you, for all.
Qîçikêm sê li wê derê ne.
Three of my kids are over there.
Maşallah, Xwedê ji te razî be lê. Silavê te gihîştinê.
Mashallah, may God be pleased with you. Your greetings
reached them.
Em hatin maşallah, birê Mustafa, vî derê malbata we pirr
kêfxweş bûn, ez jî kêfxweş bûn teb'en.
We came, mashallah, Brother Mustafa, here your family was
very happy, and I was happy too, naturally.
Ka hevalno bimar bin.
Come on friends, check this out.
Wer weryan ecêb...
Come, weird [unintelligible]...
Bi xêr hatin, ser çava hatin. Ji hatina we ra, û ji dîtina
we ra, û ji vê wez'ê ra, û ji vê cewê ra, û merivçîtiya we,
elhemdulilah.
Welcome, you came upon eyes (you are welcome). For your
coming, and for seeing you, and for this situation, and for
this atmosphere, and your kinship, praise be to God.
Hûn bi kêfxweş in, û inşallah xêr e.
You are happy, and God willing it is good.
Saet xweş.
Thanks.
Tu çawa yî? Baş î?
How are you? Are you good?
Ev çîçek noxşan e?
Is this flower decorated?
Lê?
Huh?
[Unintelligible]
Ez dibêm onî hîç...
I say that... none...
Are kekê Mustafa, li vê derê jî em li mala xaltîka te ne.
Yes Brother Mustafa, here too we are at your aunt's house.
Û bavê te jî li cem min e, maşallah cîcagê cema'tê ye, Xwedê
jê razî be.
And your father is also with me, mashallah he is the flower
of the gathering, may God be pleased with him.
Hîn wekî gilo ye, Xwedê 'emrekî dirêj bidê.
He is still like a ball (healthy/stout), may God give him a
long life.
Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê ji we giya razî be, ahlan wa
sahlan.
May God be pleased with you, may God be pleased with you
all, welcome.
Bes apê xalo, tu çi silavê dişînî ji Mustafê ro, ji miletî
li me sêr dike, tu dibê çi?
But Uncle Xalo, what greetings do you send to Mustafa, to
the nation watching us, what do you say?
Ooo, hezar silav, giya ra, ser giya jimar ra silav dikim,
pirr û pirr, geş dikim.
Ooo, a thousand greetings, to everyone, I greet all of you,
very much, I make it lively.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Erê wela, mîletê selamê, ahlan wa sahlan. Her yekî Kurmanc
silavê jimar ra dikim, li giya.
Yes indeed, the nation of peace, welcome. I greet every
single Kurmanji (Kurd) for you, everywhere.
Xwedê ji te razî be, dest xweş apê.
May God be pleased with you, health to your hands uncle.
Dest xweş, dest xweş.
Health to your hands, health to your hands.
Are, kekê Mustafa, îşta li vî derê jî, emê naha, doka
venortê ginc jî, emê çend leqta din çêkin, hevalno bimar
bin.
Yes, Brother Mustafa, now here too, we will now...
[unintelligible] the middle... we will make a few more
shots, friends stay tuned.
Xalo jî li hewşê ye, teb'en hewşe zîrqa dike.
Uncle is also in the yard, naturally the yard is shining.
Erê, erê em çûn me got kera bê çêdikin.
Yes, yes we went, we said they are making the
[unintelligible - likely part of house/garden].
Kera bê ne?
They are [unintelligible]?
Hmm, me got kera bê çêdikin.
Hmm, we said they are making [unintelligible].
Kera bê çêdikin, e meban nekir, me go wer vî derê hêna ke.
They are making [unintelligible], we didn't mind, we said
come make the place here.
Erê, Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê 'emrekî dirêj bitade xalo.
Yes, may God be pleased with you, may God give you a long
life, uncle.
Spas dikim kuro, Xwedê ji we jî razî be, mîletê selamê.
Thank you son, may God be pleased with you too, nation of
peace.
Saet xweş, ahlan wa sahlan.
Thanks, welcome.
Are wela kekê Mustafa, îşta emkê ji gund derketin.
Yes indeed Brother Mustafa, now we just left the village.
Xalo ew jî ji me negeriya, îlla me helîb lî meke nanî me
bixwin.
Uncle, he also didn't let us go (insisted we stay), he
insisted we shouldn't leave until we ate our bread.
Me go emkê herin meşwêrekî, me dûr e, em bar nadin wela, emî
naha li vir ne.
We said we are going on an errand, our [way] is far, we
can't manage by God, we are here now.
Naha paşê emê leqtanok çêkin li viro.
Now afterwards we will make a shot here.
Saeta gindiyo xweş, Xwedê pêxember jê razî be.
The villagers' hour is good (Thanks to the villagers), may
God and the Prophet be pleased with them.
Selam, ahlan wa sahlan.
Peace, welcome.
[Music Playing - Stran/Folk Song]
Elê mingo yarê delal, ava ziliya rebenê...
I said dear love, the water of the oppressed
[unintelligible]...
Zalimê dînê, şûrê limê mexî...
Cruel one of the faith, do not strike me with the sword...
Çûyîna te ji derê leylê erebê...
Your leaving from the door of Layla, the Arab...
Dilê min kuştî, ez mam mirî...
Killed my heart, I remained dead...
Elê mingo leylê, ne heryek biterra kani...
I said Layla, not everyone is a fountain for you...
Wê doston bî...
It will be friends...
Mingo ne heryek biterra kani leylê...
I said not everyone is a fountain for you Layla...
Wê ji mera dost nebî...
Will not be a friend to us...
Te agir berda canê leylê...
You set fire to the soul, Layla...
Dipêy te digerim, har û dîn...
I search after you, rabid and mad...
Te saminê ji wa tirsê te ez helandim, ez bûme hestî...
You [unintelligible] from fear of you, you melted me, I
became bone...
Te ez kirim şibqê benî dînno...
You made me like the crazy strings...
La timî li gunda...
Always in the villages...
Elê mingo, te ez helandim, emrê can da leylê...
I said, you melted me, gave the life of the soul Layla...
Te ez helandim şewitandim...
You melted me, burned me...
Elê mingo leylê, te rewş halê min tine ye...
I said Layla, you don't have my situation/state...
Te ez kirim har û dîn...
You made me rabid and mad...
Dibe taraz na xwazim...
It says I don't want the balance...
Dibe taraz na xwazim, guliya çavê reş û belek leylê...
It says I don't want the balance, the plaits of the black
and multicolored eyes, Layla...
Ez bitetim serxweş û dîn...
I am drunk and mad for you...
Dûr in ser çava, ahlan wa sahlan.
You are far but upon eyes (welcome), welcome.
Hevalno werin werin, maşallah xaltîka min çi cîcek li vir
çandine.
Friends, come come, mashallah what flowers my aunt has
planted here.
Werin, nêzîk be.
Come, be close.
Min jî maşallah...
I also mashallah...
Çi cî çêkiriye, banê?
What a place she made, look?
Hevalê min li vir bigir, vê tebîetê.
My friend, film here, this nature.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Havo, xaltîka min xwa ra cîyê rûniştinê çêkiriye.
Look, my aunt has made a sitting place for herself.
Ma'nî bes xwa ra li rûne. A wer têkeve.
Meaning just to sit for herself. Come enter.
Te jê keyfî... [unintelligible]
Did you enjoy it... [unintelligible].
Keyfî dilî xwa ra çêkiriye. A wer, a wer, hevalê min wer.
Ehê, ehê.
She made it for her heart's pleasure. Come, come, my friend
come. Ehe, ehe.
Av heye? Av heye?
Is there water? Is there water?
Av heye elhemdulillah.
There is water, praise be to God.
Bîr e? Bîr e?
Is it a well? Is it a well?
Bîr e elhemdulillah.
It is a well, praise be to God.
Maşallah, hevalno gellek vê derê, dibê bîr heye, gelek cîcek
çandine.
Mashallah, friends, a lot here, they say there is a well,
many flowers planted.
Are.
Yes.
Fermo ke, kerem ke.
Please do, help yourself.
Wer, wer, rûne, wer.
Come, come, sit, come.
Wa dît çi cako?
Did you see what a nice place?
Ser se xwa ra çêkiriye.
She made it nicely/head-on for herself.
Rûne, kerem ke, rûne.
Sit, help yourself, sit.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Wela cî tar e, bilindî ye, til hafîkî ye.
By God the place is cool/dark (shaded), it is high up, it is
[unintelligible].
Hafîkî ye, elhemdulillah.
It is [unintelligible], praise be to God.
Ah...
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Av jî... ser lûlehê cirûnê kî min e, hewşê min deynuyî.
The water too... it is on the pipe of my spout/drain, in my
yard [unintelligible].
Û emana jî heye başqa.
And there is this one too besides.
Rûne.
Sit.
Ewa rûne.
Yes sit.
Rûne, rûne, rûne.
Sit, sit, sit.
Xolê Mihemed çi cî çêkirî?
Uncle Mohammed, what a place he made?
[Unintelligible] Mihemed.
[Unintelligible] Mohammed.
Ahlan.
Welcome.
Tu çonî?
How are you?
Rind e.
Good.
Dûr e.
It is far.
[Unintelligible]
Are wela.
Yes indeed.
Xerçê avê ye... tîştî av...
It is the cost of the water... the thing of the water...
Vêderê? Ne zade.
Here? It isn't too much.
Aa, ma av nûh berdan?
Ah, did they just release the water?
Ye, hayê dilê xwe, tiştê waha ne, de xaze…
Yes, pay attention, it's something like this, look...
Av nûh berdan kanî, înşallah…
They just released the water from the spring, God willing...
Maşallah tebîetek xweş e, û vira ciyê behasê ye.
Mashallah, it is a beautiful nature, and here is a place for
relaxing.
Kû vir ji, hin bi şev karebek di nav da heye, vê dikşînin.
And over here, there is electricity (pumps) inside at night,
they pull from it.
Wele, ta kareba jî kîriye?
Really, you put electricity in too?
Kareba jê tê.
Electricity comes from it.
Ê, havûna kareba jî kîriye.
Yeah, so you've put electricity in too.
Çaxê mator dişixûlin, ciyê xweş be, ciqas ron da here av kêm
dibe.
When the engines are working, may the place be nice, as the
day goes on, the water decreases.
Ê kê de sibê zû rabim, saet şeş û wan de, kê bibînim şû da
derdikeve.
But whoever wakes up early in the morning, at six or so,
they will see it rising back up.
Ez ji royê hez dikim.
I like the sun.
Te bilindî ye?
You are at an elevation?
Erê wele.
Yes, by God.
Ana pozê wê çêkir?
So, you fixed its tip/spout?
Piştî wî lêdixwin, derdikeve li cem min. Hemdillah şikir.
After it hits that, it splashes out near me. Thank God,
gratitude.
Wele.
Really.
Hemdillah.
Thank God.
Mantiqek pir xweş e, kîbar e, vira cografya wê pir ecîb e.
It’s a very nice area, elegant, the geography here is very
amazing.
Heta… bes ji gund çîçikek, wina, bilindtir baran de, vira
bilind e.
Even... but compared to the village, a little bit, like
that, higher in the rain, here is high.
Erê, bide cî tewr bilind e, teqrîben.
Yes, this place is the highest, approximately.
Vira tewr bilind e.
Here is the highest.
Malê apê min ji, ji me bilindtir e xaniyê min e, malê
biraziyê min ji piçik ji me nimitir e.
My uncle's house is higher than my house, my nephew's house
is a little lower than ours.
Wele cîyê we jî xweş e.
By God, your place is nice too.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Ê wa qîçikê apê min in. Evê layê biraziyê min e, ev e.
And those are my uncle's kids. That one on the side is my
nephew, this one.
Ostazê me?
Our teacher?
Belê.
Yes.
Êy biraziyê te ye?
And the one behind?
Is that your nephew?
Erê, qîçikê apê min jî li vî derê kelek me ne.
Yes, my uncle's kids are also here alongside us.
Ê malbata me, pismam û kurmam.
The family, cousins and relatives.
Erê, de hemû gel cem hev in.
Yes, so everyone is together.
Teqrîben hemû kene li vir in? Hinek li jorî vê derê ne,
hinek li jêrî vê derê ne?
Is almost everyone here? Are some above this place and some
below this place?
Ava wê jî heye, bîr?
Does it have water too, a well?
Ava wê, li cem me, ya dibe… ya cîranê me dibe.
Its water, near us, it goes... it goes to our neighbor.
Ewa. Vira çiqas metro dikulin av derdikeve?
I see. How many meters do they dig here for water to come
out?
Wele dûr, sed pêncî… vî deran, sed hefteyî, sed pêncî.
Well, deep, one hundred fifty... around here, one hundred
seventy, one hundred fifty.
Ma bêjî sed pêncî du sed ye, teqrîben.
Let's say one hundred fifty to two hundred, approximately.
Ê rinde, cem me çar sed metro dikulin.
That's good, near us they dig four hundred meters.
Ê bi kû ve diçî, bahr e waha, çiqas bilind be…
It depends where you go, it's a sea like that, the higher it
is...
Wê tenê jî kêm e.
And it [the flow] is low too.
Vira, avê ver…
Here, the water...
Ê wele, bi şeklê am, çiqas mantiqe… ewê dikişînin nûke, zore
avê dikişînin.
Yes really, generally speaking, as much as the area... they
draw from it now, they draw a lot of water.
Yanî çiqas av li mantiqê bibe, hindik be, ewqas av hindik
dibe.
Meaning, the more water is [used] in the area, if it is
scarce, the water becomes scarce.
Yanî çîçike kêm dibe, derdibe.
Meaning it decreases a little, it gets troublesome.
Ê, hemdillah halê bîrê me rind in, tişt nebûne.
Yeah, thank God the state of our wells is good, nothing has
happened to them.
No no, rind e, rind e, saetê we xweş, xêr e, tiştekî rind
rind e.
No no, it's good, it's good, bless you, it's good, it's a
very good thing.
Erê.
Yes.
Mera xizmet milkê xwe, darê xwe bike jî rind e.
If a man serves his property, his trees, it is good.
Ê ekîd, ekîd.
Yes, certainly, certainly.
Havûlno tebîetê, mantiqê Efrîn pir kîbar, xweş e.
Friends, the nature, the area of Afrin is very elegant,
beautiful.
Werin, hunê li Ewrûpa çi bikin? Werin vêderê, ciyê behasê ye
ha. Werin cem xaletiyê min.
Come, what will you do in Europe? Come here, it is a place
for relaxing. Come to my aunt's place.
Ê merivê ku me jî mezin diki, dibêjin: "Wele em li Ewrûpa
çiqas dibînin, dile me li vêderê, saetêk a vêderê..."
The people who raise us say: "By God, however much we see in
Europe, our heart is here, one hour here..."
Ê, tam sîretê vê ro bibînin, me’nî dilê xwe vir bibînin.
Yes, when they see the exact image of this sun, meaning they
see their heart here.
Bêham, wa gi dikin haa.
Without a doubt, they all do that.
Bibêjin: "Îşta, çîçik li cem me hene, av heye..."
Let them say: "Look, we have a little [land] near us, there
is water..."
Bi telefonê dibînin.
They see it on the phone.
Dibên: "Ê, Ewrûpa hebit rû ye, ya rastî na, ew e, dogrî
yanî..."
They say: "Yeah, Europe is just a facade, the truth is no,
this is it, truly..."
Çiqas vê tebîetê li vêderê buyaye, li vê tiştê...
As much as this nature exists here, in this thing...
Ê xêra av hebe gite?
Is it good if you have water?
Av hebe heyat li vêderê heye.
If there is water, there is life here.
Erê.
Yes.
Lo, hevalê kê min, wî riyê dibê...
Hey, my friend, to that face he says...
Erê.
Yes.
Xwe didê ber roye. Dibê: "Vê roye cem Ewrûpa tune ye." Lo,
dibê: "Mila reş bibim, a bişewitim."
He gives himself to the sun. He says: "This sun doesn't
exist in Europe." Hey, he says: "Let me get black/tan, let
me burn."
Li Ewrûpa hebê ro ye hene dixwin.
In Europe they take pills for the sun (Vitamin D).
Hebê ro ye.
Sun pills.
Eşqê, ferqî, dibê vê bayî, cem a pak, vê ana, vê roye,
germik...
Love, difference, he says this wind, near the clean [air],
this now, this sun, warmth...
Ruh, ruh, derket xelas, her tişt ki wextê xwe heye.
Soul, soul, it came out and finished, everything has its
time.
Mantiqê cem me xas ten şiklê, ewsatê pir, xas ten sîrê, çar
fesil le... dewra darbaz dibin.
The area near us, especially the shape, the middle is
very... especially the flow, four seasons pass through it
properly.
Nîzamî.
Orderly.
Derbaz dibin, weşmê pir xweş e. Ewrûpa na, Ewrûpa derket
haavîna.
They pass, the climate is very nice. Europe no, Europe comes
out in summer.
Zivistan avînî gindî nebînin.
In winter they don't see the pool/water [unclear, possibly
referring to sun/nature].
Dî nebîniye.
Doesn't see it.
Erê.
Yes.
Encaq çend, çend ro hevinin, bes.
Barely a few, a few days they have, that's it.
Erê.
Yes.
Havûlno, saetê we giya xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be. Gotinê ten
e? Silav kî tkê bişînê? Gotinê toliyê?
Friends, bless all your times, may God be pleased with you.
Do you have any words? Any greetings you want to send? Final
words?
Silavê min ji giya ra ne, ê li me seyr dikin, li gotinê me,
derdê me.
My greetings are to everyone who is watching us, our words,
our troubles.
Û silavê min ji giya ra ne, û her yekî li dervaye dixwazim
vegere welatê xwe, welat... Meriv şên dibe.
And my greetings to everyone, and everyone who is outside
(abroad), I want them to return to their country, country...
One becomes happy/populated.
Ver ser milkê xwe, erdê xwe çêtir e.
Being on his property, his land is better.
Werin cem anê, bavû?
Come to mother and father?
Werin cem anê, bavû.
Come to mother and father.
Gerek meriv anê, bavû kûk bar nade.
One should not drop the burden of mother and father.
Na. Hemşiye, ev e, hemşiye.
No. That's the main thing, this is it, the main thing.
Wan xizmet me kir, wan xizmet me kir, em kî ji xizmet wan
bikin. Heq e.
They served us, they served us, we should also serve them.
It's right.
Besî, tebîe.
Simple, natural.
Ê de gotinê ten e? Gotinê na bike.
So, do you have words? Don't make speeches.
Hat saxbê, saxxweş.
Be healthy, good health.
Erê hevalno, li vêderê em gihiştin toliyê vîdyo xwe. Saetê
vê xaletiyê min jî xweş, şebabin, rind in.
Yes friends, here we have reached the end of our video.
Bless the time of this aunt of mine too, they are young
guys, they are good.
Birakê me Idrîs.
Our brother Idris.
Maşallah, xoliyê min jî, Xwedê ji gundiyê razî be, em
bernadan, îlla emê xwarin bînan heta nî em av bîn.
Mashallah, my folks too, may God be pleased with the
villagers, they wouldn't let us go, insisting they bring
food until we drink water.
Erê wele, me go ma'nî em dereng nemînin.
Yes really, we said, meaning, we shouldn't stay late.
Êm bûn.
We became [late].
Ka bimînin ro, bin vîdyo kî din xweş, kîbar. Înşallah nêzîk
de ezê werim [unclear name, likely 'Duvê'] gundê ra.
Stay tuned, for another nice, elegant video. God willing,
soon I will come to [Duvê] village.
Ka bimînin, saetê we xweş. Bay, bay.
Stay tuned, bless your time. Bye, bye.
Xwedê ji we razî be, saetê we pir xweş.
May God be pleased with you, bless your time very much.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Erê hevalno, li vêderê sînayê me, Cindirês e.
Yes friends, here is our industrial zone, Jindires.
Vira Cindirês e.
This is Jindires.
Tabe'n... marşê min risqî kinî.
Naturally... my starter motor has seized up.
Birê min Neşet, ê marş çêkir.
My brother Nashat, he fixed the starter.
Erê.
Yes.
Saet xweş birê Neşet, saet xweş.
Bless you brother Nashat, bless you.
Xwedê ji te razî be, spas.
May God be pleased with you, thanks.
Karê çi dike?
What work do you do?
Gerek bibî, bide selamê.
You have to be [here], give greetings.
Erê. Birê min Neşet, karebciye, xaze, tişt dike, karebîgî,
na?
Yes. My brother Nashat is an electrician, gas, he does
things, generally electrical, right?
Erê. Xaz, kareba, marş, dînamo.
Yes. Gas, electricity, starter, dynamo (alternator).
Gîşkî. Bes hûn gihiştin vêderê, bibê Neşet, karebci gî nas
dikin.
Everything. As soon as you arrive here, say Nashat, the
electrician, everyone knows him.
Marşê me xirab bûye, çêke.
Our starter is broken, fix it.
Erê hevalno, me vîdyo xwe temam kirî bî, marş sêkinî, îşta î
me ra çêdike.
Yes friends, we had finished our video, the starter stopped,
look he is fixing it for us now.
Erê wele.
Yes really.