[Music]
Belê temaşevanên hêja, yê ku vê darê lepêşme bibîne, wê
dizanibe emê îro bibin mêvanê kîjan gundî.
Yes, dear viewers, whoever sees this lepêşme tree, will know
which village's guest we will be today.
Ji kinyayê hewarê, emê bibin mêvanê gundê Avrazê.
From the slope of the valley, we will be guests of the
village of Avraz.
[Music]
Gundê Obrazê bixwe, başûrî çoyê hewarê dikeve.
The village of Obraz itself falls south of the valley
stream.
Pêşiya gund deşt e, ji paş va Hecî Boker... çiya ye.
The front of the village is a plain, and behind it is the
Hecî Boker... mountain.
Û paşê bîra Obrazê heye, bîrek mearûf e, darek mezin, dara
çinarê, yanê li ser e.
And back then there is the Obraz Well, a famous well, a
large tree, a plane tree, is on it.
Obrazê, gubekek, gulîkek şaxêl e... vê gundî, gişt av ji vê
te xwarin berê.
Obraz is a dome, a distinct branch... this village, everyone
used to drink water from this before.
Bixwe Obraz du gund in. Obrazê jûr heye û Obrazê jêr heye.
Actually, Obraz is two villages. There is Upper Obraz and
Lower Obraz.
Obrazê jûr... kî têda dijî? Mala Îmir têda dijîn.
Upper Obraz... who lives in it? The Mala Îmir [Imir family]
lives in it.
Ji mêj da bar kirine, berî vê bi sed salî bar kirine çûne
gundê Bêlê.
They moved long ago, they moved a hundred years ago and went
to the village of Bêlê.
Û mala Mamgurdê têda dijîn. Û noka Obrazê jûr xirabe ye. Tu
mal têda tunîne.
And the Mamgurd family lives there. And now Upper Obraz is
in ruins. There are no houses in it.
Û Obrazê jêr, e... aîle pir têda dijîn.
And Lower Obraz, eh... many families live in it.
Mala Belêl, ji Kemdar hebûn, mala Xelîfo hebûn, mala Xocê
Resû hebûn.
The Mala Belêl, from the Kemdar were there, the Mala Xelîfo
were there, the Mala Xocê Resû were there.
Û paşê jî pir aîle hatin, ji gundê... durbêrê gund hatin.
And afterwards many families came, from villages...
surrounding the village they came.
Ji gundê Çê hatin, ji gundê Şêx hatin, ji gubekê hatin. E...
bera delal.
They came from the village of Çê, they came from the village
of Şêx, they came from the dome. Uh... dear brother.
Tarîxa gund, sê sed sal zêdetir heye. Zêdetir heye.
The history of the village is more than three hundred years.
It is more.
Û... yanê... serweta gund, berê vê çi di... di eîşîn?
And... I mean... the wealth of the village, before this what
did... how did they subsist?
Pez hebû, û dewar hebûn, berdan çê... Yocî Boker.
There were sheep, and there was cattle, they released them
to... Yocî Boker.
Û başûr jî, rezê xwa hebûn, û av heye, ava ziravkê heye.
And to the south, they had their vineyards, and there is
water, there is trickling water.
Yanê pê debarê xwa dibûn.
Meaning, they made their living with it.
E... navê Obrazê bixwe, yanê li hember... wetiye.
Uh... the name of Obraz itself, means facing... it has come.
Yanê... Obraz li hember e. Ne tizonî?
Meaning... Obraz is facing [the slope]. Don't you know?
Û miletê têda, yanê aîlê mezin tne...
And the people in it, meaning there are big families...
Mala Îmir, yanê malek xanedan e, malek axa ne.
The Mala Îmir, meaning a noble family, a family of Aghas.
Û mala Belêl jî malek... aîlek şêxler in, yanê emliv xudê û
caw qin e... wina hene.
And the Mala Belêl is also a family... a family of Sheikhs,
meaning people of God and pious... they are like that.
Ê bera... derê meda jî, hew ne ji gundê Şêx hatine, ew jî
aîlan şêx in, erîq in.
Eh brother... in our surroundings too, not only did they
come from the village of Şêx, they are also families of
Sheikhs, they are deep-rooted.
Û ji gundê Çê da hatine, ji Gubekê hatine, ew jî aîlan şêx
in. Kok û binyatê xwa ne.
And they came from the village of Çê, they came from Gubek,
they are also families of Sheikhs. They have their own roots
and foundation.
Û ji zamanê Osmanîda, emê muxtarê gund hebû, vêra digotin
Muslimê Belêl.
And from the Ottoman times, we had a village headman, they
called him Muslimê Belêl.
Dudî vêra Şêx Mehmûd... Şêx Mem, bû muxtarê gund.
The second one was Şêx Mehmûd... Şêx Mem, became the village
headman.
Ê... û gund, hevgirtina Obraz, gubek, gulîka... yanê behsê
vê gund dike.
Eh... and the village, the unity of Obraz, the dome, the
peak... meaning it talks about this village.
Heta rêkê giştê yek e, û çoyê giştê yek e, û bêrê giştê yek
e.
Even the road for all is one, and the stream for all is one,
and the pasture for all is one.
Û merliqê giştê bi hevdira heye.
And they all have kinship relations with one another.
Û ji hevdira hez dikin û ji hevdira rind in, û tu tefrîqa
nav de kesî da tune ye.
And they love each other and are good to each other, and
there is no discrimination among anyone.
Hev xaniya, emrê gundê ser sê sed sala ye.
These houses, the age of the village is over three hundred
years.
Hev xaniya... ê mala aîlê Belêl e. Mihemed Muslim Bîlal,
hîng pîşî pîşê mala Belêl.
These houses... belong to the family of Belêl. Mihemed
Muslim Bîlal, back then, the ancestors of the Mala Belêl.
Pîşê mala Hebeş, pîşê mala Dedê... hev xaniya ê tevkevne.
The ancestors of Mala Hebeş, the ancestors of Mala Dedê...
these houses are ancient.
Û beliyê kevirê şikandî, ji gundî tne ne. Têda kevirê
şikandî tne ne.
And it is evident there are no cut stones in the village.
There are no cut stones in it.
Kevir kum kirine û pê girtine. Û ev xaniya yek kevne û
xirabe ye, noka kes têda tune ye.
They piled stones and built with them. And this house is an
old one and is a ruin, now no one is in it.
[Music]
Navê min Ebdîn e. Navê gund Obraze. Berê em li gundê jûr
bûn. Paşê em daketin vê derê.
My name is Abdin. The village's name is Obraze. Previously,
we were in the upper village. Then we came down here.
Em cotkar bûn. Cot dajotin. Dexil diçandin, pale diçinin,
car car dikutin.
We were farmers. We plowed. We planted crops, reaped the
harvest, and threshed it.
Şixre dikişandin. Paşê zeytûn çandin. Rez çandin, rez,
zeytûn.
We hauled sleds. Then we planted olives. We planted
vineyards, vineyards and olives.
Tenê koka gi... milet bi rez û zeytûna va meşgûl bûn heya...
Tine ye av, tine ye.
Only the root of... the people were occupied with vineyards
and olives until... There is no water, none.
Oooh, biroke Mihemedê Mehbîr lê xist... sê sed metro înçkû
av tine ye.
Oooh, Mihemedê Mehbîr used a drill... it went down three
hundred meters, there is no water.
Vê gundê bîrek li ber lê xistine, pîşê gulîka, jê ve em
tînin.
In this village, they dug a well in front, at the slope of
the Gulîk plant, we bring [water] from there.
Şimşêr... em meşhûr in, bi milkê xwe, bi zeytûnê xwe meşhûr
in. Ha wilo yek meşhûret...
[Unclear]... we are famous, for our property, for our olives
we are famous. Just like that, a fame...
Meşhûreta xwe heye bi zeytûn û milk, îşta rez û pê de dijîn
û tê de dişixulin û ha...
It has its fame for olives and property, look, vineyards,
and on that we live and in that we work and there...
Ev jî îşta rez, cûd, pale... Zeytûn. Darê... Îşta ha waye
zeytûnê xwe li vê derê li cem hev in.
This too, look, vineyards, plowing, harvesting... Olives.
Trees... Look, just like that, our olives are here together.
Zarê me van in. Ev jî cotkariya wekî me.
These are our children. This is also farming like us.
Welle, hin li derva ne, li Ewropa ne, pir li Ewropa ne.
Welle, dibên wa dibên ez nizanim.
Well, some are abroad, in Europe, many are in Europe. Well,
they say, so they say, I don't know.
Dibe ewil dardan... Efrîn xeyo dar dişixulin. Hin li Tirkiyê
ne, hin li Helebê ne, hin li dar... ha wilo dane, herin
derkevin.
Maybe at first... [unclear] Afrin [unclear] they work. Some
are in Turkey, some in Aleppo, some... just like that, they
have left.
Bîra dê Obraze, ew qeraş tînin ardê me gi dora ne. Û zîraet
em genim em ardê me tenê ne. Gi zeytûn in.
The well of Obraze, they bring those millstones, all our
lands are around it. And for agriculture, we [plant] wheat,
our lands are few. They are all olives.
Vê gundê bi xwe sêsmal heye. Hinek ji gundê Çiya tên, ji
mala Xelîlera ne. Ji gundê Çiya hatine, ji gundê Şêx hatine,
ji her malbatek hatine.
This village itself has three lineages. Some come from Gundê
Çiya (Mountain Village), they are from the Xelîler family.
Came from Gundê Çiya, came from Gundê Şêx, came from every
family.
Bi xwe debarê xwe şêniyê gundê me dan Efrîn dişixulin. Li
warşê xeyata dişixulin. Sibê daren heft nîv o şîv o tên mal.
Zehmeta wa dijwar e.
As for their livelihood, the residents of our village go to
Afrin to work. They work in sewing workshops. In the morning
they go at seven thirty and come home in the evening. Their
hardship is difficult.
Sê-çar sal in daren, ser bîst û obrez e daren... tên û sibê
daren êvarê tên. Her kes li kora hewla xwe.
It's been three or four years they go, on the bus to Obraze
they go... they come and go in the morning, come in the
evening. Everyone is after their own livelihood.
Em bi xwe bi zeytûna meşhûr in. Bi ardê, bi her tiştî... bi
vedana darê meşhûr in.
We ourselves are famous for olives. For land, for
everything... famous for planting trees.
Me weke eser ji ber gundê jûr hene. Û li her derkî, li bîra
Obraze heye meselen hew... şikeft katêne, şikeft sarînc
hene, qob heye, dar heye.
We have ruins from the upper village. And everywhere, at the
well of Obraze there are for example... caves, cistern
caves, domes, trees.
Li hember mala me ew da ji Obraze ew da hene. Axazên zana vê
delîba heye, bi dewar dajotinê.
Opposite our house, those from Obraze are there. I want to
say there is this stone press, they used to drive it with
animals.
Yanê, bilxurê xwe dikutan, li her derkî, li her derkî
dihatinê. Ji gundekî dihatinê... ji her derkî dihatin.
Meaning, they crushed their bulgur, from everywhere, from
everywhere they used to come to it. They came from a
village... they came from everywhere.
Delîba bi xwe noka şikestî ye. Xera kirine. Bi xwe kevirê
eserî bî. Eva ş... axazên zana heye vê delîba, noka gi
şikestî ye.
The stone press itself is now broken. They destroyed it. It
was an antique stone itself. This... I want to say this
stone press is now all broken.
Ji mêj in, kevnar e. Bi dewar dajotinê. Ji her derkî
dihatinê.
It is from long ago, it is ancient. They drove it with
animals. They came to it from everywhere.