Belê temaşevanên hêja, programa me destpêkir.
Yes dear viewers, our program has started.
Ji beşek nû emê werin pêşberî we.
We will come before you with a new episode.
Îro jî emê bibin mêvanê gundê Xelnêrê.
And today we will be guests of the village of Xelnêrê.
Temma insha' qaryat Khalneer munzu hawali al-arba'mi'at
'aam.
The village of Khalneer was established around four hundred
years ago.
Wa awwal man sakanaha kana l-jadd Khal.
And the first to inhabit it was Grandfather Khal.
Wa summiyat al-qarya nisbatan ila ismihi, idafatan ila
kalimat Neer ayy al-rujula.
The village was named after him, in addition to the word
"Neer" meaning manhood.
Yuhitu bil-qarya majmu'a min al-qura.
The village is surrounded by a group of villages.
Famin al-sharq Kafr Shila, wa min al-shamal al-sharqi
Musanka.
From the east Kafr Shila, and from the northeast Musanka.
Wa min al-shamal Juqay, wa min al-shamal al-gharbi Dargir.
And from the north Juqay, and from the northwest Dargir.
Wa min al-gharb Gundê Mazen, wa min al-janub Ma'rata.
And from the west Gundê Mazen, and from the south Ma'rata.
Amma hudud al-qarya, fal-tariq muhat bi-salasil jabaliya min
kull al-jihat.
As for the village boundaries, the road is surrounded by
mountain ranges on all sides.
Bistisna' jihat al-sharq, maftuha 'ala shakl wadi yasubbu
fihi jami' widyan al-qarya.
Except for the east side, which is open in the form of a
valley into which all the village's valleys flow.
Min al-jibal al-muhita bil-qarya, bad'an min al-shamal al-
sharqi:
Among the mountains surrounding the village, starting from
the northeast:
Sirta Musange, Sirta Merxê, Sirta Saraqê, Sirta Qara Baba,
Sirta Xocê, Cirnê Hesen, Sirta Zil Xabûdrê.
Sirta Musange, Sirta Merxe, Sirta Saraqe, Sirta Qara Baba,
Sirta Xoce, Cirne Hesen, Sirta Zil Xabudre.
Wa hiya a'la nuqta min bayn al-jibal al-muhita bil-qarya wa
yablugh irtifa'uha 435 mitr fawq sath al-bahr.
It is the highest point among the mountains surrounding the
village, reaching a height of 435 meters above sea level.
Wa yujad ladayna akhiran Qaraca Evdek wa Kurta Hemê.
And finally we have Qaraca Evdek and Kurta Heme.
Amma bi-nisba lil-widyan, fahunaka al-kathir minha dakhil
al-qarya wa minha ma yuhitu biha.
As for the valleys, there are many inside the village and
some surrounding it.
Ba'd asma'iha: Hîrî Çaqalon, Gelî Pîlê, Gelî Elî Çawîş, Gelî
Hesenê Îbê, Gelî Pîrê.
Some of their names: Hiri Chaqalon, Geli Pile, Geli Ali
Chawish, Geli Hasane Ibe, Geli Pire.
Gelî Qişlê, Gelî Zûmû, Gelî Şêx Hesen, Gelî Ne'îskê, Gelî
Ebdê Xelîl, Gelî Newala Kêrgiya.
Geli Qishle, Geli Zumu, Geli Sheikh Hassan, Geli Naiske,
Geli Abdi Xelil, Geli Newale Kergia.
Kêrgî ayy al-aranib, wa summiyat bi-haza al-ism li-kathrat
al-aranib fiha.
"Kêrgî" means rabbits, and it was named this due to the
abundance of rabbits in it.
Ewwelkî va gundo...
Firstly, this village...
Berî vê teqrîben bi sê çarsed salî çêbûye, ne gundek qedîm
in yanê.
It was built approximately three or four hundred years ago,
so it's not an ancient village.
Di vî gundî da...
In this village...
Du bra, pismam, bra, keda hebûn hatin vî gundî da rûniştin.
Two brothers, cousins, brothers, whoever they were, came and
settled in this village.
Û bîrek li jor da kolan asê kirin...
And they dug and secured a well up there...
Hêjî kola ye, hewe gund, û ştî vexwarinê, mala, gund, bex...
It is still dug, that village, and drinking stuff, houses,
village, gardens...
Ekête me, hikê me bîrê, kevirê reş e...
Our terrain, our well digging, is black stone...
Me bîr va da wexta xetimî lê mişt bû.
We had a well there, when it got blocked it was full.
Paşê dewar û doliqê gundî pir bûn, pez pir bû, naxir pir
bû...
Then the villagers' livestock and animals increased, sheep
increased, cattle increased...
Vê derê şûna vê haretê gi bêder bûn.
This place, instead of this neighborhood, was all threshing
floors.
Cer cer hebûn, şixre hebûn, pale hebûn, di gunda...
There were threshing sledges, there were workers, there were
laborers, in the village...
Gi bêderê gund gi li vir da dinit bûn.
All the threshing floors of the village were piled up here.
Nêzîka şêst heftê bêderî, sed bêder li vî derî didanîn.
Near sixty or seventy threshing floors, a hundred threshing
floors were placed here.
Ê colbana, ê nîska, ê cehê, genim, gi li ba bêderê bûn, bin
vê darê bûn.
The vetches, the lentils, the barley, wheat, all were by the
threshing floor, under this tree.
Va bîra...
This well...
Gund şa'bî gund, pezî gund, li ser vê bîrê bûn.
The village populace, the village sheep, relied on this
well.
Av vexwarinê ji gund ji ser bîrê dibin.
They took drinking water for the village from the well.
Biker (?) ya pez danîn ber, mexel dikirin, pezê xwe
dqostandin, av didan...
They placed the troughs for sheep before it, bedded them
down, sheltered their sheep, gave them water...
Naxirê gund pir bû.
The village cattle herd was large.
Dihatin naxirê xwe gi li ber av didan.
They came and watered all their herds at it.
Dewar gi vedhesî heta şevengîne û heta nîvro xirjîgîne (?)
All the cattle rested until the evening milking and until
the noon rest.
Gi li ba bêderê bûn, bin vê darê bûn.
All were by the threshing floor, under this tree.
Va dara jî...
And this tree...
Bêra dibêjin me şitla Ebdî Ûsê ji Xelnêrê...
They say we [got] the seedling of Abdi Use from Xelnêrê...
Va dara şitlekî biçûk bû, çunkî Ebdî Ûsê anî hat...
This tree was a small seedling, because Abdi Use brought it
and came...
Go vaye li ekê vê bêrê biçînim, avê vê bîrê nêzîk e yanê.
He said let me plant it in the soil of this place, the water
of this well is near, that is.
Pênc metre, şeş metre teqrîben.
Five meters, six meters approximately.
Go ekey lê biçînim.
He said let me plant it.
Yanê emrê vê darê jî qedîm e, ji mêj e ev dar e.
So the age of this tree is also ancient, this tree is from
long ago.
Gund intîşar dibe, hinek gund li war bûn...
The village expands, some village houses were there...
Bêderê jî şûna bêderan, bûn xaniyê gundiya, cih nema yanê.
And the threshing floors, the place of threshing floors,
became villagers' houses, no space was left.
Va bîra jî...
And this well...
Em jêra dibêjin bîra Kolan.
We call it the Kolan well (The Dug Well).
Kolan.
Kolan (Dug).
Malê gund, 'eîlê me vêra dibên Çeqelî.
The village families, our clan, they call us Çeqelî.
Û kurmancê din hene dibêjin em Reşwan in.
And there are other Kurds who say we are Reşwan.
Kurmancê me, hinek hane kunye pir dikin, dibê esasê me
Reşwan in.
Our Kurds, some here use surnames a lot, say our basis is
Reşwan.
Asas.
Basis.
Paşê li vî derî wexta gund şên bû gotin Çeqelî.
Then in this place when the village flourished they called
it Çeqelî.
Me nav li xwe danî Çeqelî.
We named ourselves Çeqelî.
Dibê bîra Hecî, Hecî Şêxo.
They say the well of Haci, Haci Sheikho.
Bîra Hecî Şêxo.
Haci Sheikho's well.
Lê gund...
But the village...
Ama berî vê, bi çeqas sal... yanê bîra nû kolan...
But before this, by how many years... meaning the newly dug
well...
Hecî Şêxo kola.
Haci Sheikho dug it.
Nav lê nan bîra Hecî Şêxo yanê.
They named it Haci Sheikho's well, that is.
Welle heba me na dî kê kola...
Well, the other one [the old well], we didn't see who dug
it...
Ewa nêzîk e heba.
That one is near the other.
Ewa asar kun e, ewa di wexta hîn gund şên bûye hewa hatîye
kolan.
That is an ancient ruin, that was dug when the village was
still being settled.
Wexta hewa kolan e, gund şên bû, bîr tenê bûn.
When that was dug, the village was settled, the wells were
solitary.
Hewa tenê bû.
That one was the only one.
Paşê...
Then...
Ba'dî we dît sê malan e...
After seeing three households...
Go em navê xwe da bîrekê xwa erebî bikolin.
Said let us dig an Arab-style well for ourselves in our own
name.
Kolan, kolan, kolan, av derneket.
Dug, dug, dug, water didn't come out.
Dibê bûkeke vê malê hebû gotî yû ro li ridmê, li erdê me
bikolin.
They say there was a bride of this house, she said oh day,
dig in the rubble, in our ground.
Ez heqê wava didim.
I will pay their wages.
Go bîr kolan roke bû, du ro kolan av derket.
Said they dug the well for a day, dug for two days, water
came out.
Ê bîrê jor e. Nav lê nan bîra Hecî, Hecî Şêxo.
It's the upper well. They named it Haci, Haci Sheikho well.
Welle noka eşîr e.
Well now it is a tribe.
Eşîr li Cûqê hene.
There are tribespeople in Juqay.
Li Keferşîlê hene.
There are in Kafr Shila.
Em ne eşîr in yanê, gi yek in va sê gund no.
We are not [just] a tribe, we are all one, these three
villages.
Xalitî.
Mixed [intermarried].
Eşîr in yanê, em ne eşîr in.
We are a tribe, we are not a tribe.
Eşîra Reşwan in, Çeqelî ne yanê.
We are the Reşwan tribe, that is Çeqelî.
Ji mêj e.
It's ancient.
Qedîm in.
They are ancient.
Pir qedîm in.
Very ancient.
Atê jî xweş be qurban.
May you be well too, my dear.
Ser çava, ser seran, xêrhatin...
You are welcome, upon my head, welcome...
تسمى القرية أحياناً باسم قرية المغارات، وذلك لكثرة المغارات
فيها. يوجد فيها ما يقارب الخمسين مغارة، حيث تجد لكل بيت
مغارة أو أكثر.
The village is sometimes called the Village of Caves, due to
the abundance of caves in it. There are approximately fifty
caves in it, where you can find a cave or more for every
house.
منها داخل القرية ومنها حولها. من أهمها مغارات وادي قشلة،
وأيضا هناك بعض المغارات قد سميت باسم أصحابها أو لها أسماء
أخرى.
Some are inside the village and some are around it. Among
the most important are the caves of the Qishla Valley, and
there are also some caves that have been named after their
owners or have other names.
مثل مغارة كندي، مغارة قبشو، مغارة مطبخة، أو بأسماء ساكنيها.
كانت تستخدم هذه الكهوف كبيوت للسكن وللأغنام والماشية ولأعلاف
الماشية.
Such as Kinde Cave, Qabsho Cave, Matbakha Cave, or by the
names of their inhabitants. These caves were used as houses
for living, for sheep and livestock, and for livestock feed.
ولم يكن هناك أي بناء سابقاً للسكن.
And there were no buildings for housing previously.
Bi xêr hatin. Ez nîvanê Gundê Xalnêrê me, ser serî û ser
çavê me.
Welcome. I am a resident of the village of Xalnêrê
(Khilnara), you are most welcome (upon our head and eyes).
Xalnêrê, şikeftên wê jî meşhûr e. Zîraeta wê jî zeytûn, dar,
meşhûr e.
Xalnêrê, its caves are famous. Its agriculture is also
olives, trees, it is famous.
Karê cotkariyê dikirin, manê ziraet bûye, tizanî?
They used to do farming work, meaning it was agriculture,
you know?
Û niha, em di şikeftê da ne, ev der ma'ser bûye ba.
And now, we are in a cave, this place used to be an olive
press (Ma'sar).
Eva ma'sera zeytûna bû, ya malê Mihemedê Qûşû bû.
This was an olive press, it belonged to the family of
Muhammad Qushu.
Ev ma'sera kevin e. Ji sala hezar û neh sed û çilî da,
teqriben dişuxilî.
This is an old press. Since the year one thousand nine
hundred and forty, approximately, it was operating.
Yanî emrê xwe heyştê sal heye, emrê vê ma'serê.
Meaning its age is eighty years, the age of this press.
Ma'ser berê, alat tinebûn. Alat tinebûn, şede bûn, bi desta
bûn.
The press in the past, there were no machines. There were no
machines, there were beams, it was by hand.
Bi desta... û dizanin yanî ma'ser ji gundên dorme dihatin.
By hand... and they know, meaning, people came to the press
from the surrounding villages.
Ji Maratê dihatin, Keferşîlê dihatin, ji Cûqê dihatin.
They came from Marate, they came from Kafr Shil, they came
from Juqê.
Yanî ji gundên pir dihatin. Ma'ser kêm bûn yanî, alat
tinebûn.
Meaning they came from many villages. Presses were scarce
back then, there were no machines.
Dihatin li vir zeytûnên xwe dikirin zêt.
They came here and turned their olives into oil.
Li vir ciyê xwe, cî şede ye. Di vî derî da şede bû, li vir
kevir bû.
Here is its place, the place of the beam. In this spot was
the beam, here was the stone.
Kevir pê, ya dikir bi dewar bû, alat tinebû, motor tinebû.
The stone was used, they did it with livestock, there were
no machines, there were no motors.
Paşê, ba'dî wextkê, motor anîn pê avkirin.
Later, after some time, they brought a motor and set it up.
Gî bi desta bûn yanî. Li vir zêta xwe kom dikirin. Zêt kom
dikirin.
It was all by hand, basically. Here they would collect their
oil. They collected the oil.
Li vir zeytûnên xwe didînan. Û dê nîvanê hebû, metbex hebû.
Here they would place their olives. And there was a living
area, there was a kitchen.
Wek meqbezên noka, nefsî... yanî tesmîmê meqbezên noka ji
ma'serên berê birine.
Like the modern presses, the same... meaning the design of
the modern presses was taken from the old presses.
Yanî her tiştekî noka, ne ji cem xwe daholatiye, gî ji berê
da hat... yanî berê muhendîsê xwe hene.
Meaning every modern thing, did not come from nowhere, it
all came from the past... meaning the past had its own
engineers.
Ev şikeftina, nîzîka pêncî şikeftî li vir da hebûn.
These caves, there were close to fifty caves here.
Şikeft, yanî degonê berê feqîre bûn, sêfîl bûn, yanî
sêfîlbîn hebû yanî.
The caves, meaning the people of the past were poor, they
were destitute, meaning there was poverty.
Haya yek nekaniya xaniyekî ava bike, yanî xanî bigirta, xanî
bigirta nav dar.
Until one could not afford to build a house, meaning to
occupy a house, to occupy a house among the trees.
Gî şikefta bû, cîhê xwe, unî dibînin cîhê xwe yanî... cîhê
xwe li sekan e.
It was all caves, their place, as you can see their place...
their place for living.
Û her şikeftekî pixarê xwe heye.
And every cave has its own fireplace (vent).
Gêaa mûnetê dewar têra didînan, kayê têra didînan.
They placed the livestock feed inside, they placed the straw
inside.
Gêaa paxarê dexistin, gî şîvê xwe dikirin, nefesê hindir
têra derdiket.
They operated the fireplace, they cooked their dinner, the
breath/smoke from inside would go out.
Her şikeftkê yanî... ewe xwe hebûn yanî.
Every cave, meaning... had its own things.
Jiyan di şikefta da dibû berê. Emrê vî gundî nîzîka sê-çar
sed sal e.
Life used to happen in the caves in the past. The age of
this village is nearly three or four hundred years.
Sê-çar sed sal, yanî ode tinebûn, şikeft bûn.
Three or four hundred years, meaning there were no rooms,
they were caves.
Şivan dihatin, yanî pezê xwe dikirnê, mûneya xwe dikirnê.
Shepherds came, meaning they put their sheep in them, they
put their supplies in them.
Havînê hênik e û zivistanê germ in ev şikeftina.
In the summer they are cool and in the winter these caves
are warm.
Ez zanim... ê qaling e, yanî bin erdê da ye, gî di erdê da
ye behs bikim.
I know... it is thick (rock), meaning it is underground, it
is all within the ground, let me mention.
Ne wekî yopî ye, hazir, teneke, çûçik e... li ba rûye, der
e, ev ferq e.
It is not like the buildings, ready-made, tin, small...
exposed to the wind, outside, this is the difference.
Wele gund pir in gundê... gundê eşîrê me, ev ji ber eşîrê
Çaqalî, fexdek ji fexde Reşwan e tizanî.
By God, there are many villages... villages of our tribe,
this is from the Çaqalî tribe, a branch of the Reşwan tribe,
you know.
Û ji sê-çar sed sal da li ser vî erdî ne yanî.
And for three or four hundred years they have been on this
land.
Sê-çar sed sal da yanî emrek e yanî. Em Efrînî ne, em
Xalnêrî ne, em li ser vî erdî sê-çar sed sal da em li ser vî
erdî ne yanî.
Three or four hundred years, meaning it is a lifetime. We
are Afrinis, we are from Xalnêrê, we have been on this land
for three or four hundred years.
Gundê me pir in yanî. Deh û pênc gundê xwe eşîra hene yanî.
Our villages are many. The tribe has ten to fifteen
villages.
Dorme, ee dorme, jimara tê, Keferşîlê, Cûqê.
Surroundings, uh surroundings, Jimara comes (to mind), Kafr
Shil, Juqê.
Yanî hene yanî... hene Çaqalî li heyşt-deh gunda li Efrîn
hene yanî.
Meaning there are... there are Çaqalî in eight to ten
villages in Afrin.
Belê, Gundê Xalnêrê, yê ku bi şikeftên xwe navdar e, û heya
niha jî şikeftên xwe yên kevnar, wekî hûn dibînin, hene.
Yes, the village of Xalnêrê, which is famous for its caves,
and until now its ancient caves, as you can see, still
exist.
Ev gund, beriya gî, malbatên li vê derê ku hatina gund,
beriya gî bi dewarê xwe ve di şikeftan da xwe diparastin.
This village, before everything, the families here who came
to the village, before everything, they protected themselves
and their livestock in the caves.
Piştre jî ev gund ava kirin. Lê şikeftên xwe yên kevnar heya
niha hene.
Afterwards, they built this village. But their ancient caves
still exist to this day.
Û heya niha jî dewar û tiştê xwe dixine hindirê wir û di wir
da mazin dikin.
And until now, they put their livestock and things inside
there and raise them in there.
أما بالنسبة للزراعة، فزراعة الزيتون كانت متواجدة وذلك لوجود
أشجار يبلغ أعمارها مئات السنين في سرت خوجي.
As for agriculture, olive cultivation was present, due to
the presence of trees that are hundreds of years old in Sirt
Khoji.
وبدأت زراعتها بشكل رسمي منذ المئة وعشر عاماً. قبل الزيتون،
كان الأهالي يعتمدون على كروم العنب لمصدر معيشتهم الرئيسي.
Its cultivation officially began one hundred and ten years
ago. Before olives, the residents relied on vineyards as
their main source of livelihood.
وبالإضافة إلى زراعة الحبوب والأشجار المثمرة، وكانت تزرع في
الوديان كلاً من التين والمشمش والتفاح والفستق.
In addition to growing grains and fruit trees, and figs,
apricots, apples, and pistachios were planted in the
valleys.
أما بالنسبة للمياه، فكان مصدر حصولهم على المياه قديماً،
ينبوع في وادي تيزي.
As for water, their source of obtaining water in the past
was a spring in the Tezi Valley.
وعلى الوديان التي كانت تجري على مدار السنة لكثرة الأمطار.
وفيما بعد، قاموا بحفر بئر يدوي وهو بئر حاجي على اسم من بادر
بحفره، وهو الجد حاجي شيخو.
And from the valleys that used to flow all year round due to
the abundance of rain. Later, they dug a manual well, which
is the Hajji Well, named after the one who initiated its
digging, the grandfather Hajji Sheikho.
Alo û sena, ji war û ji Gundê Xalnêrê ra, wargê me ye, hatin
bi xêr û selamet, ser çava, xweş.
Hello and praise, from the homeland and the village of
Xalnêrê, it is our home, you are welcome in peace and
safety, upon our eyes (most welcome), pleasantly.
Gundê Xalnêrê miletekî Kurd e. Û wekî dibêjin ezel da li vî
gundî jiyana xwe dîtine.
The village of Xalnêrê is a Kurdish nation. And as they say,
since eternity they have found their life in this village.
Û di vê berê da, yanî ma'rûf bî, karê berê li timî... ber
wekî tê bê, ewê xwe, heyatiya xwe, bi rez bî, bi zeytûna bî.
And in this past, meaning it was known, the work of the past
always... before, as one says, their things, their life, was
with vineyards, with olives.
Û pez bî. Heyata gunda vî lownî wekî tê bê derbas dikirin.
And it was sheep. The life of the villages was passed in
this manner, as one says.
Û ortax, dinya jî hêdî hêdî pêş ket. Milet wekî daket bajêr,
nîçuyî Efrîn, nîçuyî Helebê.
And then, the world also slowly advanced. The people, as
they went down to the city, whether they went to Afrin,
whether they went to Aleppo.
Û teknolojiya jî hedî zêde bû wekî tê bê, însan alem tetewur
dibê teben.
And technology also slowly increased as one says, humans and
the world develop, naturally.
Û gundekî jî ber Efrîn da ye yanî. Heyatiya me, ekseriya xwe
gî li Efrîn derbas dibe teben, nefsel wext.
And it is a village adjacent to Afrin. Our life, the
majority of it passes in Afrin naturally, at the same time.
Sibe radibin, pênc deqe digihîjin şuxlê xwe, û nefsel wext
êvarê tên digihîjin mala xwe.
They wake up in the morning, in five minutes they reach
their work, and at the same time in the evening they come
and reach their home.
Heyatiya me wiha derbas dibe, elhemdulîlah ji Xwedê ra.
Our life passes like this, praise be to God.
Welehî eded sekanê Xalnêrê, ê haliyan mewcûd têda rûniştin e
wekî têda qim, def de sed malî heye yanî.
By God, the number of residents of Xalnêrê, those currently
present living in it, as I estimate, there are around one
hundred households.
Taniya jî nodî heta sedî heye.
Even up to ninety to a hundred (households) exist.
Û eded nesemê gund, du hezar û çara çi bî, axir îhsaiye çi
bî, teqriben pênc hezar, pênc hezar û hinek e.
And the number of people of the village, whatever it was in
2004, whatever the last census was, it is approximately five
thousand, five thousand and some.
Erê. Û belav bûn e milet, teben em bêjin gî li Efrînê jî ne
li Efrîn in. Yê derketiye Helebê, yê derketiye Şamê.
Yes. And the people have scattered, naturally, let's say
they are all in Afrin, they are not (all) in Afrin. Some
have gone to Aleppo, some have gone to Damascus.
Yê derketiye Ewropa, Lubnanê... Xalnêrê hane, gundekî kevin
û miletiyê xwe jî pir derketiye hane, nefsel wext.
Some have gone to Europe, Lebanon... Xalnêrê is like this,
an old village and its people have also emigrated a lot, at
the same time.
Em bi xwe pênc kîlometre em ji merkezê va nêzîk in, ji
Efrînê va.
We ourselves are five kilometers close to the center, to
Afrin.
Û dûrdorê me mesela...
And our surroundings for example...
Belê li mabeyna me û şêxê me... şimolî me cûq e.
Yes, between us and our sheikh... to our north is a valley.
Mabeyna me û Efrînê de çemek heye. Çemê Efrînê, cemekî pirr
şîl e.
There is a river between us and Afrin. The Afrin River, a
very wet river.
Ane em bang kin, na... deng naçe. Em gî dûrî Efrîn in.
If we shout, no... the voice doesn't reach. We are all far
from Afrin.
Û mesafetek hindik e mabeyna me û Efrînê de.
And there is a short distance between us and Afrin.
Ane em pê nehesin, em li gund jî rûniştine.
We don't even feel it, even while sitting in the village.
Meşwerek te hebe, îşekî te hebe, pênc deqe tu kaniya herî
Efrînê werî.
If you have an errand, if you have a job, in five minutes
you can go to Afrin and come back.
Gundekî nav... cihekî... wek tu xwe bidî çepê...
A village inside... a place... like if you turn to the
left...
Miletê me Xalnêrê...
Our people of Khalnere [village name]...
Em hatin li ber... Kela Merwan û Kela Merwan rûnişt.
We came before... the Castle of Marwan, and the Castle of
Marwan settled.
Û yerle bûn.
And they became locals [settled down].
Ha du darê... yeqintî bûn, destçet o...
Like two trees... they were certain, holding hands...
Destbirsî bûn e...
They were empty-handed [or hungry-handed]...
Halêm de yeqintî bûn.
In my time, they were certain [united].
Ev jî yeqintî bûn.
This too was certainty.
Kela me hat rûnişt.
Our castle came and settled.
Pê fikirî...
He thought about it...
Yeqintî kî krosî kî ji êr e.
A certainty, a mute one from here.
No te tehmûl kirin. Çiqas tehmûl kir...
Could not tolerate you. How much he tolerated...
Li taliyê sert e.
In the end, it is harsh.
Li taliyê teke teslîm bûn.
In the end, they surrendered alone.
Hatin yeqintî bûn.
They came and were certain.
Hat rûnişt.
came and sat down.
Kaniya 'el...
The spring of 'Al...
Hat rûnişt. Balê Xwedê dûr ko.
Came and sat. May God keep the disaster away.
Bi tenê ye.
He is alone.
Xutke... xew bû...
A nap... it was sleep...
Nav Xelîl lêkirin.
They named him Khalil.
Xelîl rûnişt di vî çawî da.
Khalil sat in this spring.
Her zerqê...
Every beam/glance...
Milet xapxap... tekbîr kir.
The people, in confusion... made a plan.
Bi xew cirehet çêkirin ji xwaro.
Through sleep, they created wounds from below.
Xew naskirin dan.
They gave recognition to sleep.
Hev jî gund kir. Hev jî milet kir.
He made this a village too. He made this a people too.
Hev qalek no, hev alema gî pêşiya me xweş e...
This isn't just talk, this whole world before us is good...
...û êjwara dem dikim.
...and I spend the evenings.
Mane bir vît çe nebe niyorim.
Meaning... [unintelligible/idiomatic expression]... I don't
know.
Em îş tarîxê radan dikin. Ne ji xwaro.
We explain the work of history. Not baselessly.
Em nikanin tarîxa giya hewadin.
We cannot contain the history of everything.
Tarîx pehn e, dirêj e, mezin e, dîrok e denê...
History is wide, long, big, it is history, you know...
Ne îşê me tenê ye.
It is not only our business.
Em jî perra derbas bûn.
We also passed by on the wing/edge.
Me giyo va dîroka dî...
We all saw this history...
Lakin me her kesî, çi sax bûn me heye...
But for all of us, whatever living ones we have...
Em bi vê cirehetê dijîn e.
We live with this wound/pain.
Bi vê saxbûna mezin bûn e.
We grew up with this living.
Bi vê hezkirine mezin bûn e.
We grew up with this love.
Tarîx kevn e. Xelas nabe.
History is old. It does not finish.
Hîç wext... em nikanin bibên.
At no time... can we say.
Lakin no em hê bixwazin, bela em tarîxa xwe miqyat bin.
But now if we still want, let us take care of our history.
Mila vir vît, di heyata me da çê nebin.
Let [bad things] not happen in our life.
Xêr, hewa tarîx e.
Good, this is history.
Tarîx jî kevirê ya pîwerim.
History is also the stone of the measurer [old man].
Na dem te bilîzim.
I won't give it to you, I will play.
Sûcê me, sûcê me ye.
Our fault, is our fault.
Ne sûcê me, ne sûcê me ye.
What isn't our fault, isn't our fault.
Em sûcê xelkê nakin daweya xwe.
We don't make the people's faults our claim.
Sûcê di heqê xelkê de cî nabin ji xwaro.
Faults regarding the people do not have a place from below
[baselessly].
Belê temaşevanên hêja, îrojî em gihiştin dawiya bernameya
xwe.
Yes dear viewers, today we have reached the end of our
program.
Ji gundê Xalnêrê, em ê xatir bixwazin.
From the village of Khalnere, we will say goodbye.
Li benda me bin, di beşek nû de, ji programa Gundên Me.
Wait for us, in a new episode, of the program Our Villages.
Bi xatirê we.
Goodbye.