Merheba hevalno, dîsa hûn bi xêr hatin vîdyokî xweş kîbar.
Hello friends, welcome again to a nice, elegant video.
Vîdyayê me jî, îca me rehlek me heye, rehleya me jî wele
mişwar dûr e.
Our video today, well we have a trip, and our trip is, well,
a long journey.
Ez û xoltîkê min in, kulfetê xoltîkê min e, û dêka min e
teb'en.
It is me and my aunt, my aunt's family, and my mother of
course.
Emê herin 'Abîdanê. Merin, Melwerhan e.
We are going to Abidan. We are going, it is the Werhan
family.
Emê bi xoltîka xwe re herin cem gundiyan, emê nîvandarê
gundiyan, mezra ye ne.
We will go with my aunt to the villagers, we will be the
villagers' guests, it is a farm, right.
Ka bimînin bila bibe vîdyokî xweş kîbar. Heta em derin
dighênin 'Abîdanê înşallah hûnê kêf bikin.
Stay tuned so it becomes a nice, elegant video. Until we go
and reach Abidan, God willing, you will enjoy it.
Miletê 'Abîdanê silavê me ji giyan re hene.
To the people of Abidan, our greetings to all of them.
Bimînin em herin nîvandarê wan bin. Malbeta li mezrayê cem
gundiyan.
Stay tuned, let us go be their guests. The family at the
farm with the villagers.
Û emê wera înşallah 'Abîdanê jî înşallah emê teswîr kin.
Bimînin, helqek xweş li gundê 'Abîdanê.
And we will, God willing, film Abidan for you as well. Stay
tuned, a nice episode in the village of Abidan.
Newa ye xoltîk?
Isn't that right, auntie?
Ee.
Yes.
Bay bay. Ka bimînin.
Bye bye. Stay tuned.
Erê hevalno, li vî derî jî em teb'en gihîştin mala xalê Elî,
em gihîştin cem gundê mezrayê.
Yes friends, at this place we have of course reached Uncle
Ali's house, we reached the village farm.
Teb'en gundê ewî jî... çi bû navî wî?
Of course, his village is also... what was its name?
'Abîdanê.
Abidan.
'Abîdanê jî, ma va nêzîk e, wa li gel hamber min e.
Abidan too, well it is close, it is right opposite me.
Em gihîştin cem xalo û bimînin lextanên xweş kîbar emê noka
wera derbas kin.
We reached uncle's place, and stay tuned for nice elegant
moments we will now pass on to you.
Înşallah ji vîdyayê me jî bi ecibînin. Ka bimînin.
God willing, you will like our video too. Stay tuned.
Selamun Aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleykum selam.
Merheba xalê Hecî.
Hello Uncle Hajj.
Tu bi xêr hatî.
You are welcome.
Tu çawayî baş î?
How are you, are you well?
Elhemdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Saxiya te xweş e?
Is your health good?
Elhemdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Em nîvandarê we ne îro ha.
We are your guests today, okay.
Ser seran û ser çavan.
You are very welcome.
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God keep you.
Ma mala xweş çêkirî li vî derî.
Wow, you've built a nice house here.
Wele, wele mar...
Well, well snakes...
Mar û nav mawaliyan maro, newa ye? Axê maran e.
Snakes and among the locals, snakes, right? It's the land of
snakes.
Gund nêzîk e, Paşêrek jî şaxol e.
The village is close, Pasherek is also operational.
Wele Hecî...
Well Hajj...
Şaxol e.
It is operational.
Newa ye? Êsnê maran jî hebe?
Right? Is there snake charming too?
Selamun Aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleykum selam.
Destê xwe sar wa, cemidî bigre şûnde.
His hand is cold, hold it cold then.
Xalê Elî.
Uncle Ali.
Tu bi xêr hatî.
You are welcome.
Noka hebîbê... hesê ferî min.
Now the beloved... the voice of my [unclear].
Tu çawa yî?
How are you?
Elhemdulillah, tu çawa yî?
Praise be to God, how are you?
Baş î, zarok çawa ne?
Are you well, how are the kids?
Wele Elhemdulillah.
Well, praise be to God.
Wele çima derengî vê hatine?
Well, why have you come so late?
Wele derengî? Noka me da rê.
Well, late? We just set off now.
Wele du saet in di rê de me.
Well, I have been on the road for two hours.
Tu çûyî xaka min?
Did you go to my land?
Elhemdulillah şixul da ye.
Praise be to God, work is happening.
Ez jî li... xaka te me.
I am also on... your land.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Êbî canim.
Oh my dear.
Tu rihet î?
Are you comfortable?
Elhemdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Dera hatiye wa de, ehlen we sehlen.
Since you have come here, welcome.
Cîranê hev bûn, digot ka bibe 'Abîdanê.
We were neighbors, saying let's go to Abidan.
Arê arê wele, em bîrê kirin, go hew...
Yes yes really, we missed [you], said...
Letîfe, weke cîranek me bî, hana xatirê mirov nizanîbû.
Latifa, like you were a neighbor of ours, you know, didn't
know the worth of a person.
Kut da de çi bime rûyê min, mi digot kalê kor e, tu ji min
haq nake, min mesxere pê dikir.
[Unclear], I used to say he is a blind old man, you don't
deserve me, I used to make fun of him.
Wele pir meraq dikir wara we bibîne.
Well, he was very curious to come and see you.
Ez kuda biçûma...
Wherever I would go...
Ez li rêkê biçûma...
If I went on the road...
Ez diçûm digot çarû makîna wa derbas bû, digot noka...
diçûm...
I would go, he would say the car passed like this, he would
say now... I was going...
Ji we hez dike, wele dilê wî ketiye we.
He loves you, really his heart has fallen for you.
Em jî ji wî hez dikin.
We love him too.
Wele em jî ji wî hez dikin, bi mesxere pê dikin.
Well, we love him too, we make fun of him.
Em kê çêkin qehwê.
We will make coffee.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Maşallah, awî dibên mesbehê gundiyan pir kûr e.
Mashallah, they say the villagers' pool is very deep.
Wele qicikê qicik e, kûr bû noka têkevinê.
Well, it is very small, if it was deep, they would enter it
now.
Wele xalo xweş çêkirî li vî derî.
Well, uncle made it nicely here.
Vî derî xetasa avê heye, noka av hebe, seke pê mesbeha xwe
xet şil dikin, şebabî gund tên teb'en xwe dikinê.
Here there is a water diving [system], now if there is
water, look they wet their pool line, the village youth come
of course and put themselves in it.
Ba'dî xelas kirin şûnda û vî avê jî berdidin nav milkê xwe.
After they finish, they release this water into their
property.
Maşallah wele teyîkê xwe rind şixulîne.
Mashallah, well they have worked their [unclear] well.
Nono wele mesref lê kirî.
No no, well expenses were made on it.
Wele...
Well...
Nono maşallah kîbar çêkirine.
No no, mashallah they made it elegantly.
Vîna pismamê min e.
This is my cousin.
Migo na pismamê min e.
I said no, it is my cousin.
Nono rinde.
No no, it is good.
Maşallah li vî gundî bigre şitlek xeyarê çû tê de.
Mashallah, take a cucumber seedling in this village, it went
in it.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Ewa sirinc e?
Is that a syringe/pump?
Kûr e?
Is it deep?
Fîlter e, ne?
It is a filter, right?
Fîlterê gundî jî dida ye fîlterê mesbehê.
The villager's filter is also there, the pool filter.
Ê mesbeh ne, binî pê pak dikin.
It is a pool, right, they clean the bottom with it.
Avê paqij, rojekê sê ro fîlter digerînin.
Clean water, once every three days they run the filter.
Ewa fîlter dikin.
They filter that.
Ew dikişînin.
They pull that.
Wele di necixînin kindir li vî derî di necixînin.
Well, they rescue, the ropes here rescue.
Eger teb da avê, teb di nava avê da yê.
If [one] jumps in the water, jumps inside the water.
Migo miletê 'Abîdanê tê xwe dikinê ne?
I said, do the people of Abidan put themselves in it?
Tên, tên.
They come, they come.
Tên, dûrçûn mi gundû derketin.
They come, [unclear].
Wele evî gundî Eimersûmo...
Well, this village of Eimersumo...
Erê erê gundî Omer e, Marso ye, şîtabî ye.
Yes yes, it is Omar's village, Marso, Shitabi.
Omer Ailkê?
Gundî Omer Begê lêkê me ye.
Omer Beg's village is next to us.
Omer Begê ne. Omer Axa û vî gundana Emersûma gotin vî derî.
Omer Beg, right. Omer Agha and these villages, Emersuma they
said here.
Gundî Heftêr e, nîvê gundî Efrîn...
The village of Hefter, half the village of Afrin...
Aîlî jî tên lê, bes...
Families come too, but...
Bê aîlî jî huciz dikin.
Without families they also reserve.
Bi çi huciz dikin, çiqasî ye roj?
How much do they reserve for, how much is a day?
Pêncî dolar.
Fifty dollars.
Koley e ne?
It is cheap, isn't it?
Ê tab pir kûr e, gerekê hesabê qicika jî kiribû.
Well sure it is very deep, they should have accounted for
the little ones too.
Noka ew nêzîk e, jiyê wi da nêzîk e.
Now that is close, [unclear] is close.
Her tivir da tê kûr dibe, vir digihê sê metra.
Every step it gets deeper, here it reaches three meters.
Bo sê metra?
Damn, three meters?
De.
Yes.
Mîtirek he?
Is there a meter?
No, ji tivir nêzîk du metro ne.
No, from the edge it is close to two meters.
Tab nêzîk du metro.
Sure, close to two meters.
Xwezke... Xwezke yekî...
I wish... I wish someone...
Me digot em yekî...
We said we...
Biçûkê mesela wa çêkiriba ji qicika ra.
If they had made a small one like that for the kids.
Emê ji qicika ra çêkin.
We will make one for the kids.
Wa noka çêkirî ne?
Is that made now?
Xwe li kûnê sarfayî da feke yek din.
[Unclear] open another one.
Em kanî da fekin, emê yekî ji qicika ra çêkin.
We will open the spring, we will make one for the kids.
Noka pîşê yolî ta teyîk çandine?
Now [unclear] planted a [unclear]?
Hava hekî zêde kûr e, vî derî sê metro ye.
This is a bit too deep, here it is three meters.
Heta vî derî metro nîvek e.
Up to here it is a meter and a half.
Emê yekî ji qicika ra çêkin.
We will make one for the kids.
Bin metrekê.
Under a meter.
Ji metrekê û bin da.
From a meter and under.
Aaa ma wane vî derna maro de.
Aaa well, these places are dangerous.
Em navê maro de, marê qicik.
We are in the name of snakes, small snakes.
No aîlat tên, derbas qicik vêra hene.
No, families come, pass, there are small ones with them.
Qicikê çûçik, lewzim xuçikek...
Small tiny ones, need a [unclear]...
Emê yekî xisûsî ji qicika ra başqa çêkin.
We will make a special separate one for the kids.
Kaniyê kêlekê vî derî cî ta bîston çantiye, dikane sar wazî
bike.
The spring on the side here, where you planted concrete, can
[unclear].
Emê vir çîkî zêde bikin.
We will increase this a bit.
Ta qicika ra çêke pir kîbar be.
If you make it for the kids, it will be very elegant.
Qicik kêf kin sêdme merî mezin kêf kirî newa ye?
Kids having fun is the reason adults have fun, right?
Esas wextê aîlat tê...
Actually when a family comes...
Qicik nabêra xwe çengî naha yek qicikê dike hemêza xwe...
The kid doesn't [unclear], takes the kid in his lap...
Tê kûr e.
It comes deep.
Kûr e du metro heta sê metro ye, didê ser mero.
It is deep, two meters to three meters, it goes over a man.
No, sê metro be, ox... qundere li badanê mero.
No, if it is three meters, oh... [unclear idiom].
Ji wî zêwiyê virda heta sê metro da.
From that angle to here up to three meters.
Ji wezêyê wê da heta sê metro da.
From that angle to there up to three meters.
Sê metro nîvek didê ser Mero.
Three and a half meters goes over a man.
Dê vira metrek nîvek e.
Here it is a meter and a half.
Nono rinde kîbar e.
No no, it is good, elegant.
Te serê xwe qomîş nekir?
Did you not duck your head?
Tu.
Who?
You.
Ez dirêj im lo.
I am tall, man.
Migo te serê xwe qomîş nekir.
I said you didn't duck your head.
Xwedê min ne teslîm biriye.
God hasn't taken my surrender yet.
Awa sadiqê kelbê... mesbeh.
This [unclear]... pool.
Ê mesbeh ne, binê pê pak dikin.
Yes, pool, they clean the bottom with it.
Wele xalo rind çêkirî wele.
Well, uncle made it well really.
Dîkor jî.
Decor too.
Ava solûn e ne?
This is a salon, isn't it?
Solûn e.
It is a salon.
Mekteb, mekteb.
School, school.
Ê cemaetê ye, nîvone.
It is for the congregation, a guest room.
Awa ode nîvone, ode rûniştinê ye.
This is the guest room, the sitting room.
Rind e.
It is good.
Wele kîbar çêkirî.
Well, he made it elegantly.
Saeta xweş. Qehwê gende, derî gende.
Good hour. Coffee [unclear], door [unclear].
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Awa oda...
This is the room of...
Awa oda... metbex.
This is the room... kitchen.
Awa oda, metbexa Amerîkî.
This room, American kitchen.
Metbex Amerîkî?
American kitchen?
Metbexa Amerîkî.
American kitchen.
Wele çavê min lê neket.
Well, my eye didn't fall on it (I didn't notice).
Herçî derbero diso dadikir ne?
Everyone [unclear] closes again right?
Metbex, metbex, emrîkî vekirî.
Kitchen, kitchen, American open.
Nat, divêra dadigrin, heçî vî derê.
Not, they close here, whatever this place.
Arê noka min li vê giçê dît.
Yes, now I saw it in this corner.
Seke dewaro danîne.
Look, they put walls.
Hama hebe sehaya vê giçê.
As long as there is the area of this corner.
Ev çi metbex e kîbar çêkirî.
What a kitchen, elegantly made.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Fera çi dikin dikin, î fera rijan...
Whatever they do, this [unclear] pouring...
Ne?
No?
Nono maşallah, galek nayê şixulandin.
No no mashallah, [unclear] is not worked.
Ê bê heqê mero ne, bi rijan, bi tiştî mûheta.
It is a man's right, with pouring, with [unclear] things.
Hem hem... seke li vî giçê.
All all... look at this corner.
Nono maşallah.
No no mashallah.
Mesref lê kirî.
Expenses were made on it.
Saet o giyo xweş.
Good health to everyone.
Zelam, zelam îş, kîbar î navê...
Man, man work, elegant [unclear].
Kes nikan heqê kesî bixwe taben.
No one can eat anyone's right of course.
Î mesela rok dide sê çar, heqê te kel te biftile.
This example giving a day three four, your right [unclear]
you turn.
Noka we da cema pir xweş e Efrîn.
Now the weather is very nice in Afrin.
Wade Efrîn pir xweş e, du amle içtîma'e bîn teb'en.
Here Afrin is very nice, two [unclear] meetings of course.
Ka wera em derbasî derve bin.
Come let's pass outside.
Ema pir xweş e, mentiqa Efrîn pir xweş e. Milet ji Ewropa va
tê, pêwendî dikin, merra tewasul dikin.
But it is very nice, the Afrin region is very nice. People
come from Europe, they contact, they communicate with us.
Kasek daxwaza wan heye, werin. Matorê Heleb, mator şaxûl e
teb’en.
Anyone who has a wish, come. It's an Aleppo motorcycle, the
motorcycle is working/active, naturally.
Du per, me'rînê me hatibûn. Dakevin matorê Heleb.
Two wings/fenders, our experienced ones had come. They ride
the Aleppo motorcycle.
Mu'ezzez, mikerrem, yanî pir qîmet. Gindî zanî, wellahî
mêrek sûywar xwar, go dêka min bi avê asansorê ji teyareyê
dianîn.
Honored, respected, meaning very valuable. The villager
knows, by God, a man rode it, he said, "Mom, via the
elevator of the plane they brought it down" [implying it
rides very smoothly].
Qîmet heye. No, ev warê mator o, qîmet heye xaseten wan
ecaneb ne. Siwah pir tên.
It has value. No, this matter of motorcycles, it has value,
especially since they are foreigners. Many tourists come.
Du jî mêrek merra gotin nexweş kirin. Sar mentîqê, haş
cixrafiya xwe hebin. Hana bikin, hana bikin.
Also, a man said some unpleasant things to us. About the
region, let them have their geography. Do this, do that.
Go kes qarmîş wa dibê, ma go na welle. Heqê xwedê dam, gundo
da, kes qarmîş me nabê, te'erûd...
He said, "Does anyone mess with you?" I said, "No, by God."
Let me give God his due, inside the villages, no one messes
with us, no harassment...
Belê bîdayê, erê, çîçikê ew hebin, yanî tedeyûqat hebin.
Yes, in the beginning, yes, there was a little bit of that,
meaning there were some strictures/pressures.
Bes migo bî sê çar meh ne, maşalla, yanî wede' miye bi miye
ye.
But I said, it's been three or four months, Mashallah,
meaning the situation is one hundred percent.
Pir mentîqe xweş e. Wikanin werin, bigerin, mentîqa Efrîn
pir şêrîn e, pir xweş e.
The region is very nice. They can come, travel around, the
Afrin region is very sweet, very nice.
Î qewmê xwe heye, î cinsiyê xwe heye, jî kanê werê.
Those who have their people, those who have their
citizenship/roots, can also come.
Matorê Heleb, wikanê dakevin, lê dakevin. Eê...
The Aleppo motorcycle, they can ride it, ride on it. Yeah...
Wekî dibê, win hatin cem bavê 'Ezê jî, ez ê zikê Mosis jî
badim.
As they say, since you came to Abu Aze's place, I will twist
Moses' stomach [joke/idiom].
Wek birî me kameraman. Erê, winê wê xelqê me, winê lê sêr
kin, ez ê daxim înşallah.
Like my cameraman brother. Yes, you are [watching] our
episode, you will watch it, I will upload it, God willing.
Erê. Saeta we xweş.
Yes. Have a good time.
Are, a niha li vî derkê jî, teb'en em li cem Xalê Elî bûn,
em nîvanê gundê Mezre'e ne.
Yes, right now at this spot, naturally we were with Uncle
Ali, we are in the middle of Mezra'a (Farm) village.
Magû em gihiştine nîzîkê 'Ebîdanê. Teb'en cîyê xwe jî...
I said we have arrived near Abidan. Naturally, its location
too...
Mobeyna Nebî Hûrî û 'Ebîdanê daye. Mesbeh e.
It is between Nabi Huri and Abidan. It is a resort/picnic
area.
Ş... miletê vê gundî, gundê dûr e, tên cem gundê... mesbeh a
xwe dikin, avê...
Th... the people of this village, distant villages, come to
the village... they have their picnics, the water...
Kirî dikin, 'aylê tên.
They rent it, families come.
Yanî, mêrek xora îstîfade jî dibîne. Ew jî wekî şixûlekî ye.
Meaning, a man sees some benefit/profit for himself. That is
also like a job.
Saeta gundî jî xweş. Magû em çend lexta nav gundê 'Ebîdanê
ware çêkin.
The villager having a good time too. I said let's make a few
shots inside the village of Abidan.
Gundê 'Ebîdanê jî gundekî pir xweş e, kîbar e.
Abidan village is also a very nice village, it is
noble/neat.
Winê naha merra bin, em ê lextanê xweş nav vê gundî çêkin.
Silavê me jî ji miletê gundê 'Ebîdanê re hene.
You stay with us now, we will make nice shots inside this
village. Our greetings also go to the people of Abidan
village.
Çi nîzîk, çi dûr, silavê me ji giya re hene.
Whether near, whether far, our greetings go to everyone.
Çavê giya maç dikim.
I kiss everyone's eyes.
Arê hevalno, teb'en Xalê Elî li cem me ye, çavê gund e, maş
dikim. Arê.
Yes friends, naturally Uncle Ali is with us, he is the eye
[prominent figure] of the village, I kiss [his eyes]. Yes.
Xwedê 'emrekî dirêj bide. Xalê Elî, gundê 'Ebîdanê çiqas
hum... hewş e? Hewş.
May God give him a long life. Uncle Ali, how many hum...
courtyards [houses] is Abidan village? Courtyards.
Gundê 'Ebîdanê 125 mal in.
Abidan village is 125 houses.
125 mal?
125 houses?
Jê teqrîben sê-çar mal hîna nehatine. Wekî din milet temamî
fitiliye.
Of those, approximately three or four houses haven't come
[returned] yet. Otherwise, the people have completely
returned.
Miletê 'Ebîdanê gi mevcut e?
The people of Abidan are all present?
Are, miletê 'Ebîdanê gişt hatine.
Yes, the people of Abidan have all come.
Şikilî ye gi, her kes mala xwe daye, her kes hewşa xwe daye.
It is in good shape, everyone is in their own home, everyone
is in their own courtyard.
Welle birov. E bes sê-çar mal bat tenê ne?
By God, bravo. So only three or four families were remaining
[away]?
Bes... bes sê-çar mal bat nehatine. Wekî din milet tevdab
fitiliye, mala xwe, her kes.
Only... only three or four families haven't come. Otherwise,
the people have all returned, to their homes, everyone.
Maşalla. Xalo gundê 'Ebîdanê bi xêr nav lê kirin gundê
'Ebîdanê?
Mashallah. Uncle, why did they name the village 'Abidan'
[Worshippers]?
Gundê 'Ebîdanê livir jêr, kaniyek a sar heye, kaniya
'Ebîdanê. L'ser navê kaniya 'Ebîdanê, li ber tiliya
'Ebîdanê, nav lê dan gundê 'Ebîdanê.
Abidan village, down here, there is a cold spring, the
Spring of Abidan. Based on the name of the Spring of Abidan,
near the Abidan hill/finger, they named it Abidan village.
Gundê 'Ebîdanê.
Abidan village.
Are.
Yes.
Bi çi tê naskirin? Xalo, meselen, gundê 'Ebîdanê, meselen bi
çi tê naskirin?
What is it known for? Uncle, for example, Abidan village,
for example, what is it known for?
Tebî'eta gund e, bi seqafet e, bi çi...?
The nature of the village, the culture, for what...?
Avê xwe pir e.
Its water is plentiful.
Avê xwe pir e?
Its water is plentiful?
Are. Avê xwe pir e. Her malekê bîrek di bîr xwe hene. Û noka
jî halîyyan, gi bîr nav zeytûna dikulin. Her kes zeytûnê xwe
av didin. Tebî'et...
Yes. Its water is plentiful. Every house has a well inside.
And now currently, everyone is digging wells among the
olives. Everyone irrigates their olives. Nature...
Maşalla, ez zanim noka hatim, av maşalla hana çadike livir
derê hember me.
Mashallah, I know, I just came now, the water, Mashallah, is
doing like this [flowing strongly] over here opposite us.
Are, ew bîra 'Ecerkûl e. Tê zeytûna av didin. Milet tevdab
zeytûna av didin.
Yes, that is the Ajar-kul well. They irrigate the olives.
The people are all irrigating the olives.
Are hevalno, berî vê jî, bira kinê ma, xwahkênê ma, ji ma
xwestin gundê 'Ebîdanê. Teb'en em nikanî botana me teswîr
kira.
Yes friends, before this too, our brothers, our sisters,
asked us for Abidan village. Naturally, we couldn't film for
you [earlier].
Le'nî, ewda' ne sere hev da bî, û rêk jî ji me va pir dûr
bî.
Because, the situation wasn't settled, and the road was very
far for us.
Maşalla. Rêkê xwe jî şaxûl ne.
Mashallah. Its roads are also active.
Are, ji ma xwestin, em nikanî botana. Le'nî ji camê gind,
heta vî derê, yanî hewa jî sînor e. Sînorê Tirko ye.
Yes, they asked us, we couldn't for you. Because from the
mosque of the village, up to here, meaning the air/area is
the border. It is the Turkish border.
Pir dûr e ji me va.
It is very far from us.
E hûrû jî, rêka me livir ket. Û ewda' jî xweş bîne. Ana,
marov serbest digere. Rind e.
So today, our path fell here. And the situation has become
good. Now, a person travels freely. It is good.
Milet gi hatî malê... malê xwe, nav milkê xwe, nav mewalê
xwe.
The people have all come to the house... their houses, into
their property, among their livestock.
Saeta giya xweş. Xwedê ji giya razî be.
Everyone have a good time. May God be pleased with everyone.
Av, av hebe, rind e.
Water, if there is water, it's good.
Xalo, Koze jî ji gundî va diyar e ne?
Uncle, Koze is also visible from the village, right?
Koze di dîbîn, naha yak xera kirin, yakê maye.
You see Koze, now they destroyed one [part/structure], one
remains.
Eywa.
I see.
Koze, berê çi dikiribû? Koze.
Koze, what was it doing before? Koze.
Koze muselxane.
Koze was an armory/post.
Koze bana çêkiribû? Cîranê kî... ma... Koze naha ji vir...
Had they built Koze? A neighbor who... us... Koze now from
here...
Koze teslîm kiriyan. Heta hewa li firriyê teslîm kiriyan.
They surrendered Koze. Up to the air [airport/high point] at
the flight, they surrendered it.
Koze silaf ê gundiya bî?
Koze was [trouble/burden] for the villagers?
Silaf ê gundiya bî. Noka em bi faxrî teslîm kiriyan.
It was for the villagers. Now we proudly surrendered it.
Afaxrî jê bir kirîye.
Proudly took it away.
Hew... hew... hew anam berê.
Ye... ye... yes just like before.
Saeta gundiya xweş, rind e.
The villagers having a good time, it's good.
Welle rind e. Cîyê Koze hebe di vî gundî da rind e.
By God it's good. If the place of Koze is in this village,
it's good.
Rind e.
It's good.
Bes zilme... zilmetiya l'serî avda nekin, zilmet ne rind e.
But oppress... they shouldn't do oppression on top of this,
oppression is not good.
Tiştê rind tim rind e. Tiştê xirab jî, tim bi xirabî ye va
dare.
A good thing is always good. And a bad thing, is always with
badness in it.
Marov 'omtom ser avda da neke, dar neke. Şûra marov yo qabda
nebîne.
A person shouldn't block the water [metaphor], shouldn't
block. One shouldn't look at one's neighbor's wall
[privacy].
Yawaş yawaş darê gir rind dibin. Eh rehet bibe.
Slowly, slowly the big trees become good. Uh, let it be
comfortable.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Xalo camî jî gundî wa da heye ne?
Uncle, is there a mosque in your village too?
Evana camî.
This here is the mosque.
Camî berê te nebî?
Was the mosque not there before you?
Na, berê te nebû.
No, it wasn't there before.
Mekteb heye gundî wedo?
Is there a school in your village?
Mekteb didu hene.
There are two schools.
Maşalla. Heta çendê mekteb xalo?
Mashallah. Up to what [grade] is the school, uncle?
Heta nehê heye.
There is up to ninth [grade].
Ji nehê şûnda darink...?
After ninth, where do they go...?
Ji nehê şûnda diçin Qestelê.
After ninth they go to Qastal.
Qestelê?
Qastal?
Qestel ji vir va dûr e.
Qastal is far from here.
Qestel haft kîlometre teqrîben dûr e.
Qastal is approximately seven kilometers far.
Are hevalno, vî gundê me Efrîn, gundê me Kurmanc o, pir ne.
Bes em dibên sê sed û şêşat gund, lê em nizanin... xalo
gundî wa tab'ê kîdarê ye?
Yes friends, these villages of ours in Afrin, our Kurmanj
villages, are many. But we say three hundred and sixty
villages, but we don't know... Uncle, your village belongs
to where?
Tab'ê Bilbilê ye.
It belongs to Bilbil.
Tab'ê Bilbilê ne?
It belongs to Bilbil, right?
Are.
Yes.
Tab'ê Bilbilê. Ji Bilbilê va dûr e çend kîlometre heye?
It belongs to Bilbil. How many kilometers far is it from
Bilbil?
Deh-pênc kîlometre Bilbil xerbî me ye.
Ten-five kilometers, Bilbil is to our west.
Are, deh pênc kîlometre ji Bilbilê va dûr e. Magû tab'ê
nahiya Bilbilê.
Yes, it is ten-five kilometers far from Bilbil. I said it
belongs to Bilbil district.
Vir jî mala Xalê Hecî ye. Em hatine mala gund jî. Emê niha
lextanê xweş kîbar amê hilkşîn jûr, amê wara teswîr kin.
Here is Uncle Haji's house. We came to the village house
too. We will now take nice, noble shots, we will climb up,
we will film for you.
Vê gundî. Tebî'eta vê gundî jî pir xweş e. Malbat jî ge
hene. Yanî 'aylê vê gundî ge mevcûd ne.
[Of] this village. The nature of this village is also very
nice. There are many families too. Meaning the families of
this village are all present.
Xalo gundê wa bi kijan 'eylê tê naskirin? Yanî 'eylê silaf
hatî esasî?
Uncle, by which clan is your village known? Meaning the clan
that came originally?
'Eyla... divir da 'eyla pir ne. 'Eyla Mele Kûtê heye.
'Eyla...
The clan... in here the clans are many. There is the Mele
Kute clan. The clan...
Esasî ya hatî gund?
The original one that came to the village?
'Eyla me ra dibên 'eyla Mele 'Urraş. Em jî gundê 'Eşûnê û
gundê Karrê hatine vir.
Our clan is called the Mele Urrash clan. We also came here
from Ashun village and Karre village.
Ewa.
I see.
'Eyla esasî berê livir a, Qasimler a, Şêxûrzê hatine vî
derê.
The original clan here before, the Qasimlers, they came here
from Sheikhurze.
Û 'eyla Mele Kûtê heye. 'Eyla Mele Xayû heye.
And there is the Mele Kute clan. The Mele Xayu clan.
Maşalla. Silavê me ji vê 'eylanê giya re hene. Miletê vê
gundî, silavê me ji giya re hene. Çûçik mezin.
Mashallah. Our greetings to all these clans. The people of
this village, our greetings to everyone. Small and big.
Maşalla. Waay.
Mashallah. Wow.
Heta sê qatî ye.
It is up to three floors.
Welle av... av... av livir jî heye.
By God water... water... water is here too.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Merheba ji te re. Xwezîk, çû ye?
Hello to you. Auntie, how are you?
Maşalla. Tê bê ava we herimî ye? Xêr e?
Mashallah. You say your water is forbidden? Is it good?
[Likely a joke about the water being exclusively good or
plentiful].
Are hevalno, her... her hewşekê vî gundî...
Yes friends, every... every courtyard in this village...
Bîrê avê di malê da heye. Ne'met e, ev jî ne'met e.
Has a water well inside the house. It's a blessing, this is
also a blessing.
Xêr û bêr e.
It is bounty and abundance.
Are. Le'nî îsal bi şekl 'am cafaf çêbî, cafaf jî çêbî, av,
avê... avê cem milet pir kêm bî ye.
Yes. Because this year generally a drought happened, a
drought happened, water, water... water with the people was
very scarce.
Ema gundê 'Ebîdanê, em ketin her malekê, bîrek di malê da
heye.
But Abidan village, [in] every house we entered, there is a
well in the house.
Maşalla, xaltîkê jî viro bîstanê xwe çandî. Saeta gundî
xweş.
Mashallah, the auntie has also planted her garden here. The
villager having a good time.
Şta av hebe, seke teyîkê noka diçinin, bîstanê noka diçinin.
Look if there is water, look they are picking the vegetables
now, picking the garden now.
Jine jî mûlûxiyê hez dikin.
Women also love molokhia [Jute mallow].
Nase d'mûlûxiyê, ez ê nav mûlûxiyê da meho.
Look at the molokhia, I will... inside the molokhia...
Maşalla, bi bîrê jî av didin, taze ye.
Mashallah, they irrigate with the well too, it is fresh.
Are welle. Ah, no jin li me sêr dikin, ot bê ooo, me re
buxarê mûlûxiyê.
Yes by God. Ah, now women watch us, they'll say, "Ooo, give
us the steam/smell of molokhia."
Le? Mûlûxiyê 'enkûr o, û av didin, pir xweş e.
What? The molokhia is [like] grapes [abundant], and they
irrigate it, it's very nice.
Ooo, bacan çandine, her enw'akî sê xet çar xet xwa çandine.
Ooo, they planted eggplants, every type they planted three
lines, four lines for themselves.
Xalo jî dibê ev gundê Heftêr e hember min, havalî min nîzîk
bike.
Uncle also says this is Haftar village opposite me, my
friend bring it close [zoom in].
Miş xalo pirs kir, ez îstîxrab mam, migo hewa kîdar e? Go
gundê Heftêr e. Seke mobeyna gund û vir va kîlometrek tine.
I asked uncle, I was surprised, I said where is that? He
said it is Haftar village. Look, between the village and
here there isn't [even] a kilometer.
Berî vê jî, a hatim gundê Awe...
Before this too, I came to Awe village...
Gundê Zarê holeka hember me ye.
Zare village is right there opposite us.
Berî vê hatim Zarê, min Zarê kişand.
Before this I came to Zare, I filmed Zare.
Are. Ev jî gundê Heftêr e hember ma.
Yes. And this is Haftar village opposite us.
Xalo ew gundê hûyda kîdarê ye?
Uncle, that village over there, where is it?
Gundê Jare.
Jare village.
Ha ew gundê jî gundê Jare... Jare, na?
Ha, that village is also Jare village... Jare, right?
Gundê Jare.
Jare village.
Gundê Jare hember me ye.
Jare village is opposite us.
Teb'en gi nahiye... tebî'a nahiya Bilbilê ne?
Naturally all district... nature of Bilbil district, right?
Gişt, tebî'a nahiya Bilbilê ne.
All, are the nature of Bilbil district.
Are. Ew di he... deh-pênc kîlometre, deh-çar kîlo...
Yes. That is te... ten-five kilometers, ten-four kilo...
Are, gundê Heftêr.
Yes, Haftar village.
Xalo gundê Heftêr te go çend mal in?
Uncle, Haftar village, you said how many houses are they?
Gundê Heftêr 55 mal in.
Haftar village is 55 houses.
Nîzîk...
Close...
Xalo gundê Heftêr te go çend mal in?
Uncle, Haftar village, you said how many houses are they?
Gundê Heftêr 55 mal in.
Haftar village is 55 houses.
55 mal.
55 houses.
Avê wir jî wekî cemo heye?
Is the water there also like here [at your place]?
Avê wir jî, wekî me heye bes avê 'Ebîdanê kêmtir e. Wekî
heftê... bes av li Şêxûrzê tina ye.
The water there is also like ours, but Abidan's water is
less [or slightly different context]. Like Hafta... but
there is no water in Sheikhurze.
Şêxûrzê kêm e, na?
Sheikhurze is scarce, right?
Are.
Yes.
Dikunda gundê Heftêr de hene?
Are there shops in Haftar village?
Welle tina ne.
By God there aren't.
Dikan tina ne? Tên cem wa dikanê darê divin, na?
No shops? They come to you for the shops, right?
Tên 'Ebîdanê.
They come to Abidan.
Rind e, nîzîk e, hema meş e lo. Kefrînek bavê pêkî ne?
Good, it's close, just a walk. Throw a stone and it hits it,
right?
Em bavînê me û gundê Heftêr wekî gundkî ştî hevdû tenê,
marov hekî erre gîştî hevdû.
Us throwing [a stone] between us and Haftar village is like
one village, something like that, one can walk to each
other.
No, no, maşalla.
No, no, Mashallah.
Na, na, rê vekêş... rêkê seftêr o jî mal gîştine hevdû.
No, no, the road pull... the asphalt road, the houses have
reached each other.
No, no, rind e, maşalla.
No, no, it's good, Mashallah.
Ko, were hevalî min, were hemman jûr.
So, come my friend, come up to the bath/terrace.
Derence pir xweş e, şuxul jêr.
The stairs are very nice, bottom work.
Are. Hîm meta...
Yes. Even meta...
Maşalla, seke me hatime hedîka xwe.
Mashallah, look I came to my limit/slowly.
Çi menzer ne.
What views.
Welle...
By God...
Xalo, tê bê wana vî hewşê jî kevnar e, kevrê gund e?
Uncle, you say this courtyard is also ancient, stones of the
village?
Are kevnar e, hewş o... are.
Yes it is ancient, the courtyard... yes.
Emrê gundê 'Ebîdanê te zanî çiqas sal heye?
Do you know how many years old Abidan village is?
Teqbînc e.
Approximately.
Welle dibên 250 sal.
By God they say 250 years.
Bes.
Enough.
Em zanin lê esas em zanin...
We know but basically we know...
Em zanin dabeş û pêncî sal em zanin dibê Ebidanê...
We know fifty-five years we know, saying Abidan...
Bes tu wê rê nizanî.
But you don't know that road.
Na dabeş û pêncî salî em zanin dibê Ebidanê bere... malek du
mal li Şêxurzê li vir bûn û mal... yavaş yavaş pir bûn.
No, fifty-five years we know, saying Abidan used to be...
one or two houses were here in Shexurz and houses... slowly
increased.
Aîla her zêde dibin.
Families keep increasing.
Begim.. xencî wan jî hebin... meriv nizane.
Maybe.. besides them there are others too... one doesn't
know.
Eyo em wanekî zanin, lakin gundî kevin li ber til hebu.
Yes we know like that, but the old village was by the hill.
Ber til.
By the hill.
Ber tilî Ebidanê gundî mezin... gundî berê, gundî kevin.
By the hill of Abidan, the big village... the former
village, the old village.
Eyo.
Yes.
Paşê gund hatî vî alî yê şê...
Then the village came to this side of She...
Ka emê biçin jor jî.
Let's go up too.
Ha rêka darê Bilbilê.
Ah, the road to Bilbile.
Darê Bilbilê.
To Bilbile.
Bes dûr e darê Bilbilê. Xalo diyar bûn aven nîzik e viderê.
Yes.
But it's far to Bilbile. Uncle, they were visible, look it's
close here.
Mabeyna me çar kîlometre ne.
Between us is four kilometers.
Çar kîlometre ha? Ez zanim xuyate diyar e.
Four kilometers huh? I know it appears visible.
Erê.
Yes.
Şar'e divere ji darê jêr, na xalo?
The street goes down from the tree below, no uncle?
Are, divere heta tijî.
Yes, it goes until the end.
Wela viley muwa'ir divere.
By God, the winding road goes.
Mal mal diyar e derxe.
House by house is visible outside.
Miletiyê gundê Ebidanê li gundê xwe seyr kin.
People of Abidan village, watch your village.
Wele berê vê ji me dixwastin, ne ji me va berda dûr e, gelê
ruh di de...
By God, they asked for this from us before, not from us
[but] allowed it's far, lots of soul in it...
Tim min digot temê hûr werin sibe werin...
I always said come a bit later, come tomorrow...
Bû ro mecal ket me... Destê Xalo bigir werin.
Today the opportunity fell to us... Hold Uncle's hand, come.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Xalo voyî hember me xuya te çi ye? Ewa yê bilind ana?
Uncle, the one opposite us that is visible, what is it? That
high one there?
Ewa me'emelê çîmente ye.
That is the cement factory.
Me'emelê çîmente ye? Tab'ê kîderê ye ewa?
Cement factory? Where does that belong to?
Ê Tirk e, tab'ê Kilis e.
It's Turkish, belongs to Kilis.
Tab'ê Kilis e?
Belongs to Kilis?
Ha. A vî li milê vira lê bigir.
Yes.
Aha. Take this one on this side.
Ewa me'emelê çîmente ye, dibê me'emelê çîmente ye, tab'ê
Kilis e. Kilis, migil hember xuya te.
That is the cement factory, he says it's a cement factory,
belonging to Kilis. Kilis, look opposite it is visible.
Xalo ew gundê hember kîderê ye lê? We viley mile bigir.
Uncle, what is that village opposite? By God take that side.
Ewam Marsa we ye.
That is our Marsa.
Erê.
Marsa?
Yes.
Balo Marsa ber têlê da ye.
Man, Marsa is by the wire/border.
Erê lê.
Yes man.
Wele dûr e.
By God, it's far.
E, yek Marsa zimê bixwaze ezê kî zane bim warim.
Uh, if someone from Marsa asks me, who knows if I can go.
Bibîne gund bu... Têlê va teqrîben sê sed metre.
See the village was... from the wire it's roughly three
hundred meters.
Ha. Xalo rêka Marsa dikeve deran?
Aha. Uncle, does the road to Marsa fall there?
Şîltahtê ra tê.
It comes via Shiltaht.
Ti rora Dêrsuwanê paşê were?
You go via Dersuwan then come?
Erê. Şîltahtê ra were.
Yes. Come via Shiltaht.
Ma'ne rûna rêka me virket, em zanibin gunda ji me bixwazin.
Meaning look, our road fell here, so we know if the villages
ask us.
Erê, Şîltahtê ra tê.
Yes, it comes via Shiltaht.
Ev gundê hember me, e Tirk e, lê me?
This village opposite us, is it Turkish, or us?
Avoye gundê Kurd e.
That one is a Kurdish village.
Av gundê Kurd e?
That is a Kurdish village?
Gundê Kurd ji ber têlê ve.
Yes.
A Kurdish village from across the wire/border.
Gundê Kurd ji ber têlê ve. Ewa mala Reşkelê.
Kurdish village across the wire. That is House of Rashkele.
A, mala Reşkelê.
Ah, House of Rashkele.
Ewa mala Izrî ye, vî jûrim.
That is House of Izri, this upper one.
Êwa.
Okay.
Wele xalo ve gundiyana diyar ber o derê.
By God uncle, these villages appear in front there.
Ê, ê, her du gund ber o derê.
Yes, yes, both villages in front there.
Ewa kîderê ye lê?
Where is that one?
Ewa mala Reşkelê ye.
That is House of Rashkele.
Gundê Reşkelê ye.
Village of Rashkele.
E tab'ê Kurd e da.
It belongs to Kurds then.
Gundê Reşkelê tab'ê gundê Kurd e.
Village of Rashkele belongs to Kurdish village.
Erê, û gundê Izrî tab'ê gundê Kurd e.
Yes, and Village of Izri belongs to Kurdish village.
U lewê gundê hana di kûkê çiya da?
And in that village there in the peak of the mountain?
Ewa Moxirjix e.
That is Moxirjix.
Moxirjix e?
Moxirjix?
Ewa Tirk e erê.
That is Turkish, yes.
Ewa gundê t... Tirka ye.
That is a village of T... Turks.
Ewe Tirka ye, erê.
That's Turks, yes.
Ê ne yê li me ye?
So not ours?
No.
Vola nîzîk in ser hev o.
By God they are close on top of each other.
Maşalla avolî wadiyê tebîetê gund, maşalla, maşalla.
Mashallah look at the valley of the nature of the village,
mashallah, mashallah.
Teb'en hatina nîvandara cam xalo, me go em hono destê lextê
nov gund ji wara bikşînim mila dilî milet çîçke şa be.
Of course, the coming of the viewers to Uncle, we said let
us film a bit inside the village for you so the heart of the
people becomes a little happy.
Tiştê em kanin emê bikin.
What we can do, we will do.
Işte... me da'em kin, me pêş xin... emê hîn tiştê xweş kibar
wara darxin.
So... support us, push us forward... we will bring out more
beautiful nice things for you.
Erê.
Yes.
Barê me pir nekin... barê me pir nekin tişt wara teswîr kira
em 'om biçûna dera.
Don't make our load heavy... don't make our load heavy, [if]
we filmed things for you we would go everywhere.
Bes... jor û şûnda... jor û şûnda... weke xwast em kanin
harin.
But... up and back... up and back... as requested we can go.
Qorta wekî dibê hurriye kamil bi me ra ye, em kanin gi dera
wara teswîr kin.
If, as they say, complete freedom is with us, we can film
everywhere for you.
Du mêrek me ra dan kir, e nuh gu kas xurmiş wa dibê, kas
xurmiş wa nabe, yanê gotina xweş me ra dan kir, se'eta wî ji
xweş.
Two men communicated with us, now saying someone gets angry,
someone doesn't get angry, meaning they spoke nice words to
us, bless their time.
E... qorta wekî dibê izin kamil me ra ye, kîdo bî em herin.
Uh... if, as they say, full permission is with us, wherever
it is we go.
Ê me jî em wekî e'lamkî ne, em suretkî xweş digrin miletî
xwe.
So we too, we are like media, we take a beautiful picture
for our people.
Em tiştê xerab nakin, em tiştê... siyasî û didîn... em da
nakin.
We don't do bad things, we don't do... political and
religious things... we don't do that.
Tebîet, tiştê xweş em kêfa we kin.
Nature, beautiful things, we entertain you.
Ev mala wekî dar nakevin, wîne qusûrê ef bikin ho.
Those houses that don't appear in the trees, excuse the
shortcomings, okay.
Yanî em di şar'e ra daren.
Meaning we go via the street.
Cêre xalo dibê.
Uncle says go up.
Xalo bazar cem wa çê dibin? Bazar?
Uncle, do markets happen with you? Market?
Na, Bilbilê çê dibe.
No, it happens in Bilbile.
Bazar Bilbilê çê dibe ne?
Market happens in Bilbile right?
Erê.
Yes.
Ecêb? Em nêzîkî Bilbilê ye bes e şmêş da çû me. Vê çaxê me
pir ne kani bisevrînin da.
Strange? We are close to Bilbile but I went from there too.
That time we couldn't film much.
Avo cihê Şêxurz e.
That is the place of Sheikhurz.
Cihê Şêxurz e.
Place of Sheikhurz.
Wele çqkî dexm e.
By God it's a huge place.
Xûn pirr e, qelebalix e.
People are many, it's crowded.
Xalo avê şîrketê jî cem wa heye? Avê şîrketê?
Uncle do you have company water too? Company water?
Wele... hulyan tinne ye.
By God... currently there isn't.
Cem wa avê şîrketê tinne ye?
You don't have company water?
Na, hulyan... teqrîben ji deha salê va tinne ye.
No, currently... roughly for ten years there isn't.
Ê xezan heye yê bra gundî heftê...
So there is a tank for village of seven...
Erê berê evê şîrketê çêkir lê nebî hûrî de hat.
Yes before this company made it but... [unclear] came.
U şîrket ji mêş xerab bî.
And the company network broke from us.
Ne a pirr darim gundo, munazzama vêra xezanê avê dar miim
kirine, çê kirine.
No I go to many villages, organizations have set up water
tanks there, made them.
Şîrketê cem me zêde me... zêde û pênc gundo bî.
The company network with us was more... more than five
villages.
Eywa.
Aywa.
Ji vir heta Bîbaka û Şerqiya û bî, bes xerab bûye şîrket.
From here to Bibaka and Sharqiya and it was, but the network
is broken.
Erê avê tafto, şebeke xerab bûye mûmkin.
Yes the pumped water, the network is broken possibly.
Abo min wadiye her gundine... navî gundine heye him di 'emrê
xwe de curo vê gundina nabîstine.
Look I say look every village... there are village names
even in my life I haven't heard these villages yet.
Şerqiya.
Sharqiya.
Şerqiya, Bîbaka, erna...
Sharqiya, Bibaka, those...
Bî tab'ê vê şebekê bîn. Şebeke xerab bû.
They belonged to this network. The network broke.
Şebeke xerab bû.
Network broke.
Maşalla gundekî hadarî ye, seqafet ji cem gundiya heye,
maşalla.
Mashallah it's a civilized village, the villagers have
culture, mashallah.
Xwedê vê gundî mehfeze ke.
May God protect this village.
Her gundekî ez dikevimê, gundek ji ser gundekî xweştir.
Every village I enter, one village nicer than the other
village.
Maşalla, xwedê giya mehfeze ke. Xwedê rizqê giya bide.
Mashallah, may God protect all. May God give sustenance to
all.
Erê çîçke êş hat dîn lê bes xwedê be'ewidîne.
Yes a little pain came to life but God will compensate.
Mele canî mero sağ be, xwedê giy be'ewidîne inşalla.
As long as one's soul is healthy, God will compensate all
inshallah.
Xalo vê Huretê ra dibên kîderê?
Uncle what do they call this Hurata?
Avo Huretê jor e.
This is upper Hurata.
Avo Huretê jor e?
This is upper Hurata?
Avo Huretê jêr bî, av ji jor e.
Yes.
That was lower Hurata, this is upper.
Erê.
Yes.
Silav Xalê Elî.
Greetings Uncle Ali.
Xalê Elî.
Uncle Ali.
Wele dikan cem wa do pirr ne.
By God shops with you are many.
Erê dikan çar heb hene.
Yes there are four shops.
Xalo avê wa biro bîrê dukulin çend metro derdikeve?
Uncle your water goes via well digging, how many meters does
it come out?
Wela niholiyan sedî û jor da derdikeve.
By God currently hundred and up it comes out.
Sedî... erind e.
Hundred... it's good.
Avo rêka Şêxurz e.
That is the road to Sheikhurz.
Avo rêka darê Şêxurz e.
Darê xestexanê kuta.
To the hospital end.
Em heta tûtî biftilin, em warin Hureta din.
Let's turn around at the corner, we come to the other
Hurata.
Hêm hafizê tiskî.
Also remember a bit.
Me dixwara rehet kir xalo. Qusûrî ma ji ef ke ho.
We bothered you uncle. Excuse our shortcomings okay.
Ser çava.
You're welcome.
Qîçkê te yê lê seyr kin na?
Your kids watch, right?
Ê seyr kin.
Yes they watch.
Na? Qîçkê xalo lê seyr kin o, avo Hureta we ye.
No? Uncle's kids watch, look this is your Hurata.
Ê Ebidanê dibînin.
Yes they see Abidan.
Lê, gundê Ebidanê li Huretê xwe seyr kin.
Man, village of Abidan watch your Hurata.
Silavê me ji were hene, qîçkê xalo.
Our greetings are to you, Uncle's kids.
Xalê Elî.
Uncle Ali.
Li Elmanya ne ta bû? Danîmarka ne?
They were in Germany? Denmark?
Danîmark û Fînlanda ne.
Denmark and Finland.
Danîmark û Fînlanda.
Silavê me germ ji wara hene.
Our warm greetings are to you.
Emî ber wavo digerin işte, emî o tebîetê pêş wa dikin.
We are wandering like this for you, we show you that nature.
Ekî duwazdeh sîzdeh sal in nedî ye.
Those who haven't seen it for twelve thirteen years.
Wî ne seyr kin o texyîrat pir çêbûne.
Look at it, changes have happened a lot.
Ya hewş zêde kirî, ya dikan zêde kirî.
Either a yard increased, or a shop increased.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Xalo avo mekteb e na?
Uncle that is a school right?
Avo mekteba jor e.
That is the upper school.
Mekteba jor.
Upper school.
Avo heta i çendê di vir da dixwîne?
That until which [grade] reads in here?
Avo haliyan heta nehê dixwîne.
That currently reads until nine.
Heta nehê. Maşalla.
Until nine. Mashallah.
Avo mala min hawa.
That is my house there.
Av hewşa we ye na?
That is your yard right?
Host: Are qeçkê xalo li ser ka xwe lîstine, xwedê alî.
Yes.
Host: Look, Uncle's kids have played on the straw, may God
help them.
Host: Wa go... hewş e wa ye.
Host: This is... this is the yard.
Host: Are avo mektebo ve gundî ye he? Qeçkê meriv tê heta
nehê dixwînin ve mektebê?
Host: Look, is this the village school, huh? Do people's
kids study up to ninth grade in this school?
Host: Maşallah xalo rind çêkiriye. Dîkurekî xweş çêkiriye.
Host: Mashallah, Uncle has built it well. He has created a
nice decor.
Host: Av reko jî xalo dibê derê bilbile. Av reko. Ku em
darbost hewşê bin.
Host: And this path, Uncle calls it the Nightingale's
Stream/Pass. This path. Let's go through the garden yard.
Host: Ya Allah, ya Xwedê, ya Bismillah. Maşallah.
Host: Oh Allah, oh God, in the name of God. Mashallah.
Host: Hewşê xalo binêrin. Maşallah.
Host: Look at Uncle's yard. Mashallah.
Host: Xalo ney tî cennetê daye?
Host: Uncle, didn't you bring this from paradise?
Host: Seydî, wala eza bi mistixrabî maşallah. Xêr û bêr cem
te pir e.
Host: Sir, I am amazed, mashallah. The bounty and blessings
are abundant with you.
Xalo: Elhemdulillah.
Xalo: Praise be to God.
Host: Xêr û bêr gil cem xalo heye li vê derê.
Host: There is a lot of bounty and blessings with Uncle
here.
Host: Em çûne ewê... ciyê din?
Host: Shall we go to that... other place?
Xalo: Her cîk jî, cîkî xweştir.
Xalo: Every place is nicer than the other.
Host: Xwedê rizqî te bişînê, Xwedê te mehfeze ke.
Host: May God send your sustenance, may God protect you.
Xalo: Ê wekî ya bişînê.
Xalo: Yes, may He send it.
Host: Av di vir de jî tê ne wa ye?
Host: The water comes through here too, doesn't it?
Xalo: Bele, bele, erê.
Xalo: Yes, yes, indeed.
Host: Hm, maşallah.
Host: Hm, mashallah.
Host: Selatan nebî. Xalo te tûrko noke vê terî?
Host: (Prayer phrases). Uncle, did you plant radishes here?
Xalo: Xwedê wala nizanim.
Xalo: By God, I don't know.
Host: Vê tûrkinê, vê zeytûn ho... dikine? Yanî Semsûr der û
avana...
Host: These radishes, these olives... do they do/grow them?
Like in Adiyaman and those places...
Xalo: Hinek ta'mê çûka tê ne ye.
Xalo: Some bird taste doesn't come to it (Birds eat them).
Xalo: Çûk pir birin.
Host: Huh?
Xalo: Birds took/ate a lot of them.
Host: Lo de her kes kî rizqê xwe bixwe. Ha?
Host: Well, let everyone eat their own sustenance. Huh?
Xalo: Çûk pir birin digel.
Xalo: The birds took a lot anyway.
Host: Maşallah, avana bine? Maşallah wala xalo pir girtiye.
Host: Mashallah, look at these? Mashallah, by God Uncle, it
has yielded a lot.
Host: Gerek te baniya.
Host: You should have called.
Xalo: De her bise'e waha rûne.
Xalo: Just sit like that all the time.
Host: Qizik... qizik li vir e?
Host: Cress... is the cress here?
Host: Jêr... ta jêr jî xweş e, ciyê ta jêr jî xweş e.
Host: Down... down there is nice too, your place down there
is nice too.
Xalo: Are qizik û kutik û herik û varik liver e ne.
Xalo: Yes, cress and stumps and streams and everything are
here.
Host: Maşallah, wala xalo bistan rind çandiye. Lipik
çandine, bacan... Xalo avana fistiq in ne?
Host: Mashallah, by God Uncle, you planted the garden well.
You planted seedlings, eggplants... Uncle, are these
peanuts?
Xalo: He, fistiq in he.
Xalo: Yes, they are peanuts, yes.
Host: Fistiq cema dîn nacih e?
Host: Are peanuts successful with us?
Xalo: Wala xom de nacih e fistiq cema.
Xalo: Well, peanuts are not successful/don't grow well with
us.
Host: Kower... ere me'ze tovo, ovo.
Host: Look... hey look at the seed, here.
Host: O sîrîmî ovo, luyim ovo, wer. Wudû de?
Host: That is garlic here, look here, come. Is that it?
Host: Em kê xitî ye bixwin, xitiyê teze enqûre.
Host: We will eat a snake cucumber, a fresh snake cucumber,
an acur.
Host: Ovo, ovo luyim, ovo... ovo luyim jêk, jêk he?
Host: Here, look here, here... look here, pick it, pick it,
huh?
Xalo: Ovo jêke.
Xalo: Pick that one.
Host: Ba yo?
Host: Is it good?
Xalo: E tû çikî ne, rind ow nabîne.
Xalo: It's small, it won't be seen well.
Host: Qeçkê xalo avana heye, noko buxwaran e teze. Luyim te
noko bişo ha. Yoş.
Host: Uncle's kid, these are here, now they are ready to
eat, fresh. Look, wash them now, okay. Okay.
Host: Maşallah wadiye hanorê... Xalo hanor pir manî bibin?
Host: Mashallah, here are the pomegranates... Uncle, have
the pomegranates remained/grown a lot?
Xalo: Wala hanor mehîn dihê dibin.
Xalo: Well, the pomegranates ripen slowly slowly.
Host: Mehîn dihê? Yanî ma'nîfîkî din.
Host: Slowly slowly? Meaning they are holding on.
Xalo: He, ma'nîfîkî din.
Xalo: Yes, they are holding on.
Host: Are, avona, avo jî fistiq in ha, werin.
Host: Yes, those, those are also peanuts, huh, come.
Host: Avana fistiq in ha.
Host: These are peanuts, see.
Host: Xalo fistiq ku çaxê diçinin lê?
Host: Uncle, when do they harvest peanuts?
Xalo: Wala mehîn mehîn, mehê dehê, mehê nehê, mehê...
Xalo: Well, slowly slowly, tenth month, ninth month, month
of...
Host: Mohkî dan, mohkî dan.
Host: They have taken root, they have taken root.
Xalo: Dibê kîlîk katê, dibê vê kilkî zer katê, zanibê bihin
e.
Xalo: The stalk must drop, this yellow stalk must drop, then
know they are ready.
Host: Are, ene obo.
Host: Yes, look at that.
Xalo: Oho, vê kîlko.
Xalo: Look, this stalk.
Host: Mehê dehê.
Host: Tenth month.
Xalo: Mehê dehê, awe fistiqo heye, mewsîmê fistiqo.
Xalo: Tenth month, that is the peanut time, the peanut
season.
Host: Ha. Keşîrî mebiger.
Host: Ha. Don't grab the carrots.
Host: Yoş hekê vê bacanê bixwim, ma hîn in?
Host: Okay, let me eat this eggplant, are they still unripe?
Host: Bacanê bîstên.
Host: Garden eggplants.
Host: Pir xweş e, ye 'enqûr e xaseten.
Host: It's very good, the snake cucumber especially.
Host: Ona miza ye, ne wekî mehalata ye.
Host: This taste is different, not like the ones in the
neighborhoods/city.
Host: Eş, a buxum xweş e?
Host: Eat, eat this one, is it good?
Host: Sa'et bêş tar e.
Host: It is five o'clock.
Host: Xwe oxta ta'm didê, ta'm didê.
Host: It gives a taste when eaten, it gives a taste.
Host: Migo jî tahîkî jêke, xwe oxta ta'm didê, maşallah.
Luyim gazke le.
Host: I said pick one too, it gives a taste when eaten,
mashallah. Look, bite it.
Host: Gûşt e gûşt. Maşallah.
Host: It's meat, it's meat (fleshy). Mashallah.
Host: Noç oxta dilê gundiyo midimê.
Host: I don't want to make the villagers' hearts crave it.
Host: Maşallah.
Host: Mashallah.
Host: Wadiye bacano. Bacanê tahîkê, bacanê 'enqûro.
Host: Here are the eggplants. The individual eggplants, the
cucumber-like eggplants.
Host: Wadiye?
Host: Is this it?
Woman: Bismillahi.
Woman: In the name of God.
Host: Maşallah, maşallah. Xwedê bereketê têke.
Host: Mashallah, mashallah. May God put blessings in it.
Host: Maşallah.
Host: Mashallah.
Host: Lo damar lo, 'enqûrê do, ono hişînê biçininê?
Host: Oh man, in the snake cucumbers, pick those greens?
Host: Mehen, me'nî xwarinê jî, hin te'sîla ye, tezanî?
Host: Wait, meaning eating too, some are cravings, you know?
Xalo: Hin pê tesela dibe.
Xalo: One gets cravings for some.
Host: De?
Host: Here?
Child: Bide min.
Child: Give it to me.
Host: Hê.
Host: Here.
Host: Maşallah.
Host: Mashallah.
Host: Ah, ah bîber o binê, maşallah. Maşallah.
Host: Ah, look at those peppers, mashallah. Mashallah.
Host: Av bîber, av bîberno pir sûr in ho. Mero tirşû çêkero,
ji vê bîberno pir rind e.
Host: This pepper, these peppers are very red/spicy. One
should make pickles, it's very good from these peppers.
Host: Ehe, Allahumme salli 'ala seyyidina Muhammed.
Host: Ehe, O Allah, bless our Master Muhammad.
Host: Xalo avo çi new'a kilîke ye?
Host: Uncle, what kind of pepper/tail is this?
Woman: Kilkê berfê.
Woman: Snow tail.
Host: Kilkê berfê? Avolo navî vê kilkê vêrdibin kilkê berfê.
Host: Snow tail? Look, they call the name of this pepper
"Snow tail".
Host: Mêşîn girtîn ser, maşallah gil hanor o ne.
Host: Flies/bees have swarmed it, mashallah lots of
pomegranates.
Host: Maşallah, maşallah.
Host: Mashallah, mashallah.
Host: Gundî 'abîdan e, gi bi xêr û bêr e.
Host: It's a village of worshipers/devout people, all with
bounty and blessings.
Host: Avê xo pir e, miletî gundî, miletî têda ta'yiş
dibêjî...
Host: Its water is plentiful, the village people, the people
living in it as they say...
Host: Aw e, hedarî ye. Milet ne pir kîbar e.
Host: It is that, they are civilized/settled. The people are
very noble/polite.
Host: Yanî qîmetê cografî xo zanin, xizmet cografî xo dikin.
Host: Meaning they know the value of their geography, they
serve their geography.
Host: Wa avo neçêkirî xalo?
Host: Haven't you fixed this, Uncle?
Xalo: Are, are.
Xalo: Yes, yes.
Host: Hm, wa jêr jî Henefî kiriye ne?
Host: Hm, Henefi did the lower part, right?
Xalo: He, ma'nî avê gundê awerê kawirîn.
Xalo: Yes, meaning the village water comes down this way.
Host: Avolo, maşallah.
Host: Look here, mashallah.
Host: Kuçik jî li vir çêkirine?
Host: Did they build a sitting spot/fireplace here too?
Xalo: Are, kuçik me li vir çêkiriye, kêfî me li vir e.
Xalo: Yes, we built a sitting spot here, our pleasure spot
is here.
Host: Min serê nekiriye, ma ne?
Host: I haven't fixed my head (groomed myself/worn a hat),
have I?
Xalo: No, mahîn serê nekirine, avê dare emkê nofurê, vira
wira bira kemînî, avê ona kê çêke ser hewda...
Xalo: No, wait, they haven't finished the top (roof/cover).
This tree, we will... the fountain... here and there...
cut/arrange it, make water flow over the pool...
Host: Eş te serê bike înşallah Xwedê ye.
Host: Well, you will fix the top/finish it, God willing.
Xalo: Xwedê 'emrekî dirêj bide, Xwedê re... aw bike, rizqî
te bişîne, te çêke, te serê bike.
Xalo: May God give long life, may God... do that, send your
sustenance, you will build it, you will finish it.
Host: İnşallah, em dogra em çûn jêr.
Host: God willing, we went straight down.
Host: Bika vêr jêr anî ne? Bika vêrê milawa nanîn e lver
darê ne?
Host: Look, did they bring it down here? Look, didn't they
bring the colored/painted stuff under the tree?
Xalo: Jêr jî xweş e.
Xalo: Down there is nice too.
Host: Nonê kevrê vir ma hanî ne?
Host: Haven't they brought the stone bread here?
Xalo: Belê, gêçê na... me şixul kani dî kevrê milawwan e, ê
sîndel ê zar, ê heşîn, ê...
Xalo: Yes, later... we worked on the spring, the colored
stones, the sandal ones, the yellow, the blue, the...
Host: Emkê hîn telbîs ker.
Host: We will pave/clad it later.
Host: Ko were, hato vir am he?
Host: Look come, did we come here?
Host: Aw jî şawoyê.
Host: That is the sound/waterfall too.
Host: Xalo şkêfî dilê xwe ra çêkiriye.
Host: Uncle has made a pleasure spot for his heart.
Host: Wara am... amkê şawî... am livir çêkin, ovir.
Host: Come let's... let's make the sound/water... let's do
it here, over here.
Host: Nono se'et xoş... Maşallah xalo bahîvî têda pir na, ge
heşk bûne.
Host: No, wait... Mashallah Uncle, aren't there many almonds
in it? They have all dried.
Xalo: Are wudare te'sîrê êr lê buye.
Xalo: Yes, over there the effect of the wind/climate
happened to it.
Host: Vir jî way? Maşallah avana e çû ne xalo?
Host: Here too? Mashallah, what are these, Uncle?
Xalo: Avna yê fistiqî ne.
Xalo: These belong to the peanuts.
Host: Fistiq ne?
Host: Peanuts, right?
Xalo: He.
Xalo: Yes.
Host: E wala êş am fistiqê sakin.
Host: Oh well, let's check the peanuts.
Host: Are, xalo dibê avna yê fistiqî ne.
Host: Yes, Uncle says these belong to the peanuts.
Host: Bi destan dikişkin?
Host: Do you pull them with hands?
Xalo: Are, are, bi luy dikişkin.
Xalo: Yes, yes, we pull them with the hoe/hand.
Host: Gaskê?
Host: Wait?
Host: Hîn, duranê min, duranê min ê aw bin. Hacer e, çîçkê
hişk bibin, bixo dikişkin.
Host: Wait, my turn... my turn will be that. It's
stone/hard, if the buds dry, they pull them themselves.
Host: De nî, hîn çîçkê oftê da he.
Host: Look here, wait, there are buds of water/freshness in
it still.
Xalo: Çîçkê teze girtine.
Xalo: It has held fresh buds.
Xalo: Çîçkê teze girtine xahe.
Host: Huh?
Xalo: It has held fresh buds, look.
Host: Maşallah.
Host: Mashallah.
Host: O da... ma'nî viston e, marê xor pê tasela dibê.
Host: Oh look... meaning it's a garden, one craves it for
oneself.
Host: Hewşo de çî hebe rind e. De?
Host: Whatever is in the yard is good. Here?
Host: Maşallah, maşallah.
Host: Mashallah, mashallah.
Host: Som som e, a jî hûrû germ e wala. Du çîçkê hênik bî,
bes hûrû zîde germ e.
Host: It's scorching, it's scorching hot really. It was a
little cool, but it's excessively hot.
Host: E, maşallah.
Host: Eh, mashallah.
Host: Wala xalo Semsûr a Memsûr a gi khorî ye abine? Çûko...
Host: By God Uncle, Semsûr (Adiyaman) and such is all fiery
hot, you see? The birds...
Xalo: Are lê çûko semsûr. Da milo bixwe riziq pir e
maşallah.
Xalo: Yes, but the birds of Semsûr. Let the people eat, the
sustenance is abundant, mashallah.
Host: Her kes kî rizqê... na wey?
Host: Everyone [eats] their sustenance... isn't it?
Host: Migo gil wêzikê heywanîne. Heta wê çûkno...
Host: I said it's all sustenance for animals. Even those
birds...
Host: We jî li wêzikê heywanîne.
Host: That is also sustenance for animals.
Xalo: Waye.
Xalo: That's right.
Host: Maşallah, qe vira nêhiştine çûka.
Host: Mashallah, the birds haven't left anything here.
Host: De berê ne dorê kejiriyê ba, çibo diçû da, digot çi
heywan... tîtik... di vira da çû...
Host: Before, if it wasn't a thorny surrounding... whatever
went through, they would say what animal... critter... went
through here...
Host: Rêwîk di vira çû, ma'nî bixwe, xêr ik bê. Gi xêr e.
Host: A fox went through here, meaning let it eat, let it be
a charity. It's all charity.
Host: Maşallah, xalo wa bizrî şemis rêxistî saxê ne?
Host: Mashallah, Uncle, did you spill sunflower seeds
intact?
Xalo: E, diwû qîskê rêxistî.
Xalo: Yes, two sacks spilled.
Host: Xalo avna hişk dibin şûnda hûn radikin ne?
Host: Uncle, after these dry, you pick them up, right?
Xalo: Em radikin, erê, avo...
Xalo: We pick them up, yes, look...
Host: Maşallah, wala aw ne...
Host: Mashallah, by God that is not...
Host: Hîn teze ye.
Host: It is still fresh.
Host: Teze ye belê ser lêv didin, ona ma'ne hişk bibe.
Host: It is fresh but they give it to the edge (leave it),
meaning so it dries.
Host: Ewa. Are.
Host: Yeah. Yes.
Host: Avolo lê me'ze...
Host: Look here, look...
Host: Ba hat ho, Tadî.
Host: The wind came, Tadi (Cameraman).
Host: Firtone çêbû. Ha, noka em li jêr bûn çoxta germ bî.
Maşallah, sek... derka wekî firtone çêbî.
Host: A storm happened. Ha, just now we were down, it was so
hot. Mashallah, look... suddenly it was like a storm
happened.
Host: A bine? Maşallah, maşallah.
Host: Do you see? Mashallah, mashallah.
Host: Tima go ba tê ne, tê ne, germ e.
Host: We were saying the wind isn't coming, isn't coming,
it's hot.
Host: Em çûçik bûn virra bikin, çûka... ma'nî bawerê, ne
dibê virra bike ba tê?
Host: When we were small, spin around, birds... meaning
belief, didn't they say spin around so the wind comes?
Xalo: Firtone çêbû.
Xalo: A storm happened.
Host: Ba re wa digotin. Em çûçik bûn digotin virra bikin,
ma'nî ba were.
Host: Before they used to say that. When we were small, they
said spin around, meaning so the wind comes.
Host: Maşallah a bine? Avna berberûk ne?
Host: Mashallah, do you see? Are these sunflowers?
Host: Bizrê şems.
Host: Sunflower seeds.
Host: Maşallah.
Host: Mashallah.
Host: E hişk bibê ê doşînin, bistan e, tav zehmetiyan dikin,
tav... dixin.
Host: Well, when it dries they will milk/harvest it, it's a
garden, they labor in the sun, they eat... in the sun.
Host: Avolî mola vê tebîetê bigir wer.
Host: Look here, capture this nature, come.
Host: Ono vê... vê molno nîzîk bike.
Host: Zoom in on these... on these houses.
Host: Gundê Hevtêr ne xalo?
Host: Isn't it Hevter village, Uncle?
Xalo: Gundê Hevtêr. Mola Hevtêr.
Xalo: Hevter village. House of Hevter.
Host: Xalo mola Hevtêr, lê gundê Hevtêr.
Host: Uncle, House of Hevter, but Hevter village.
Xalo: Gundê Hevtêr.
Xalo: Hevter village.
Host: Ewa. Te got mola Hevtêr.
Host: Yeah. You said House of Hevter.
Xalo: Em, wextê em nîsik bûn, em mexteser em di mola Hevtêr.
Xalo: We, when we were close/young, we abbreviated, we said
House of Hevter.
Host: Mola Hevtêr, eywa.
Host: House of Hevter, exactly.
Host: Ao gundê Hevtêr e.
Host: That is Hevter village.
Host: Teyb xêl nov lê kirin gundê Hevtêr, tû yekî zanî?
Host: Well, they gave many names to Hevter village, do you
know one?
Xalo: Wallahî dibê... mezinî mola Hevtêr qasî girsî, serxo
bî, dexm bî, digotin Hevtor.
Xalo: By God, they say... the elder of the Hevter house was
somewhat large, huge, sturdy, they called him Hevtor.
Host: E, vira da gotin Hevtor. Hevtor jî quwet e.
Host: Yes, from there they said Hevtor. Hevtor also means
power/strength.
Xalo: Are.
Xalo: Yes.
Host: Are. Maşallah.
Host: Yes. Mashallah.
Host: Avolî mola vê, vê molno jî derxe, vê molno derxe.
Qeçkê xalo mila lê serke, miletî gundî genda mila lê serke.
Host: Look, bring out this house too, bring out these
houses. Turn the camera towards Uncle's kids, turn the
camera towards the village people too.
Host: Maşallah, maşallah.
Host: Mashallah, mashallah.
Host: Emî ser xûnî man e.
Host: We have remained on the blood/kinship.
Host: Maşallah.
Host: Mashallah.
Host: Wala wekî zerzalo kî çêbî dergê bavê ot...
Host: By God, like a yellow plum/baby that was born,
father's gate...
Host: Were avolî.
Host: Come here.
Host: Siheta te çawa ye?
Host: How is your health?
Elderly Man: Wala elhemdulillah, siheta te çawa?
Elderly Man: By God, praise be to God, how is your health?
Host: Wala gap gap î.
Host: Well, just talking/getting by.
Host: Xwedê 'emrekî dirêj bide te, xwedê sihetê xweş bide.
Elderly Man: Huh?
Host: May God give you a long life, may God give you good
health.
Saeta we gelekî xweş.
Good health to you.
Xalê Hecî?
Uncle Hajji?
Ehlen.
Welcome.
Tu rihet î?
Are you comfortable?
Hemd ji Xwedê re, rihet in şikur.
Praise be to God, we are comfortable, thanks.
Xalê Hecî, emrê te çend e?
Uncle Hajji, how old are you?
Xalê min ê.
My uncle.
Xalê te?
Your uncle?
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Bereke, emrê xwe çend e?
A blessing, how much is his age?
Welle gerek heştê û pênc be.
Well, it must be eighty-five.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Xalê, emrê te dibê heştê û pênc e, maşallah tu ji min
ciwantir xuya dikî te.
Uncle, he says your age is eighty-five, mashallah you look
younger than me.
Waye, waye, qey na, qey hene heqîq...
That's right, that's right, no, there is truth... [mumbling]
Na?
No?
Maşallah, Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike, Xwedê destê te û ser te
ra bigire.
Mashallah, may God prolong your life, may God hold his hand
over you [protect you].
Xwedê te neke ber destan.
May God not leave you dependent on others.
Were, werin rûnin.
Come, come sit down.
Xalê Hecî were.
Uncle Hajji come.
Welle em kar nakin, em ê vîdyo çêdikin, em ê herin.
Really, we aren't working, we are making a video, we will
go.
Were, were.
Come, come.
[Music playing]
Erê miletê gundê Abîdanê, em ê xatira xwe ji miletê gundê
Abîdanê bixwazin.
Yes, people of Abidan village, we will say our goodbyes to
the people of Abidan village.
Saeta giyan xweş.
Good health to all of them.
Erê welle.
Yes, indeed.
Em ê nika tekra dakevin mezra ye.
We will now go back down to the farm.
Binerin inşallah, hûn ê vîdyoyek xweş bibînin, inşallah
vîdyoyê me jî bi ecibînin.
Watch hopefully, you will see a nice video, hopefully you
will like our video too.
Bîr mekin her yek sê çar te'lîqa li cem me binivîsînin.
Don't forget, each one of you write three or four comments
for us.
Bela bikin li dost û ahbaban bela bikin.
Share it, share it with friends and loved ones.
Heta em çûn nav gund û hatin...
By the time we went into the village and came back...
Xaltîk ma ra, ew ê çêdike şîvê çêdike?
Auntie is for us... is she making dinner?
Saeta xweş Xaltîk, ma te xwarin radikir?
Good health Auntie, did you put the food away?
Ee te jî xwar.
Yes, you ate too.
Ko ka? Ew dera ze çêkim?
Where is it? Shall I make [sit] right there?
Ehlen wa sehlan, bi silametî.
Welcome, in safety.
Ez ê lê bar bim.
I will be a burden on her.
Ez ê çêkim.
I will do it.
Seke fehm rind e, ne wekî êzinga ye.
Look, charcoal is good, it's not like firewood.
Me pir êzing amade kiriye yaw.
We prepared a lot of firewood, man.
No, aa.
No, ah.
Ko ha vêna biraştin hem wana dîtin?
Where are those roasted ones, did they see them?
Erê welle.
Yes, really.
Mako em pir xwarinê daro dernaxin, mlo... feqîra... î heye
dilê xwe bi mera dimînin.
We don't show the food outside too much, man... the poor
people... there are those who lose hope in us [feel bad
because they can't eat].
Îşê xwarinê daro em pir dernaxin. E... kesên heye tiştê
wano...
We don't show the act of eating outside much. Uh... there
are people who [don't have] such things...
Welle dilê xwe mera dimînin, na we?
Really, they lose hope in us, isn't that right?
Heram e. Erê.
It is forbidden/shameful. Yes.
Welle.
Really.
Na we? Xalê Elî jî me, feqîre me rad kir. Xwedê emrê te
dirêj bike.
Isn't it? Uncle Ali also, the poor man turned us down. May
God prolong your life.
Çavê gundê me maç dikim.
I kiss the eyes of our village.
Xwedê ji we razî be, Xwedê we razî be.
May God be pleased with you, may God be pleased with you.
Pişta jî Xwedê emrê te dirêj tade, Xwedê te neke ber destan.
Furthermore, may God give you a long life, may God not leave
you dependent on others.
Xwedê rizqê te bişîne.
May God send your sustenance.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Me te rad kir.
We turned you down.
Na hûn astengê nekin, ka wîna didin min. Ew ê jor hatin
xwar.
No, don't make trouble, give those to me. Those came down
from upstairs.
Ez ê te bibim wara, ehlen wa sehlan.
I will take you there, welcome.
Wola zan tê derxist.
By God, I know you figured it out.
Ez yêkî wekî te bikim.
I will get one like you.
Hişînî hez dikim.
I like greens.
Ee were de, were têke.
Uh come then, come put it in.
Tamam, ezê...
Okay, I will...
Welle cenet e. Xaltîkê min jî parparê dikî. Xaltîk!
It's really paradise. Auntie is doing the purslane. Auntie!
Lê te çi dikî? Parpar e?
Hey what are you doing? Is it purslane?
Na, bextenîs e.
No, it's celery/parsley.
Parparê dikî, bextenîsê dikî.
You do purslane, you do celery.
Xweşim jî parparê hez dikim. Dibêke tim ter herim gundê
bigerim.
I also like purslane myself. I have to always go looking
around the villages.
Na.
No.
Na, ew jî bîst û sê çar man ji Heleb hatî, a derim gundê
teswîrî, tim dibê mixarê bibe. Dibêke tera bigerim.
No, that one came from Aleppo twenty-three or four months
ago, I go to film the village, she always says take me to
the cave. She says I have to walk around.
Ez jî qey mişêne nabim e... dinya germ e.
I also don't [unclear word: mişên], it's not possible... the
world is hot.
Lê?
Right?
E jinê bi emrê mezin jî, tim lona li korî çolê hez dikin.
Uh, older women also always like the outdoors/wilderness
like that.
Tiştê xidra, hişînî, parpar, bextenîs...
Green things, greenery, purslane, celery...
Tiştê wano pir hez dikin, jinê pîçikî bi emrê mezin.
They love things like that very much, women slightly older
in age.
Silav û rêz ji we giya re.
Greetings and respect to you all.
Tê de ne, tê de canim.
Put it in, put it in my dear.
Ca mezin, mezin têke. Ca mezin têke.
Put a big one in. Put a big one in.
Waha.
Like that.
Muko me hîna bigre ta bînin ha.
Man, hold this for us until they bring it, ha.
Inşallah me hefti merdî û Xwedê heye.
God willing, we have seven generosities [idiom for plenty]
and God exists.
Himm?
Hmm?
Maxbûr, yêkî waha...
Forced, one like that...
Saeta xweş Xaltîk, feqîra xwe helak kirin welle.
Good health Auntie, the poor woman exhausted herself really.
Lo ka camkê sifrê berxwe ra kin?
Hey, can you guys lift the glass of the table for
yourselves?
Cem me buhar e.
It is spring at our place.
Saeta xweş Xoltîk, Xwedê ji we razî be û Xwedê rizqê we
bide.
Good health Auntie, may God be pleased with you and may God
give you sustenance.
Xwedê rizqê we jî bide, ehlen wa sehlan.
May God give you sustenance too, welcome.
Welle hîsa nakim.
Really, I don't feel it.
Xwedê qeye, wajo loko qeyix, jêr pênc deqîqe.
God implies, drive the boat, the boat, under five minutes.
Bismillah.
In the name of God.
Na ve, tu zêde neke.
Not that, don't do too much.
Arê, ev olno, li vê dere jî...
Yes, this one friends, at this place too...
Xolû û xaltîkê saeta we gelek xweş, qîçikê xaltîkê...
Uncle and Auntie, good health to you, Auntie's little one...
Ma ra sifre amade kirin, heta em çûn gund û hatin, sifre giy
amade kirin.
They prepared the table for us, by the time we went to the
village and back, they prepared the whole table.
We jî xweş...
You also [have a] good...
Me go hem parîk nanê xwe jî bixwin, teben qortix nîrûbî ye.
We said let's eat a morsel of our bread too, of course it's
near the border.
Saet xweş pismam canî wara xwar.
Good health cousin, come here down.
Dilê wa ketê ray, birin kerem kin, em bi hev ra parîk nan
bixwin.
If your heart desires, please come, let's eat a morsel of
bread together.
Cem Xalê Elî...
At Uncle Ali's place...
Berî gund, berî gund bi du kîlometra ye.
Before the village, it is two kilometers before the village.
Arê.
Yes.
Destê te sax be.
Bless your hands.
Noşî can be.
Bon appetit.
Şama brayê keremkin.
Dinner of the brother, please [eat].
Dînivana ezîmet nakin, nîvan?
The religious ones don't invite, the middle ones?
Welle ma ka ezîmet kin, çi kin?
Really, well let them invite, what should they do?
Nîvana me nesekiniye.
Our middle ones didn't stop.
Noko, qîçikê xolû heban, ew jî ano me ra ser sifre rûniştin
o, me nan bi hev ra bixwara.
Look, Uncle's little ones were there, they also sat at the
table with us like that, so we could eat bread together.
E pir xweş bû.
Uh, it was very nice.
Hestiyê zarok.
The bones of the kid [meaning the person is thin/small].
Inşallah, inşallah ew werin, em ê... wekî dibê em ê dîsa
werin, parîk nan bi hev ra bixwin, nan xêyê çê bibê.
Hopefully, hopefully they will come, we will... as it says,
we will come again, eat a morsel of bread together, may the
bread be benevolent.
Heye dilî ye, horikî biya, her yek deqîqe da bela wî ye.
It's the heart, let it be small, in every single minute it
is his trouble/distribution.
Xwedê ye.
It is God.
Arê avolno, em gihîştin talê vîdyo xwe. Teben malê Xalê Elî.
Yes friends, we reached the end of our video. Of course,
Uncle Ali's house.
Naku mabeynê mefraqa Nebihûrî û Abîdanê va.
Look, between the junction of Nabihuri and Abidan.
Vî katine, ba'dî bi du sed metre, li cem gundê mesbeha avê
heye.
This cut [location], after two hundred meters, near the
village there is a water pool.
Aîlî jî heye û şebabî jî heye. Imkanin derbas vî darê bin.
There is [space for] families and there is [space for]
youth. It is possible to pass through this place.
Saeta Xalî me Elî xweş û saeta xoltîkê xweş.
Good health to our Uncle Ali and good health to Auntie.
Bi me ra pir rehet bûn, a çavê wana maç dikim.
They were very comfortable with us, I kiss their eyes.
U silavê me jî ji qîçikê xoltîkê û xolû ra hene.
And our greetings are also to the little ones of Auntie and
Uncle.
Jiber heta cê gendo lê.
Because until the place of the... [unclear] there.
Bi me ra bin, dîsa vîdyoyek xweş, kîbar.
Be with us, again a nice, elegant video.
Hilqok Hacer, inşallah em ê nîzik da wara daxin. Vîdyê me jî
hûr ana bî. Hûn ê qusûrî me jî efkin, şaşbîn, moşbîn hene.
[I am] Halkawt Hajar, hopefully we will upload for you soon.
Our video was just like this. You will forgive our faults,
if there were mistakes or anything.
Bi xatire we, vîdyoyek din xweş, kîbar. Bye bye.
Goodbye, [until] another nice, elegant video. Bye bye.
Elî!
Ali!