Belê, temaşevanên hêja, programa me dest pê kir.
Yes, dear viewers, our program has started.
Di beşa xwaya nû da, em ê serdana gundewarê Maratê bikin.
In this new episode of ours, we will visit the village of
Maratê.
Di vî gundî da jî, em ê gelek hunermend û gelek tiştên
hunerî jî nîşanî we bidin.
In this village, we will show you many artists and many
artistic things as well.
Li benda me bin, beşa me dest pê kir.
Stay tuned, our episode has started.
Bi haseb kitab Jabal al-Kurd, al-dirasat al-jughrafiyah fi
Afrin...
According to the book "Jabal al-Kurd: Geographical Studies
in Afrin"...
...yu'taqad anna Marata ism Suryani wa ta'ni al-maghara.
...it is believed that Marata is a Syriac name meaning "the
cave."
Amma ahl al-qarya yaqulun anna al-tasmiya ta'ud ila ism al-
hakim al-romani Maratinus...
As for the villagers, they say that the name goes back to
the name of the Roman ruler Maratinus...
...allathi hakama al-mantiqa abban al-hukm al-romani.
...who ruled the area during the Roman rule.
Tem al-ta'arruf 'ala al-qarya munthu akthar min 720 'aman...
The village has been known for more than 720 years...
...yadull 'alayha tarikh mudawwan 'ala sakhra kanat mawjuda
fi Kahf al-'Arab, Şikefta Ereban.
...indicated by a date recorded on a rock that was located
in the Cave of the Arabs, Şikefta Ereban.
Fuqidat tilk al-sakhra munthu akthar min 50 'aman.
That rock was lost more than 50 years ago.
Amma al-tarikh al-haqiqi lil-qarya yadull 'alayhi al-mawaqi'
al-athariya al-muntashira fi tilk al-qarya wa dawahiha...
As for the true history of the village, it is indicated by
the archaeological sites spread throughout that village and
its suburbs...
...wa al-qura al-muhita biha, mithl Gundê Mazen, Qaziqlê,
Xilnêr, Kefir Şîlê wa madinat Afrin.
...and the surrounding villages, such as Gundê Mazen,
Qaziqlê, Xilnêr, Kefir Şîlê and the city of Afrin.
Tatba' idariyan ila markaz Afrin wa tab'ud 'anha 5 km.
Administratively, it belongs to the center of Afrin and is 5
km away from it.
Kanat lil-qarya basma wadiha fi al-thawra al-suriyya al-
kubra...
The village had a clear imprint on the Great Syrian
Revolution...
...hayth qadima ila al-qarya Ibrahim Hananu lil-tansiq ma'
thuwar Afrin lil-musharaka fi al-thawra.
...where Ibrahim Hananu came to the village to coordinate
with the revolutionaries of Afrin to participate in the
revolution.
Ehlen we sehlen, ji we ra, ji watanê we ra...
Welcome, to you, to your homeland...
...û ji vê hezkirina... di nav me da...
...and for this love... amongst us...
...ev hatina we ser seran û ser çavan. Hûn xêr hatin gundê
me Maratê...
...this visit of yours is most welcome (upon heads and
eyes). Welcome to our village, Maratê...
...ji herêma Efrînê ne.
...from the Afrin region.
Elhemdulilah em gîş hev re rind in. Xwedê hezkirina me zêde
bike.
Thank God, we are all good with each other. May God increase
our love.
İnşallah em ê ji vê çêtir bibin, inşallah Xwedê me gîş ji vê
tengiyê derxîne ya Reb.
God willing we will be better than this, God willing, God
will bring us all out of this distress, Oh Lord.
Wele gundê me bi zîraatê meşhûr e.
Well, our village is famous for agriculture.
Bi zîraatê meşhûr e, û teqrîben umrê me bûye heftê heştê
sal.
Famous for agriculture, and our age is approximately seventy
or eighty years.
Elhemdulilah tim hezkirin heye û tim rindî heye.
Thank God there is always love and always goodness.
Û îşek tune cem me, û zêde elhemdulilah gîş hevdura rind in.
And there is no issue among us, and mostly, thank God,
everyone is good with each other.
Ehmed... Mala Henan Elî...
Ahmad... The House of Henan Elî...
...ewa sê gund... sê mal di gund da bûn. Maratê sê mal.
...those three villages... three houses were in the village.
Maratê was three houses.
Mala Henan Elî, û mala Bêd Xidir, mala Xidir. Û mala Erê.
The House of Henan Elî, and the House of Bêd Xidir, the
House of Xidir. And the House of Erê.
Evna sê mal, hewa... [unintelligible] bûn.
These three houses, they... were [here].
Paşê bûn heft mal.
Then they became seven houses.
Ji wan heft malan bûn... yani hêdî hêdî tim pê da zêde bûn û
çûn.
From those seven houses they became... meaning slowly they
always increased and went on.
Elhemdulilah heta nika tim mişkîlet tunene û hezkirin heye.
Thank God, until now there are never problems and there is
love.
Gundê me gundekî qedîm e û meşhûr e bi zîraatê.
Our village is an ancient village and is famous for
agriculture.
Meşhûr e bi... bi dar û bi giya, yani bi zîraata me pir rind
e elhemdulilah.
Famous for... for trees and plants, meaning our agriculture
is very good, thank God.
Wele gundê me... gundê me jimej e, pir jimej e.
Well, our village... our village is old, very old.
Umrê me bûye heftê heştê sal, teqrîben... ewa kî ez zanim...
My age is seventy or eighty years, approximately... what I
know...
Berî me bi sed salî ye, bi çi qasî ye, yani... ewa pir qedîm
e gundê me.
It was a hundred years before us, or however much,
meaning... our village is very ancient.
Û kaniya xwe jî... wextê berê kaniya me...
And its spring too... in the past our spring...
Kaniya me heft heşt înç, deh înç av hebu.
Our spring had seven, eight inches, ten inches of water
[flow].
Diçû digihîşt Efrîn û me baxçe jî pê av didan.
It would go reach Afrin and we irrigated gardens with it
too.
Yani gundekî pir meşhûr e, gundekî pir kîbar e, pir rind e.
Meaning it's a very famous village, a very elegant village,
very beautiful.
Wele hektar pir e yani.
Well, there are many hectares, I mean.
Û ededê gund jî... teqrîben... bi hezar heye yani.
And the number [population] of the village...
approximately... is around a thousand, I mean.
Jimej e, gund, gund qedîm e, gund pir rind e.
It's old, the village, the village is ancient, the village
is very beautiful.
Yani mişkîlet têda tunene.
Meaning there are no problems in it.
Belê, kanî...
Yes, the spring...
Gundekî meşhûr e, rind e yani bi zîraatê, bi gî tiştî.
It's a famous village, beautiful, meaning regarding
agriculture, regarding everything.
Kanî... heft heşt înç av çêdikir, deh înç av çêdikir.
The spring... produced seven or eight inches of water, ten
inches of water.
Erdê di Maratê gî pê dihat avdan, heta av digihîşt Efrînê
jî.
The land in Maratê was all irrigated by it, the water even
reached Afrin.
Yani av zêde dibû, diçû digihîşt avê Efrîn.
Meaning the water was abundant, it went and joined the water
of Afrin.
Gundekî pir meşhûr e, û avê xwe jî pir kîbar e. Avê xwe sehî
ye, avê kaniya mezin, jor va re dibêjin kaniya mezin.
A very famous village, and its water is very fine. Its water
is healthy, the water of the Great Spring, up there they
call it the Great Spring.
Pir kîbar e.
It's very elegant.
Na, kanî mirî ye wele.
No, the spring is dead, honestly.
Berê pir bû av.
Before, there was a lot of water.
Gî çêkiribûn bi kevir û... sê şorik têda bûn.
They had built it all with stones and... there were three
spouts in it.
Û av behr bû maşallah. Belê.
And the water was like a sea, Mashallah. Yes.
Bes nika... încek e, înç û nîvek e, du înç in... yani...
But now... it's one inch, an inch and a half, two inches...
meaning...
Baran jî kêm e. Belê. Baran jî kêm e, bes berê baran pir bû,
avê xwe pir bû.
The rain is also scarce. Yes. The rain is scarce, but
before, rain was plentiful, its water was plentiful.
Xwe av pir bû, zêde pir bû.
The water itself was plentiful, very plentiful.
Wele bi meşhûrê... ê pir... pir meşhûr bi zîraatê bûn. Bi
pêz bûn.
Well, famous... very... very famous for agriculture they
were. With livestock.
Tiştî kef di Maratê da ne wek berê... ê pir giya ew bûn.
The things in Maratê are not like before... they were very
[abundant with] grass and such.
Eseret berê pir neman.
The traces of the past didn't remain much.
Berê şikeft bûn, der bûn... ê pir di şikeftan da bûn.
Before there were caves, outside... most were in the caves.
Paşê, ba'dî şikefta... yek, du de xanî girtin... têda av
bûn.
Later, after the caves... one, two built houses... they
settled in them.
Û paşê dinya pêşket, qedem... pêşketin... xaniyê hewşê paqij
girtin...
And then the world advanced, progress... development... they
built clean courtyard houses...
Û însan pêşket, rind bû, hezkirin zêde bû. Gundê me mişkîlet
têda tunebûn.
And people advanced, it was good, love increased. There were
no problems in our village.
Û gundekî me, gundekî me jî gundekî pir qedîm e.
And our village, our village is also a very ancient village.
Darekî me heye, darekî... vêra dibên... darê Gelberiyê.
We have a tree, a tree... they call it... the Gelberiyê
tree.
Koka xwe dike deh... pênc şeş mêr destê xwe bidin hevdu,
destê xwe nagihînin hevdu. Pir mezin e.
Its trunk makes ten... [if] five or six men hold each
other's hands, their hands don't reach each other. It's very
big.
Dibê du sed sal e, çar sed sal e... ew dara. Pir qedîm e.
They say it's two hundred years, four hundred years [old]...
that tree. It's very ancient.
De hinek dibên sê sed sal e, hinek dibên pênc sed sal e. Her
hinek şurhekî dikin.
Some say three hundred years, some say five hundred years.
Everyone gives a different explanation.
Fi al-qarya akthar min 500 manzil wa 'adad sukkanuha 3000
nasama taqriban...
In the village, there are more than 500 houses and its
population is approximately 3000 people...
...bima fihim al-muqimin fi al-duwal al-kubra wa al-mahjar.
...including those residing in major countries and in the
diaspora.
Tantashir fi al-qarya 'adad min al-manazil al-qadima min al-
khashab wa al-tin wafqa nizam al-qantara...
A number of old houses made of wood and mud according to the
arch system are spread in the village...
...wa aqdam hathihi al-manazil huwa manzil al-sayyid Sheikh
Zakariya wa aydan al-sayyid Hajji 'Izzat.
...and the oldest of these houses is the house of Mr. Sheikh
Zakariya and also Mr. Hajji Izzat.
Welle navê min Şiyar e, Şiyar Mihemed Şêxo ji gundê Maratê
me.
Well, my name is Shiyar, Shiyar Mihemed Shexo, from the
village of Maratê.
Û tişt, wanê tiştê turas, ê kalê me ne dihêwinim.
And things, those heritage things, belonging to our
ancestors, I collect.
Mesele, heba... turasê bav û kalan henda nebe. Tiştê kevn,
wekî carcar heye...
For example, so the heritage of fathers and grandfathers
doesn't disappear. Old things, like there is the threshing
sled...
Melêbêdarî ne, şixre ne, tiştê, ana, tiştê kevn. Ê turasê, ê
kalê me ne. Carcar heye meselen.
Wooden plows, harrows, things, you know, old things.
Heritage, belonging to our ancestors. For example, there is
the threshing sled.
Edwatê zira'î hene, ê menzîlî hene.
There are agricultural tools, there are household ones.
Wekî zira'î, ê berê pê kar dikirin meselen. Şûnê fatos û dar
e...
Like agricultural ones, that they used to work with in the
past, for example. Instead of lamps and wood...
Û ê menzîlî, tiştê baqil kevn, wekî tiştê textîn e, fişekî
dê we... pê berê dawçê dikirin.
And household ones, old copper things, like wooden things,
cartridge belts... they used to go hunting with them in the
past.
Heve. Û ê din jî... heywan cem me heye. Tawûs in, mirîşk in,
qumrî ne, hew şokûçik in, tiştê ana heywan e, em pê tesela
dibin.
That's it. And the others... we have animals. Peacocks,
chickens, doves, and just small things, animal things like
that, we find comfort in them.
Em ê xwe pê diqetînin.
We pass our time with them.
Û ê din jî, sê jî... hewş... min ana çêkiriye ji xwe ra wekî
nofûra tê de hene, tenûr heye min çêkiriye, firne, weke
şiklê wekî turasê berê ye.
And the other thing, thirdly... the courtyard... I have
built it for myself, like there is a fountain in it, there
is a tandoor I built, an oven, like the shape of the
heritage of the past.
Em tê de nanê darê dikin. Me'neya berê tînim bîra xwe.
We make bread on wood fire in it. Bringing the meaning of
the past to my memory.
Heve li cem me.
That is what I have.
Welle vî tiştî em ji kalê xwe elimîn. Meraqê... hewa ji kalê
min jî wey bû, hewildana tiştê ana hez dikir, em jî elimîn.
Well, this thing we learned from our elder. The passion...
my father was also like that, he loved collecting things
like this, we also learned.
Ma, me 'eyb dît nebe jî, em qişkê xwe, pêş qişkê xwe dikin.
So, even if it wasn't seen as shameful, we follow our roots.
Hem şî heve, qişkê me, û cîlî 'acar zane be. Bîr nebe,
turasê me yê Kurmancî bîr nebe, mentîqa 'Efrîn bi şeklê 'am
bîr nebe.
Everything is this, our roots, and so the new generation
knows. So it isn't forgotten, so our Kurmanji heritage isn't
forgotten, the Afrin region in general isn't forgotten.
Û gundê Maratê jî, anê berê da, bi henar û... ew jî zeytûn
û... anê tiştê ana, rez û...
And the village of Maratê, in the past, with pomegranates
and... also olives and... things like that, vineyards and...
Karê xwe pê dikirin. Noke ê pir zeytûn in, û ard a diçînin
meselen. Xidre ye, genim e, tiştê ana diçînin.
They did their work with them. Now, most are olives, and
they plant the land, for example. Vegetables, wheat, things
like that they plant.
Ê esas heve li cem me, Maratê.
This is the main thing with us, Maratê.
Tişt pir e, hema du tebeqe, ben hezar û çarsed qite' li cem
min e, kevn.
There are many things, about two floors, there are about
1400 pieces with me, old ones.
Min tişt pir kirîye. Û ê din jî, ê kalê, ê malê kalê min in
ma wanînan.
I have bought many things. And the others belong to the
elders, to my grandfather's house, remaining like that.
Û pir ehbaba jî ji min ra wanînan. Ehbab dîtine cem min,
zanîbûn meraqê min vî şî heye, anê tiştê bav û kal li cem
min didan min.
And many friends also brought them for me. Friends saw them
with me, knew I had a passion for this, they gave me the
things of fathers and ancestors.
Niko bile li cem te be te mehfeze bike. Firotanê, em
nafiroşin.
Saying, "Let it be with you, you preserve it." As for
selling, we do not sell.
Em dikirin, em nafiroşin. Ev o tişta, me'neya hinda nebe.
We buy, we do not sell. These things, so the meaning doesn't
get lost.
Ez li cem xwe mehfeze dikim.
I preserve them with me.
Welle tişt, kevn min got pir e yek. Ê didiyê, tiştê ê kalê
min e avayê pir. Ê malê kalê min e.
Well, things, old ones as I said are many. Secondly, things
of my grandfather are very many. Of my grandfather's house.
Wanê meselen, xanîk û qabîk û kevn ebî min ji ê derxist.
Like, for example, old roofs and arches and things, I took
them out from there.
Û ê hin hene min kirîn. Û hin hene ehbaba dan min. Wanê cem
gunda yek qite' hene didin min.
And there are some I bought. And some friends gave to me.
Like in the village someone has a piece, they give it to me.
Û pir hene nûfer... anê em didin te, hinek jî xozin jî, pera
didin min. Nadin, em dikirin.
And many are... "we give to you", some ask for money, they
give to me for money. If they don't give, we buy.
Û ê tûlê jî em nafiroşin em. Em li cem xwe mehfeze dikin. Ev
o turasê me yê 'Efrîn e em mehfeze dikin.
And these tools, we do not sell. We preserve them with me.
This is our Afrin heritage we are preserving.
Wanê em tikî bifiroşin, em nafiroşin. Heta em kanin, em kom
dikin. Em na... bifiroşin.
Like, if we were to sell a piece, we won't sell. As long as
we can, we collect. We don't... sell.
Habo turasê me ma hinda nebe.
So that this heritage of ours doesn't get lost.
Em ji qişkê xwe ra li dû dirin. Te dît, me yê oda ji xwe ra
çêkiriye, oda ji textî ye, me tê da me danînan e.
We follow our roots. You saw, I built a room for myself, a
wooden room, we placed them in it.
Wanê em her derê, ewa dibe em tê da rûdinin. Em... wanê pir
ewa dibe, em pir dûr darin.
Like, everywhere, whenever possible we sit in it. We... like
it happens a lot, we go very far back.
Welle ev o esas text, û tiştê kevir çêkirin, text û axî, ev
o tiştê kevn dide, me'neya wî çêdikim.
Well, this basic wood, and things made of stone, wood and
earth, this gives the old feeling, I create its meaning.
Wanê ev jî wek turas e. Wanê e noke gev... kevirê meselen,
kevirê nehît e, a...
Like this is also like heritage. Like now... stone for
example, cut stone...
Na, ev o text xêr e, ev jî kevn dide. Ê didiyê, ez bi xwe
çêdikim, ev o giş şuxulê destê min e.
No, this wood is better, it also gives an old look.
Secondly, I build it myself, this is all my own handiwork.
Meselen wekî firnê min çêkirî, tenûr e... Wanê ev o wekî
nofûra, ez noke kora î min e, ez bi xwe çêdikim.
For example, like the oven I built, the tandoor... Like this
fountain, it is my work now, I build it myself.
Text e, yan ko kevir, ev o karê min e. Ez bi xwe tê de
dişuxilim. Keherebe, av, karê min e esasî ye ev o.
Wood, or stone, this is my work. I work in it myself.
Electricity, water, this is my main work basically.
Û ê din berhem çêdikim, bi texta, dara... wanê text, ev o
yek şê... wanê pir kevn dide, me'neya wî çêdikin.
And the other I produce, with wood, trees... like wood, this
is one thing... it gives a very old look, we create its
meaning.
Meraqa me ser text pir e, we axê bû.
Our passion for wood is great, and it was earth.
Dayîm xaniyê me çêbî, em kanîn xanîk axî wekî berê çêkin.
Wanê dîrekî û axî.
If we build a house, we can build an earthen house like
before. Like with pillars and earth.
Noke çikî wez'ê me ne ewa.
Now, our situation isn't like that.
Welle min pirr got, evî tiştî çêdikim...
Well, I said a lot, I make this thing...
Eb heyata berê pê dihesim. Se'a me ne dît, bes ez pê dihesim
min kirî vî karî.
I feel the past life with it. Although we didn't see it, but
I feel it, having done this work.
Hewa me'neya wî ye. Wanê, ewa min heve. Wanê wekî kalê min
berê em noçûbûn xanêt axî bûn, textî bûn.
That is its meaning. Like, my desire is this. Like my
grandfather before, we hadn't gone... they were earthen
houses, wooden ones.
Wanê ez pê dihesim, êş bûm ro 'eyşî me.
Like I feel it, I lived that day of our living.
Ê ewa min, ewa min pir heve.
That is mine, that is my great desire.
Fenan hene, wanê klamcî, tembûrcî gunda heye, me'rûf e,
gundê me da hene.
There are artists, like singers, lute players in the
village, it's known, there are some in our village.
Bes vî tiştî turas, kes teneqey min nade hewan. Ê tenê
dihewînim.
But this heritage thing, no one competes with me. I am the
only one keeping it.
Bes wekî din hene gundê me da, 'uyla hene... tembûrê, klamê,
ma'rûf in evna, malê Çawîşler fêra dibên.
But otherwise there are in our village, families... of the
lute, of songs, these are known, they call them the house of
Chawishler.
Havno hene. Û necar tê da hene, tişta çêdikin.
Those exist. And there are carpenters in it, they make
things.
Bes vî tiştî turas, ano tiştî kevn, kesî nade hewan.
But this heritage thing, these old things, no one keeps
them.
Da noke dihewînin, ez nizanim.
Whether they keep them now, I don't know.
Mistefa Ebdulrehman Ose ji Maratê.
Mistefa Ebdulrehman Ose from Maratê.
Berê, xet a em dîtin e... ta'nîya me ê xerbî dond.
In the past, the line that we saw... our side, the western
side.
Ta'nîya xwe da... ponzeh îçe bû. Heta fidanê destê...
In its side... it was fifteen inches. Until the saplings of
the plain...
Dikirin pembû havînê, û av pir bû.
They planted cotton in the summer, and water was plentiful.
Dirim.
I'm going.
Em dîtine, îsta pembû diçandin, da şandin av didan, rind bû.
We saw it, now they planted cotton, they sent water, it was
good.
Dûra... av tune bû. Yane din di pef da. Ya bi çerxê, ya bi
qudusa, diçûn av ji ta'nê danîyan.
Later... there was no water. Like, inside the struggle.
Either with wheels, or with buckets, they went and provided
water from the side.
Tincê xwe, deryê xwe disistin, diçûn bi be'l, de de serê xwe
disistin.
They washed their pots, their outsides, they went with
containers, washed their heads.
Av danîn bi... ya bi çerxa... ya zî bi sê serî... ya zinetê
danîya.
They provided water with... either with wheels... or with
three heads... or ornaments they placed.
Ê dûra... bîr çêbûn.
And later... wells were made.
Noqta danî me, çapîn sê du mar e.
We put a point, [using] Shahin number three.
Hele mar tê bîra te heye...
Is the "Mar" still in your memory...
Mebhaza çêbû, me ev o xeta sana ba'dayê... em vê dixînin, da
îstembêt istîxaf tin veda xin daetin.
The press was made, we... this line... we drive this... it
was better.
Çêtir bû.
It was better.
A dîsta me, malê me nêzîkî we darê mezin bû, we palûte. Ma
zu darê 'îdê.
Ah, I saw, our house was near that big tree, that oak. Our
press worked quickly during Eid.
Sibê 'îdê, du roj, sê roj, çar roj 'îdê...
Morning of Eid, two days, three days, four days of Eid...
Dadî da tin, hêlê da didan, ê sibê ba tana, heta nîvê şevê
xwo, xê dikişandin, da tirin, eb wem yanê destê merê li bin
tûndûz in û mêrava.
They gave force... until morning came, until midnight, they
pulled the line, they brought out, with men's hands under
the... and the water channels.
Didûtan dorê 'îdê.
They smoked around Eid.
Malê me rûr bû, ma'sera me ya zindî bû.
Our house was deep, our press was active.
Wanê çend nefer lê dixebitîn, zêt derdixistin, bi hewa
heywanan.
Like several people worked on it, extracted oil, with the
aid of animals.
Bergîr bûn, hêstir bûn, hesp bûn.
There were mules, there were mules, there were horses.
Zeytûnê wan hindik bûn. Zeytûnê me yên... yanî kalê me, babê
me, kalê me, zeytûn çêkirin.
Their olives were few. Our olives of... like our
grandfather, our father, our grandfather, produced olives.
Ê zeytûna...
The olives...
Mesele, diçûn çuwal danîyan, de berê mûsim zê hano hindik bû
ê zeytûna.
For example, they went and placed sacks, back then the
season was small like this for olives.
Ê bavê no, meselen, ditirrin, 'atî 'aresa hebû. Û xota
ditirrin e.
The fathers, for example, brought them, there was a
courtyard. And they brought the lines.
Û dihêran.
And they ground them.
Zê sîn da wetî... ewa hebû, zenbîla, ditirrin e.
Then... there was that, the baskets, they brought them.
Seda diwan bi badanê bû. Mandane. Neb dexte bû.
One hundred, two hundred were by twisting. Manual. Not by
pressure.
Îsta zêt he da derxistin, da ditirin.
Now they extract oil there, then bring it.
Dûra...
Then...
Însan ştê pêst e. Zeytûn pir bû, milt pir bû, matbez çêtir
in.
Humans are skinned. Olives were plenty, harvest was plenty,
the presses are better.
Matbez çêtir in...
The presses are better...
Matbez, se çuwal, disê çuwal, sê se çuwal datînê em bên,
rind bû.
The press, a hundred sacks, two hundred sacks, three hundred
sacks they put, we brought, it was good.
Ê ma hono dî... yanî berê dî ya ma'serê me hebû, û yek li o
cîwê da ma'sere dewr hebû.
And we saw like this... like before we saw our press
existed, and one in that place, the press had a role.
Teb'en zeytûn zî hinda t'in we çaxê. Îsta wa zêt bû ma'serê
bû.
Of course, olives also disappeared at that time. Now that
oil belonged to the press.
Faroze, maroze tune bûn. Ê zêt têtin no benî, zêt tastî
tinda sero didirtin.
Separators didn't exist. The oil came... the oil... on top
they spilled it.
Ê zê da derxistin. Ê nota ma'ser, matbez disale vdare
zeytûna te lê tê...
And they extracted the oil. And like the press, the press...
olives come to you...
Derê we da zêt li farozê te detê teneka to.
In that place, oil comes from the separator into your tin.
Yane pir rind bû.
Like it was very good.
Yanî heya tîrmehê sê heban cismê dinê de, behs dikin, dihat
û diçû, ew axa doniya, destê Xwedê re xwarin, wek heban çi
dibûn, bi qudreta Rebê Alemê. Evro dibêjin ziyareta Xidir
Êlyasî...
Meaning, until July, regarding the three grains in the body
of the world, they talk about it, it would come and go, that
soil of the world, eating by the hand of God, how the grains
would form, by the power of the Lord of the World. Today
they call it the shrine of Khidr Elias...
Ziyareta Xidir Elî... yanî ziyaret bû. Baran mesela biharê
tê da bû... Tê da bû baran ne dibariya... yanî... tê bîra
min em dihistine, alemê mesela duwemê roj înê herin
xêrûberat, deware, berxa, mîllet ser jê dikirin.
The shrine of Khidr Ali... meaning it was a shrine. For
example, rain would come in the spring... It would come,
[but if] rain did not fall... meaning... I remember we used
to leave it, for example, on the second Friday, people would
go for charity and blessings, [sacrificing] cattle, lambs,
the people would slaughter them.
Û ban Rebê xwe, alemê dikirin... yanî... we rûyî ellim baran
pê dibariya, xêr û bereket baran dibariya. Haaa, va hebû.
And they would call upon their Lord, the world [people]
would do it... meaning... upon that face [for the sake of
that], rain would fall, rain of charity and blessing would
fall. Yes, this existed.
[Music]
[Arabic] معراتة، قرية كبيرة تتميز ببنائها بشكل متصاعد من
الأسفل إلى الأعلى، فوق سفح جبلين متقابلين.
Ma'arata, a large village distinguished by its construction
rising progressively from the bottom to the top, upon the
slopes of two facing mountains.
[Arabic] يجاور القرية وادي يدعى الوادي العميق، "Galyê Kûr".
وفي القرية وبجوار النبعة شجرة بلوط معمرة، يناهز عمرها
الأربعمائة عام.
Adjacent to the village is a valley called the Deep Valley,
"Galyê Kûr". In the village, next to the spring, stands an
ancient oak tree, nearly four hundred years old.
[Arabic] ذات ساق ثخين يحتاج إلى أربعة أشخاص ممدودي الأيادي
ومتماسكين حتى يتمكنوا من ضم ساق الشجرة بأكملها.
It has a thick trunk that requires four people with
outstretched arms holding hands to be able to embrace the
entire trunk of the tree.
[Arabic] في القرية معصرتين قديمتين، دشنتا داخل كهفين من
الكهوف المنتشرة في القرية.
In the village, there are two old presses, inaugurated
inside two of the caves scattered throughout the village.
[Arabic] عرفت هذه القرية أيضا بشخصيات فنية ومهنية وتراثية.
منهم علي رمزي عازف البزق، وأيضا محمد رمزي، عازف البزق
والنجار والحلاق.
This village was also known for its artistic, vocational,
and heritage figures. Among them, Ali Ramzi, the Buzuq
player, and also Muhammad Ramzi, the Buzuq player,
carpenter, and barber.
[Arabic] خالد بكر، عازف بزق متألق. وأيضا المايسترو علي،
والمشرف على الأجهزة الصوتية في المناسبات والأعراس. والمطرب
التراثي عبد الرؤوف. والفنان المتألق محمد جاويش.
Khalid Bakr, a brilliant Buzuq player. Also Maestro Ali, the
supervisor of sound equipment at events and weddings. And
the heritage singer Abdulraouf. And the brilliant artist
Muhammad Jawish.
[Music]
[Arabic] وأيضا هاوية جمع التراث الزراعي والتاريخي، يشار أحمد
شقلي. العائلة المتألقة بالرقص الفلكلوري والفردي، عائلة رشيد
ريبي.
And also the amateur collector of agricultural and
historical heritage, Yashar Ahmed Chaqali. The family
brilliant in folklore and solo dancing, the Rashid Ribi
family.
Ehlen wa sehlen, eleykum selam. Ez Ehmed Ebdilrehman Ebû
Şiyar, jimara tê, tewelûd 56. Ez bixwe mwezef bûm li Heleb.
Welcome, peace be upon you. I am Ahmed Abdulrahman Abu
Shiyar, my number [referring to ID/reg], born in '56. I was
personally an employee in Aleppo.
Me kar kir, em badî em teqawid derketin, em fitilîn hatin
gundê xwe rûniştin. Badî em li gund rûniştin, de me kar kir,
em vir de çûn, wê de çûn, em şkora misê kirin, em de aciz
bûn.
We worked, and after we retired, we returned and settled in
our village. After sitting in the village, we started
working, going here and there, we did some pruning/tree
work, and we got annoyed [tired].
Wa çaxê êzing jî hebûn, kûtkê zeytûna. Me got ka em şkora...
wele kêserkî me hebû, çakûç me hebû. Yanî karê... ewê mijî
tune bû bixwe, va tiştî ne şixulî me, ne caran ne şixulî me.
At that time there was firewood, olive stumps. We said let's
do the pruning... well, we had a [dull] saw, we had a
hammer. Meaning the work... there wasn't even a proper saw
itself, we hadn't worked on this thing, we hadn't worked on
it before.
Mi şkora derxist û eşkora rû bi rû me, derdixist, wa pê te
seleh dibûm, va tiştan min rid derxist. Wek pênc şeş meh e
tê de şixulî me ji va tiştî de. Erê.
I brought out the pruning shears and openly faced it, I
brought it out, I was fixing it up, I brought these things
out. It's been like five or six months I've been working on
this thing. Yes.
Û hav tiştî me çêkir, tiştê ji eslen hewa ê berê... ê kolkê
me, va tişta pê ow dikir, gi dar lûxe, gi şixre ye, gi
hefcar e.
And we made these things, things originally from the past...
our plowing/stubble tools, they used to do that with these
things, whether it's the wooden roller, the wooden harrow,
or the plow beam.
Yanî berê dîrektor tune bûn, bi cot û bi dewar dajotin.
Şixre... dîrektor û der tune bûn, bi dewar dîsa şixre ow
dikirin.
Meaning, in the past, there were no tractors, they plowed
with a pair [of animals] and cattle. The harrow... there
were no tractors or threshers, again they used cattle to do
the harrowing.
Gi genim e, gi nîsk in, lê bar dikirin, dianîn ser bêderê.
Cercer hebû... cercer jî me pê dewar, girêdida, me pê hûr
dikir. Mehnî genim e, gi nîsk in, gi nok in, me pê dihêra.
Işta va tiştana hebûn.
Whether wheat, or lentils, they loaded them and brought them
to the threshing floor. There was a threshing sled
(cercer)... we tied the threshing sled to the cattle, and we
crushed [the crops] with it. Meaning wheat, or lentils, or
chickpeas, we ground/threshed with it. So, these things
existed.
Dergûş heye, dergûş ê textî bûn. Berê qîçik çûçik dikirinê,
dihezandin, darda dikirin. Pê işta, pê disekinîn.
There is a cradle, cradles were made of wood. In the past,
they put the small children in it, rocked them, hung them
up. With that, they stood/stayed.
Ew tune bû dest... berê va... ewê dask, hedîs, destar genim
bikutan û derbixin. Tûmaq me çêdikir ji... avê kefir... me
dikuta, menî wa kepeka jê derkeve.
There was no... in the past this... that sickle, iron, hand-
mill to pound the wheat and extract it. We made sheaves
from... [unclear, possibly place name or material]... we
pounded it, meaning so the chaff would come off.
Me paşîngê delûb hebû, paşê destar hebû, me dihêra, wa
genimê, badî me kelandin, me hûr dikir, dikir bilxur, menî
işta xwarinê.
Later we had a delûb [winnowing/cleaning tool], then we had
a hand-mill, we ground it, that wheat, after we boiled it,
we crushed it, made it into bulgur, meaning, well, for
eating.
Eyy, hewa yek, yek, tiştê me yê kevn e. Wele xweşiya xwe
tenê hewa me gîş darê zeytûnê hew kir. Kutek min dipaqijand,
çi cî, vî mîsekir [mûşekir], neqlekê min hane kutek paqij,
mîsekir ji cî da, wekî neqşa derdikeve.
Yes, that is one, one of our old things. Well, its own
beauty, we just finished with the olive trees. When I
cleaned a stump/trunk, what a place, I pruned this, once I
cleaned a stump like this, pruned it from the spot, it comes
out like a painting.
Mîgî kutkê zeytûnê min dipaqijand û min ji wa kutkê zeytûnê
çêdikirin va... ewna.
I cleaned/polished the olive stump, and from those olive
stumps I made these... those things.
Mara... berê kanî hebûn. Kaniya Maratê me‘rûf bû, digot ew
henarê di Maratê. Berê di Basûtek dageriyan, henarê Maratê
me‘rûf bûn. Kaniya xwe av pir bû, jiber dima, diçû teva
Efrînê dibû.
Mara[te]... in the past there were springs. The Spring of
Marate was famous, they spoke of the pomegranates of Marate.
In the past, they went down to Bassouta, the pomegranates of
Marate were famous. Its spring had much water, it remained
over, it went and flowed into the Afrin river.
Ê de henar hebûn, wa çaxê. Paşîngê de henar hişk bûn, dar
bûn. De her yek arta gî fitilîn bûn zeytûn. Berê va zeytûna
tune bûn. Me nûq diçandin, me bîstan diçandin, yanî de va
kara me dikir. Em li gund rûniştî bûn yanî wa çaxê.
So there were pomegranates at that time. Later the
pomegranates dried up, became wood. So everyone turned their
land into olives. In the past, these olives weren't there.
We planted chickpeas, we planted vegetable gardens, meaning
we did this work. We were living in the village, meaning, at
that time.
Ê, badî ew bûn, noqan erd nema, gî bûn e zeytûn, û gî kask,
kar mar jî nema. De her kes berdabûn, yek çû li Heleb şkora
şixulî.
So, after that happened, there was no land left for
chickpeas, it all became olives, and all green, there was no
work left. So everyone left, one went to Aleppo to do
pruning/work.
Û dîsa ehbab, cîran, hewa li hene, em dihatin cem hev de, em
tên bêvarê em şkora rûdinin, em weraqa dilîzin, yanî... em
lefdê rûdinin. Em hezkirin zêberê çêtir bûye. Elhemdu
lîllah, rind e.
And again friends, neighbors, those who are here, we would
come together, we come in the evening, we sit like this, we
play cards, meaning... we sit together. Our love [for each
other] was better than before. Praise be to God, it is good.
Wele hene. Hene yekî din heye, bixwe berber di şixulî. De
hew jî va kîrê çêdike, biçqo destgirtê biçqo çêdike, yanî
cota, qol, molan, hene, şixre û cota çêdike. Yanî tişt
miştan çêdike.
Well, there are. There is another one, he works as a barber
himself. He also makes these things, he makes small handles
for knives, meaning plows, armrests, etc., they exist, he
makes harrows and plows. Meaning he makes bits and bobs.
Û heye jî yekî din, Ehmed Ebû Şiyar, vê re dibêjin... Ehmed
Şiyar heye. Hew jî tiştê... gav... me yê kevn, esasî. Gî va
tiştana kom dike, turasê me, di kal û... kalê di me. Gi mi
cem heye, va tişta heye. Ê hew jî wa tiştî kom dike.
And there is also another one, Ahmed Abu Shiyar, they call
him... There is Ahmed Shiyar. He also [collects] things...
steps... our old, essential things. He collects all these
things, our heritage, of our grandfathers and... our
ancestors. It is with me, these things exist. So, he also
collects those things.
Na, ê... ihtîmamê xwe em dibêjin, mehnî qişke bila
bizanibin, va cîlê ecer derdikeve, zanibin berê me çi kar
dikir. Bi çi tûnî me va kara dikir, yanî.
No, the... our interest, we say, meaning let the kids know,
this new generation that is coming out, let them know what
work we did in the past. With what difficulty we did this
work, meaning.
Hewa mehnî bimîne turasê me yê Kurmanc, cî kî em pê
dişixulîn e. Gi şixre ye, va tiştana işta, gi yekî kevn e
berê.
That implies that our Kurdish heritage should remain, the
place where we worked. Whether it's the harrow, these things
now, or any old thing from the past.
Ez dixwazim em ji hevdu ra rind bin. Em wekî ew tî, em gi bi
hevdu ra yek bin. Wekî ew tî, gi li ser mirikê ye, li ser
dawetê ye, li ser naxweşiyê ye, em li hevdu wenxwin [werin
xwedî], em hevdu ji bîr nekin.
I wish for us to be good to each other. Like that, that we
may all be one with each other. Like that, whether it's at a
funeral, at a wedding, or during sickness, let us look after
each other, let us not forget each other.
Û tiştê berê em ji bîr bikin... gi berê çi hebû, wa tiştî em
ji bîr bikin. Tiştni ecer em pêda bikin û pê da herin.
And the things of the past, let us remember [lit: forget,
but context implies 'recall' or he misspoke and meant 'let's
not forget']... whatever existed in the past, let us
remember those things. Let us create new things and move
forward with them.
Ez Can, babê Remzî, meqamê turaz ji we xwestin, emê daxin
jêra... Xemê Zalim.
I am Jan, father of Remzi, you requested a heritage Maqam,
we will play for it/you... "Cruel Sorrow" (Xemê Zalim).
Pêşkêş dikim ji bo... Mihemedê Elî Tijo... ji bunyana gundê
Hesen Dêra, hezar rehmet li gora wî be, û li hecî meytê te
hazira be.
I present this for... Muhammad Ali Tijo... from the
buildings/foundations of the village of Hesen Dêra, a
thousand mercies be upon his grave, and upon all the
deceased of you who are present.
Wî jî xoşgir Xemê Zalim. Em kanibin bibêjin, ji wî dama Xemê
Zalim. Ax Xemê Zalim...
He also liked "Xemê Zalim". If we are able to sing/say it,
we give "Xemê Zalim" for him. Oh, Cruel Sorrow...
[Music playing - Buzuq Instrumental]
[Music continues]
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Bi xêr hatin.
Welcome.
Bi xêr hatin ser çavên me. Ez ji gundê Maratê me, berîkiya
ji malê Çiwîş im. Ez Elî lawê Remzî Xaçê me. Bavê Remzî.
You are welcome upon our eyes. I am from the village of
Maratê, from the section of the Çiwîş family. I am Ali, son
of Remzi Xaçê. Father Remzi.
Hûn bi xêr hatin ser çavên me.
You are welcome upon our eyes.
Fena cem me, yanî di bav û pîrên me de, em pê dazin dikin...
aîla me bi şiklê giştî em ji fen hez dikin. Çimkî mezinê me,
em guhdariya fen dikin. Ciyê destê me dan tîşandin.
Art among us, meaning among our fathers and grandfathers, we
boast of it... our family generally loves art. Because our
elders, we listen to art. They made our hands sore
[playing].
Yanî di aîla me de, hinek dibêjin dengbêj... hene...
dengbêj... em karin bêjin... mekin hene.
Meaning in our family, some say 'dengbêj' (bards)... there
are... bards... we can say... there are experts.
Tembûrvan jî jê çêdibin.
Tambur players also come from them.
Tembûrvan di aîla me de pirr in.
There are many tambur players in our family.
Ê... hîwa ye ev xwa... ev xwa hîwaya coka... di hîsê me de
hatiye çandin, va mûsîqa xwa.
Uh... it is a hobby... this hobby... this music itself has
been planted in our feelings.
Mûsîqa jî yanî... alek jî hez dike mûsîqa. Mûsîqa rinde
yanî.
Music as well... people also love music. Music is good, you
know.
De men... ez bi xwa... ez gîştimê bavê min kilamcî bû, Xwedê
rehma xwa lê ke bavê min Remzî Xaçê, bavê min Remzî.
So I... personally... when I reached [that age], my father
was a singer, may God have mercy on him, my father Remzi
Xaçê, my father Remzi.
Bapîrê min Ehmedê Reşo, bavê min bi xwa kilamcî bûn.
My grandfather Ehmedê Reşo, my father himself were singers.
Ez di sefê didûyê sêsê bûm diçûm mektebê... ez elimîm...
yanî meraqa tembûrê... hîwaya tembûrê bi min girt û min
deqet pê girt, berber me da.
I was in the second or third grade going to school... I
learned... meaning the interest in the tambur... the hobby
of the tambur seized me and I focused on it, it pulled us
forward.
Bavê min dida kilama... me guhê dida... em jî elimîn toraz
jî, em jî elimîn mûsîqa jî... em elimîn fen yanî.
My father used to sing songs... we listened... we learned
the traditional songs, we learned music too... we learned
art, basically.
Û pêşiya me giya yanî... qonmiş fen û mûsîqa dibûn.
And before us... they were engaged in art and music.
Hîwa ye yanî... ev tiştekî, aîla me di hîsêiyayê de hatiye
çandin.
It's a hobby... this is something, in our family, it has
been planted in the feelings.
Me bi kêr helanî? Me bi giyayê helanî?
Did we pick it up by utility? Did we pick it up naturally?
Yanî... me bi pirra ra... pirr cimeet hatin cem me û em jî
pirr çûn pirr cimeeta...
Meaning... we with many... many gatherings came to us and we
went to many gatherings...
Berê giya, em elimîn va kilamê toraz.
First of all, we learned these traditional songs.
Û... hunerek... me ji Elî Tico rehmetî jî, ciyê wî dinê be,
ji wî jî me zêde dikirî, hinek tiştin wî jî di hîsê me de
hatin çandin. Hez jê tê heye, xweş... yanî... maqamê xweş wê
hebin.
And... an art... from the late Elî Tico too, may his place
be paradise, we benefited from him too, some of his things
were planted in our feelings. There is love for it, good...
meaning... he had good maqams.
Me ji wî jî girtin, ji xelkê dinê jî... ji Cemîl Horo me jê
birin...
We took from him too, from other people too... from Cemîl
Horo we took...
Me guhdariya wî jî kir, me tembûr jî jê bir û me... lehnê
kilama jî me jê birin.
We listened to him too, we took the tambur [style] from him
and we... took the melody of songs from him.
Elî Tico, em rûniştin, em pirr ba rûniştin, bes vê taliyê em
bi hev re rûniştin... ê... berê dihat gundê Maratê.
Elî Tico, we sat [together], we sat together a lot,
especially lately we sat together... uh... he used to come
to Maratê village.
Heta em kanin bibêjin jî, em ji dûr de xaltiya hev du jî
tên.
We can even say, we are distant maternal cousins.
Yanî... fen, ya heyatê ji her yekî re vedike. Û hewa
ciwaniyê te ye.
Meaning... art, it opens life for everyone. And it is the
atmosphere of your youth.
Ya... ji êşa derbirîn... hewayê birîn, mûsîqê di wî, kilamê
di wî... ya ji Elî Tico, ya ji Cemîl Horo, Xwedê rehma xwa
lê kin... kî cimeeta hazira be.
Or... to express pain... the air of the wound, the music in
it, the song in it... whether from Elî Tico, or from Cemîl
Horo, may God have mercy on them... whoever is present in
the gathering.
Ê hîwa ye, meraq e.
It is a hobby, an interest.
Yanî mûsîqa ta her... û fenê te jî tebe'en heye. Û hîwayê ji
her... kanê ji her yekî re çêbibe.
Meaning music is always... and your art naturally exists.
And the hobby... can happen for anyone.
Ê min ez li mal lê dixim. Ba zewac çêdibin, wekî we tên cem
min, ez lê dixim.
As for me, I play at home. Sometimes marriages happen,
[people] like you come to me, I play.
Ba dawet dibin, diwacînin ez darim.
Sometimes there are weddings, they invite me, I go.
Fenan nînin hene... yanî fenanîn ji aîla me de hene... wek
din kes pirr fenan tune ne di gundê me de.
There aren't [many] artists... meaning there are artists in
our family... otherwise there aren't many artists in our
village.
Mihemed Şo, Wehîd... lawê xalê min e... Evana kalê Tirkiyê
ne.
Mihemed Şo, Wehîd... my cousin... They are the old ones of
Turkey.
[Muzîk]
Maratê, we haven't seen an owner, we have been in the
village. Meaning we haven't seen an owner, we were in
Maratê. And until today, Marat is ancient. The world is old,
you know. And the village, we haven't seen an owner, we were
with the villagers.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Lê vurxûnê, vurxûnê...
Oh Vurxûn, Vurxûn...
Delalê şur şêrînê...
Beautiful one, with the sweet face...
Lê vurxûnê, vurxûnê...
Oh Vurxûn, Vurxûn...
Delalê şur şêrînê...
Beautiful one, with the sweet face...
Xeyrê ji te min nabîne...
I see no good from you...
Wer derman ke birînê...
Come, cure the wound...
Şurxweşê şurşêrînê...
Pleasant faced, sweet faced...
Xeyrê ji te min nabîne...
I see no good from you...
Wer derman ke birînê...
Come, cure the wound...
Lê vurxûnê, vurxûnê...
Oh Vurxûn, Vurxûn...
Şurxweşê şurşêrînê...
Pleasant faced, sweet faced...
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Lê vurxûnê, vurxûnê...
Oh Vurxûn, Vurxûn...
Delalê şur şêrînê...
Beautiful one, with the sweet face...
Lê vurxûnê, vurxûnê...
Oh Vurxûn, Vurxûn...
Delalê şur şêrînê...
Beautiful one, with the sweet face...
Xeyrê ji te min nabîne...
I see no good from you...
Wer derman ke birînê...
Come, cure the wound...
Hingivê tevlî rûn e...
[You are] honey mixed with butter...
Zerka te bi kûr ve nîne...
Your paleness is not deep...
Ziravê hatim mala we...
Slender one, I came to your house...
Silav çûyî te ne da min...
I greeted, you did not give me [a reply]...
Min dît deka te li min kir...
I saw the trick you played on me...
Dibê xanê ez nas nakim...
She says "Dear, I don't know you..."
Çima kî ye vayî kalê...
"Why, who is this old man..."
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Belê, ji gundewarê Maratê, ji yên kevneşopî û tiştên
kevnar...
Yes, from the countryside of Maratê, from the traditions and
ancient things...
Me îro li vî gundewarî jî gelek tiştên kevnar dîtin.
Today, in this countryside, we saw many ancient things.
Û me gelek hunermend jî nas kirin.
And we met many artists as well.
Li benda me bin, di beşek nû de ji bernameya me...
Stay tuned, in a new episode of our program...
Yê gundê me.
"Yê Gundê Me" (Of Our Village).
[Muzîk]
[Music]