Ka nêçîna orpadara?
Where is the map of Europe?
Cama hişk ke re.
Dry the glass.
Vêce leke li ber pir na...
Then the stain isn't much in front...
Ew çiye leke? Pênc, deh tişt pırne.
What is that stain? Five, ten things are too much.
A dewar têda av dıdın? Vêjî û vêjî ne?
Do they water livestock in it? This and that?
Heryekî, heryekî otî, awe xwa ser fıkiri.
Each one... hotel... thinks of himself.
Ne bûr aşê berî şikeftê...
No, pass the mill before the cave...
Bîna derk, kabirjîkê vir çêdikiran du diwêr de diçûna.
Look at the door, they made a tomb here going into two
walls.
Ehu, de işê xwa bike lo... tiştek...
Uh, just do your job man... something...
Silavê teyê bi miletî...
Your greetings to the nation...
Dile none...
[Unintelligible]
Ya selam, çar... ay pênc.
Oh my, four... oh five.
Merheba ji we ra hevalno, hûru dîsa vîdyoyeke xweş, kîbar em
bo we ra ne.
Hello to you friends, today again we are with you for a
nice, lovely video.
Dîsa em vegeryan hatin gundê Kîmarê.
We have returned to the village of Kimar again.
Neqla çûyî me kêm teswîr kir, em manikanî merata mesûrê
meşîkî...
Last time we filmed very little, we stayed...
[unintelligible]...
...me go xelekekê emê werin li vî gundê Kîmarê wera teswîr
kin.
...we said we would come for an episode to film this village
of Kimar for you.
Teben hûru, em hatine gundê Kîmarê, saet dehê sibê ne.
So today, we came to the village of Kimar, it is ten in the
morning.
Xweşk û birakê me jê me xwestina gundê Kîmarê em keveran
teswîr kin.
Our sisters and brothers asked us to film the ruins of the
village of Kimar.
Tebîetek pir xweş e, wînê bi me ra bin, emê tiştê xweş wera
derxin, tiştê eserî emê wera derxin.
The nature is very nice, stay with us, we will show you nice
things, we will show you historical things.
Xweşkek me jî ji me xwestî emke rehmetî tirba Gindyo
biseurînin...
A sister of ours also asked us to film the tomb of the late
Gindyo...
...u emê naha derbas bin.
...and we will head there now.
Bûrin micazet.
Excuse us.
Merheba mûtabiînê me, hûn çawan in, baş in, sihet xweş?
Hello our followers, how are you, are you well, is your
health good?
Hêvîdarim rihet bin.
I hope you are comfortable.
Erê dîsa hîro em hatin vîdyoyeke xweş, kîbar em wera çêkin.
Yes, today again we came to make a nice, lovely video for
you.
Bi me ra bin heta toliya vîdyoyê, bîr mekin layk û îştîrakê
me ra bidin...
Stay with us until the end of the video, don't forget to
give us a like and subscription...
...û te'lîqna xweş, kîbar me ra yazmîş kin.
...and write us nice, lovely comments.
Saet xweş, micazet.
Thanks, excuse me.
Erê hevalno, me go vî gundo tiştê eserî têda pir e...
Yes friends, we said there are many historical things in
this village...
Gundê Kîmarê, tiştê eserî têda pir e, emê naha wera teswîr
kin.
The village of Kimar, there are many historical things in
it, we will film them for you now.
Bi me ra bin em tê derbas nav gund bin.
Stay with us, we are passing into the village.
Silav û rêzê me ji miletê gundê Kîmarê ra hene...
Our greetings and respect to the people of the village of
Kimar...
...ser serê me ne, ser çavê me ne.
...they are on our heads, on our eyes.
Çi dûr dibe, çi nîzik dibe, agir silav dikim.
Whether far or near, I greet them warmly.
Hewşê xwe jî ketin nav çavê da ne.
Their courtyards are also right in front of the eyes.
De înşalah vîdyoyê me bi ecibînin.
God willing, you will like our video.
Mala te'lîqê we pir bin, le ser kin heta toliya vîdyoyê...
May your comments be many, watch until the end of the
video...
Manî vîdyoyê me jî bişuxilînin...
Meaning, share our video as well...
...manî kesê vîdyoyê me nedîtine, bi wan gihînin jî...
...meaning, let it reach those who haven't seen our video
too...
...u laykê we pir bin, kesê vîdyo nedîye vîdyo cam wan jî
derkeve.
...and may your likes be many, so the video appears for
those who haven't seen it.
We dîye gi tiştê eserî ye.
You saw, it is all historical things.
Înşelah naha ezê wera rind teswîr kim.
God willing, I will film it well for you now.
Erê hevalno li vî derî jî em hatin gundê Kîmarê ne.
Yes friends, here we have come to the village of Kimar.
Teben pismamî me kê me ra dikeve cewlê nav gund...
So, our cousin here will take a tour with us in the
village...
...tiştê eserî pêş me ke, saeto genda xweş.
...to show us the historical things, a pleasant time to you.
Hîn neqla çûyî me we'd daye, em nikanî batona...
Since last time we promised, we cannot [break our word] to
the cousins...
Erê Xwedê pêxember jêgi razî be, û ji miletê gundê Kîmarê,
ser serê me ne, ser çavê me ne.
Yes, may God and the Prophet be pleased with him, and the
people of Kimar village, they are on our heads and eyes.
Hûnê nuka me ra derkevin cewlake.
You will now go on a tour with us.
Şebab çîçkê ew dikin... fay dikin...
The guys are doing a little... waving...
Tamam haca ew nekirne.
Okay Hajj, they didn't do that.
Me go gundê Kîmarê hewşê xwe çiqas hewş in?
We said, how many households are in the village of Kimar?
Wela dora sê sed hewş... sê sed û pêncî hewş heye.
Well, around three hundred households... there are three
hundred and fifty households.
Hewş? Sêkanê xwe gi heye?
Households? Are all its inhabitants there?
Sêkanê xwe nîvî heye nîvî tine ye.
Half of its inhabitants are there, half are not.
Nîvî heye nîvî tine ye, ne?
Half are there, half are not, right?
Bi Kîmarê bi çi tê naskirin?
What is Kimar known for?
Eserê xwe tê naskirin... bi dewarê xwe... mesela şîr û mast,
penêr û dehr û...
It is known for its ruins... for its livestock... for
example milk and yogurt, cheese and butter and...
Tiştî wan? Çêlek pir ne?
Their stuff? Are there many cows?
Teben ne.
Of course.
Ma jêgi laf na dibên çêlek?
Don't you guys also say 'çêlek' [cow]?
Em jî dibên çêl.
We also say 'çêl'.
Em jî dibên çêl, lavna dibên çêlek, ne wîn waha dibên?
We also say 'çêl', the boys say 'çêlek', isn't that what you
say?
Em jî dibên çêl.
We also say 'çêl'.
Kijan gunda dibê çêlek?
Which village says 'çêlek'?
Xwedê jêder do ye.
God knows.
Me go sê sed hewş e ne? Tabe'ê nahiye... bajarê Efrîn...
Efrîn na nahiye ye?
We said three hundred households, right? It belongs to the
district... the city of Afrin... isn't it Afrin district?
Nahiye Şêrawa ve ra tê.
It comes under the Sherawa district.
Tabe'ê navçeya Şêrawa ye, tabe'ê Efrîn e.
It belongs to the sub-district of Sherawa, belonging to
Afrin.
Ka bi me ra bin em derbas cihê eserî bin, nav gund jî emê
wera çêkin, ka bi me ra bin.
Come with us, let's pass to the historical places, we will
film the inside of the village for you too, come with us.
Ew kevir no go wane... Boni sikini no kevin?
Those stones... They stand like that, they won't fall?
No kevin, cî da...
They won't fall, in place...
Wela biro.
By God, brother.
Lê la însanê berê cebar bîn.
Look man, the people of the past were powerful.
Em man caholo me ra da ne ke?
Are you giving us this young man?
Xolo no we...
Uncle, not him...
Çi kêfî û niştine?
How is the mood and sitting?
We ber wela...
Like this, by God...
Işke dey ka.
Look at that a bit.
Erê, teb go vî derî ra dibên birc ne?
Yes, so they call this place the tower, right?
Erê.
Yes.
Erê hevalno li vî derê... di vî derkê ra dibên birc.
Yes friends, here... they call this place the tower.
Wek dît kevirê ginde çû seref disikinin...
As you saw, how the massive stones stand in rows...
Maşalah.
Mashallah.
Hey... wekî oda ye çi ye gi qanterm çêkirine.
Wow... it's like a room or something, they built arches.
Seke li vî derî...
Look at this place...
Resm hene?
Are there pictures?
Te be şeqaf divê deran çi ye?
Look at the cavern in this place, what is it?
Na na, ewa waki kele bûn.
No no, those were like castle parts.
Ha wera bes em vê sêkin.
Come here, let's just look at this.
Hevalno, avo manî çi ye?
Friends, what does this mean?
Avo bîr vira ye.
This is a well here.
A bîr e?
Ah, it's a well?
A bîra kevnare.
Ah, an ancient well.
Guna kele daye ne?
From the time of the castle?
Teben li wir.
Of course, from there.
A dewar têda av didin? Vêjî û vêjî ne?
Do they water livestock in it? This and that?
Erê...
Yes...
Berê av dikişandin bi zembîla... baş e vira kûr e?
Before they pulled water with baskets... Is it deep here?
Haf... lê av tehta jî têbûn wekî kursiya çêkirine.
Look... look, the rocks were also there, they made them like
chairs.
Nezo mavo...
I don't know, this...
Ew jî wekî wî ye fekî şkandine.
That one is like it too, they broke the opening.
Tirba ne.
It's a tomb.
Xalo ew jî tirba ye?
Uncle, is that a tomb too?
Erê tirba ye, haho.
Yes, it's a tomb, over here.
Serbaz... dilê me.
Soldier... our heart.
Çu halê te? Tu ji vî gundî yî xalo?
How are you? Are you from this village, uncle?
Belê.
Yes.
Ser serê min, tahr dibî navê çi ye?
On my head, may I ask what the name is?
Abû Seîd? Ser serê min, ser çavê min. Dilê min.
Abu Said.
Abu Said? On my head, on my eyes. My heart.
Avo tirba ye...
This is a tomb...
Erê.
Yes.
Romani ye bu?
Was it Roman?
Tirba Romani ye, ew kî ye.
It's a Roman tomb, that's what it is.
Belê nake kî ye?
It doesn't show who it is?
No, belê nake, bes eser e, yê Romanya ne.
No, it doesn't show, but it's a ruin, of the Romans.
Ecib hewa xetayê gunda ser e.
Strange how the village line is on it.
Ewle belê nake qlaftina.
It doesn't show, the cover is gone.
Ha wa yek li bera ha yek li bera.
Look there's one over there, one over there.
Yek li wîr jî heye tirbe.
There is a tomb over there too.
Têbê awê qîçik çûçik e.
Look, that one is tiny, small.
E çûçik in ew.
Those are small.
Havo tirba mezin e, wer xolo wer mir wer.
This is a big tomb, come uncle, come man come.
Avo jî ê qîçik çûçik e tirba ne? Bêlî kevirê xwa çûçik e.
This one is also a tiny, small tomb, right? It's evident its
stone is small.
Erê...
Yes...
Avo mezin e.
This one is big.
Avo mezin e, eserê mezin e.
This one is big, a big ruin.
Avo resma dîsa li ser e?
Is this a drawing on it again?
Erê.
Yes.
Xolo, af qantermo manî çi ye?
Uncle, what does this arch mean?
Xulo avo wekî... berê... qesr...
Uncle, this is like... before... a palace...
...kele, wekî kele.
...a castle, like a castle.
Erê erê, go wekî qopiya wona çêkirine.
Yes yes, they built it like a copy of those.
Seke ono wekî...
Look like that...
Avo eslê wanda qesra Romani bû.
Its origin was a Roman palace.
E avo hewayê xwe bû...
And this was their area...
Kele xwa... kenîse xwa ha va.
Their castle... their church is right here.
Xwa ne kenîse, avo kenîse jêr e.
Not the church itself, the church is below.
Qesra jor e mezin e ha wa.
The upper palace is big, right there.
Destê ya ni qestî min berê tim hono vekirî bî, hono dika
tinê çe?
I mean, my intention is, was it always open here before, or
was it closed?
Na... dorê xugî girtî bû...
No... around it was closed...
...heyet... derê xugî girtî bû, hewra gi girtî ye.
...walls... its doors were closed, all of it was closed.
Yanê qopa der tine ye?
Meaning there is no door arch?
Na.
No.
Qopa heys bêle dike.
The arch is barely visible.
Belê dike.
It is visible.
Ko wera em derbas bin.
Come, let's pass.
Ko wera pismam em derbas bin.
Come cousin, let's move on.
Evi nîvê wana bigir.
Capture the middle of those.
Tê bikeve, ewil doye tê bikeve.
Enter, enter first.
Bîntaze kevir bikem.
[Unintelligible]
Mekava ba.
Don't fall, man.
Mışka, xafire leke...
Mice, diggers [unintelligible]...
Avo qopiya gund e ne?
This is the village arch, right?
Baş e Xalo, deqa kamîra çîçkê li vî resmî jî bigire, ev resm
û...
Alright Uncle, let the camera take a moment on this drawing,
this drawing and...
Neqşên li vêr çêkirine.
The carvings made here.
Ev neqş e, çî ye, di dêrê da ye xalê min.
This carving, what is it, it is inside the church, my
nephew.
Berê dêr xeybe?
It was a church before?
Ewa ro... wekî ro ye.
That is sun... like a sun.
Ev o seke...
This one, look...
Selîbîn hatin, hewaqa xalê xistin, Îslam hatin, seke,
Allah...
The Crusaders came, they put that mark, Islam came, look,
Ee.
Yes.
Her yekî, her yekî hatî, ewê xwe ser çêkiriye.
Everyone, everyone who came, made their own mark on top.
Ev o di eslê xwe da, berî Roman, Bîzentîn û hewa... seke, ro
ye ev o, ro a kê ye?
Originally, before the Romans, Byzantines and those... look,
this is the sun, whose sun is it?
Kurd bûn.
They were Kurds.
E Kurd bûn.
Yes, they were Kurds.
Ewa.
Yes.
Paşî gap...
Then the conversation...
Her, her yek hatî, her qewmek hat, îşaretek xwe daniye ser.
Every, everyone who came, every tribe that came, put their
own sign on it.
Her, her yekî remzek xwe çêkir ser.
Every, everyone made their own symbol on it.
Seke, ev o qopî ye.
Look, this is a mace (scepter).
Ev o qopî ye, ne?
This is a mace, right?
Lê ev o seke, hot girtin.
But look at this one, it was covered.
Aha.
Eva hewê xane.
This is of that place.
Ka cihê kewirî gindirîne?
Where is the place where the stone was rolled?
Lê, kewir seha bi dotgirtin e ev o.
But, the stone is solid for closing/locking, this one.
Himm.
Hmmm.
Qopî ya xwe li vir.
His mace is here.
Li vir jî wekî curnekî heye.
There is also something like a basin here.
Ew jî wekî, ewî di serî da av e, yan texzîn tişt çêdikirin.
That is also like, that one on top is for water, or they
made storage things.
Mm.
Ev o ge wekî dîkor çêkirine, ne? Neqş.
This looks like they made it as decor, right? Carving.
Erê, wekî diwêl e ev o, diwêl.
Yes, it's like a hook/ring, this one, a hook.
Eywa.
Okay.
Merbetê seke, cindê dewar, ha.
The tethering ring look, for tying animals, see.
Aa.
Ah.
Ev o cihê espê wan.
This is the place for their horses.
Ev o, pêva esp girêdidin?
This one, they tie the horse to it?
Girêdidin, cihê xwarina wan.
They tie them, their eating place.
Erê, ev o nuh... gelo...
Yes, this is now... wonder...
Vira esp pêva girêdidin, vira jî cihê ewê bî...
Here they tie the horse to it, and here would be the place
of...
Xwarinê. Vêra wekî kayê dero dikirine çivê?
Eating. Would they put straw/hay here inside?
Kayê fî, werisî, giyayî didanê.
Straw, ropes, grass they gave them.
Bivî alî va girêdidin, yê vî alî din jî heye. Her du alî ye.
They tie on this side, there is one on the other side too.
It is on both sides.
Hinek li vî alî bin, hinek li vî alî bin. Ev o cihê dewar e.
Some would be on this side, some on that side. This is the
place for animals.
Cihê dewar e.
Right?
It's a place for animals.
Dihate...
It used to...
Ev jî ekî têda av didan?
Did they give water in this one too?
Erê av didan, av e, seke cihê avê ye.
Yes, they gave water, it's water, look it's a place for
water.
Vêli ye, xew?
It's empty, Uncle?
Yo.
No.
Tiştê dewar...
Things for animals...
Dikirin peşî dewar.
They put it in front of the animals.
Eywa.
Okay.
Xweş e, bes ew çîçkê gamor ketiyê.
It's nice, but a badger has entered it a bit.
Gamor ketiyê, na, xirab gamor ketiyê.
A badger entered, no, sadly a badger entered.
War.
Come.
Xolo we qaliknê hember me neçine lê.
Uncle, those holes in front of us, don't go there.
Hewo taqek din e bo xolê mezin.
That is another archway to the main hall.
Tamam, nekî roçkî kêvir geqlek lê ne.
Okay, lest a stone falls a lot there.
Hewo, cirek diketnê. Taqek din e. Seke yek di dêrê ardî ye,
seke.
That one, a stream enters it. It is another arch. Look, one
is at the ground level, look.
Eywa.
Okay.
Ewê gorinê erd kolane.
The grave diggers (treasure hunters) dug the ground.
Dîrek bîn berê?
Were there wooden pillars before?
Lê taqê di binî da ma ye.
But the arch remains underneath.
Eywa.
Okay.
Lê...
But...
Hewo goriyana, em zanin yanê alem tê wera dibe.
Those grave diggers, we know, meaning people come and mess
with it.
Erê erê, no hewa mero zane yanê sosis yekî xeşîm ware, mero
zane ê, ê, ê dewara, dewarî qebe.
Yes yes, no, people know, meaning if an ignorant person
comes, people know it's, uh, uh, uh animals, cattle of the
tribe.
Ê dewar e ewa.
Yes, that is for animals.
War war.
Come, come.
O vir va.
Oh, this way.
Vir va, vir va.
This way, this way.
Lê berê, berê ge bi şûra, dibil... dewarî qeba diçûn ewê.
But before, before with swords, heig... the tribal cattle
went there.
No lê, em çûn herba, erê hewa hemû girêdidan dewarê xwe,
diketin pesrê meselen de...
No but, when we went to war, yes they tied all their animals
there, they went into the corner for example...
Aha seka merbet hewa.
Aha look, the tethering ring is there.
Seke her darekî yek heye.
Look, every section has one.
Û merbetê xwe heye, meselen ber qopî xwe girêdidan derbazî
hundir dibûn.
And it has its own tether, for example they tied it before
the mace/entrance and entered inside.
Eywa, seke, bi vî va jî heye.
Okay, look, there is one on this one too.
Bi vî va jî heye, bi vî va jî heye.
There is one on this, there is one on that.
Seke.
Look.
O merbetî dewar pêva girêdidin, bi vî va heye.
Oh, the tether for tying animals, it's on this one.
Li vîr jî heye.
It's here too.
Bi vî va jî heye, o yê yêna va.
It's on this one too, oh the one over there.
Wekî garacê...
Like a garage...
Wekî garacê, wekî bi eyşê.
Like a garage, like for living.
Em dîsa ser eserê berê dimeşin.
We are walking on the ancient ruins again.
Xalê Mihemed, te serî li der ney?
Uncle Mihemed, won't you hit your head on the door?
Nizm e.
Live (Be careful).
It is low.
Yeş.
Live.
Ev o şikeft o gindirî ye?
Did this cave collapse?
Ev elî mwar lê bigir.
Film this side.
Kûr e Xolo.
It is deep, Uncle.
Bo...
Don't fall/get hurt.
Because...
Li neketnê xar û xirab.
This one here.
So you don't fall down and get ruined.
Kuçik tê da, kuçik.
A stone is inside, a stone.
Kure, kure, teh, teh, teh, teh. Were, were.
Boy, boy, come, come, come, come. Come, come.
Gamor Xolo?
Is it a badger, Uncle?
No, no hewa, hewa.
No, no that one, that one.
Bes hewa ne?
Just that one right?
E, bes o na.
Yes, just that one.
Ev o wan e, seke o na, o o na.
Ah.
These are theirs, look there, oh there.
Aa, kolandin e.
Ah, it's digging.
Na, gix ser hev e.
No, it's all on top of each other.
Ewa, têbê qopîk li wir jî heye.
Yes, you say there is a mace symbol there too.
Ew çûçik e.
That is small.
Uda wekî uda.
A room, like a room.
Ew toko diordan.
That archway of the yard.
Çî gindirî, eynî qebûl nû?
What rolled down, same as the one accepted (built) recently?
No çûçik e, ewa no mezin e.
No it is small, that one there is big.
Av jê derya, bawer bike, diket vêrê.
Water came out of it, believe me, it went in here.
Aa, lê manê av, av nemaşe, nekeve hîç vur wekî serincekê
çûçik.
Ah, meaning water, water shouldn't walk, shouldn't fall at
all here, like a small cistern.
Manê vistan e, av di wur keve.
Exactly.
Meaning it's a garden/pool, water falls there.
Manê tanzîm dikirin, çêdikirin berdidan.
Okay.
Meaning they organized it, made it and let it flow.
Eywa.
Okay.
Baqil e, însanê berê baqil bî.
Smart, the ancient human was smart.
Noko jî baqil e.
Now they are smart too.
Noko jî baqil e, lê mişkle...
Now they are smart too, but the problem...
Arê wele.
Yes, by God.
Ma hewaq.
Is that so.
Hacer li vir sewranda?
Did Hajar film here?
Eywa.
Okay.
Ma we fîlmî nebestî?
Haven't you stopped the film?
Ser wî tû, wî tû bîyozika, kom kî hacer da weke.
On that mulberry, that mulberry tree, the group that Hajar
gave like that.
Wele li ve derê jî neqş hene, bismam.
Well, there are carvings here too, cousin.
Dê nefs hewa, nefs hewa.
It's the same as that one, same as that one.
A, nefs hewa ne?
Ah, same as that one right?
A, evro wekî selîbkî çêkirine.
Ah, here they made something like a cross.
Selîb e, seke.
It is a cross, look.
Eywa.
Okay.
Seke, neqş ev li vir jî hene.
Look, carvings are here too.
Seke, haf selîb e, ne wek wî ya ye. Selîb o...
Look, this is a cross, not like that one. The cross...
Mm.
Jêr da kirine.
They brought it down.
Jor da kirine, jêr da rêsgar e, selîb jor da dirêj be, giyek
pêva.
Okay.
Jor da kirine, jêr da rêsgar e, selîb jor da dirêj be, giyek
pêva.
They put it up, down is straight, the cross should be long
upwards, with something attached.
Mm.
Berê vê kevir ro çol digirtin didînîn ser.
Before, they took these stones from the wild and put them on
top.
E bixwedê, hevo berê emloq bîn, emloq. Ge emloq bîn.
Yes by God, these were giants before, giants. They were very
huge.
No hevo, hewê xo, wekî refo ke, dare ke.
No these, its own, like a shelf, a wood piece.
Menzere çêkirine wadiye?
They made a view/scenery, is it?
Seke, jê rasm e, ev jî wekî qopîkî ye, ne?
Look, below is a picture, this is also like a mace, right?
Qopî ye hevo.
It is a mace, that one.
Aa, seke pêşiyê îşaret çêkirine.
Ah, look, they made a sign in front.
Cokî yek hot, w hevo çiye, me go meqîrê cî dêwer derî.
Someone came, and [asked] what is this, we said it's the
place of the mukhtar/leader.
Mm.
Ber vê ne, meqberê mo kevim bû.
Not before this, it was our old graveyard.
Eywa.
Okay.
Hevo mîser cînta dihot wera.
This one, the corpse/body came here.
War Xolo, em hema vro paş.
Come Uncle, let's just go back this way.
Ev o eçî do uda hene?
Are there rooms inside this?
No, ewa ê pêşiyê, bîzemonî girtin, bes ev, evoyê osar
qedîme.
No, the one in front, they took it recently, but this, this
one is ancient ruins.
Mm.
Paşê xudanê hewşê ser temam kir û wona kir.
Later the owner of the courtyard completed the top and did
that.
Seke, ev jî remz in.
Look, these are symbols too.
Hev ro qope li vir jî heye?
Is there a mace here too?
Lê.
Yes.
Hef ro qopîkê li hewa.
Here is a small mace on that one.
Qope heve?
Is this the mace?
Lê bnr, te nêr qopî me seke.
Yes look, you looked at our mace, look.
Mm.
Are hevo nuh, dibê qopî kelê li vî derê ye.
Yes that one now, they say the skull mace is in this place.
Hm.
Ha.
Zor tine lê.
There is no force on it.
Ev no emûdane ne?
These are pillars, right?
Lê emûd e.
Yes, it is a pillar.
Wele emûd ji ser şimêtî çiye, loyi min hû dero heve kevin.
By God, the pillar on the cement is nothing, in my opinion
these inside are old.
No, arê, qeske em tim e, qeske me tim e ser e.
No, yes, our story is complete, our story is complete on it.
E, Xolo, li vî derê wane her emîdkî, wane wekî kortkê têda
çêkirine.
Yes, Uncle, in this place, on every pillar, they made
something like a hollow in it.
Ecêb çira mîra dikirine?
Strange, did they make lamps for princes?
No, çira dikirin.
No, they made lamps.
Beli.
Yes.
Wekî fanûsa daro dikirin.
Like they put lanterns inside.
Tiştê xwe dikirne, tiştê xwe dikirne.
They put their things, they put their things.
O girtiye, girtiye.
Oh it is closed, closed.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Hevo seke, du sûret û şûr in, du şûr in.
Look at this one, two images and they are swords, two
swords.
Ah, kanî?
Ah, where?
Hevo pesrê çêkirine.
They made this on the corner.
A.
Ah.
Arê hevo li vî derê ye wekî du şûr a çêkirine, û orte da jî
av çêkirine.
Yes, this one is here, like they made two swords, and in the
middle they made that.
Hm.
Şûrek von e, şûrek von e.
A sword is here, a sword is here.
Eywa.
Exactly.
Hevo pesr, hevo xok e.
This corner, this is earth.
E xok e hevo.
Yes, that is earth.
Lê dîrok, dîrok... Dûrş, gî hono di...
But the history, history... beams, all here in...
Arê hevo no, gile hember me cî dîrok o heye?
Yes that one no, look opposite us, is there a place for a
beam?
Tebe'en seqf hebî seqf, şûnê bêtûnê dîrok dikirin, hono
dikirin, ser digirtin.
Of course there was a roof, a roof, instead of concrete they
used beams, they did that, they covered the top.
Dîrok, b şûnî biton, dork û...
Beams, instead of concrete, beams and...
Qamîş û...
Beams and...
Reeds and...
O da binyê, hevo di kira derdikeve.
Oh underneath, this comes out from where.
Hevoş biro çû dero, hewşê me ye hevo.
That one went outside, that is our courtyard.
Aa, hewş e we?
Ah, is it your courtyard?
Lê hewşê me ye.
Yes, it is our courtyard.
Wele pir kevnor e. Havolî mwar.
By God, it is very ancient. This side, Uncle.
Admiyone... sa kes mes ne, meselen ejnebî ware, konê diso vê
kevr no braq bîne wekê berê biken.
People... no one touches it, for example if a foreigner
comes, so that these stones remain shiny like before.
Çi qas sal da ejnebî dihat diçû, bes hane sewrandin, bes
berê, kes nedişka.
How many years foreigners came and went, only filming, but
before, no one broke it.
Xelkê me yê nuh hatin, xezîne, xezîne...
Our people of today came, treasure, treasure...
Eywa.
Okay.
Ne xezîne, xezîna çiye xalê min.
Not treasure, what treasure my nephew.
Hemû şkandin, seke, seke, seke.
They broke everything, look, look, look.
Pêkînan e?
Is it chipping/breaking?
Pêkînan e, xirab kirin.
It's breaking, they ruined it.
Çi jê neanîn.
They didn't get anything from it.
Çi jê neanîn, xera kirin.
They didn't get anything from it, they destroyed it.
Yanî kevrê xwa hene, maro konê braq bîne, ew bike.
Meaning the stones are there, one should keep them shiny, do
that.
Benav kirin.
They defaced them.
Katin e ne?
It is cut/fallen, right?
Di katin.
They cut it.
Ev o zînc, zole, dê xiz berî vê...
This zinc, sheet, will... before this...
Em hîvîdarîn b hewşê da b nîvî qulibî ye no ho ne.
We hope in the courtyard half of it collapsed like this.
Obo, no tirs ra mirin.
Oh my, no fear died (it's scary).
Wa tirs çû.
The fear is gone.
Yanî...
Meaning...
Mişkle, belki rêke, rêka jam wanov kin çîçkê çetin bin ne?
Problem, maybe the way, the way of the glass/path make it a
bit difficult right?
No no, adî, bes...
No no, normal, but...
Bes vr o na ye.
There are paths.
Just here it is not.
Yalla.
Let's go.
War.
Come.
Arê no, amê noko derbas nav gund bin jî.
Yes no, we will pass through the village now too.
Nav gund amê teswîr kin û cî dink derê tagû.
Inside the village we will film and another place there.
Ew jî wina sarilwera, kinîsê biderin.
That is also like that... church is outside.
Kinîsî ye, amê noka an knîsê jî.
It is a church, we will [film] the church now too.
Meşê wudê, wîkî teswîr kin, ow kin.
Walk there, film like that, do that.
Şînî kanê qobî nezîr?
Where is the blue dome of Nezir?
Tebe' Xolo, vro sarhinc heye?
Of course Uncle, is there a cistern here?
Belê sarinc bû hewa ne.
Yes it was a cistern, that one.
Yek li jêr jî hebî.
There was one below too.
Yek li jêr hebî, yek li vro ye, hevo sarinc in kûr e, do çor
mitro kûr e.
There was one below, one is here, these are cisterns, deep,
around four meters deep.
Hevo me dewar jî av dida, ewş cindê dêwer bû.
This one, we watered the animals too, that was the place for
animals.
Eywa.
Okay.
Bê tolîe hono dor girtin, berê kevir...
Without support they built it around like that, before
stones...
Çor mitir...
Four meters...
Çor mitir teqrîben.
Four meters approximately.
Çor mitir.
Four meters.
Hevo jî derece.
This is also stairs.
Hevo kes têda heye?
Is anyone in this one?
B hewş e, a mol têde.
It's a courtyard, ah cattle is inside.
Pencere bigire, na mişkle nîne.
Close the window, no it's no problem.
Mişkle tine ne. No no em aw nakin.
No problem. No no we won't do that.
Arê hevo lno.
Yes that one now.
Hevo berê derecê kevin hewna bîn, gile.
These ancient stairs were like this, look.
Havolî mwar nîzîk bike çîçkê dereco.
This side Uncle, bring the stairs a bit closer.
Hevo sîsmomkî ma girt, Allah yerhemu, hef kevro çêkirin.
This one, Sismomki held/built it, may God have mercy on him,
they made these stones.
Hew derece bê bêtûn, bê çîmento.
And held it.
These stairs without concrete, without cement.
Bê bêtûn naha bî nadar, kevr şkê dikirin di dîwr de diçûn e.
There was no concrete then, they broke the stones and they
went into the wall.
Dîwr diqora.
The wall holds/swallows it.
Oo.
Oh.
E na xetere wano?
Is it not dangerous like that?
No, diqora hetta darbozî olî din biya.
No, it holds/swallows it until it passes to the other side.
Eywa.
Exactly.
E bas bine, na emîdek, na şîşek, tiştek tê tine, di dîwr da
sabit mandine.
Yes look, no pillar, no rebar, nothing in it, they remained
fixed in the wall.
Rinde. War.
Nice. Come.
Tarîxê xwe li ser e.
Its date is on it.
Tarîx li ser heye?
Is there a date on it?
Dîrokê xwe li ser e.
Its history/date is on it.
Sevrandin.
Filmed.
Seke vê kitêbê, seke.
Look at this book, look.
Ko emkê çû...
Where did we go...
Were, were, bawer bike...
Come, come, believe me...
Têbê vrov qebûk heye.
You say there is a dome here.
Hevo qebû ye.
This is a dome.
Xwe çêkir xwedanê hewşê çêkir.
He made it himself, the owner of the courtyard made it.
Eywa.
Okay.
Hef kitabe wiyoz mîşkirî.
This book/inscription is written.
Ko hevolî mwar bes nîzîk bike.
Where, film this side Uncle, just bring it close.
Hevo kê yozmîş kir vê kîtabê?
Who wrote this book/inscription?
Hevo mamê bavkê miniv xo Hamo bû. Allah yerhemu nîvîsî.
This was my father's uncle, Hamo. May God have mercy on him,
he wrote it.
Gî wî... hef kîteba, hef tişta gî wî yezmîşkirî.
All him... this book, these things, all written by him.
Yê ginde çêkir.
The one from the village made it.
Însankê cebbar e, Xwedê rehma xolê kê.
He is a capable person, may God have mercy on him.
Li vir çoxsaye mîş, salê hezar neh sed pêncî û şeş a.
Here it is written, the year one thousand nine hundred
fifty-six.
Pêncî û şeş a, hef hewşo gind girtin.
Fifty-six, they built this courtyard.
Benê Hamo.
Built by Hamo.
Novî xo jî dinivîsar.
He wrote his name too.
Rehma tî... rehmetî vê hewşo girtî û novî xo jî dinivîsar.
The deceased... the deceased built this courtyard and wrote
his name too.
Solê hezar neh sid pêncî û şeş a.
The year one thousand nine hundred fifty-six.
Xwedê rehma xolê kê, cîhê xo cinnet bê.
May God have mercy on him, may his place be paradise.
Çi zexrafê çêkiriye.
What a decoration he made.
Vir kirine çi?
What did they do here?
Hewo ayet... ayet...
That is a verse... verse...
Îna fetahna leke fethen mubîna.
"Inna fatahna laka fathan mubina" (Verily We have granted
thee a manifest Victory).
Cîcek jî yozmîş kirine.
They wrote a flower too.
La îlahe îllalah w fî kîtabî...
La ilaha illallah and in my book...
Wa xeyren hafîzen.
"Wa khayran hafiza" (And He is the best Guardian).
Hef jî camîk çêkiriye.
He made a mosque here too.
Camî ye.
It is a mosque.
Wekî camîkê resmekî çêkiriye.
Like a mosque, he made a picture.
Camî ye, camî ye.
It is a mosque, it is a mosque.
Wele yî me'lem e.
By God, he is a master.
E hef jî qumriyê neda qumriyê.
Yes, and this one didn't give the turtledove, the
turtledove.
Teyb hef çî ye? Hicrî ne?
Okay what is this? Hijri, right?
Hicrî hewa.
That is Hijri.
Hezar sê sed hevtê û şeş a.
One thousand three hundred seventy-six.
Hewo jî...
Exactly.
And this one...
Li vê derê jî, ona çûk ne çêkirine, çûk.
In this place too, look they made birds, birds.
Ev çiye?
They made two birds opposite each other.
What is this?
Ew...
That...
Tesmîmê qabê biner ê... Xoraseke...
Look at the design of the arch... It is concrete (mortar)...
Ber e, ber e.
It is stone, stone.
Were xwarê gulê min.
Come down, my flower (dear).
Nefs wî hemû yî?
Is it all the same (style)?
E, hewa, hewa kevir çêkiriye.
Yes, exactly, exactly, he made it from stone.
Nefs yê hindê yê kevir çêkiriye?
The same person made this out of stone?
Nefsê wî, nefsê wî çêkiriye.
The same one, the same one made it.
Çi me'ne didî wî kevirî?
What meaning do you give to that stone?
Ew qanûnê bînê ye, yanî şîşî bînê ye.
That is the law of the structure, meaning the iron
(reinforcement) of the structure.
Şîşî bînê ye.
It is the iron of the structure.
Wellehî muhendis, muhendisê berê cebar bî ne bes bî ne?
By God, the engineers, the engineers of the past were
mighty, weren't they?
Kevrê neqşê çêdikirin.
They used to make engraved stones.
Xwedê rehma xwe lêke cihê cinnet be.
May God have mercy on him, may his place be paradise.
Were torîxê vana bibîne.
Come and look at the history of these.
Ev ji teb'en cihê dewar pe ve girtin dan na, ekîd?
This was naturally a place to keep cattle, right, surely?
Na menzer e, hewa menzer e.
No, it is a view, this is a view (balcony).
Heva hewş e.
This is a courtyard.
E tew bi qulik li heye.
Oh, look, there are even small holes in it.
Erê wina menzer çêkiriye, yanî hewş bî.
Yes, they made it like a view, meaning it was a courtyard.
Hev ji xora tim de hat pşîqe pan orê rûniştin.
This was for themselves, so the cat could come and sit there
comfortably.
Rûniştin.
Sitting.
A welleh, erê welleh.
Ah really, yes really.
Seke torîxê vê were bibîne.
Look, come see the date on this.
Aaa.
Hezar du sed û...
One thousand two hundred and...
Hezar du sed û bîst û çar.
One thousand two hundred and twenty-four.
Hezar du sed û bîst û çar?
One thousand two hundred and twenty-four?
E.
Yes.
Hezar du sed û bîst û çar.
One thousand two hundred and twenty-four.
Çi yazîye ev Erebîye?
What script is this, is it Arabic?
Çi neqşa cwan çêkirine le bes biner ji vir.
What beautiful designs they made, just look from here.
Ji vir, seke wekî ew çakrîd...
From here, look, like that...
Wî dîye hamberî çi neqşa çêkirine?
Did you see over there what designs they made?
Neqşên gelekî resim çêkirine.
They made many engraved pictures.
Gelekî resim neqşa çêkirine.
Nefs ewa nî...
The same as that one, look...
Nu fiqîra çiqas cefayetê didîgê wana bi Îzmîrê ina çêkirine.
Look at how much effort the poor things put into it, they
made them like in Izmir.
Gi bi zmîlê, gi bi şer, gi bi...
All with chisels, all with fighting (hardship), all with...
E welle nuke 'ede hebitin nuke wana çêke?
Oh really, does anyone have the custom (skill) to make these
now?
Weri muhendis nikanin nuke wana çêkin.
Bring an engineer, they cannot make these now.
Na?
No?
Na wexwdê.
No, by God.
Lo kevir, kevirî sebîl, kevirî sebîl ekê çêkim qubetî dehar
o werbibe kevirîkî.
Oh the stone, the Sebil stone, if I make a Sebil stone now,
a dome will collapse from just one stone.
Nefs ewa, nefs ewa.
It's the same, the same.
Seke derec wî derkevin...
Look, the stairs go up...
Çi neqiş li ser çêkirine.
What engravings they made on it.
Seke wa kevirêk wekî kursîya biner.
Look at that stone, look, it's like a chair.
Welle pir kevne ev derê cemaet.
By God, this place is very old, folks.
Cihê kevne.
It is an old place.
Ka wulim were jûr.
Come on, come inside (up).
Were jûr.
Come inside (up).
Esas kevin berê...
The foundation is old stone...
Ox, çi mewqi'e.
Oh, what a location.
Ew gundê, gundê hember me...
That village, the village opposite us...
Wê din, wê din.
Leave it, leave it.
Wadîye çi tebîet gundî wana heye.
You see what a nature their village has.
Hewa gund gîda ye bi xêra.
This is all the village, with blessings.
Eywa.
Yes.
Hewayê bilind e.
The air (altitude) is high.
Heva jî me'na wekî şerqê çêkiribî ne?
This was also made like a balcony/terrace facing east,
right?
Erê me'na wû bî.
Yes, that was the meaning.
E.
Yes.
Ka wulim li gund biger û nîzîk bike hewşê, vidarê bilind e.
Come on, walk around the village and zoom in on the
courtyard, it is high here.
Gundikî xweş e.
It is a nice village.
Tirbê camaetê li kîderê ne?
Where are the community's graves?
O camî li kîyê wo?
Oh, where is the mosque?
Ê wa.
Right there.
Paş gund û wî alî gundî.
They are behind the village.
Behind the village and on that side of the village.
Eywa.
Yes.
Emê noha lextokî li wîjî xin.
We will take a little tour there too.
Emê herin, emê herin ne were emê herin.
We will go, we will go, come on, we will go.
Eve embara me kîderê ye xolo?
Where is our storehouse here, uncle?
Ewa soxanek e.
That is a cellar (cold storage).
Soxanek e?
A cellar?
Cihê vî de berad e.
Yes.
This place is a refrigerator (very cold).
Berad e çîme, ev soxaneke goştime.
Refrigerator is nothing, this is our meat cellar.
Ewa soxanek e.
That is a cellar.
E.
Yes.
Ka wulim nîzîk bike, hewşê nîzîk bike û dûr bike, hunom li
kîbar derkevin.
Come on, zoom in, zoom in on the courtyard and zoom out, so
you appear elegant.
Tirbê rehmetî mezin.
The grave of the late elder.
Seke xaniyê wiha, xaniyê wiha.
Look at houses like this, houses like this.
Vira ketiye?
Has it fallen here?
E vira, ev ji dumahîkê kevirê mezin ketiye xwarê.
Yes here, this huge stone fell down at the end.
Berê mezin ketiye?
A big stone fell?
E.
Yes.
Xwedê hefezat kiriye.
God protected us.
Wellehî.
By God.
Were wulim.
Come on, son.
Serî yazî heye li wîr.
There is writing on top over there.
Lebbe, ber.
Wow, stones.
Çi kevir têt, çi derece cwan... Du yî mi mekevin.
What stones come here, what beautiful stairs... Don't make
the two of us fall.
Ka wer hevalim lê bigir.
Come here my friend, hold this.
Eve berê çi bî, eve berê çi bî?
What was this before, what was this before?
Hevû sekanî dewar û berî, berî wî.
This was the place for cattle and before, before that.
Kur ne?
Is it deep?
E mezin e.
Yes, it is big.
Welle.
Really.
Û nîv alemîş wî çî...
And half the world's things...
Bi xêra xwedê.
With God's blessing.
Berê dewarê gundî gişt li vir dabû.
Before, all the village cattle were here.
Gişt li vir dabû.
All were here.
E.
Yes.
Gî nebû gemar tişte hebû qedexe bû, memnû' bû.
There was no dirt or anything, it was forbidden, prohibited.
E wextê yê rehm.
Yes, in the time of the deceased.
Welle pir fere ye.
By God, it is very spacious.
Fere ye.
It is spacious.
Wede lo, wede.
Give it here, give it.
Biçûk te dûye.
It gave you a small one.
E.
Yes.
Welle vidarê jî oqenter me dî virdê çêkirine, şefreşe ne,
hevalim?
By God, even here we saw an arch, they built it here, it's a
black bat, my friend?
Xwîna tê?
Does it bleed?
Xwîn tê?
Pir fere ye welle.
It is very spacious, by God.
Qonder de hewşoye.
The arch is in the courtyard.
Wê.
Yes.
Wê gêcê jî wane ye ne?
That plaster is theirs too, right?
Heva fike xerab kirine nîvi wan.
They ruined this part, half of them.
Xerab kirine rengê wiya.
They ruined its color.
Heva no, maro teslîhekî xora tê de îstîmal kirin, pir rind
e.
This is not... if a man uses reinforcement in it, it is very
good.
Pir rinde.
It is very good.
Ewa hat.
Here it comes.
Emê herin, emê herin ne were emê herin.
We will go, we will go, come on, we will go.
Min hewar xora horetok xwest...
I asked for a little yogurt for myself...
Ne.
No.
De hewa horetok ne?
Is this the yogurt?
Horetok tey?
Is it your yogurt?
Xwedê jê razî be.
May God be pleased with her.
Razî be.
Be pleased.
Eke dimen zikro, torîx, eke dimen ser qenatê...
If it's a view, memory, history, if it's a view on the
channel...
Dê vir de bê.
It should come from here.
Lo da.
There.
Hîn kûçik hene?
Are there still dogs?
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Gundî we pir xweş e, tişt nameradî binyê, merad darê, mera
ecêb dimîne, mera darê dinyok din.
Your village is very nice, something... beneath it... a man
stays amazed, a man is in another world.
No, no tiştê kevin gundî pir e.
No, no, there are many old things in the village.
Belê, belê, gund.
Yes, yes, the village.
No cîlê, cîl nuhane, wekî me, tiştê wana nizanin meselen
tiştê eserî û torîxê xwa nizanê.
No, the generation, the current generation, like us, they
don't know these things, for example, they don't know their
artifacts and history.
Belê.
Yes.
Ne ne no ez gor 'emrî min, ez derim dinyok din, ez pir ecêb
çû dikirin.
No, no, right now, according to my age, I go to another
world, I wonder a lot how they did it.
Vêda tiştê kevin pirr e, eserî pirr e wana.
Here there are many old things, many artifacts.
Ekîd bêrî xware, hene hewşê kevin hene, tiştê kevin hene.
Surely looking down, there are old courtyards, there are old
things.
Ez ji tiştê wana hez dikim, tiştê eserî, wana maro...
I also love those things, artifacts, those things make a
man...
E emîn, em...
Yes sure, we...
Zane be berê çû de'işîn, çû dikirin.
So one knows how they lived before, what they did.
Wextê pospîtî...
The time of passports...
Berê bo hewşekê da...
Before, to a courtyard...
Ber gup hewş...
In front of the clustered courtyard...
Hewşek bo, hewşek...
It was a courtyard, a courtyard...
Û berê xoret, hemû labûna.
And before the yogurt, it was all gathered.
Xweş.
Nice.
Wa xwedê ji we razî be mala we ava.
Oh may God be pleased with you, may your home be prosperous.
Hev ne hewş bî?
Was this not a courtyard?
Berê genimê xwa, mûnetê xwa didanîn vira, karê îşê kirin ne?
Before they put their wheat, their provisions here, they did
their work, right?
Dewer hebû.
There was cattle.
Dewer hebû cemaet.
There was cattle, folks.
Ka wîlî me were jûr.
Come on, come inside (up).
Berî boyê, in berî vê bi çiqas sal, teb'en ê bi Helebê gihan
nufûsê wan sekin.
Before this, well before this by some years, naturally those
who reached Aleppo, look at their population.
E.
Yes.
Jibarode mekin te bî sê hezar û pênc sed mal e, nufûs.
Don't compare with us, it was three thousand five hundred
houses, population.
Sê hezar û pênc sed mal e?
Three thousand five hundred houses?
Hêj bêtir.
Even more.
Heva wextê belediyê hen busûte, hem ser busûte bîn.
This was when the municipality was there, when they were on
the...
E naho ser o ye.
Well now it is on it.
E nuko ser o ye ekîd.
Yes, now it is on it, surely.
No gîşt sê sed û pênc hezarî.
Now all together three hundred and five thousand.
O teb'en ê gund dişemlandin, ê ma ê Helebê gihan, rûniştin
dişemlandin giştin.
Oh naturally, they adorned the village, those who reached
Aleppo, settled and adorned everything.
Nufûsê kîmorê heva virdê bû.
A huge population was here.
Arê heva berê vê zmeş de ye.
Yes, this is from long before.
Hevo lê berî ge nizom xerab kirin.
This, but before the system/order was ruined.
Nono vo hîn pir bîye.
No, no, this was still much (intact).
Ê nuhên zêde bûn, taba'en, ekîd.
The new ones increased, naturally, surely.
Rehetiye?
Are you comfortable?
Welle, xwedê rehetî bide te de.
Well, may God give you comfort.
Çûdike, siheta te çûye?
How are you, how is your health?
Elhemdulillah, çûna çûne.
Praise God, as good as it gets.
Welle elhemdulillah, xwedê emrê te dirêj bike te de.
Well praise God, may God prolong your life.
Xoltîk ê...
Auntie...
E.
Yes.
Maşallah gundî we pir gundekî kîbar e, gundekî pêşketî ye.
Mashallah, your village is a very elegant village, an
advanced village.
Eywa.
Yes.
Û miletî tê de jî, one ze'rxweş, one xedûm e, baqil e.
And the people in it too, they are hospitable, helpful,
smart.
A xwedê ji we razî be.
Oh, may God be pleased with you.
Gundî we gundekî hedarî ye.
Your village is a civilized village.
Maşallah, e.
Mashallah, yes.
Û qîmetê nîvanî xwa jî pir zanin xoltî.
And they know the value of their guests very well, auntie.
Arê.
Yes.
Mm.
Maşallah xolû, ê va teqsîr nekirine maro. Xoltî ti çis...
Mashallah uncle, hey they didn't fall short for us. Auntie,
you...
Na, çawran din e.
No, they are waiting (welcoming).
A, ti çi silovê dişîne ji miletî, e, kîmorê ro.
Ah, what greetings do you send to the people, uh, the great
[Kurdish] people.
Ser serî min, ser çavî min ge, em gi Kurmanc in, em gi xûn
ava heven, haw nî?
Upon my head, upon my eyes, we are all Kurds, we are all of
the same blood and water, aren't we?
Elhemdulillah, em rob hev da de'îşin, pok delal, şte.
Praise God, we live together, clean and dear, like that.
Silovê teyê bi miletî, gundî we gi ne gişko?
Do your greetings go to the people, to all of your village?
E bila ehlen we sehlen, bila herin.
Yes let them, welcome, let them go.
Xwedê bereke 'emr çande?
How old are you, God bless?
Eşgî 'emrî min, heftî didine.
My age, they give me seventy.
Maşallah, hîn te can e. Maşallah.
Mashallah, you are still young. Mashallah.
Ez girska me, babê min, hem... ez da.
I am the eldest, my father... and me.
Maşallah, xoltîk te ji min contir xwî tê, maşallah, xalta
bêlinoke.
Mashallah, auntie, you look younger than me, mashallah,
don't make a mistake.
Welle guretayî, wextî.
Well the changing of times, the time.
E 'eyn çoka, maşallah.
Yes, exactly (touch wood), mashallah.
Selem mesele no bêjim, wextî min.
No problem, let me say, in my time.
Bûrin.
Go ahead.
Wextînê xa da.
In my own time.
Mm.
Min nan dikir, mi pole dikir.
Oh.
I baked bread, I did farm labor.
Mi ov bi serê xwa, ma tonî.
Ah.
I brought water on my own head.
Wa dîtino ser serî xwa tonî?
You see, she brought it on her own head?
Arê welle, em hon nema non dikir.
Yes really, we used to bake bread here.
A.
Ah.
Û 'uber diheqçik ber ko xodê, pez, du sed dewer, bi zin mi
didot.
And the load... before God, sheep, two hundred cattle, I
milked the goats.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Me ev kora gi kirye.
We did all this work.
Te cefa pir dîye.
You have seen much hardship.
Cefa, hên, ov tinebû, zûk hêştirî me hebûn.
Hardship, yes, there was no water, we had young mules.
Me barkir av di îna.
We loaded them and brought water.
Çû ov, Geliyê Lûlkê ji me wova ye, dibên Lûlkê, Geliyê
Lûlkê.
The water went, Lulke Valley is over there from us, they
call it Lulke, Lulke Valley.
Geliyê Lûlkê, a, Geliyê Kerzêlê.
Lulke Valley, ah, Kerzele Valley.
Geliyê Kerzêlê.
Kerzele Valley.
Voyî binî çiyayê midîye.
That one is below the mountain.
Ewa ke kaniya kîliya, me diçû av dikirê, em da daxil hetar
me ew rawiyate ji dikirin.
That Kiliya spring, we went and fetched water from it, we
entered until we watered [the animals] from it too.
Ded vî koşîrê, me tanî.
Up this slope, we brought it.
Cefa bî?
Was it hardship?
Cefa, me pî pez av dida.
Hardship, we watered the sheep with it.
Êvarê me pî gakov dida.
In the evening we watered the oxen with it.
Me pî ser û kênc, mol dişişt... mol şiştin tinebû, ax bû.
With it [we washed] heads and clothes, washed the house...
there was no house washing, it was dirt [floor].
Xoltîk, berê rind bî yan nuko rind e?
Auntie, was the past better or is now better?
Welle nuko rind e, bes tam nemaye.
Well now is better, but there is no taste left.
Nuko rind e, tam nemaye ne?
Now is better, but no taste left, right?
A, berê lo av tinebû, lo holî çenda...
Ah, before there was no water, the situation was so...
No ga heye hûn ne rozî ne jî.
Now it exists and you are not satisfied either.
Lê, e ber ko xodê, ga goşt...
No, well before God, sometimes meat...
Eke pok be goştê ev dikevin ne?
If it is clean, this meat falls (is good), right?
Av ya hûr bûn.
The water [sources] were small.
Me kerş danda, şîva min lêkirin, û kênc û derbrek ser kaniya
bosûtê me dişiştin.
I put brushwood, I made dinner, and we washed clothes and
pants at the Bosute spring.
Me heve, heve t'aba cefa gidiya, noko çavî me ra derdikeva.
We have this, this exhaustion and hardship of the ancestors,
now it comes out of our eyes (we pay for it).
Nono maşallah, xoltîk to maşallah, tu wekî bisklêto ye.
Maşallah, lê tu bi heftî dida.
No, no, mashallah, auntie, you are mashallah like a bicycle.
Mashallah, but you give seventy [years].
E 'emrî min hîn ney bî çêl, pûr mûr sêrî min vona me yî.
My age hasn't even reached forty, hair and all on my head is
like this.
Welle rême, ye me gi spî bîne.
By God, ours have all become white.
Welle ge vo, kîlawiya o nekra şekir şimra ye çima.
Well look at that, having kidney [problems] or not having
sugar [diabetes] is unlucky, why.
Te tiştek tine ye, xwedê rehetê ta de, maşallah, siheta ta
rind e.
You have nothing [wrong], may God give you comfort,
mashallah, your health is good.
Bê qîja xîskekê rintir bûm, ê de şta viye kiro.
Without the screaming of a cyst/pain I was better, but well,
things are like this.
Maşallah, xwedê 'emirke dirêj ta de, xwedê ta neke ber
destan.
Mashallah, may God give you a long life, may God not make
you dependent on others.
Lo welle nuko ez hotim yanê tano xom xos serxo kir da, pêşê
molê me derec netê, reto ge.
No, by God, now I came by myself, I wanted to fix my head
[hair/scarf], in front of our house the stairs don't come,
it's just a slope.
Xoş hebû, xoş hebû.
It was nice, it was nice.
Arê welle.
Yes really.
Xwedê jita rozî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Xwedê şita rozî be, xoltîk, emkê derkevin, hîn cewlê me
xilas nebîye. Xwedê şita rozî be.
May God be pleased with you, auntie, we will go out, our
tour isn't finished yet. May God be pleased with you.
Eyax, dengî min bisewirîne belav kesî?
Oh my, will you record my voice and distribute it to anyone?
Belav dibe, belav dibe, ogid disewire xoltîk.
It will be distributed, it will be distributed, the whole
world watches, auntie.
Eywa, ser dawa xosh.
Yes, have a good time.
Av hewşê xolî wa?
Is this your uncle's courtyard?
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Av hewşê xolî min hev e?
Is this my uncle's courtyard here?
Ber kale da, nîzîk e na?
By the Kale (citadel), it's close, isn't it?
Ta kêf kiriye.
You enjoyed it.
No çoksa siwah hotin, viro hotin centa na?
Now so many tourists came, they came here [with] bags,
right?
Ecanib, ga Firansî ba, ga Ewnabî ba, ga çi bû, tewê royî em
virda rûniştin...
Foreigners, sometimes French, sometimes European, sometimes
whatever, that day we sat here...
Medofê mi da, rûniştin, teswîr kirine, gi belav kirine.
In my Madafa (guest room), they sat, took pictures,
distributed them all.
Welle?
Really?
Welle şê fam dikir.
By God, he understood.
A fam dikir.
Ah, he understood.
Erê erê em mat arxist.
No no, mashallah, your courtyard is elegant, and this is a
well, right?
Erê erê em mat arxist.
Yes, yes, we are very relaxed.
Ev bêna ferqet ere...
This space between the intersections, yes...
Ewa darê Zoratê nîne?
Isn't that the Zorat road?
Zoratê nîne.
It is not Zorat.
Darê serekê yê Helebê.
The main road to Aleppo.
Beriya rêya Zoratê ye...
It is before the Zorat road...
Biro Helebê?
Go to Aleppo?
Şêst kîlo.
Sixty kilometers.
Li vî derî jî sarinc hene?
Are there cisterns here too?
Bozor.
Market.
Miletî vire?
Are the people here?
Na na bozor vî derî bêtir, ber jêr e.
No, no, the market is further this way, further down.
Me xêm nekir şûna bozorê.
We didn't notice the place of the market.
Welle pir xaniyê kevnar in ha?
By God, very ancient houses, huh?
Mentiqa we, şarê we, eqdem şî belkî ne?
Your region, your city, is perhaps the oldest thing?
Ebû Cemîl!
Abu Cemil!
Xaletê min nîzik bike, hewşê gunda, milo lê ser kin.
Zoom in my shot, the village yards, so the people can watch.
Berê sed tirba?
Before a hundred graves?
No noka em nayên ser tirba.
No, we aren't going to the graves right now.
Dure ji vir va tirba?
Are the graves far from here?
Ku em herin.
Where we are going.
Qewet be, qewet be. Siheta te xweş.
Strength to you, strength to you. Good health.
Ev na ne?
Are these them?
Erê emê bixwînin.
Yes, we will read [Fatiha].
Xalo, Xalo!
Uncle, Uncle!
Bîsmîllah... Yoş, Xalo yoş.
Bismillah... Slowly, Uncle, slowly.
Şifêr me, lê ez dibim şifêr.
We have a driver, but I become the driver.
Ya Selam.
Oh Peace [God].
Were te pêz xe o.
Come, put your foot there.
Her sarsî, her sarsî ye.
It's all an ascent, it's all an ascent.
Wey sax bin destê we, we ez temam kirim înşallah.
May your hands be healthy, you have completed me [helped me
greatly], God willing.
Xalo ne çetin e te telmo dixê?
Uncle, isn't it difficult, do you want support?
Aha herdu tirbê jorê yê berhevdan e co.
Look, the two upper graves are facing each other, look.
Yê berhevda ne.
They are facing each other.
Wana durê kevir lê xistine.
Those far ones, stones have been placed on them.
Henan Nasir... Miqdad Henan.
Maşallah cemaat pir kîbar û xweş e min eciband welle.
Mashallah, the community is very noble and nice, I liked it
really.
Sax be.
Thanks.
Tu ji vî gundî ye Xo?
Are you from this village, Uncle?
Tu çi karî dikî vê gundî?
What work do you do in this village?
La bi Xwedê çi kar kî? Ebad e, dewar e, zeytûn e.
Oh by God, what work? Cultivation, livestock, olives.
Kareba tune ye.
There is no electricity.
Bes ra nî vê mantiqê me çira û kimore tune ye?
But generally in our region there are no lights or anything?
Tu çi silav dikî dişînî ji miletê gundî xwere?
What greetings do you send to your village people?
Miletê gundî me, Xwedê rehetiyê bide, Xwedê selametiya milet
bide.
Our village people, may God give comfort, may God give
safety to the people.
Hezkirinek hebe bese.
Having love is enough.
Evna tirbê vê gundî pir kevnar in ha?
These graves of this village are very ancient, huh?
Avo tirbê vono çiqas kevnar in... yanî telbîs melbîs tune yê
berê.
These graves of theirs are so ancient... I mean there is no
facing/cladding like before.
Erê hevalno, li vê derê jî... Xwedê rehma xwe li miriyê giya
ke...
Yes friends, here also... May God have mercy on all the
dead...
... tirba Miqdad Hisên.
... the tomb of Miqdad Hussein.
İnşallah Xwedê miradê dilê gundî jî kir...
God willing, God granted the wishes of the villager too...
Nava nîzik bike, nava nîzik bike.
Zoom in on the inside [names], zoom in on the inside.
Sala deh, heftê, rehmetî biye...
The year ten, seventy [1970], he passed away...
Deh hezar heftê, yekî deşta heftê.
Ten thousand seventy, one of the plains of seventy [reading
numbers incorrectly].
Awa mewalîdê gundî kirine, ne?
They put the birth date of the villager, right?
Şêst û heft.
Sixty-seven.
Maşallah tebîeta cemaa pir xweş e.
Mashallah, the nature of the community is very nice.
Mentiqê Efrîn gişt wisa xweş in.
The whole Afrin region is nice like this.
Bes yê din tune kevirê din... ev bi Kurmancî nivîsandine.
But there isn't the other one, the other stone... this is
written in Kurmanji.
Kêlekê jî bi Kurmancî ye, bi Îngîlîzî ye, welle nizanim.
The side is in Kurmanji, in English, by God I don't know.
Em cem bozorê bisekinin.
Let's stop near the market.
Welle maşallah gundî jî qerebalix e.
Wow mashallah, the village is also crowded.
Maşallah miletê gundî wa pir heye.
Mashallah, there are a lot of village people.
Gund mezin e.
The village is big.
Heleb...
Aleppo...
Bozor li vira?
Is the market here?
Daxînin were.
Film down here.
Boy boy kin, awha, hûnê li xwe ser kin, boy boy kin, ewa.
Wave bye-bye, like that, you will watch yourselves later,
wave bye-bye, yes.
Hûn giş vê gundî ne?
Are you all from this village?
Erê.
Yes.
Maşallah, hûn ti korî dikin? Hûn diçin mektabê?
Mashallah, do you do anything? Do you go to school?
Mekteb hene, hene.
There are schools, there are.
Şerûd man e?
Is it crowded?
Yanî...
So-so...
Ê baş e, heta were.
Okay good, until it comes.
Yekî, yekî, vî bazarî ye me.
One, one, this is our market.
Rind e, rind e. Bixwînin.
It's good, it's good. Study well.
Erê apê wilo, li vî derî jî bazar hene çêdibin? Çend hefteyê
çêdibin xalo wilo?
Yes Uncle Wilo, are there markets held in this place too?
How many times a week are they held, uncle?
Heftê dudo.
Two a week.
Hene du bazar ne li vir çêdibin ne?
There are two markets held here, right?
E Sûsiyê.
The Susiyê one.
Bazara Sûsiyê?
The Susiyê Market?
E Sûsiyê.
The Susiyê one.
Bazara Sûsiyê li vî derî çêdikin, ne?
They hold the Susiyê Market in this place, right?
Heta milet hîn bibe, no, çimkî hereket sist e, heta milet
çîçikê dielimê, li vî derî bazare şên bibe maşallah.
Until the people get used to it, no, because the movement is
slow, until the people learn a bit, hopefully the market
will become lively in this place, Mashallah.
Rind e. Ti nayê?
It's good. Aren't you coming?
Na, na, xwedê zêde ke.
No, no, may God increase [your wealth].
Xidir e, ti nayê? Bas tiştê hêşke û der e.
It's Xidir, aren't you coming? It's just dry stuff and
outside.
Ê heqê we ye.
That is your right.
Yo şaş, heta milet ba'elimê der bibe, xidre jî yê were.
Or wrong, until the people get used to going out, vegetables
will come too.
Heta îşê wan bişixule.
Until their business gets going.
Pîskewîtê xalo bişîne.
Pass the uncle's biscuits.
De...
Here...
Bişîne.
Pass them.
Xalo, tizbî li vir hene? Tizbî? Bo sîte... bo sîte tizbî
hene, biro difroşin? Tizbiyok?
Uncle, are there prayer beads here? Beads? For the lady...
are there beads for the lady, brother do they sell them?
Small beads?
Na.
No.
No firoşin?
They don't sell them?
Na.
No.
Ha banim, min ê cotek wara bikira ji wan ê qalind ra.
Oh, I would have bought a pair for you, the thick ones.
Yê tewî corem a ra bîne.
Bring the long ones for us.
Ê ez corê te hatim, ez ê varim, gerek tin bimiro hebana min
ê wekî nida...
Well I came for your sake, I will bring them, you should
have told me so I would...
Min digot qey tu bîr nakî ya.
I thought you wouldn't forget.
Xalas. Ha banim, min ê nika te'r bikirna, min ê yek hecer
tewî bikira.
Done. If you had told me, I would have prepared them now, I
would have put a stone with it.
Temam, îstireh ke vîno.
Okay, rest here then.
Eywa. Rind e, maşallah.
Yes. Good, Mashallah.
Erê apê wilo, li vî derî ez ê piskewîta ji qicika ra
bikirim.
Yes Uncle Wilo, here I will buy biscuits for the little
ones.
Erê. Ko, mera têke, ko, wek kûlîkê didiyo mera têke. Wer ji
qicika ra têke.
Yes. Here, put some for us, here, put like a second bag for
us. Come put some for the little ones.
Bi çî ye kîlo?
How much is a kilo?
Xemse sebîn.
Seventy-five [Arabic].
Xemse sebîn. Ko mera têke kûlîkê didiyo têke. Kujan ê win
dixwazin, kujan ê?
Seventy-five. Here put some for us, fill a second bag. Which
ones do you want, which ones?
Win vana hez dikin? Ko van mera dagir.
You like these? Here, fill these up for us.
Têke, têke, dagir.
Put it in, put it in, fill it.
Abî, abî...
Fill it, fill it...
Evna tûrî vana biçin, avna.
Let these go in their bags, these ones.
Mistê xwe vekin.
Open your hands.
Vekin.
Open them.
Mistê xwe vekin.
Open your hands.
Ewa.
Yes.
Yoş, merin, ekê tiştê din jî tadim, yoş. Ha.
Slowly, don't run, I will give you something else too,
slowly. Here.
Merin, kê bir, merin.
Don't run, whoever took some, don't run.
Hine.
Here.
Hine piskewîto, hine.
Here are biscuits, here.
Maşallah, qicikê vê gundî, herin mektebê ha!
Mashallah, kids of this village, go to school okay!
Erê.
Yes.
Ba'elim in. Ha.
Be educated. Here.
Ki vîna wado mezin e?
Who is the older one among you?
Ez me.
It's me.
Ha win ê nuko lev belav kin, ne?
Here, you will distribute them among yourselves now, right?
We kîlo halva ye risq e.
Like a kilo of halva, it's sustenance.
Ne? Ha. Bigir. Ha.
Right? Here. Take it. Here.
Wara.
Come.
Bigir.
Take it.
Merin o.
Don't run.
Wara, ha.
Come, here.
Xalo vîna ve?
Uncle, [do you want] this one?
Kanî? Wara ha, tu jî wara.
Thanks.
Where? Come here, you come too.
Ha.
Here.
Ê min, ê min, ê me talîkî yo, mla qicik aw idara bin. Wara,
kê nebir?
Mine, mine, ours is for later, let the kids manage with
this. Come, who didn't take any?
Min nebir.
I didn't take any.
Ha.
Here.
Min jî nebir.
I didn't take any either.
Me jî nebir.
We didn't take any either.
Kiş, ni? Ha. Wara, yoş.
Who, you? Here. Come, slowly.
Avna wa şekirî qidman e, vêra dibên. Bigir, ê te yek.
These are those old style candies, they call them. Take it,
yours is one.
Aybî dida, hine.
There are two, here.
Ay sise.
That's three.
Ay çar.
That's four.
Çar.
Four.
Ay pênc.
That's five.
Pênc. Pênc.
Five. Five.
Şeş.
Six.
Heft, hine.
Seven, here.
Heft.
Seven.
Heyşt.
Eight.
Neh.
Nine.
Deh. Hine.
Ten. Here.
Wara.
Come.
Wara ha.
Come here.
Mamoste.
Teacher.
Ha.
Yeah.
E lo yê me tişbê. Dav yek.
This is ours counting. Eleven.
Dav yek.
Eleven.
Dav dida.
Twelve.
Kê nebir? Kê nebir?
Who didn't get any? Who didn't get any?
Min nebir.
I didn't get any.
We herduka nebir? Dav da, dav se, dav çar.
Both of you didn't get any? Twelve, thirteen, fourteen.
Dav çar ne?
Fourteen right?
Dav çar.
Fourteen.
De xoltîkerê jî boy boy kin, xoltîkerê boy boy kin.
Come on, wave bye-bye to the Auntie too, wave bye-bye to the
Auntie.
Ewa. Boy boy kin.
Yes. Wave bye-bye.
Xwedê we risq ke.
May God provide for you.
Xwedê we risq ke maşallah.
May God provide for you, Mashallah.
Bixwînin ha, hûn mektebê nexwînin, hefte tê ez warim, hûn
nexwînin, aqûbet kel wakeve. Gutye bixwînin.
Study well okay, if you don't study at school, next week
when I come, if you haven't studied, the consequences will
be bad. I said study.
Rast xeber didê xalo.
The uncle is speaking the truth.
Înşallah... Înşallah xeleqek din, înşallah ez ê çêkem
teber'a kî ji qicikê mektebê ra, ez ê çêkem, defter û qelem
û çentê ye mektebê, em ê ji van qicikan ra bînin.
God willing... God willing, another episode, God willing I
will make a donation for the school kids, I will do it,
notebooks and pens and school bags, we will bring them for
these kids.
Ma kî derê ixtiyar kir, em ê wekî qirrekî çêkin, kîj o gundî
damkarin, kitêb û defter em ê bînin ji qicika ra, mla...
We chose this place, we will make a decision, which of the
villagers are capable, books and notebooks we will bring for
the kids, so that...
Da di gundo da kar hîç tune, mla ba'elim in, xwendinê.
Since there is no work at all in the villages, let them be
educated, reading.
Xêncî xwendinê kî çu bukin?
Other than studying, what can they do?
Wa em nizim bixwînin.
So let them study well.
Abno, kul wahid bi xamse?
Guys, each one is five? [Arabic: kul wahid bi khamsa]
Yek, dudu, sisê, çar, pênc, şeş, heft. Wara ha.
One, two, three, four, five, six, seven. Come here.
Em van jî bibin, ha.
Let's take these too, here.
Hine, bibin.
Here, take them.
Heft. Bigir ha, heft, bisebir. Heft, heyşt, neh, deh.
Seven. Take it here, seven, hold on. Seven, eight, nine,
ten.
Dav yek. Îdaş wahid? Xalis.
Eleven. Eleven [Arabic]? Done.
Wahid baxşîş?
One as a tip?
Ko yekî mi da, yekî...
Here I gave one, one...
Min indek wahid? Hey.
One from you [Arabic]? Okay.
Şukran, ye'tîk el-afiye. Hine, hine, bibin.
Thank you, God give you health. Here, here, take them.
Ha. Hine, wina. Ha, birin.
Here. Here, you guys. Here, run along.
De... Sat xweş hecî, şukran, ye'tîk el-afiye. Boy boy.
Okay... Have a good time Hajj, thank you, God give you
health. Bye-bye.
Boy boy.
Bye-bye.
Bi xatirê te.
Goodbye.
Te çi got me'zet?
What did you say, with apologies?
Meke, tîrîk sakirî bûn.
Don't do it, the tires were locked.
De war ko em an...
Come on let's now...
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Qiciko kêf kir, welleh.
The kids were happy, honestly.
Erê welle, xwedê berqeda belo ke, xwedê barqeda belo ke.
Yes honestly, may God prevent trouble, may God prevent
trouble.
Maşallah, miletekî pir zerxweş e, niş'ebî, şa'bî.
Mashallah, a very pleasant people, lively, popular.
Evî dey, nuke hîn şa'bî yê wan no.
This one here, now their popularity is not [fully shown
yet].
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Îş û ta'etê yek jî je qut nabe.
One's work and obedience [livelihood] does not get cut off
from it.
Yanî yek şil tet, yek qitme? Maşallah, xwedê ji giyo razî
be. Zerxweş nin maşallah.
You mean one is wet underneath, one is dry? Mashallah, may
God be pleased with all. They are pleasant, Mashallah.
Welle pir kêfxweş bûm bi vê miletî va ra.
Honestly I was very happy with these people.
Sato wa xweş xoltî!
Have a good time, Auntie!
Ela boy boy.
Come on, bye-bye.
Boy boy, xwedê ji wa razî be.
Bye-bye, may God be pleased with you.
Sat xweş, xalo qicik pir kêfxweş bûn.
Have a good time, Uncle, the kids were very happy.
Qicik basît nin, basît, sa ke.
The kids are simple, simple, look.
Xwedê barqeda belo ke.
May God prevent trouble.
Bazar jî taban hîn hereket tine ye.
The market, of course, still has no movement.
Hîn hereket tine ye, hine bî sê bazar ne çêdibê, hîn milet
ne'limî ye.
Still no movement, look, about three markets are held, the
people still haven't gotten used to it.
No milet ba'elimê bazar heye, ê potix, ê xidre jî wînin, ê
her tişt kî wînin.
No, when the people get used to there being a market, they
will bring melons, they will bring vegetables too, they will
bring everything.
Gundê dûr me jî warin.
Those from distant villages will come too.
Le, ê ba'elim in, coka wa bazar çêkir, ê ba'elim in, ceme'e
jî wa bî.
Yes, they will get used to it, since they made a market,
they will get used to it, the gathering will be like that
too.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Rind bû.
It was good.
Em hîn gund dernaketin.
We haven't left the village yet.
Em hîn na gund da nê.
We are still inside the village.
Welle gundê me fereh e.
Honestly our village is spacious.
Livir daweta dikin?
Do they hold weddings here?
E hewstiyê me re, hişyê mezin.
That is our courtyard, the big courtyard.
No ez dibêm hewşê ne mezin e.
No, I'm saying the courtyards are big.
No şebeka, yanî şebekê avê, şebekê...
No the network, I mean the water network, the network...
Qeblî me hewşnê hemberê giyo darxistin.
Before us, they planted all the facing courtyards.
Maşallah, gundekî pir xweş e.
Mashallah, it is a very nice village.
Gundekî pir dirêj be, yanî emkanî bin av bikin têda
bişxilin.
It's a very long village, meaning if there were
possibilities to irrigate, to work in it.
Dî... du ciz e.
It... it has two parts.
Gund î wa, maşallah gundekî mezin e.
Your village, Mashallah it is a big village.
Welle hewşek avna lvir dopir nin.
Honestly, a courtyard like these here is full.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Xwedê 'emrê dirêj bide xwedîyê wan.
May God give long life to their owners.
Gundîkî pir mezin e.
It is a very big village.
De ka em herin a we tekin.
So come on let's go put yours [make your delivery/visit].
Li berka ne, li jêr e.
It's at the front, it's down below.
Em ê herin jêr, em ê bizivirin.
We will go down, we will turn around.
Heta em ji vî alî derkevin ne?
Until we exit from this side, right?
E em ê derkevin.
Yes we will exit.
Pasorî avka em tefora rehet bikin.
The passport [or pass/road], let us make the crossing easy.
Ewe, wana şabek, wana ji gundekî şabek marora hebe, rêka
peşmaroke, rinde.
Yes, those networks, those from a village that has a network
for us, the path of the Peshmerga, it's good.
E tizonî no, heta em pêşda werin, mesele, tehdîrat o çêkin,
û me'lûmato ser gund bidin, kû am harin, û tek û cor gund va
kin, yanî pir zehmet dibe, bo me jî.
Yes you know right, until we come forward, for example, make
preparations, and give information about the village, that
we are coming, and open the odd and even [parts] of the
village, I mean it becomes very difficult, for us too.
E em ê ema jî vidimage efewî ne, an miface'et derketin.
Yes, we also in this regard are spontaneous, or turning up
as a surprise.
El waqih, çi heye em dardixin. Em tehdîrato çê nakin.
The reality, whatever exists we show it. We don't make
preparations.
Ah tizonî ev bername pirsa gund dike.
Oh you know this program asks about the village.
E.
Yes.
E çawa gund avabû, kî avakir, çend mal in, çend kes in.
Yes how the village was built, who built it, how many
houses, how many people.
Te bîvîro cew germ e ne?
You see the weather is hot, right?
Asê cehime, tne hinek... hinek şewq.
It's like hell, only a little... a little light [sun].
A we neqle hotim bro, berod ê, ba... ba... ba kêm bî, ba
mekêm bî.
That time I came brother, it was cold, wind... wind... the
wind was little, the wind wasn't little.
E me ba qut nebû, bes wî rojê şewq.
Yes our wind didn't stop, but that day the sun [was strong].
Ha, buro pir germ e.
Yeah, brother it is very hot.
Tibe.
Indeed.
Abo xalkî, milet avê ji vir dadigire, ne?
Look uncle, the people fill water from here, right?
E ji bîrê.
Yes from the well.
Ji bîrê dadigirin. Sîtêl biçitînin cema.
They fill from the well. Buckets planted [placed] for the
community.
Bidesit bî.
It was by hand.
Bidesit bî?
It was by hand?
E rinde, bereket bixe.
Yes it's good, may it bring blessings.
Lo mila hebe.
As long as there is some.
Hebe, ava şor heye.
There is, there is salty water.
Cîran o biname.
Neighbors [unclear].
E re.
Yes right.
Em ji vî derê bizivirin.
Let's turn from here.
Em ê bizivirin.
We will turn.
Rind e, maşallah.
Good, Mashallah.
Gundekî pir xweş e.
It is a very nice village.
E vîna Kelê.
And this is the Castle.
E.
Is this the Castle?
Yes.
Vîna Kela gund e.
This is the village Castle.
E kela kevnar e.
Yes it is an ancient castle.
Bê vîno bavêje, bavêje ser Kelê. Wê Kelê jî bigire.
Let him cast this, cast it on the Castle. Film that Castle
too.
Kevnar e?
It is ancient?
E kevnar e.
Yes it is ancient.
Kela kevnar e.
It is an ancient Castle.
E dîwarê wê hîn dîyar in.
Yes its walls are still visible.
E welle rast e.
Yes honestly it is true.
Hîn diyar in, le hinekî xera bûn e.
Still visible, but somewhat ruined.
E.
Yes.
Avoli me li vê kelê jî bigir.
First film this castle for us too.
Erê, avol no, Kelok li vî derê jî heye.
Yes, first then, there is a small Castle in this place too.
Lê em nizanin dîroka wê çi ye.
But we don't know what its history is.
Ta bidakê didin orna ga'elmidinê.
Until [someone] gives a sign [explanation] there, they will
learn about it.
Were Kela bere bertam mezin bî? Seke?
Come, was the Castle bigger before? Look?
Sê sed mal e, vê gundo.
Three hundred houses, this village.
Sê sed mal e, vê gundo?
Three hundred houses, this village?
Sê sed hewş e.
Three hundred courtyards.
Dakê da zarem kebra yan a glek.
[Unclear - likely about it being big or crowded].
Abo akîd bila bila dîwarê gundî wina.
Look, surely these are the walls of the village.
Dîwar giya heye.
The walls are all there.
No gund tiji ye. Gi hewa.
No the village is full. It's all air [open/visible].
E hewa.
Yes air.
Yekê we, berwê malê de jî heye.
One of yours, in front of that house there is one too.
E.
Yes.
E wanê hewşek.
Yes that is a courtyard.
Hewşê hember in.
They are facing courtyards.
Êm dîwar e, dîwar.
And walls, walls.
Dîwarê xobî bere.
Walls of [unclear - adobe/mud?] before.
E.
Yes.
Dîwarê kevin.
Old walls.
E.
Yes.
Bêje kevin.
Say old.
E kevin e tizonî.
Yes it is old you know.
Le keran î yo, kevir e kevir.
But it is stone, stone and stone.
E kevir û herî.
Yes stone and mud.
Bazar wa no, cam wa çêbê pir xweş bibe ho.
The market like that, if the glass [display/atmosphere] is
made like that it will be very nice.
Milet qane nare Efrîn, nare dera.
The people convinced not to go to Afrin, not to go outside.
Ne we? Çi garek be, hefte hefteyê bibin.
Isn't it? Whatever is needed, let it be week by week.
Qisûrî kem be, kofirî kê tewsîlê her, ekîd bi şexs ke,
herin.
Let the shortage be less, [unclear - likely about delivery
services], surely by person, let them go.
E pênca, pêncora her şexsê sed wereq bas tînin.
Yes fifty, for five every person brings only a hundred
papers [money].
E.
Yes.
Abolî me vê hewşê ha, wane hember mabikir, vona, vê kelan.
Look at this courtyard here, look at the facing one, those,
these castles.
Nîşan nade.
It doesn't show.
De van nîşan nade.
It doesn't show these.
Lo vî malno jî bigir.
Film these houses too.
Ha.
Here.
Ewa.
Yes.
E vana.
And these.
Bigir.
Film it.
De...
Okay...
Kinisî ye?
Is it a church?
Belê kinisî ye, ya wira. Kinisî ya...
Yes it is a church, that one there. It is a church...
Aha, lê bi fermî, navê wê yê rast, rast mi jûr çiye, you
know?
Aha, but officially, what is its real name, frankly, do you
Tawus e, seke vî alî tawus heye, vî alî wurt e wekî rû ye.
It is a peacock, look on this side there is a peacock, on
this side it is a figure like a face.
Aha, tawusek li vî alî ye, tawusek li vrê û rûyê ji di wurtê
da ye wekî rû ye.
Aha, a peacock is on this side, a peacock there, and a face
is in the figure like a face.
Erê, gih naqişî çêkirine.
Yes, they have all made carvings.
Pir kevnar e hef jî.
It is very ancient too.
Wa dî ye, wa dî ye, çet... her tîbe kevir çêkirine.
Yes.
It is visible, it is visible... whatever it is, they made it
of stone.
Maşallah, ha kevir kî çû kirine vî derê?
Mashallah, how did they put this stone here?
Heta.
Even.
Erê, ev hewş no...
Yes, these courtyards...
Ev hewş no jî pir kevnar ne, derece, tiştê ginde pir kevn e.
These courtyards are also very ancient, the stairs, things
of the village are very old.
Ez bawer dikim ez li derê dinyayê me.
I believe I am outside of this world.
Aha, havlî me dîroka wê jî bigire derxîne.
Aha, my friend, capture its history too, bring it out.
Nîzîk bike.
Zoom in.
Eyne xûyn we re.
Look, read it.
Maşallah. Gundekî mîr e.
Mashallah. It is a princely village.
Kele ne li jêr e jî.
There are castles below too.
Gundî we tev de kele ye lo, tev de eserî ye.
Your village is entirely castles man, entirely historical
artifacts.
Oh, mê.
Oh, look.
Binêre rimetî gund lo ye, binêre hewşê xo binêre.
Look at the value of the village man, look at its
courtyards.
Havlî me dûrçoyê me bikişîne.
My friend, film our view through the binoculars.
Wêr heta...
There until...
Mewqiê we pir bilind e.
Your location is very high.
Kîbar e maşallah.
It is beautiful, mashallah.
Vê hewşê no... vê hewşê giyo derxist.
These courtyards... grass has grown out of this courtyard.
Zef nagiştin vî derê.
They didn't reach here much.
Erê dîsa tehliya...
Yes, again the trouble...
Bi meşê nav gund bike re... bi rê ve... basko bide newê.
Walk inside the village... on the road... turn to the
valley.
... mala... be meşê nav gund hûretire...
... house... walking inside the village is finer...
Bi fehm neza berê...
Understanding, before...
Yakî zêde ye.
One is too much.
Lê hecer çê dikin.
But they make stone.
Hecer?
Stone?
Hecer...
Stone...
Hecer?
Stone?
Erê dîsa...
Yes again...
Ma rebbî çi kelar... xef haydikin?
Oh Lord, what castles... how do they keep it?
Çi hewş di virdo girtine?
What courtyards are occupied around here?
Belê.
Yes.
Maşallah. Hewşek kîbar e.
Mashallah. A beautiful courtyard.
E rêka camaa... ev demim... yanî asar di virdo pirr ne,
gerek rêka camaa gez...
The mosque road... this time... meaning ruins are many
around here, the mosque road should be cleaned...
Zift pan e.
Asphalt is wide.
Zift pan e?
Asphalt is wide?
Erê yani berê... gis wa hildigirtin na we?
Yes, meaning before... they all carried it like that, didn't
they?
Wa hildigirtin, riya çêkirana berê xweş e... nîvîsandin.
They carried it like that, the road construction of the past
is good... writing.
Lê tiştê asarî dinav wa de heye, gerek rêka camaa gez zift
bana, ge pak bana.
But there are historical things inside them, the mosque road
should have been asphalted, should be very clean.
Eş nebî danin, gerek çêkiribana.
If there isn't fire put down, it should have been made.
Heta nuka kofiya mûyî nizanin... ooo birjî tot de tiştê
kevin hene.
Until now they don't know the hair kofi... ooo in the tower
there are old things.
Wan ê aser... av dikin... bi emel dikin no lê sêr dikin çawa
dikin.
Those historical ones... they water... they process them,
look how they do it.
Biner, kevirê...
Look, the stone...
Bi jor de xwar bûn, ne ne xwar bûn.
They came down from above, no they didn't come down.
Heta bi jor de.
Even from above.
Welle semon li vî derê jî heye.
By God, there is cement here too.
Welle hewşê virdo pirr ne...
By God, the courtyards around here are many...
Ev hewşa Hacer Teyr e.
This is the courtyard of Hacer Teyr.
Oo rind e.
Oo good.
Her sal...
Every year...
Darê çi ye dizanî?
Do you know what tree this is?
Falûte ne? Yan gelbe rû?
Is it acorn? Or wild pear?
Na, falûte ne.
No, it is acorn.
Selamun aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleykum selam.
And upon you peace.
Sehet xweş.
Good health.
Ev av li berê bigire.
Film this water from the front.
Wasat, wasat.
Middle, middle.
Erê hevalno li vî derê jî em gihiştin talyê vîdyo xwe.
Yes friends, here we have reached the end of our video.
Inşallah wa vîdyo me ecibandibe.
God willing, you liked this video of ours.
Lê nî pirr cî... bêcûz me derneketibe mera... qusûrî efû
kin...
But because many places... maybe it didn't come out for us
to see... forgive the faults...
Ji ber ku vîdyo pirr dirêj bî ji bo min.
Because the video became very long for me.
Ka kase mala xwe derneketî bila qusûrî efû ke.
If someone's house didn't appear, let them forgive the
fault.
Saeta we xweş. Bi mera bin, vîdyokî din, xweş, kîbar.
Have a good time. Stay with us, for another video, nice,
beautiful.
Heke mala we derneketî şîrove de binivîsin emê.
If your house didn't appear, write in the comments, we
will...
Şîrove de binivîsin inşallah emê werin nêzîk de emê dîsa
werin, bazar cîkî şên bibe emê dîsa werin helqek din çêkin
inşallah.
Write in the comments, God willing we will come soon, we
will come again, if the market becomes a lively place, we
will come again and make another episode, God willing.
Lê nî bazar hêna we... me pirr jamaa eciband.
Because the market is still... we liked the community a lot.
Saeta te jî xweş... te meta xwe rehet kir.
Your health also be good... you tired yourself out.
Hadi ye.
It's okay.
Xwedê emrê ki dirêj bide te de.
May God give you a long life.
Maşallah miletî vî gundî wekî vê pêşketî ye, zêr xweş ne.
Mashallah, the people of this village are developed like
this, very nice.
Bi mera bin vîdyokî din xweş kîbar inşallah emê werin o miş
kin û milê şîrove we jî pirr bin.
Stay with us for another nice, beautiful video, God willing
we will come and ... and may your comments be many.
Bye bye. Xwedê ji we razî be.
Bye bye. May God be pleased with you.