Were, Semîr were.
Come, Semir come.
Evo Elî ye.
This is Ali.
Are, apo lo, ev cihê Elî ye, kesî nas nake tenê apo.
Yes, uncle, this is Ali's place, no one knows him except
uncle.
Slovo bişîne, slovo.
Send a greeting, a greeting.
Qereşî ye?
Is it Qereshi?
A, tu muxtar e?
Ah, are you the mukhtar?
Ha ha ha.
Erê apo lo, ev der e jî saha Şiyê ye. Dewer o ye, ev der e
dewer o ye.
Yes uncle, this place is the Sah of Shiye. It is the
roundabout, this place is the roundabout.
Gundî Şiyê ye.
The people of Shiye.
Kesî ji bo Ewropa tine.
There is no one for Europe.
Tine?
None?
I hotê wari.
Those who came, came.
I hotê wari, i ne hot mila qale qale.
Those who came, came, those who didn't come are just talk.
Erê biçin e, mûz... mûz pêncî wereq e.
Yes go, bananas... bananas are fifty papers.
Mûz pêncî, yanî dolar e o...
Bananas fifty, meaning dollars or...
We ne dî, mûz kîlo heke bi sedî şêst... Heke bizewicin
derbak mekin, hinke werin.
Don't you see, if a kilo of bananas is one hundred sixty...
If they get married don't delay, let some come.
Siba dê tayre qis kin werin.
Tomorrow they will cut the tire and come.
Apo lo, li vê derê, hem hatin ketin...
Uncle, here, they also came entered...
Li vê derê jî dawet heye. Ka bimire bin...
Here there is also a wedding. Let's see...
...ji teleban û mûşahdîna ye.
...from the requests and viewers.
Ka kerem kin, ji mutabîna re jî sitranekê pê dine.
Please, play a song for the followers too.
Merheba hevalno, hûru dîsa em wer hatine vîdyoyekî xweş û
kîbar. Hez dikin em likin e.
Hello friends, today again we have come with a nice and
lovely video. We hope you like it.
Vê derê gelî Şiyê ye, kaniyik heye, vêra dibên Kaniya Sor...
yan vêra wa dibên. Wek ez zanim.
This place is the Shiye valley, there is a spring, they call
it the Red Spring... or they call it like that. As I know.
Vîdyo me jî hûru em ketin nav Şiyê ye. Em ketin nav Şiyê ye.
Our video today, we entered inside Shiye. We entered inside
Shiye.
Dost û ehbab xwestî... nav gundî Şiyê, em kî teswîr kin.
Friends and loved ones asked... inside the village of Shiye,
for us to film.
Bimînin, vîdyoyekî xweş kîbar, nav Şiyê ye, em ê çêkin.
Bimînin heta toliyê vîdyo.
Stay tuned, a nice lovely video, inside Shiye, we will make.
Stay until the end of the video.
Hindik me jî em bedea hazir kirine, seata we xweş, xwedê ji
we razî be.
We have also prepared some things, have a good time, may God
be pleased with you.
Ma ze tu gotinê ten e?
Don't you have anything to say?
Merheba hevalno, we çûne, îşê we çûne, siheta we çûne, şolê
we ger û rehet ne?
Hello friends, how are you, how is your work, how is your
health, are your affairs rolling and comfortable?
Bimînin, vîdyoyekî xweş kîbar, em hatin gundî Şiyê werê
bisewirînin.
Stay tuned, a nice lovely video, we came to the village of
Shiye to film it.
Bîr nekin, me re laykê û îştrîkê pê din. Û seata we giya
xweş.
Don't forget, give us likes and subscriptions. And have a
good time everyone.
Erê hevalno, vê derê me go em legel in e. Ka hevala min vê
tebîhetê jî bigir.
Yes friends, here we said we are together. Here my friend,
capture this nature too.
Tebîhet ek pir xweş e.
The nature is very nice.
Hêşînahî, zeytûnê me jî xwedê... dar e. Im Semîr?
Greenery, our olives too God... are trees. Um Semir?
Çûbît... ve de hese?
Where did he go... is he over there?
Ere darê li wir wa, çiparax binin de. Darê li wir wa binin
de.
Yes the trees are there, under the twigs. The trees are
there under them.
Gundî Şiyê ye.
It's the village of Shiye.
Hevalno mintiqa pir xweş e.
Friends, the area is very nice.
Darê kivî...
Kiwi trees...
Kaniya heye? Werin bala xwe pê din.
Is there a spring? Come pay attention to it.
Vax vax.
Wow wow.
Maşalla avekî hênik e. Hevalno kûr e.
Mashallah, a cool water. Friends, it is deep.
Avê xwe hênik e, bûz e bûz. Maşalla.
Its water is cool, it's ice, ice. Mashallah.
Wan bixwin werin.
Eat those, come.
Xweş e, hênik e?
Is it good, is it cool?
Ere, pir xweş e.
Yes, very good.
Hevalno, milletê me, milletê me ewa... jînketî ye, ne
pêşketî ye. Alem gi pêşket, em... em pêşnakevin.
Friends, our nation, our nation is this... backward, not
developed. The whole world developed, we... we don't
develop.
Xasatan em, em milletê me em kurmanc, em pêşnakevin, kûk.
Mizanim xêr e?
Especially us, our nation us Kurds, we don't develop, at
all. Do you know why?
Yanî em derin kî derê, em şûnê xwe digemirînin em tên. Em
derin rehla keyfê dikin.
Meaning wherever we go, we dirty our place and we come back.
We go on a picnic to enjoy.
Û xwarin vaxwarina em dixwin, û wê zibalê jî em gi şûnê xwe
dêlin.
And food and drink we consume, and that trash too we leave
all of it in our place.
Yanî, yo yo xo nabînin, yo qil kêmî wa dikin, ez nizanim.
Bas li vê derê binerin.
Meaning, either either they don't see themselves, or they
act lowly, I don't know. Just look at this place.
Noka rûk kamil gereke maro vê zibalê berevke. Yanî vê derê
nîmetek heye.
Now a full day is needed for a man to gather this trash.
Meaning here there is a blessing.
Xêr bereketek heye li vê derê. Xêr bereketek li vir heye,
milet xorê vê vira tê, avekî xwo vedixwe, çavê xwo dişû.
There is goodness and abundance here. There is goodness and
abundance here, people come here for themselves, drink some
water, wash their eyes.
Bin vir jî, ro têne, têne vê derê şevî xwo çêdikin. Etemena
kes zibalê xwo ça neke vê derê nalet.
Under here too, they come, come here and spend their
evening. I hope no one throws their trash here damn it.
Bes şîşa û zibalê binerin. Yanî madî maro nayê, maro li vir
rûniye.
Just look at the bottles and trash. Meaning essentially a
man won't come, a man won't sit here.
Seke xêr bêr li vir heye, û madî te nayê ti li vir rûniye.
Bas hevala min li vir bigir.
Look there is goodness here, and essentially you won't come
to sit here. Just my friend capture here.
Binerin. Em pêşnakevin. Yanî her mayekî yek, we xwar zibalê
xwo di tûrikê xwo kin.
Look. We don't develop. Meaning every single one, you ate,
put your trash in your bag.
Xora bibin çakin cî zibalê bişewitînin. O bin vê derê madî
te nayê ti rûniye.
Take it with you throw it in a trash place or burn it. Or
under here essentially you won't come to sit.
Yanî milet xizmet cuxrafiya xwo dike, xizmet tebîeta xwo
dike, em e jî em xira dikin. Ne eyb e, yo xo bibînin.
Meaning nations serve their geography, serve their nature,
and we, we destroy it. Isn't it a shame, see yourselves.
O noka eke em vîdyo çêkim, ya ji vê gemarê jî berev kim,
anca rûk kamil gereke min ra, wa binale?
Or now if I make a video, or to gather this dirt too, barely
a full day is needed for me, isn't it so?
Ti ji ya.
It is true.
We jî derin vîdyo xwo çêkim. Wala nizanim.
I'm also going to make my video. Well I don't know.
Ya eşaş me, yo xînci me şaş ne. De nizanim. Em e jî vîdyo me
heke efuyê çê dikim.
Either I am wrong, or others are wrong. I don't know. We too
make our video if with apology.
Şaşbûnê me hene, qusûrê efû kin. Ka were em man Şiyê.
If we have mistakes, pardon the faults. Come let's go to
Shiye.
Hevalî min were em man Şiyê. Were, Semîr were.
My friend come let's go to Shiye. Come, Semir come.
Erê hevalno, li vê derê jî, em li gundî Şiyê ne. Şêx Hedîd
vêra dibên. Hav tebîhetê gund e.
Yes friends, here too, we are in the village of Shiye. They
call it Sheikh Hadid. This is the nature of the village.
Seke binerin çiqas kîbar e. Rêka gund ziftê jî paq çêkirine.
Look how lovely it is. The asphalt road of the village is
also made well.
Maşalla, ji gundî Şiyê ra rêk paq çêkirine, ana kîbar
çêkirine.
Mashallah, for the village of Shiye they made the road well,
very lovely they made it.
Bimînin, tebîhetek xweş, li nav tebîhetê gundî Şiyê.
Maşalla, rêk zift kirine, paq çêkirine.
Stay tuned, a nice nature, inside the nature of Shiye
village. Mashallah, they asphalted the road, made it well.
Sehet xweş. Bimînin noka em leqtek xweş nav gunda rxin.
Good health. Stay tuned now we will put a nice clip inside
the village.
Erê hevalno, vê derê jî saha Şiyê ye. Dewer o ye, vê derê
dewer o ye.
Yes friends, here is the square of Shiye. The roundabout,
here is the roundabout.
Gundî Şiyê... xwo îspat kin ser vîdyo gundî xwo.
People of Shiye... prove yourselves on the video of your
village.
Ez axiriyan, ez hatim gundî Şiyê. Maşalla mehlet... kîbar
na.
I finally, I came to the village of Shiye. Mashallah the
neighborhood... is lovely.
Hareket rind e ma. Maşalla seke.
The movement is good man. Mashallah look.
Hevala min li vir jî bigir mehela... Ko were were, mirov
were.
My friend capture here too the neighborhood... Come come
come, man come.
Selamun Eleykum. Hûn çawa ne?
Peace be upon you. How are you?
Eleykum Selam, ehlen we sehlen.
Peace upon you, welcome.
Merheba xalo.
Hello uncle.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Tu halê we, keyfa we çawa ye?
How is your condition, your mood?
Bî selameti.
With health.
Hûn çawa ne?
How are you?
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Siheta we çawa ye? Xalo, o we ye, bostana we ye?
How is your health? Uncle, is that yours, is the garden
yours?
Wela nanê me ne, û cîranê me ji o we.
Well it's our bread, and our neighbor is that one.
E, şixil çawa ye, heket rind e?
Uh, how is work, is activity good?
Tine.
None.
Tine?
None?
Maşalla ez se dikim heket nav milet pir e.
Mashallah I look and see activity among the people is a lot.
E noka e... noka nîv seata din tu kesî veşernake. Germ dibe
na?
Uh now uh... now in another half hour you won't find anyone.
It gets hot right?
Haraket hebe hebe tê nanê xwo dibin diçin dikan diyo kin.
If there is activity, they come take their bread and go
close the shops.
Dinya germ dibe gi dikevin hindir î.
The world gets hot everyone goes inside.
Eywa. Maşalla milet ji min daxwaz dibe gundî Şiyê teswîr ke.
Ev o gundê Şiyê.
Okay. Mashallah the people request from me to film the
village of Shiye. This is the village of Shiye.
Evo kaniya ne xalo? Evo kaniya? Ko?
These are the springs right uncle? Are these the springs?
Where?
Heşk bûye? Wara hevala min wa kaniya bisewirîne.
Has it dried? Come my friend film those springs.
Wê kaniyê?
That spring?
Heşk bûye?
Has it dried?
Kaniya... bin mizgeftê.
The spring... under the mosque.
A. Hevala min kaniyê bigir.
Ah. My friend capture the spring.
Hevalno kanî li vir heye, bes kanî heşk bûye wela.
Friends there is a spring here, but the spring has dried up
honestly.
Xalo mer dibê kanî heşk bûye. Gamor tê de.
The uncle says the spring has dried. Mud is in it.
Evo Elî ye.
This is Ali.
Are, apo lo, ev cihê Elî ye, kesî nas nake tenê apo.
Yes, uncle, this is Ali's place, no one knows him except
uncle.
Slovo bişîne, slovo.
Send a greeting, greeting.
Goreşî ye.
It's Goreshi.
A, tu muxtar e?
Ah, are you the mukhtar?
Ha ha ha.
Ere, Yala bay bay.
Yes, Yallah bye bye.
Ez bawer dikim xalo.
I believe uncle.
Ne bawer dikim... falan kes falan kes te nas dike.
I don't believe... so-and-so so-and-so knows you.
Lê lê lê, çawa nas nakin.
Le le le, how do they not know.
Heke we ye.
If it's yours.
Na na, ne ecnebi me na, nas dikin.
No no, I'm not a foreigner, they know.
Ne?
No?
Ez kurekî Kurmanc im.
I am a Kurdish boy.
Tu ji kîderê yî?
Where are you from?
Xalo tu çi silava dişîne miletî Şiyê ro li Ewropa, milet wa
rin?
Uncle what greetings do you send to the people of Shiye in
Europe, are the people there?
Kesî li Ewropa tine. Gi pişkin.
There is no one in Europe. They are all gone.
I hotê wari.
Those who came, came.
I hotê wari, i ne hot mila qale qale.
Those who came, came, those who didn't come are just talk.
Ha. De hevalno ko. Gundî Şiyê kesî nas nake.
Ha. So friends look. People of Shiye don't know anyone.
Xalo silava ji we re dişîne.
Uncle sends greetings to you.
Kesî nas nake.
He doesn't know anyone.
Silav û hurmet.
Greetings and respect.
Ere, silav lê bin.
Yes, greetings be upon him.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Avolno, vana işta, hereket pir e ho!
Guys, look at this, there is a lot of activity/movement
here, huh!
Hereket pir e ne, li gundê Şiyê?
There is a lot of activity, isn't there, in the village of
Shiye?
Erê.
Yes.
Were.
Come.
Ev çend e reqem de xalo?
How much is this number [price], uncle?
Pênc û deh.
Five and ten.
Pênc û deh, hay pênc e, tabaa me'denus e.
Five and ten, this is five, for the parsley.
Hay reqem yanî qedeş?
This number means how much?
Pênc lîra.
Five Lira.
Pênc lîra?
Five Lira?
Ê.
Yes.
Yanî çend sent?
Meaning how many cents?
Ma bi rûxmî... pênc sent mû? Yanî, yanî.
Like roughly... five cents, right? Approximately,
approximately.
Bi pênc wereqî tirk... avolno, nan pênc wereq tirk.
For five Turkish papers [notes]... guys, the bread [parsley]
is five Turkish notes.
Û em tivê hej derbas kim, he?
And we will pass through further, okay?
Derbas bin, derbas bin.
Pass through, pass through.
Wele, 'indkun tebî'a, cemal, kûyis.
By God, you have nature, beauty, it's good.
Helwe, cenet e hon.
It's beautiful, it's paradise here.
Cenet e mû?
It's paradise, isn't it?
Elhemdu lîlah.
Praise be to God.
Ê wele.
Yes, by God.
Erê avolno, vî derî...
Yes guys, this place...
Em li gundê Şiyê ne, mewerre wekû, tebî'eta per xweş e, per
kîbar e.
We are in the village of Shiye, as you can see, the nature
is very nice, very elegant.
Hereket pir e, zehmet e maşallah.
There is a lot of activity, it's crowded, Mashallah.
Seh, Seh.
Correct, correct.
Erê.
Yes.
Ka bimerin bin, xudanê kulê extîaran, xweş mrov, em ê ginc
hekin.
Let's go down, the owners of all [these shops] are elders,
good people, we will talk to them.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Tu sax bî şêx hecî.
May you be healthy, Sheikh Haji.
Wele, şukran.
To your health.
By God, thank you.
Yallah.
Thank you.
Let's go.
Şukran hebîbî.
Thank you, my dear.
Avolno, li vî derî jî hember camiyê, bira cîh s... semûn
haye, xidr e.
Guys, right here opposite the mosque, brothers, there is a
place... this is the Khidr [tree/shrine].
Wêra dibên Mihemedî Firîkê. Ka derbas bin em xolî Mihemed
pirskin.
They call it Muhammedi Firike. Let's pass by and ask Uncle
Muhammad.
Hello, selam.
Hello, greetings.
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Hello, uncle.
Welcome.
Tu çawa yî, sihet çawa ye?
How are you, how is your health?
Wele elhemdu lîlah, tu hatî xêrê.
By God, praise be to God, welcome.
Wele elhemdu lîlah.
By God, praise be to God.
Dêrîk, ahlan wa sahlan.
Derik [referring to host's origin], welcome.
Xolo, ekîd miletê Şiyê giş tenê ne?
Uncle, surely the people of Shiye are all one [united]?
Teb'en.
Naturally.
Ê Ewrûpa û dera...
And Europe and places...
Gi dera.
Everywhere.
Ha.
I see.
Xolo hereket çawa ye? We da?
Uncle, how is the movement/business? With you?
Wele hereket, elhemdu lîlah. Yani meşî el hal e, meşî el hal
e.
By God, the movement, praise be to God. I mean, it's getting
by, it's getting by.
Ha.
I see.
Es'ar biçine?
How are the prices?
Mûz biçine, mûz?
How much are bananas, bananas?
Mûz pêncî wereq e.
Bananas are fifty notes [likely 25-50 TL contextually].
Mûz pêncî, yanî dolarek û bîst û pênc sent e.
Bananas are fifty, meaning one dollar and twenty-five cents.
Û sêv?
Yes.
And apples?
Sêv şêstî... şêstî.
Apples are sixty... sixty.
Şêstî.
Sixty.
Teqrîben ew jî kêmi du dolar e, sêv.
Approximately that is also less than two dollars, apples.
Ha.
I see.
Bamî biçin e?
Okra?
How much is okra?
Bamî heftê û pênc e.
Okra is seventy-five.
Û hevna çelî?
And these are forty?
Hevna bi heftê û pênc ne, bamî.
These are seventy-five, the okra.
Û hevna jî xolo dibê çelî.
These ones are forty.
And for these, the uncle says forty.
Me'ne hişkiri ne ne.
Meaning they are dried ones, right.
Ha.
Yes.
Erê.
Xolo tu çi silavê dişînî ji milet ra?
Uncle, what greetings do you send to the people?
Wele, silavê ji vî miletî giş ra hene.
By God, there are greetings to all these people.
Bi seheta we xweş. Û Xwedê we razî be, û Xwedê eyyame we
zimîk ke inşallah.
May your health be good. And may God be pleased with you,
and may God make your days [prosperous/bright] God willing.
Amîn, amîn. Maşallah, hereket nav gundê we de rind e, xweş
e.
Amen, amen. Mashallah, the activity inside your village is
good, it's nice.
Hereket heye elhemdu lîlah.
There is activity, praise be to God.
Şêna... Ev çiqas kevn e? Çiqas kevn e?
Ancient... How old is this? How old is it [the mosque/tree]?
Hene, hene.
It is, it is.
Got mezin e?
They said it's big/old?
Çiqas sal e xolo?
Yes...
How many years, uncle?
Dizanî?
Do you know?
Teqrîben...
Approximately...
Hezar, çar pênc sed mole...
A thousand, four or five hundred [years] old...
Ewe, hezar... demek edet sekanîk zere...
That is, a thousand... meaning a specific time/date...
Berê hezar sê sed...
Before one thousand three hundred...
Ta wek hezar û hinek bûyî.
Until it became one thousand and something.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Ê bes noka xay kevn e yanî, kevn e yanî.
Yes, but now brother, it is old, meaning, it is old.
Kevnar e ne, cim'ê ye xolî, emrê xwe çiqas sal e teqrîben.
It's ancient, isn't it? It's a Friday mosque uncle, its age
is approximately how many years.
Ser pênc sedî re heye?
It is a Friday mosque (Jami/Cim'ê).
Is it over five hundred?
Çiqas sale ez nizanim, bes Jmêş e.
How many years I don't know, but it is a Friday mosque.
Erê.
Yes.
Erê avo, saeta te xweş xolo.
Yes brother, good health to you uncle.
Saeta te jî xweş.
Good health to you too.
Avolno bimerin jî, noka em derkevin nav gund, em cewlekî
lêxin.
Guys, let's go down, now we will go out into the village, we
will take a tour.
Xolo xweş çêkin, tebîetek pir, mentiqek şiyê pir xweş e,
kîbar e.
The uncle explained it well, a great nature, the Shiye area
is very nice, it's elegant.
Ha, saeta xweş xolo.
Okay, have a good time uncle.
Tu ser serê me yî.
May God be pleased with you.
You are highly respected (on our heads).
Saxbê te xweş xolo.
Good health to you uncle.
Saxbê te xweş.
Good health to you.
Avolno, heva maşallah camiye, Şiyê. Bibînin işta camiye.
Guys, this is Mashallah the mosque, of Shiye. Look at the
mosque structure.
Heva camiya.
This is the mosque.
Maşallah, tebîetek pir xweş e.
Mashallah, it is a very nice nature.
Cîcak no milet, we jî derxê. Livana jî bigir vanê gulûk.
People are coming out [like flowers?]. Film these little
ones [flowers] too.
Navê te çi ye?
What is your name?
Ovan.
Huh?
Ovan?
Ê wa, tu dibê çi milet ra, tu silav kî dişînî?
Oh wow, what do you say to the people, do you send
greetings?
Ha?
Huh?
Bûy bûy kî vira.
Do "bye bye" to here.
Ovan... de wer ka, were em herin.
Ovan... come on then, come let's go.
Yallah.
Let's go.
Tune dikanê we l'kin e, dikan.
Isn't there a shop of yours nearby, a shop.
Emê kin?
Should we do it?
Huh?
Emê kin?
Should we do it?
Basim.
Hay hay.
Yes yes.
Basim, da no bibêje qesta min.
Basim, let him say my intention/request.
We 'aleykum selam.
And peace be upon you.
Kîjan waye?
Which one is it?
Li vê dikanê no bigir şirîk.
Film these shops here partner.
Berê Ehmed, evna dikanê wan o...
Look Ahmed, these are their shops...
Lê sêr kin.
Look at them.
Dikanê wa, xûratê waye.
Their shops, this is their lathe workshop.
Jê bigir.
Film it.
Maşallah, xolo dibê hedet sikonê gund pir e.
Mashallah, the uncle says the number of residents in the
village is high.
Mezin e, bajara Şiyê.
It is big, the town of Shiye.
Bego Şiyê, bazara...
They say Shiye, the market of...
Miletê xwo pir e, maşallah.
Its people are many, Mashallah.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Wa bîrê kirîn he? Wa bîro gundê xwo kirîn.
You missed it huh? You missed your village.
Kanê me da'm kin. Miletê Şiyê, xwo isbat kin ha.
Where are you, support us. People of Shiye, prove
yourselves/make your presence known here.
Emê Şiyê ne, Şiyê.
We are Shiye [residents], Shiye.
Vî derî jî wekî sîna'a ye ha.
This place is also like the industrial zone, huh.
Silam 'eleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Avolî min li hember jûr jî bigir?
My brother, film the upper side opposite us too?
Bilindî ye.
It is high ground.
Em han bilindî ye û ew jî jor, ew jî paş da.
We are on high ground here and that is also up, that is also
behind.
Wadî ye.
It is a valley.
Le ştê gundê çiqas rind e. Dor barê gundê.
Look how nice the layout of the village is. The surroundings
of the village.
Maşallah wele mezin e.
Mashallah, by God it is big.
Miletê xwo pir e.
Its people are many.
Çi tebîet?
What nature?
E he...
Oh yeah...
Cenet e, cenet.
It is paradise, paradise.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Hewşê kê derkeve, te'lîqê pir binivîskin ha.
Whoever's courtyard appears, write lots of comments, okay.
Ji vira derdikeve?
Does it exit from here?
Na na... Meşê asteng e.
No no... The path is difficult/blocked.
Eraq cem polîsê...
By the police...
Ji me vut vira derdikeve?
If we go through here does it exit?
Ha? Na na, jor derdikeve.
Huh? No no, it exits upwards.
Belkî pîşe asteng e.
No?
Maybe ahead it is blocked.
Eraq cem polîsê were.
It's blocked?
Come by the police station.
Ha.
Okay.
Muşkîle.
Problem.
Hena, ereq cem polîsê were xwarê.
There, come down by the police station.
Ha.
Okay.
Maşallah çi tebîetek xweş e. E he!
Mashallah what a beautiful nature. Oh wow!
Cenet e, cenet.
It is paradise, paradise.
Wadî ye.
It is a valley.
Le ştê gundê çiqas rind e. Dor barê gundê.
Look how nice the layout of the village is. The surroundings
of the village.
Avolno ma teb'en hatim ketim Şiyê, min izin bir.
Guys, naturally I came and entered Shiye, I got permission.
Maşallah saeta gundiyan jî wele ze'rê gundiyan xweş bîn.
Mashallah, the presence of the villagers, by God the
children of the villagers were nice.
Wala yixşimke me tu me'zûnî.
By God, forgive us/shame on us, we didn't recognize/invite
you.
Xêr tiştê rind rind e.
Anyway, things are very good.
Wala nizanim em çûk rona.
By God, I don't know where we entered.
E he!
Oh wow!
Avolno.
Guys.
Ji nav gund, em daketin xwarê.
From inside the village, we went down.
Walle Zuheyr, Zuheyr te em xistine feqe...
By God Zuheyr, Zuheyr you got us into a trap...
Qusirî me efû ke.
Forgive our fault.
Qusirî me efû ke Zuheyr...
Forgive our fault Zuheyr...
Hêşta bike.
Stop it.
Walle Zuheyr, Zuheyr te em xistine feqe, em naha di nava
meqbera da ne.
By God Zuheyr, Zuheyr you got us into a trap, we are now
inside the cemetery.
Zuheyr ma efû ke.
Zuheyr forgive us.
Hêşta bike.
Stop it.
Qusirî me efû ke Zuheyr.
Forgive our fault Zuheyr.
Vira jî... reke darê tirba ye ha hevalno.
Here too... is the path to the cemetery trees, friends.
Silavê me ji giyan ra, hûn xaçik birakê me giyan, kesê li me
seyr dikin.
Our greetings to everyone, you are all our brothers,
everyone watching us.
Erê hevalno, ev jî mala Ribcî ye, mala Ribcî vêra dibên.
Yes friends, this is the Ribji family, they call this the
Ribji family.
Reşîtê Ribcî.
Rashid Ribji.
Erê.
Yes.
Ka hevalî me li tirba jî bigre.
Let our friend film the grave too.
Birê Ehmed, ev jî tirba rehmetiyê Xidirê Hemo Xalê ke, cihê
xwe cenet be.
Brother Ahmed, this is also the grave of the late Khidir
Hemo Khale, may his place be paradise.
Hesen? Ehmed na bêje.
Hasan? He's not saying Ahmed.
Nîzik bike hevalî min.
Zoom in my friend.
Xidirê Hemo Xalê ke, cihê xwe cenet be.
Khidir Hemo Khale, may his place be paradise.
Ka ber bi vir jî.
Come this way too.
Ev jî... ya xaltîka Zelîxê ye, Xidirê Hemo Xalê ke, cihê xwe
cenet be.
This too... belongs to Aunt Zelix, Khidir Hemo Khale, may
his place be paradise.
Erê walle.
Yes, by God.
Bes gerek cem hev bana, xêj hev dûr kirine.
But they should have been together, they put them far apart.
Ma nabînin dahan.
Can't you see the wilderness.
Gerek cem hev kirina. Xidirê Hemo Xalê ke, cihê xwe cenet
be.
They should have put them together. Khidir Hemo Khale, may
his place be paradise.
Birakî me jî... ê mala Ribcî jî me tirba ne dîtin... ê mala
Ribcî.
Our brother too... the Ribji family, we didn't find the
graves... of the Ribji family.
Da ba ketim biyê... çû xoy nate... em lê digerin em nabînin.
The vegetation is thick... the place is not visible... we
search but we don't find.
Qusirî me efû ke, ka lextokê vêra tirba bigre.
Forgive our fault, film the grave here for a moment.
Ew jî mala we ye.
That is your family too.
Bes qusûr efû ke walle ez lê digerim ez nabînim.
But forgive the fault, by God I am searching, I am not
finding.
Kevnar e... meqber bi deqqe nadin... ez nizanim.
It is old... the graves are not distinct... I don't know.
Mehemed... me li... bes berê gotibûn Reşîtê Ribcî.
Mehemed... we... but before they had said Rashid Ribji.
Ê Reşîtê Ribcî... hezar tirba ye. Ez kî... walle lê digerim
ez nabînim.
The one of Rashid Ribji... there are a thousand graves.
Which one... by God I am searching, I am not finding.
Navî biriqî ye Mihemed.
The name is worn off, Mihemed.
Erê walle, yî kî tenê diyam lê digerim.
Yes by God, which one, I'm just searching around.
Da zor ba heye çûbiyayê kevnar e...
There is a strong wind, it's gone, it's old...
[Music playing - Slideshow of photos]
Erê hevalno, ev jî... navê vî rehikî nizanim... Ev gundê
Qermilq e...
Yes friends, this too... I don't know the name of this
ridge... This is Qermilq village...
Hûn dibînin gundê Qermilq e...
You see it is Qermilq village...
Walle gundê Qermilq, gundekî pir xweş e.
By God Qermilq village, it is a very nice village.
Hevalno Qusirî efû kin, mala wekî ye dernakeve... şiye pir
mezin e.
Friends forgive the fault, that house is not showing up...
Shiye is very big.
Reke ez zanim ez têre derim... û tirba jî me... nekirin... ê
mala Ribcî.
The path I know I go through... and the graves too we...
didn't do... of the Ribji family.
Ez zanim hûnê terez bibin.
I know you will be upset.
Mala Qusirî me efû kin. Me daxwaza derxim... lê gerîm ne
dî...
Ribji family forgive us. I wanted to bring it out...
searched didn't find...
Ya zehmet e çûbîye walle nizanim... pirr ne.
It is difficult, it is gone, by God I don't know... there
are many.
Ewwelî yek hatim keyfa min gisa kirin, min ne dî.
At first I came to one, they spoiled my mood, I didn't find
it.
Hevalno ev jî darê Qermilq bi hudûd va nîzîk e...
Friends this too is the Qermilq forest, it is near the
border...
Pir pir nîzîk e...
Very very near...
Hûn dibînin...
You see...
Ev darê Qermilq... ev darê Qermilq e.
This is Qermilq forest... this is Qermilq forest.
Ev jî gundê Qermilq e hevalno... wek hûn dibînin gundê
Qermilq e...
This is also Qermilq village friends... as you see it is
Qermilq village...
Erê hevalno li vê derê jî am li gundê Qermilq in...
Yes friends, here too we are in Qermilq village...
Li mala Xalê Henîf, cem Eb Reşîd.
At Uncle Hanif's house, with Abu Rashid.
Am hatin nîvandarê mala gund e...
We came as guests to the village house...
Meriv qehwa kova xwin... istirehet a xwe bibin...
One drinks bitter coffee... takes a rest...
Vîdyê me hîn xilas nebûye...
Our video has not finished yet...
Hîn am ke noka dîsa herin nav şiyê...
We will still go now again into the thing
[village/center]...
Dinya germ bû, me got em istirehet a xwe bibin.
The weather got hot, we said let's take a rest.
Miletî şiyê bi me ra bin... vî gundê Qermilq... vîdyûyê mi
temam nekirî...
People of Shiye be with us... this Qermilq village... I
haven't finished the video...
Te'lîqa pirr roj miş kin... layk û iştîraq pê de ne...
Write many comments... give likes and subscriptions to it...
Hinek ma bi deh hezarî gihînin ma bi deh hezarî gihînin jî
iştîraq.
Let us reach ten thousand, let us reach ten thousand
subscriptions.
Ka hevalî me l'cema'tê jî bigir...
Film our friend in the group too...
No em istirehet a xwe çûçik bibin...
Now we take a small rest...
Em ê helkişin nav gund û şiyê... vîdyû xwe temam bikin.
We will go up into the village and the thing... finish our
video.
Teetê te xweş e.
Bon appetit.
Xalê Xezal... Xatûnê...
Aunt Ghazal... Khatun...
Qîçkê Xalê Henîf lê sêr kin...
Look at Uncle Hanif's little ones...
Reşîd lê sêr ki Reşîd...
Rashid look here Rashid...
Tu çi bêji ji vîdyûyê xwe...
What do you say to your video...
Ehmed... Ehmed...
Ahmed... Ahmed...
Silavê me ji warê hanê... wurtê gundê Qermilq da.
Our greetings from this place... in the middle of Qermilq
village.
Me vîdyok berê çêkiribû Qermilq...
We had made a video of Qermilq before...
Emê vîdyo noka xweş... laxtê xwe jûr mana.
We will make a nice video now... our time stayed up there.
Ka bi me ra bin.
Come, be with us.
Weleh niha virdora te lê minê kanî... Te têne ne sal?
By God, now around you... where is mine... Did you bring it
not this year?
Çi?
What?
Ketin caye wilo kuş...
They fell into a place like that...
Ketine na?
They have fallen (ripened), haven't they?
Ê ê...
Yes yes...
Berê darek mezin bî, gelek heşk bî, çû bî, berfê şikand.
Before, there was a big tree, it was very dry, it was gone,
the snow broke it.
Heşk bî.
It was dry.
Hm, heşk bî. Ka were em hewşê, tebîetê bikişînin.
Hm, it was dry. Come, let's film the courtyard, the nature.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Selamun Aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleykum Selam.
And upon you peace.
Maşallah...
Mashallah...
Avolno, tirê hindik mayî bibê. Tirê hindik mayî bibê.
Guys, looks like there are a few grapes left. Looks like
there are a few grapes left.
Selamun Aleykum. Çewanî xaltîm?
Peace be upon you. How are you, my aunt?
Başim, çewanî?
I am good, how are you?
Weleh elhemdulilah. Tu rihet î?
By God, praise be to God. Are you comfortable?
Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God.
Ez ji tebîetê hez dikim, vê hewşê bikişînim.
I love nature, [I want to] film this courtyard.
E vilo... ka were.
Well like this... come here.
Xalo, ev cihê çi ye? Te be kevnare?
Uncle, what is this place? Do you say it is ancient?
Ere, cihê ca reş de...
Yes, a place for black barley...
Êwa... Yêk lê hûr jê heye?
I see... Is there one for chopping it?
Ewa jî sifrê yê reş...
That one is also a black table...
Êyo ne wextî na çi dikirin bi avo?
No, what were they doing with this back in the day?
Têda genim dikutanin...
They were pounding wheat in it...
Bilxur?
Bulgur?
Are, genim...
Yes, wheat...
Are avolno, di vir da bilxur û genim dikutanin. Xalo dibê.
Yes guys, in here they were pounding bulgur and wheat. The
uncle says.
He wilo ye? He wê paşda?
Is that so? What about that one in the back?
Evana... ev kever e.
Those... that is limestone.
Êwa.
I see.
Amûd in evana... amûd in.
These are columns... columns.
Amûd in e? Kevnar in?
They are columns? Are they ancient?
Kevnar in, pir kevnar in. Yê kalên... mezin... min ne dîtiye
wan dewrana.
They are ancient, very ancient. Of the elders... great
ones... I haven't seen those eras.
Êwa.
I see.
Em ne dîtin, hew em bûn.
We didn't see it, we just existed [after].
Ka wer em dakevin nav tebîetê, hêşînî ye.
Come let's go down into nature, the greenery.
Xalo temenê vî gundî zane çiqas e?
Uncle, do you know how old this village is?
Weleh... tahrîba ez nizanim... Le tahrîben zane...
By God... approximately I don't know... But roughly I
know...
Sed salî bibore?
Does it exceed a hundred years?
Tahrîben sed sî mal heye.
Approximately there are a hundred and thirty houses.
Sed sî mal.
A hundred and thirty houses.
Miletê xwe ge heye, têda ye.
Its people are there, inside it.
Sed sî heye?
Are there a hundred and thirty?
Baş e, ê pir tenê nin... Hama mal vala bûn ne?
It's good, [but] there aren't many... But the houses became
empty, right?
Êwa.
I see.
Na mal... tu herî mal... dûr... tişt têda nîne.
No, the houses... if you go to a house... far away... there
is nothing in it.
Weleh xalo te kibar çêkiriye. Ev çi ye, çi ye şev ye?
By God uncle, you made it grand/beautiful. What is this,
what is it at night?
Evana... ev firne ye.
Those... this is an oven.
Ev firne ye?
This is an oven?
Are.
Yes.
Xalo firne ye virdê ye?
Uncle, is the oven over here?
Tu lê...
You look at...
Baş e, îş nake ne?
Okay, it doesn't work, right?
Na îş nake...
No, it doesn't work...
Are.
Yes.
Weleh te xweş çêkiriye xalo. Te xizmet kiriye, tu cihekî bi
hêşînayî hez dikî.
By God you made it nice, uncle. You served [the land], you
love a place with greenery.
Ez çûbûm...
I had gone...
Ka avolîm ware.
Come my folks, come.
Maşallah çi çak bûn.
Mashallah, how good they are.
Avana sîsin ne, çine xalo?
Are these lilies, what are they uncle?
Z... zembeq. Zembak.
L... Lilies. Lilies.
Zembaq. Ka were, ka were.
Lilies. Come, come.
Me berê vê jî leqtek hewşê te kişand.
Before this, we shot a clip of your courtyard.
Baş e.
Good.
Are.
Yes.
Wa xola hanîf warin, werin.
Oh Aunt Hanîf come, come.
Werin, werin.
Come, come.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Xalo ev ta bîr e na?
Uncle, this is your well, right?
Are bîr e, bîr.
Yes it's a well, a well.
Êwa.
I see.
Avolno bîr e herê.
Guys, it's a well, yes.
Avolno werin hêşînayê binêrin, werin.
Guys come look at the greenery, come.
Xalo kîbar çêkiriye maşallah.
The uncle made it grand/beautiful, mashallah.
Naqla çûyîn em hatin, avolno gelek xez bîn.
The last time we came, guys, it was very thick (overgrown).
Naqla çûyîn gelek xez bîn, noka jî gelek xidra çandî.
The last time it was very thick, now he has planted many
vegetables.
Are. Maşallah.
Yes. Mashallah.
Ehê...
Aha...
Ka were, avolîm were, ka were.
Come, my folks come, come.
Oooh.
Av hebe, av hebe, hêşînayî rinde.
If there is water, if there is water, greenery is good.
Weleh bacanê te yê ketine.
By God your tomatoes have appeared (ripened).
Ere bacan ketine, xetî av...
Yes tomatoes have appeared, the water line...
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Avolno binêrin, xetî teze. Bes xalo pir jê meke, bes bes.
Guys look, fresh row. But uncle don't pick too many, enough
enough.
Ev teze zû têne çêbûn.
These fresh ones form quickly.
Maşallah, avolno, hûn binerin... tiştêkî bike wele xweş ne.
Mashallah, guys, look... if you make something [with this]
by God it's good.
Helal li avo...
Halal to this...
Helal li avo.
Halal to this.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Ehê...
Aha...
Evê me jî başî ne.
Ours are also good.
Xalo ev şitlî bacanê reş e te çandî?
Uncle, did you plant these eggplant seedlings?
Are, ev reş ne, herê.
Yes, these are black (eggplants), yes.
Êwa.
I see.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Avolno av, av... av... av heyat e.
Guys water, water... water... water is life.
Av hebe îna ku dorkê... dorkê hişk da erdê ketê der.
If there is water, that which is a dry log... a dry log
falls to the ground and sprouts.
Dorkê hişk.
A dry log.
...[inaudible]
Xalo sêvê te ge weşîne? Xêr e?
Uncle, are your apples shedding a lot? Is it good?
No, derman... evana hûrik in, pir dweşîn.
No, medicine... these are tiny, they shed a lot.
Maşallah, bes jê meke xalo, bes, bes.
Mashallah, but don't pick [more] uncle, enough, enough.
Evû begîm... pîrê miha re dabin.
This gentleman... gave it for the old sheep.
Avna yên ankûrê ne.
These are the spider's [apples].
Av noeyî çî ye?
What type is this?
Sêvê, sêf in ev, sêf in.
Apples, these are apples, apples.
Seyfî ne.
They are summer (apples).
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Sake vî ankûrê da tiştê wan hebe, kîbar e. Bacanê sûr.
Look at this spider [web] if they have something, it's
grand. Red tomato.
Av heyatek pir xweş e.
Water is a very good life.
...[inaudible]
Be canê.
[Singing] Oh my soul.
Canê bike.
Do "Canê".
Xatra hela hela sala... Hela hela sala.
For the sake of "Hela hela sala"... "Hela hela sala".
Çibê zû be, wa xweş e.
Say it quickly, it's nice.
Kuro tu zewicî na?
Boy, are you married or not?
Na wele, ez bekar im.
No by God, I am single.
Hela bisa min zirar kir ne, hela hela sala...
Wait, I messed up the tune didn't I, "Hela hela sala"...
Are em... lî gundê Qermîliq ne, malê Ebû Sîwar ve tê nas
kirin.
Yes we... are in the village of Qermîliq, known as the house
of Abu Siwar.
Are, Cemal Ebû Sîwar.
Yes, Cemal Abu Siwar.
Cemal.
Weleh Cemal. Ebû Sîwar.
By God Cemal. Abu Siwar.
Dibê germ e, çiçkê çiçak çêlmîsî ne.
It is hot, the little flowers have wilted a bit.
Are germ e, rûş e. Çîçak çêlmîsî ne.
Yes it's hot, it's sunny. The flowers have wilted.
Maşallah hûn hêşînahiyê hez dikin.
Mashallah you guys love greenery.
Kesî jê hez nake tine ne?
What?
Is there anyone who doesn't love it?
Welle wilo ye.
By God it is so.
Na av jî heye, av jî maşallah hêşînahiyê çêdike.
No there is water too, water also creates greenery,
mashallah.
Xweşî, xweşî.
Goodness, goodness.
Har wextî ki wan bi selametî ne...
Any time that they are in safety...
Are.
Yes.
Naqla çûyîn em hatin, ge xez bî we çandibûn.
The last time we came, it was very thick, you had planted.
Ê...
Yeah...
Gindî Qermîliq, avolno, leymûn darê xwo pirr ne. Leymûn
dibe.
The village of Qermîliq, guys, their lemon trees are many.
Lemons grow.
Ev Hecî... me da seyr dike saetê giya xweş e.
This Hajji... he watches us, the hour of grass is good.
E te ji xwo. Di silav ki dişînê ji milet ra?
And you yourself. Are you sending greetings to the people?
Silavê... wekî gotî ji milet gihayê ra ne.
Greetings... as said, are to the people of the grass.
Ê do wilo poşperde, heta wilo po silavê me ji we giya ra
hene.
So behind the curtain, until then our greetings are there
for all of you.
Sax bî.
Be healthy.
Ax...
Oh...
Werê o qîçkê xaltîkê. Ê xitiya enqerê me dixwazin.
Come oh daughter of the aunt. They want the line of Ankara
from us.
Sîbelê sîber mistafê...
Sîbel, sîber mistafê... [Singing]
We ne dî min go kî wa ke bi zewicî ne?
Didn't you see, I said who is the one to get married?
Bedî xolû dibê çi? Dibê wîna dinê ke bi zewicî derbek makkî
nû ke werin.
Look what the uncle says? He says look at the world, let
them marry, let them come at once.
Sibata teyreqet kin werin.
Let them make a February storm and come.
Xatê xweş be weyê înşallah.
May your time be good, God willing.
Are avolno, ka bi me ra bin jî, emê noka herin vîdyo xwe nav
gundî şî ye, temam bikin.
Yes guys, stay with us too, we will now go finish our video
inside the village.
Ma go em cam xolî min bro laxtokê çêkin, hewşê xwo hêşînê
pirr e.
I said let's make a clip with my uncle bro, his courtyard
has a lot of greenery.
Pir rind e...
Yes.
It's very good...
Rind û pir ji...
Good and very...
Ava xweş...
Good water...
Maşallah wexta tirê jî, têbê tirê no qorta bî belûta...
Mashallah during grape time too, you'd say the grapes are
like acorns...
Emê xala te, wele tektîk beleta çê dibin.
We, your uncle, by God tactics [and] trouble happen.
Ka bi me ra bin da me nav gundî şî ye avolno.
Come be with us so we [go] inside the village guys.
[Scene changes, walking sound]
Are avolno, am hîn li gundê Qermîliq ne.
Yes guys, we are still in the village of Qermîliq.
Am diçûn şîyê, hîn em gundê Qermîliq ne, vederê dawetek lê
dikişe.
We were going inside, we are still in the village of
Qermîliq, a wedding is taking place here.
Ka bi me ra bin.
Come be with us.
Davul and Zurna play, people dancing]
Avolno li vê derê jî...
Guys, over here also...
Şoreş... Biratî me Şoreş hefsa zava ye.
Şoreş... Our brother Şoreş is the groom's companion.
Gundê Qermîliq.
Village of Qermîliq.
Are.
Yes.
Zava hebe...
If the groom is present...
Ka bimerabin ez amja kirîfa mi lo stranekê xwoş ji we ra
bidê, ji mutabeînê miro.
Come be with us, my uncle Kirîf will give a nice song for
you, for my followers.
Ka werin darbas bin. Tebîetê gund binihêrin avolno.
Come enter. Look at the nature of the village guys.
[Music and Singing starts]
Are avolno...
Yes guys...
Silavê ma ji Hisên Hacno re hene.
Our greetings are there for Hisên Hacno.
Li bajarê gundê Qermîliq.
In the town of Qermîliq village.
Silavê min jê re hene.
My greetings are there for him.
[Music continues]
Are avolno li vê derê jî...
Yes guys, over here also...
Sofê Biro, Hecî Ose...
Gundê Qermîliq.
Village of Qermîliq.
Are.
Yes.
Sofê hebe...
If the Sofi is present...
[Music continues, Zurna playing loudly]
[Dengê Def û Zurnê]
[Sound of Drums and Zurna]
Erê hevalno, li vê derê hêşta me go vira dawetek hebî.
Yes friends, here we just said there was a wedding.
Şababê malê Hec Nesir ne, Silavê me jê re hene.
They are the youth of the Hec Nesir family, our greetings to
them.
Kekê Hisên, Hisênê Hec Nasir, silavê me jê re hene.
Brother Hisên, Hisên of Hec Nasir, our greetings to him.
Malê Hec Nesir jî mentîqê Efrînê da bi deng û nav ne, me'rûf
ne.
The Hec Nesir family is famous and well-known in the Efrîn
region.
Saeta wan jî xweş, ew jî bi rengekî xizmet milletê xwe
dikin.
Bless them, they also serve their people in a way.
Saeta giya xweş.
Bless everyone.
Zava jî zotir ma we re derxist.
We showed you the groom earlier.
Ka bimênin, em herin nav gundê Şiyê, mekanî em temam bikin.
Stay tuned, let's go into the village of Şiyê, let's finish
the location.
Me hot vira dawet ew bî, me teswîr kir, ka bimênin.
We came here as there was a wedding, we filmed it, stay
tuned.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Wî mi camê bikir, camê.
Close that window, the window.
Baş xwo.
Okay.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Wesa Samir? Lo Samir de...
Where is Samir? Oh Samir, come on...
Erê hevalno li vê derê jî em gihîştin talyê vîdyo xwe.
Yes friends, here we have reached the end of our video.
Silavê me ji gundiyan re hene.
Our greetings to the villagers.
Şoşbînê me ji hene, wanê qusurî me efû kin.
Our groomsmen are there too, may they forgive our
shortcomings.
Vîdyo me jî ekserî vîdyo me jî giş efewî ne.
Our videos are mostly all spontaneous.
Tab'an vîdyo jî min nekari rind bisewrînim, lenî dinya pir
germ e.
Of course, I couldn't film the video well, because the
weather is very hot.
Di nav Şiyê, Qermîlq, bi hidûd va nîziket, dinya pir germ e.
In Şiyê, Qermîlq, close to the border, the weather is very
hot.
Cîhaz pênc şeş neqlo miro mir.
The device died five or six times.
Ne weba min ê rind çêkira vîdyo.
If not for that, I would have made the video well.
Etem cîhaz dimirî, tam tê nebî min teswîr kiro.
When the device dies, there is no taste to what I filmed.
Înzor dido min, difesilî.
It gives me a warning, it shuts off.
Erê li vê derê jî em geliyê Şiyê ne.
Yes, here we are in the Şiyê valley.
Ma gotina te hene?
Do you have any words?
Erê hevalno me em gihîştin toylê vîdyo xwe.
Yes friends, we have reached the end of our video.
Saeta we giya xweş, vîdyo me heta toylê sêrkin.
Bless you all, watch our video until the end.
Û bîr mekin me ra like û iştîrakê pêdin.
And don't forget to give us a like and subscription.
Û gula gula heta xelekek din bimînin di xêr û xweşiyê da.
And goodbye, until another episode, stay in goodness and
happiness.
Bimênin, vîdyo ke din, xweş, kîbar, em ê werin teswîr kin.
Stay tuned, another nice, elegant video, we will come and
film.
Daf tebîetê geliyê Şiyê ye.
This is the nature of the Şiyê valley.
Maşallah darber pir ne.
Mashallah, there are many trees.
Samsûn ma hêişta, dinya germ e, ez nizanim çiye.
The Samsung gave up, it's hot, I don't know what it is.
Cîhaz temero mir.
The device completely died.
Lê sêrkin te'lîqa pir... milletî Şiyê... inşallah xelekek
din ez ê Şiyê da çêkim.
But look, many comments... people of Şiyê... God willing I
will make another episode in Şiyê.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Ah wulo gundê jûr bigre, wî gundê jûr.
Ah like that, film the upper village, that upper village.
Evok gundekî... ceh ket vê gelî da.
This is a village... located in this valley.
Ah wulo Misa'd Qerma pîkir, Qerma qederê wî mişkile.
Ah like that, Misa'd measured Qerma, Qerma's destiny is a
problem.
Kêlo? Alo? ... gundê Kela ye.
Kêlo? Alo? ... it is the village of Kela.
[Muzîk]
[Music]