Havolno, vaye derecê meqbaza zeytûne ye, ê vê gindî ye
teb'an.
Friends, here is the location of the olive press, naturally,
it belongs to this village.
Xwediyê meqbezê, xwediyê zeytûne, xwediyê nenê biroyê.
Maşallah kîbar çêkiriye, sehetan destxweş.
The owner of the press, the owner of the olives, the owner
of the bread [sustenance] go together. Mashallah, he built
it elegantly, health to your hands.
Malê elî...
Ali's house...
Çar mal ne? Çar mal ketine?
Are there four houses? Are four houses located there?
Ev xaniya Mehemedi ye, ew Mehemedi ye.
This is Mohammed's house, that is Mohammed.
O wî jî xaniyê Mehmûd e.
And that one is Mahmoud's house.
Maşallah meqam heze mezin e.
Mashallah, the status/place is great here.
Kekê Xelîl, ev malbata kê ye teb'an?
Brother Khalil, whose family is this, naturally?
Miletê Ewropa milet, vegerin.
People of Europe, people, return.
Miletê Ewropa gerek neşkinin bên werin.
People of Europe, don't be lazy, come back here.
Xweş bû, menteqe xweş bû havolno.
It was nice, the area was nice friends.
Neçîrvan xweş he?
Being a hunter is nice, huh?
Teb'an ma'ber mebû nîzîk e.
Of course, the crossing was near us.
Esteradê xwe pak e maşallah.
Its highway is clean/good, mashallah.
Merheba havolno.
Hello friends.
Cejna we pîroz be, her roj di xêr û xweşiyê da bin.
Happy Eid to you, may you be in goodness and happiness every
day.
Erê havolno, îro em hatine gindekî pir pir dûr.
Yes friends, today we have come to a village very, very far
away.
Vîdyokî xweş, kîbar. Em hatine kijan gindî?
A nice, elegant video. Which village have we come to?
Em hatine gundê Axcele.
We have come to Axcele village.
Gundê Axcele.
Axcele village.
Ez silav dikim li xêr mutabeîni me, çûnê, başin, sihet çawa
ye, inşallah hûn gir û nirhet ne.
I greet our good followers, how are you, are you well, how
is your health, God willing you are all comfortable.
Cejna Remezanê li we hemûya pîroz be.
May the Ramadan Eid be blessed for all of you.
Bi xêr û selameti ser we ra derbas be.
May it pass over you with goodness and safety.
İnşallah qebûleta salê tê be, hûn giş biftilin ser war û
malê xwe, ser ardê xwe û axa xwe.
God willing, may it be accepted for the coming year, that
you all return to your homes and lands, to your earth and
soil.
Erê bimênin, îro emkê derbasî gundê Axcele bibin. Vîdyokî
xweş û kîbar, bi me ra bin.
Yes, stay tuned, today we will pass into Axcele village. A
nice and elegant video, stay with us.
Erê havolno, naha bi me ra bin, emkê vîdyokî xweş, kîbar,
emkê nav gund teswîr kin.
Yes friends, now stay with us, we will film a nice, elegant
video inside the village.
Teb'an ev jî teleb e, dûr e, wele pir dûr hatine.
Of course, this was a request, it is far, by God we came
very far.
Ewel mere têm vê derê.
It is the first time I am coming here.
Divero jî teb'an daren rêka Idlibê, Idlibê, Sermada, divero
daren, pir dûr e.
From here, naturally, they go on the road to Idlib, Idlib,
Sarmada, they go from here, it is very far.
Bab el Hawa daren waye. Xo bi me ra bin em derbasî gind bin.
Bab al-Hawa goes that way. Okay, stay with us, let's enter
the village.
Werin. Werin havolno werin.
Come. Come friends, come.
Havolimê li gel min bigir.
My friend, film next to me.
Erê havolno, noko lextana xweş emkê wara nav gundê Axcele
çêkin.
Yes friends, now we will come and make nice clips inside
Axcele village.
Ewel mere heyata xwa da têm vê gindî.
It is the first time in my life I am coming to this village.
Dûr e wele.
It is far, by God.
Me go, em divero jî herin, darê awe... Idlibê, Sermada.
We said, let's go from here too, the road to that... Idlib,
Sarmada.
Sê çar seeta meriv dikşîne.
It takes a person three or four hours.
Maşallah wele gindekî xweş e.
Mashallah, by God, it is a nice village.
Tebîata vê gindî pir xweş e havolno.
The nature of this village is very nice, friends.
Ev der ser tirba ye?
Is this place above the graves?
Tamam heta ber tirba herin em biftilin.
Okay, go until in front of the graves and we will turn back.
Valê Kekê Xelîl, hewa sar e bavo.
By God, Brother Khalil, the weather is cold, man.
Cama hilde.
Roll up the window.
Cama hilde kekê min.
Roll up the window, my brother.
Hewa sar e, sar e îro.
The weather is cold, it is cold today.
Avne muxeyem ne?
Are these not camps?
Erê havolno, avo tirbê vê gindî ne.
Yes friends, these are the graves of this village.
Teb'an avnê pîşî me jî gi muxeyemat ne.
Of course, those in front of us are all camps.
Av li vê gindî pir in he?
There is a lot of water in this village, huh?
Wele maşallah.
By God, mashallah.
Kekê Xelîl, avo malbata waye teb'an, ezê paşê werim.
Brother Khalil, this is their family [home] naturally, I
will come later.
Avê enber nê hewa?
Isn't this a warehouse?
Avo malbata waye, Kekê Xelîl wê enber nê.
This is their family [home], Brother Khalil, that is not a
warehouse.
Gindê mekrmança pir rind in ha.
The Kurmanji villages are very beautiful, ha.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Miletê me cebar e, cebar.
Our people are resourceful, resourceful.
Avo xezana hecer çêkirina...
This stone tank is built...
Avo munezeme çêkiriye.
An organization built this.
Ava vax gindekê.
Drinking water for the village.
Texma malekî ev hejmar...
I guess about this number of houses...
Sed û bîst pênc mal, havolno.
125 houses, friends.
Vê ginda teqrîben xuletî min dibê sed û bîst û pênc mal in.
In this village, approximately my guide tells me, there are
125 houses.
Aree havolno, vaye derecê meqbaza zeytûne ye, ê vê gindî ye
teb'an.
Yes friends, here is the location of the olive press,
naturally, it belongs to this village.
Xwediyê meqbezê, xwediyê zeytûne, xwediyê nenê biroyê.
The owner of the press, the owner of the olives, the owner
of the bread [sustenance] go together.
Maşallah kîbar çêkiriye, sehetan destxweş.
Mashallah, he built it elegantly, health to your hands.
Hêêê pak.
Yeaaah, clean [good].
Hîn aletê xwe yê darva ne...
Their tools are still outside...
Gi sîyane darva dikin.
They do all the maintenance outside.
Sehetan destxweş.
Health to your hands.
Aferim.
Bravo.
Avo mala kê ye, te kê got nîne?
Whose house is this, didn't you say [name]?
Avo rîkê jûr e.
This is the upper road.
Xani xêra wa, ezê gindaa jî bibînim.
Houses, their goodness, I will see the villages too.
Oğca le cora di heyata xwe da nehatime.
Oğca up top, never in my life have I come here.
Eslen qet min nizanîbû li kuderê dikeve.
Actually, I never knew where it was located.
Havolno vayî pîşî me jî meqbeze?
Friends, is this in front of us a press too?
Bir jî bîrikê avê heye.
There is also a water well.
Her însanek bi rengekî xizmet miletê kê.
Every person serves their people in a way.
Yê heye meqbezê zeytûna li cem heye.
One has an olive press with them.
Yê heye bîra avê li cem...
One has a water well with them...
Yanî her yek bitûnekî xizmet dike.
Meaning everyone serves with a method.
Aree havolno, vê derê...
Yes friends, this place...
Divero daren Cindirêsê teb'an.
From here goes to Jinderes, naturally.
Avo rêka Cindirêsê.
This is the Jinderes road.
Û divero jî daren Hemamê, Hemamê nîzîk e.
And from here goes to Hemam [village], Hemam is near.
Teb'an ma'ber nîzîk e.
Of course the crossing is near.
Esteradê xwe pak e maşallah.
Its highway is clean/good, mashallah.
Ka wara emê nav gund temam bikin havolim.
Come on, let's finish inside the village my friend.
Arê hevalno bibihîzin vî meqbezî, meqbezê...
Yes friends, listen to this clip, this clip...
Wele cemaet ev meqbez pirr xweş e.
Really folks, this clip is very nice.
Teb'an noka emkê no bi gund kevin, dîsa emkan no bi gund
temam bikin.
Of course, now we will enter the village, again we will
complete the village.
Ev wa bes me dûrê ra weire av kir.
We just filmed this for you from a distance.
Avolno min bîra vî ji gund bigir.
Folks, let me take the memory of this village too.
Avolno gundekî xweş e, ew gundî... vî gundî jî li ser estrad
e.
Folks, it is a nice village, this village... this village is
also on the highway.
Estrad... eferim, riya ko me weire got, darê ser meda, edlî
be, şaxûlî yanî.
Highway... bravo, the road we told you about, the trees over
us, let it be straight, vertical that is.
Û vê qo jî heye.
And this place is here too.
Vêra jî garajê mokinê çêkin, mokinê hecar teb'an.
Here they make a mechanic garage, stone cutting machines of
course.
Evra mekteb e, di rûşin e.
Here is the school, it is in front [of us].
Oncam e, yek... hol vî darê bikin.
It's the curvature/corner, one... do it like this tree.
No gewr e, mezin bûye, gewr e.
Now it is grey/mature, it has grown big, it is grey.
Maşallah, maşallah ji vî gundî ra.
Mashallah, Mashallah to this village.
Pirt xweş e, gundekî pirt xweş e.
It is very nice, a very nice village.
Avolno ew her cîb gerake weke... ew bira erzan nîno.
Folks, every Jeep car like that... those brothers aren't
cheap.
Hîn her edlî be ser meda, hîn erzan nîne... ferq şeş heft
sed dolar e.
Let it all be straight/fair upon us, they are not cheap...
the difference is six or seven hundred dollars.
Cîb nîne?
Is it not a Jeep?
E ne hebin tu bikirî?
If you don't have [money], how can you buy it?
Avolno her dera gundekî... her gundek ser gundekî ra.
Folks, every place is a village... every village is upon
another village.
Glek xelîl tê tên ji vî gundî, gundekî şêrîn bibe.
Many people come to this village, may it be a sweet village.
Heke mal mal weire vîda estxîl kim... a malekê beramberî me
ye, em herin odê.
If I film the houses for you house by house... ah, there is
a house opposite us, let's go to the room/guest house.
Miletê Axcele xwo îsbat kirine.
The people of Axcele have proven themselves.
Miletê Axcele... Milo kes pîşê vîdyo a naxe.
The people of Axcele... Let no one come in front of the
video.
Gundekî 'etîq e mi'elem, maşallah vîdyo xwo dişuxulin.
It is an ancient village master, mashallah the videos work
themselves.
Milet bîra mantiqê xwo kirî.
The people have missed their region.
Ev hevolo ro wa dibên, ezbenî gundekî ciwan e da dikevin, a
firqê xweş... ciwan ji vî gundî derdikevin, adem diqehirin.
These friends say, sir, we are entering a beautiful village,
ah what a nice group... the youth leave this village, one
gets upset.
Herê welle merê çetîn e.
Yes really, it is a difficult situation.
Avolno teqsîra me hene wînê qusûrî me efû bikin.
Folks, if we have faults, forgive our shortcomings.
Yanî şoşbîl moşbîl, me berê weire gotî vîdî me efe wîna em
çêdikin.
Meaning shaking and such, we told you before, our video is
like this, this is how we make it.
Te'lîqê ne xweş kîbor mera ne nivîsînin, çavê wa maç dikim.
Don't write unpleasant comments to us out of arrogance, I
kiss your eyes.
Maşallah vî eqîdê Erefatê çiqas milet hatî, ji Ewropa bû,
çiqas milet hatî, camahê xwoş hatin e.
Mashallah, this gathering of Arafat [referring to a specific
gathering or time], how many people came, from Europe, how
many people came, a welcome group.
Ji Heleb vo, ji Şamê vo, ji Ewropa... pir milet hatî.
From Aleppo, from Damascus, from Europe... many people came.
Ji bo 'eydê.
For the holiday (Eid).
Avolno hewşê kevnar dibrêjiyan e.
Folks, the old courtyards are falling down.
Avolno vî hewşê kevnar bigir, ev hewşoka bi axê ye, gelê
zemana berê.
Folks, capture this old courtyard, this courtyard is made of
earth/mud, friends, from the old times.
Wadyê blokê gundê ye girt axîn e, axîn.
Look, the village blocks [houses] are captured [made of]
earth, earth.
Cemaet zilzole wana hedimand lê...
Folks, the earthquake destroyed them but...
Lê tiştê din... zilzole ne?
But other things... was it the earthquake?
Arê, arê, zilzole.
Yes, yes, the earthquake.
Arê avolno, em hîna li mala xulê, xulê me navê wî çi bû?
Yes folks, we are still at the uncle's house, our uncle,
what was his name?
Apo Ekrem.
Uncle Ekrem.
Em hatin vî malbetê, cem xulî min.
We came to this family, to my uncle.
Emkê qehweyek vexwin, îstîrahet pênc deqe bibin.
We will drink a coffee, rest for five minutes.
Û megû em çend gotina ji xulû pirs kin, ser vî gundî,
tarîxeta vî gundî, vî gunda çi çêdibin, çi naskirin.
And I said let's ask the uncle a few words about this
village, the history of this village, what is produced in
this village, what is it known for.
Xulû megû... Merhaba ji te ra.
Uncle, I said... Hello to you.
Ahlen wa sehlen, wa sehlen.
Welcome, welcome.
Ser vî gundî tûkê me ra xeber de, vî gundo eded mal, malbet
çiqas mal iskan, yanî hewş?
Tell us about this village, in this village, the number of
houses, families, how many inhabited houses, meaning
courtyards?
Hewş tu pênc, heftê nûd malî ye.
Courtyards, you [can say] seventy-five, seventy-nine houses.
Heftê nûd malî?
Seventy-nine houses?
Arê.
Yes.
Eywa.
I see.
Aîla binbên... aîla tên naskirin, mala Xelê tên naskirin...
efû, mala Xelê...
The families underneath [the main ones]... the families are
known, the House of Xelê is known... sorry, the House of
Xelê...
Mala Hisên, mala Şa'bê, û mala Elûşê.
The House of Hisên, the House of Sha'be, and the House of
Alush.
Wa çor mol no, are tên naskirin.
Those four families, yes they are known.
Yanî havno asasiyê gund in, ê gund in.
Meaning these are the foundation of the village, they are of
the village.
Ê gund şên kirî?
The one who founded/populated the village?
Ê gund şên kirî.
The one who founded the village.
Ew bo bavê kalikê min e.
That was my grandfather's father.
Ewa.
I see.
Bavê kalikê min e.
It is my grandfather's father.
Nav çiye?
What is the name?
Nav Hisên e.
The name is Hisên.
Hisên.
Hisên e.
It is Hisên.
Ewa.
I see.
Kalikê min jî Hisên bû, û navê bavkê jî Hisên bû, lianne
wehîd bû gunda.
My grandfather was also Hisên, and the father's name was
also Hisên, because he was the only one in the village.
Arê.
Yes.
Wehîd bû. Ji bavkê xwe da wehîd bû.
He was the only one. From his father, he was an only child.
Gundo hat li ba gundî rûnişt, vêra dibên Axcele.
He came to the village, sat with the villager, they call
this place Axcele.
Axcele bixwe... wekî cîkî pir leyla ye, yanî pir leyla ye, û
rind e, û hênikayî ye, û însan lê vedihesiya ne.
Axcele itself... is like a very beautiful place, meaning
very beautiful, and nice, and cool, and a person could rest
there.
Wî navî jî Axcele lê nan.
So they gave it the name Axcele.
Wê navî maneyê lê kirin Axcele?
Is that the meaning they gave for Axcele?
Axcele lê nan.
They named it Axcele.
Gundikî yanî hênik in û awe...
A village, meaning they are cool/refreshing and such...
Mewqi'ê gundî jî rind e.
The location of the village is also nice.
Mewqi'ê xwo rind e. Wa tûnî nav lê nan Axcele.
Its location is nice. That's how they named it Axcele.
Ewa.
I see.
Xulû Axcele bi çi tên naskirin? Wekî ana... meselen, bi
seqafeta gund e, bi ziraet e, bi çi tên naskirin gundî
Axcele?
Uncle, what is Axcele known for? Like now... for example, by
the culture of the village, by agriculture, what is the
village of Axcele known for?
Welle hînî, ez ji te re bêjim... bi seqafeta xwo kêm e.
Well look, let me tell you... for its culture, it is little.
Kêm e.
It is little.
Bi zerî'etê tên naskirin.
I see.
It is known for agriculture.
Zerî'etê.
Agriculture.
Bi zerî'etê tên naskirin. Bi çandina zeytûna ye, meselen
pembo bû, genim bû, ceh bû, yanî bi zerî'etê va tûnî dihat
naskirin, menşûr bû.
It is known for agriculture. For planting olives, for
example it was cotton, it was wheat, it was barley, meaning
it was known for agriculture like that, it was famous.
Bi zebeş bû... bi va tûnî dihat naskirin.
It was [known for] watermelons... it was known for these
things.
Xoş e.
That's nice.
Arê avolno, vî gundî bi vî rengî tên naskirin, xulû me ra wa
da.
Yes folks, this village is known in this way, the uncle gave
it to us like that.
Xulû sukanê vî gundî ge mewcûd in hene?
Uncle, are the residents of this village still present, are
they there?
Sukanê vî gundî em bêjin... teqrîben... heft heşt mal ji nav
hatine hînî.
The residents of this village, let us say...
approximately... seven or eight families from among them
have come/remain now.
Wekî tê digihîne?
As you understand?
Gelek in.
There are many.
Sikonê vî gundî he?
Are there residents of this village?
Sekanê xwe gelek in.
Its residents are many.
Erê, evan navê sikonê vî gundî he, teqrîben gelek in, bes
heft heşt mal ji eynî hewşê ne?
Yes, these residents of this village, they are approximately
many, but are only seven or eight families from the same
courtyard?
Yanî sedî yek tkebê nehatî.
Meaning, not even one percent has come.
Sedî yek nehatî.
Not even one percent has come.
Wele kîbar e yanî, malbat gelek in.
Well, it is large, meaning the families are many.
Û gundî van jî, xalo gundî we jî hena ser mefreqê ne, qopî
Hemamê ye, hinek ser rêkê Idlibê ye, şaxolê gundî, kîjan
şaxol e?
And about these villagers, uncle, your village is at the
intersection, toward Hammam, some are on the Idlib road, the
branch of the village, which branch is it?
Hinek ser rêkê, rêkê Hemamê ye.
Some are on the road, the Hammam road.
Hinek ser rêkê Idlibê ye.
Yes.
Some are on the Idlib road.
Xalo mango, malbata tewr kevnar di gundê Oqcelê da, kijan
malbat e?
Uncle, they say the most ancient family in the village of
Oqcel, which family is it?
Malbata tewr kevnar, ê Oqcel...
The most ancient family, of Oqcel...
Çêkirî û şênkirî, bavkê Kalkê min e, Hisên e.
The one who built and populated it is my grandfather's
father, Hisên.
Hisên e.
It is Hisên.
Hisên e, û Xelîl û Elî wan e.
It is Hisên, and Xelîl and Elî are them.
Eywa.
I see.
Hisên, layê brakê Xelîl û Elî ye.
Hisên is the son of the brother of Xelîl and Elî.
Layê birê ye.
He is the brother's son.
Bavkê xwe wefat kirî, biçûk bû.
His father passed away, he was small.
Apê xwe dida çûn, bi xwe ra dibirin.
His uncles would go, taking him with them.
Bi xwe ra dibirin.
They took him with them.
Gotin di ortê ji Walê, ji kuderê hatine?
They said originally from Walê, from where did they come?
Ji pîyê Tirkî da hatine.
They came from the Turkey side.
Tirkî da hatine.
They came from Turkey.
Tirkî da hatine. Da evê Herb Alemî... ewledê... berî Herb
Alemî ewladê du çaxê da hatine.
They came from Turkey. During that World War... the sons...
before the World War [I], the sons came in two eras.
Hatin va gundî.
Yes.
They came to this village.
Ewa qeçik bû, bê ramazan bû.
He was small, without Ramazan [fasting/age].
He was small, without Ramazan.
Û di vir da man.
And they stayed here.
Di hezar nehsed û çelî da, sî û pênca da hatine.
In nineteen forty, thirty-five, they came.
Kevnar e?
Is it ancient?
Erê, kevnar e.
Yes, it is ancient.
Yanî emrê vî gundî dikebe çiqas sal teqrîben?
Meaning, the age of this village is approximately how many
years?
Emrê vî salî, vî gundî, di salê hezar nehsed çelî pêncî da,
mesele behs be çiqas sal e ketiye.
The age of this year, this village, in the year nineteen
forty-fifty, for example, calculate how many years have
passed.
Erê.
Yes.
Ewa ne weke gelo tarîxa no, xalo dibê vî gundê esasî vî
gundî çiqas sal daye?
That is not like, say, the history now, uncle says the
foundation of this village dates back how many years?
Walo kevnar e.
Well, it is ancient.
Xalo çend camî di gundî we da hene?
Uncle, how many mosques are in your village?
Camîk e.
There is one mosque.
Mekteb yek e.
School?
There is one school.
Heta sefê çendê ye?
Up to what grade?
Heta sefê şeşê ye.
Up to the sixth grade.
Heta şeşê, û şeşê şûnda derin ku?
Up to the sixth, and after the sixth where do they go?
Derin Cindrêsê.
They go to Jinderes.
Erê.
Yes.
Derin Efrîn.
They go to Afrin.
Derin, kî dixwînin, derin wir.
They go, whoever studies, they go there.
Heta şeşê li vir dixwînin, şeşê şûnda derin Cindrêsê, Efrîn.
Up to the sixth they study here, after the sixth they go to
Jinderes, Afrin.
Rind e. Xalo, ema Qenat Efrîn 366...
Good. Uncle, but the Afrin Channel 366...
Te çi silavê dişîne millet ra, te çi nesîhetê didê millet,
milletî li me seyr dike?
What greetings do you send to the people, what advice do you
give to the people, the people watching us?
Mentiqe çawa ye? Rind e? Ne rind e?
How is the region? Is it good? Is it not good?
Mentiqe pir rind e.
The region is very good.
Û milletî gel me seyr dike, û kat mesele qenatê me lê me
seyr dikin, ez giya razî me.
Yes.
Û milletî gel me seyr dike, û kat mesele qenatê me lê me
seyr dikin, ez giya razî me.
And the people watching us, and when, for example, our
channel watches us, I am pleased with everyone.
Xwedê ji giya razî be, haskirinê ez dixwazim ji milletê xwe.
May God be pleased with everyone, I want love from my
people.
Haskirinê dixwazim.
I want love.
Ne maslehet be.
Let it not be for self-interest.
Bila haskirin ji dil da be.
Let love be from the heart.
Îsanê ser keve. Bes haskirin ger bû maslehet, îsanê bikevin
keve.
Humankind will rise. But if love becomes for self-interest,
humankind will fall down.
Bikevin keve.
They will fall down.
It is true.
Bikevin keve.
They will fall down.
Erê, avanû... teyîb xalo, emrê te bereket çend in?
Yes, so... alright uncle, your blessed age is how much?
Emrê min... mewlîdê min... hezar... mesele, ê heft... pêncî
û diduyê me.
My age... my birthdate... one thousand... for example, of
seven... I am of fifty-two.
Ê pêncî diduyê me.
I am of fifty-two.
Maşallah. Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te de.
Mashallah. May God give you a long life.
Ê pêncî diduyê me.
I am of fifty-two.
Erê avanû, şûra xalo gi tarîx ne. Te be heftê sal jî, ne
hindik e, heftê sal umr ne.
Yes so, uncle's talk is all history. About seventy years is
not a little, seventy years is a lifetime.
Yanî ne bê de û şêst sal nin, de û pênc sal nin, heftê sal.
Meaning it is not say, sixteen years, fifteen years, it's
seventy years.
Xalo jî tarîxa pir zone, û şûra xwe jî gi tarîx ne.
Uncle also knows a lot of history, and his words are all
history.
Lê?
Right?
Xaltîk, te bi millet ra te dibê çi? Kesê li me seyr dike, te
çi silavê dişîne?
Auntie, what do you say to the people? Those watching us,
what greetings do you send?
Silavê me ji giya ra hene, Xwedê wekî vî ti rindî bide,
saxta giya xweş, şa û ne dinya gi bibû yek.
Our greetings to everyone, may God give goodness like this,
health to everyone, happy, and may the whole world become
one.
Em gi şa ne, em gi memnûn e, niyanî pir xweş e, welat xweş
e.
We are all happy, we are all grateful, meaning it is very
good, the country is good.
Me giya qeçikê xwe dîn, û wekî vî ti heval cîrana giya
qeçikê xwe dîn.
We saw all our children, and like this, friends and
neighbors all saw their children.
Hemdullah.
Thank God.
Pir e yanî em fereh bûn lemiş bûn, pir rind e yanî.
It is a lot, meaning we rejoiced and gathered, it is very
good, meaning.
Hemdullah.
Thank God.
Ya ehem şî meriv qeçikê xwe bibîne.
The most important thing is for a person to see their
children.
Meriv qeçikê xwe bibîne rind e, berê vî em gi bitenê bûn,
kal û pîr bitenê.
If a person sees their children it is good, before this we
were all alone, old men and women alone.
Meyno nedikirin qeçikê xwe bibînin.
We were not able to see our children.
Îneko maşallah dur me şên e, wekî dibê eyda giya belav bûn
çûn xudanê xwe.
Now mashallah around us is populated, as they say, the Eid
for everyone, they dispersed and went to their owners
[homes].
Erê, werin inşallah, sibahî giya werin.
Yes, they will come God willing, tomorrow everyone will
come.
Erê.
Yes.
Saxta we giya xweş, Xwedê wekî vî ti rindî bide, inşallah ji
berê çêtir be.
Health to you all, may God give goodness like this, God
willing may it be better than before.
Amîn.
Amen.
Inşallah.
God willing.
Amîn.
Amen.
Silavê me ji Xelîl ra hene, jinkê Gindî ra hene...
Our greetings to Xelîl, to Gindî's wife...
Encîla ra, qîza tî min e, ew jî layê tî min e Xelîl, û tîyê
qîza min e.
To Encîla, she is my brother-in-law's daughter, and Xelîl is
my brother-in-law's son, and the husband of my daughter.
Silavê taybet bigihîne xaltîk.
Convey special greetings, auntie.
E, inşallah. Û heva jî malê xwe, owa pîşê me hewa, malê
Xelîl e.
Yes, God willing. And this one too is his house, that one in
front of us there, is Xelîl's house.
Erê.
Yes.
Saxta we giya xweş.
Health to you all.
We giya gotî ji badîna da heta Oqcelê, saxta we giya xweş.
And to you too.
You all said from Badina up to Oqcel, health to you all.
E te jî xweş, Xwedê te bihêle.
And to you too, may God keep you.
Ew we jî xweş, Xwedê ji we jî razî be.
And you too, may God be pleased with you too.
Hûn bi xêr hatin.
You are welcome.
Xwedê ji we jî razî be.
May God be pleased with you too.
Xalo, vê... evê gindino digerim, ser vê eydino...
Uncle, this... I am wandering these villages, on this Eid...
Me bala xwe dayê millet pir ji Heleb û ji Ewropa vegeriya,
vegeriya.
We noticed that many people returned from Aleppo and from
Europe, returned.
Pir millet hatiyê.
Many people have come.
Erê hatî.
Yes, they came.
Nuha ceme'a gund... îna, îna ke...
Now the community of the village... here, here that...
Pir xelk habîn, minos na?
There were many people, right?
Pir xelk hatin, bi hezaran hatin.
Many people came, they came by the thousands.
Jê şîna jî hebû, yanî wek bere vefitilî, bere çûbî, millet
ji gundo va, ji Heleb va şar va dotin?
It was crowded too, meaning like it turned back to before,
before they had gone, people from the villages, from Aleppo
came to the city?
Tê jî zehmet. Maşallah millet pir vegeriya.
It was crowded. Mashallah many people returned.
Xelk ra ji Birîtanya hatî, ceme'a ra ji Birîtanya hatin.
People came from Britain, a group came from Britain.
Vir jî, vir jî hatin.
Here too, here too they came.
Elhemdullah, cî hatin.
Thank God, they came to the place.
Erê me jî pirskir, me got çûbî, go wellehî meeziz mikerem,
go qîmetek dan me, ne her naware, waye lew ke li mala xwe
ye.
Yes, we also asked, we said when you went, they said by God
honored and respected, they said they gave us a value, not
everywhere is like that, it is like being in their own home.
Ji çi bêrûte da hat, gondon. Pşo qepe. Bi teksê.
From what disrespect they came, sent away. Back to the door.
By taxi.
Rind e.
Good.
Pir, pir xelk hatî.
Many, many people came.
Avone, ey, kanê, ey cinsîyê xwe ha, kanê dokave.
So, hey, where, hey their nationality [nature] is here,
where do they fall.
Me şikir elhemdullah, rind bû, bereket Xwedê lê bû.
We give thanks, thank God, it was good, God's blessing was
on it.
Î doxê herbe me nehatine, em gi ji tirs re hew bibûn.
In the time of war we didn't come, we were all stuck out of
fear.
Em berî giya hatin.
We came before everyone.
Î me tirse dîna û me dere dîna û me ezab dîna.
Yes.
And we saw fear and we saw outside [exile] and we saw
suffering.
Inşallah tişt namîne.
God willing nothing remains.
Cew rind bîya, pir xweş bîya. Maşallah millet jî gi
vedigeriya malbetê xwe.
God willing nothing remains.
Cew rind bîya, pir xweş bîya. Maşallah millet jî gi
vedigeriya malbetê xwe.
May the atmosphere be good, may it be very happy. Mashallah
the people also all returned to their families.
Silavê me jî, ji her kesê kî li me seyr dike ra hene, ji
gundî Oqcelê da, silavê me ji we ra hene heta cîyê min lê.
God willing.
Silavê me jî, ji her kesê kî li me seyr dike ra hene, ji
gundî Oqcelê da, silavê me ji we ra hene heta cîyê min lê.
Our greetings too, to everyone who is watching us, from the
village of Oqcel, our greetings to you until my place/end.
Na wey xalo?
Isn't it so, uncle?
Inşallah.
It is so.
God willing.
Xwedê we mehfeze ke, inşallah gi biftilin welatê xwe.
May God protect you, God willing may all return to their
country.
Ê weletiya xêr e.
Their homeland is a blessing.
Inşallah.
God willing.
O ana seke, roş Be'dîna hatin viderê.
And look now, from Be'dîna they came here.
Şêst heftê kîlometre ye, yanî tişt tinne ye, yanî tebîî.
It is sixty-seventy kilometers, meaning it is nothing,
meaning natural.
Wekê berê, berê çûbî heyatî me wena em derbas dikin.
Like before, before how it went, our life is like that, we
pass it.
Ji Be'dîna ewî nehatin vir o, ewî caran negihiştin vir o. Em
hatin, do derbas bîn.
From Be'dîna they didn't come here, they never reached here.
We came, passed through yesterday.
Erê, avanû viderê jî xalo, teben hewşê da av heye.
Yes, so here too uncle, naturally there is water in the
courtyard.
Bîstanê xwe çandî, hêşînayî, xorikê sebrê xwe tînê.
He planted his garden, greenery, brings food for his
patience.
Saxta gindê xweş.
Health to the village.
O de mero emr mezin bî, mero kî çû gihîşte, çîçik bîstan
mero kê biçîne. Mero ke here peşî dewar ki.
And when a person's age is great, a person who reached [old
age], plants a little garden. A person goes after the
livestock.
Tabben l'gundo jî, însanî l'gundo rûnişt, gerek her tişkê
xwe hebe.
Naturally in the village too, if a person lives in the
village, they must have everything of their own.
Gerek [inaudible] xwe hebe, mirîşkê xwe hebin, çêlekê xwe
hebin.
They must have their [inaudible], have their chickens, have
their cows.
Her tişk... tiştek gerek hebe. Mero l'gundo eyşî.
Everything... something must be there. For a person to live
in the village.
Na.
No.
Tabben na.
Naturally no.
Hews, noka çû mirîşka bihewîne? Tine hewîne.
Courtyard, now what will shelter the chickens? None shelter.
Erê.
Yes.
Dinê ne wek berê ye.
The world is not like before.
Hewş teng bûn e, cî teng bûn e, gize tûnîne.
Courtyards have become narrow, places have become narrow,
there is no [gize - possibly energy/strength?].
Maşallah hûr û dinya germ jî o.
Mashallah it is hot and the world is hot too.
Germ e, heye lew da.
It is hot, yes indeed.
Wele germ e.
Well it is hot.
Teet hikmê, wîzê avê hebe.
Under the rule, if there is the flow of water.
Hesar jî cefaf e, na xalo, cefaf hatî êşta...
This year is also a drought, isn't it uncle, drought came
now...
Wele zeytûn dar ber ketine.
Well the olive trees have fallen [yield/health].
Xalo, berê rind bû, noka rind bû?
Uncle, was before better, or is now better?
Wele berê, berê rind bû.
Well before, before was better.
Teqes sewatê mesele... zexîre malê dixwest...
Definitely the times for example... supplies needed for the
house...
Te didî... nan... noka na wye.
You gave... bread... now it's not like that.
Noka ecişa çiqî noka zehmet e.
Now living a little now is difficult.
Fereke di mewcûdî yan, tem hebin.
There is money in existence, let them all be there.
Berê pere tina bûn, zora tina bû.
Before money didn't exist, difficulty didn't exist [or force
didn't exist].
Moka, te vî pere didîma zora tina bû.
Now, you give this money, there was no difficulty.
Bes noka.
But now.
Du ro pere tina bûn da emrî.
Two days money didn't exist in life.
Na.
No.
Xalo berê, me digotin lo berê înternet tina bûn, mesela
telefon tina bûn.
Uncle before, we were saying before internet didn't exist,
for example phones didn't exist.
Vê milletî kevnar, berê çû derbas dikirin ano?
This ancient people, before how did they pass [time/life]
then?
Ê çû, yek wefatek di va gundî dibû.
How, one death would happen in this village.
Ê biçûna cîranê xwe, bedewê, ê bigota er filan gundî, meriyê
me hene xeberê pê de.
They would go to their neighbor, the Bedouin [or messenger],
they would say in such and such village, we have relatives,
give them the news.
Eywa.
I see.
Bi dewarî qebat diçûn, bi hesp bûn, bi hadho ne ki hebin.
They went with livestock/horses, they were with horses, with
whatever they had.
Ba hesbo diçûn gundo xeber didan.
With horses they went to the villages to give news.
Diçûn, digu her kora, her kasefre, her mesela boflore, her
badîna, her kuder bûse.
They went, saying every Kora, every Kasefre, every for
example Boflore, every Badîna, every wherever it was.
Meriyê xorkê, te seke, nîşev da...
The relatives of the guy, you look, at midnight...
Meriv lê diniştin, diçûn xeber dan digu wele meriyê we wefat
kirî.
People sat there, went to give news saying well your
relative passed away.
Û lê diqesidîn dihatin.
And they set out and came.
Ê noka na waye, noka telefon hema çite, wê şevê têk...
But now it's not like that, now the phone just goes, that
night connects...
Hezar gundî, gi telefon kî, gi xeberê xweş hebin.
A thousand villagers, all phone, all have good news.
Erê, noka bê elo derkê Almanya, elo Swîsra.
Yes, now say hello out to Germany, hello Switzerland.
Derkê Almanya, Swîsra.
No?
Out to Germany, Switzerland.
Û hîn tu sûretê gindîş dibînî.
And still you see the villager's face too.
Hîn sûret jî dibînî.
Still you see the face too.
Ji vî cî da xweş e.
From this side it is good.
Yes.
Ji vî cî da xweş e.
From this side it is good.
Avone, berê, cafof pir bî, mesela tiştê hono tina bîn.
So, before, drought was much, for example things like that
didn't exist.
Noho dîsa elhemdullah ji Xwedê re, vê telefonê çêbîn, dinya
hedîsî bî ye, na wey xalo?
Now again thank God, these phones were made, the world has
become modern, isn't it so uncle?
Pir rind bî ye, noka pir rind bî ye.
It has become very good, now it has become very good.
Bes, ji serî da rind e.
But, from the beginning it is good.
Bes ji serî eman da, na tina, eman tina.
But from the beginning in trust, no it doesn't exist, trust
doesn't exist.
Nav millet da eman tina, sîqet namay kêm bî ye.
Among the people trust doesn't exist, confidence has not
remained, it has become less.
Berê hebî sîqet hebî, haskirin hebî, na wey?
Before it existed, confidence existed, love existed, didn't
it?
Berê sîqet, berê haskirin hebû.
Before confidence, before love existed.
Berê yek wefat dikir di gundo da dibû...
Before one passed away in the village it would happen...
B'meha, b'bîst ro, deh ro, cîran gindî bila b'kincê xwe dîn
nedikirin.
For months, for twenty days, ten days, the neighbor villager
would not even change/wear their [fancy] clothes.
Nedişûştin, rihê xwe çê nedikirin.
They didn't wash, didn't fix their beards.
Eywa.
I see.
Emê l'vir mirî rodibê, l'viderê dawetê xwe dikin.
But here the dead lies, here they have their wedding.
Şûra xalo got tarîx ne, avolno.
Uncle's words are history, folks.
Rast e.
It is true.
Berê mirîk bimra, dukan dihatin digirtin, bi hefta kewe
malbat no, aza çê dikirin.
Before if a dead person died, shops came and closed, for
weeks that family, they held mourning.
Noho cîran dimre, roy dî roj dawet pîşî qepe lê dikabe.
Now a neighbor dies, the next day, the day, a wedding is set
up in front of the door.
Dawet çê dibê.
A wedding happens.
Na?
No?
Ê lo kanî? Ê ma'eto... aw nemo.
So where is it? So the meaning... that didn't remain.
Hurmet nemo, qîmet nemo.
Respect didn't remain, value didn't remain.
Kêm bî ye.
It has become less.
Yanî îsan ne bû tu nî ye.
Meaning human has become nothing.
Erê.
Yes.
Îsan ne bû tu tişt nî ye.
Human has become nothing at all.
Berê îsan bi qîmet bî.
Before human was valuable.
Pir, pir bi qîmet bî.
Very, very valuable.
Mesele berê, berê digot filan kes, filan kes.
For example before, before they said so and so person, so
and so person.
Qîmet didanê.
They gave him value.
Noka, noka qîmet tina.
Now, now value doesn't exist.
Noka qîmet didin pere.
Now they give value to money.
Didin pere.
They give to money.
Qîmet didin pere.
They give value to money.
Erê.
Yes.
Ne ji mêra didin.
They don't give to brave men.
Erê.
Yes.
Ne.
No.
Ne ji mêra didin.
They don't give to brave men.
Wele xalo tu mêr î, tu mêrxas î.
Well uncle you are a brave man, you are a hero.
Tu sax bî, Xwedê te bihêle.
May you be healthy, may God keep you.
Tu mêr î, tu mêrxas î.
You are a brave man, you are a hero.
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God keep you.
Çêtere?
Is it better?
Aywa.
Yes.
Tu dibêjî çêtere, lolo ne çêtere.
You say it is better, oh man, it isn't better.
Erê, bes heba cîranê te, ew herb alemî ye dibe.
Yes, but if your neighbor has it [and you don't], it becomes
a world war.
Selam eleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Eleykum selam.
And upon you peace.
Cejna te pîroz be.
Happy Eid to you.
Ya we pîroz be.
Happy Eid to you all.
Tu çawanî baş î?
How are you, are you well?
Ez xulam.
At your service.
Sihet xweş.
Good health to you.
Erê.
Yes.
Yanî dibêjî hîç çêdibe?
So you are saying it is getting any better?
Qîmetê ajelê qey namaye.
The value of livestock is gone.
Merreqa namaye.
There is no desire left.
Tenabîn we dke, xalo tenabîn we dke.
They are winding you up, uncle, they are winding you up.
Mago tenabîn we dke, ne?
You said they are winding us up, right?
Ne tenabîn, wellah yê heye heye jixwe.
Not winding up, I swear whoever has [wealth], has it anyway.
Yê heye, heye jixwe.
Whoever has it, has it anyway.
Yê tune, bila bibêjin "tine no".
The one who doesn't have it, let them say "there isn't any,
no."
No, eger tenê, yê heye heye, behre ye, yê heye.
No, if it's just that, the one who has it, has it, it's an
ocean, the one who has it.
Noka wellah feqîrê sedî, em bibêjin, sedî nod û pênc heye
jê.
Now, strictly speaking, ninety-five percent of the poor have
it [struggle].
Erê, yê pir zengîn in.
Yes, the ones who are very rich.
Yê pir halê xwe xweş in.
Their situation is very good.
Em kê bawer nakin, yê pir halê xwe xweş in.
We don't believe who, [but] their situation is very good.
Rast e.
That's true.
Yê berê sedî heftê û pênc feqîr bûn.
In the past, seventy-five percent were poor.
Sedî bîst û pênc zengîn bûn.
Twenty-five percent were rich.
Lê noka sedî heftê û pênc, heştê zengîn e.
But now, seventy-five, eighty percent are rich.
Bîst jê têda sîfîl in.
Twenty percent among them are destitute.
Sîfîl in.
They are destitute.
Erê.
Yes.
Rast e heval, nişûra xalo gelek tarîx e.
That is true friend, the uncle's perspective is quite
historic.
Şûra xalo diqre ez gund da digerim.
The uncle's perspective... I am walking around the village.
Rast e, malbat ne hene zengîn in, yanî behr e, Xwedê rizqê
gîna bide şînê.
It is true, there are families that are rich, like an ocean,
may God grant sustenance to everyone.
Û malbat ne jî hene, heqî nîn vêra tînana.
And there are families who don't even have the right [means]
to bring [food] here.
Heqî nîn vêra tînana?
They don't have the means to bring it here?
Wellah ez pir molo katimê girî me ra re hemberê te.
I swear I have cried many times over the situations in front
of you.
Û mal ne jî hene dkevine, pere pir in, nizanin çikin.
And there are homes where money is falling [abundant], lots
of money, they don't know what to do with it.
Nizanin çikin.
They don't know what to do.
Gerek meriv xêra bike, yê hebîna xwe heye, gerek meriv li yê
xîncî xwe jî binêre.
One must do charity, the one who has wealth, one must look
after the others too.
Însanê feqîr nane.
The poor human being.
Ser bo cejnê de, ser cejnê de.
Especially for Eid, during Eid.
Cejna qurbanê ye.
It is the Feast of Sacrifice (Eid al-Adha).
Cejnê qurbanê ye.
It is the Feast of Sacrifice.
Xwedê qurbanê giya qebûl bike.
May God accept everyone's sacrifice.
Erê.
Yes.
Ya me jî, ya te jî.
Ours too, and yours.
Ya me jî, ya te jî, ya giya.
Ours too, yours too, everyone's.
Umeta giya bike.
The entire Ummah (community).
Umeta Mihemed giyşta bike.
The entire Ummah of Muhammad.
Belkî dibir da çel dewar hatûye şarşê tîra.
Perhaps forty trucks of livestock came to the market today.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Çel dewar masûkera hatin şarşê gi.
Forty trucks loaded came to the whole market.
Ji çel dewarî, hev çel dewaro gel feqîra, gibela kirin o
şindo.
Out of forty trucks, regarding those forty trucks, the poor
made a commotion and such.
Çel dewar ji çel kîlo daye çarsed kîlo ye.
Forty trucks... from forty kilos it is four hundred kilos.
Erê.
Yes.
Çarsed kîlo goşt lba deha malet feqîra were belavkirin.
Four hundred kilos of meat to be distributed among ten poor
families.
Yekî çû be, yekî xobka gîne.
One might have gone, one might bring a handful.
Qçkî xwe jî bişîne, kêfa wan xweş be.
Send their little one too, so they become happy.
Mîvanê xwe jî, mîvanê xwe jî, yekî bi kêf bixwe vexe.
Their guests too, their guests too, so one can eat and drink
with joy.
Rastokî wan zikî têr nîn e.
Truly their bellies are not full.
Ê bes noka çiye, çel hatî şarşê kin, ji çelî çel kîlo nehatî
belavkirin.
But now what is it, forty came to the market, out of forty,
not even forty kilos were distributed.
Rast e.
True.
Şûra xalo rast e.
The uncle's perspective is correct.
Çel kîlo nehatî belavkirin.
Forty kilos were not distributed.
Ê din kanî?
Where are the rest?
Kerna berrad û kera başqe, kerna berrad û emê bixwin.
They put them in the fridges and put them elsewhere, they
put them in the fridges and "we will eat them".
Erê.
Yes.
Ew nebî xweşî qurban e.
That isn't the joy of the sacrifice.
Wana ne qebûl e, gava gerek sê tilt ê feqîra be, tiltek yê
te be.
That is not accepted, it should be that three thirds are for
the poor, and one third is yours.
Ewa xalo.
Exactly, uncle.
Wana ra hewna jî nesab in.
Those people, they are also swindlers.
Eywa.
Yes.
Nesab in hewna.
They are swindlers.
Ew heqî, heqî feqîra bixwe, ti dibêjî çi, heqî feqîra ê
sêwiy bixwe?
That right, to eat the right of the poor, what are you
saying, to eat the right of the poor and orphans?
Bişîni, bişîni jî feqîra ra.
Send it, send it to the poor.
Na.
No.
Bişîni, yeki feqîra ra.
Send it, one to the poor.
Ê feqîra naverê bixwe.
He won't eat the poor man's share.
Lê vêra tûn û, yanî zeh, dubare derbas nebî wey feqîra.
But here... meaning... again, may it not pass by the poor
man.
Bes wayî din zengîn tu jêr dşînî, wî pir tûq qethandine.
But the other rich person you send it down to, he has
snapped many necks [eaten much meat].
Pir fintas e kirine û pir firr û vût kirine, derbas be vêra,
ha ê xwe bide birîni ta ra.
He has done much showing off and much running around, let it
pass to him, let him feed it to his wound.
Bes ê feqîra tu du sal a jî pirskin kanî ça bet a, did a na
la ne, mekşûf e.
But the poor one, if you ask him for two years "where is it,
how is it?", he won't give it... it is exposed.
Mekşûf e.
It is exposed.
Ê xwe biekşîfîne.
He exposes himself.
Bes wayî zengîn naekşîfîne.
But the rich one doesn't expose himself.
Erê, xalo berî vê jî me ra şandin, teb'en xêrxwazoy me ra
şandin.
Yes, uncle, before this they sent to us, naturally
charitable people sent to us.
Min helqe, du helqe jî çêkiribûn, bernameyê Xêrxwaz.
I had made an episode, two episodes, of the "Xêrxwaz"
(Charity) program.
Ser vê cejnê û berî cejnê jî me ra şandin.
For this Eid and before Eid, they sent to us.
Me gundê xwe wana kir, me bela nekir.
We did [organized] our village, we didn't distribute it
[randomly].
Me got ma'nî nabe no gundê xwe bela ke.
We said there is no meaning in distributing to our own
village [only].
Em derdikevin gundo.
We are going out to the villages.
Kîja malbatê feqîra ba, me didan wê malbatê feqîra, li
gundo.
Whichever family was poor, we gave to that poor family, in
the villages.
Rast e.
True.
Ti dibêjî çi ser vê yekê?
What do you say about this?
No rinde.
No, it is good.
Rind e, na wey?
It is good, isn't it?
Rind e.
It is good.
Mesela em digerin, kîja malbatê feqîra ye, sêwî têda heye?
For example, we go around, which family is poor, are there
orphans in it?
Em li cem bîn, me pirs dikir û em zanin jî.
We would be with them, we asked and we also know.
Me zarfek dida wê malbatê, li her gundekî.
We gave an envelope to that family, in every village.
Me du helqe wano çêkirin, ê bes wele wê helqê jî vîdê me
hewna naşixûlîn.
We made two episodes like that, but honestly for this
episode, the video... we didn't operate those.
Kemre.
Camera.
Em dazanin, em dazanin.
We know, we know.
Xalo ti bi vê xêrxwaziyê li sêwiyay danêrin, vanê meriyê
naxoş...
Uncle, with this charity looking after orphans, these sick
people...
Î îmkanê xwe tine, evê xêrxwazna cohê li wan danêrin, ti
bwan ra dibêjî çi?
Who don't have the means, these charitable people who look
after them, what do you say to them?
Saeta wana xweş, Xwedê ji wan razî bin.
Bless their hearts (lit: may their hour be good), may God be
pleased with them.
Li meriyê feqîra seh dikin.
They look after the poor people.
We inşallah Teala, Xwedê bwan ra jî bihesirîne.
And God willing, the Almighty, may God make it easy for them
too.
Amîn.
Amen.
Bihesirîne.
Make it easy.
Amîn.
Amen.
Li meriyê feqîra seh dikin, li meriyê naxoş seh dikin, li
sêwiyan seh dikin, li meriyê feqîra seh dikin.
They look after poor people, they look after sick people,
they look after orphans, they look after poor people.
Saeta wana hezar carî xweş.
A thousand blessings on them.
Hezar carî xweş.
A thousand times good.
Ey te jî xweş.
And yours too.
Wellahî xalo vê cejnê, vê cejnê û berî cejnê jî me vîdyo jî
çêkir.
I swear uncle, this Eid, this Eid and before Eid too, we
made a video.
Xêrxwaza merra tebera kirin, me da malbatna, înak înak...
Charitable people donated to us, we gave to families, here
and there...
Pir malbatê me dayê, giriyê ma hat, ji tenabîniyê ji
feqîrbîniyê.
We gave to many families, our tears fell, from the distress
and from the poverty.
Heqî nîn dver tînana, sêwa destê da bîn.
They didn't have the means to bring [food] here, they had
apples in their hands.
Çi bi xêra te bighîjinê, Xwedê xêra te mezin bike.
Whatever reaches them through your charity, may God make
your charity great.
Em tenê navçî ne.
We are only intermediaries.
Ewe hec e, hec.
That is Hajj, [like performing] Hajj.
Ji hecê mezin tir e, ji qurbanê kê çêtiro, hewa ji hecê
çêtiro, hewa ji giçê çêtiro.
It is greater than Hajj, better than any sacrifice, that is
better than Hajj, that is better than everything.
Lê tu 'elmîj ti dikî.
I swear.
But you know what you are doing.
Erê.
Yes.
Û tu tenfîz dikî.
And you are executing it.
Û teb'en wekî vanê xêrxwaz hebin, mletê vanê, iqintî jî li
'ardê namînin.
And naturally, if there are such charitable people, this
nation, these destitute ones won't remain on the ground.
E namînin.
They won't remain.
Na wey?
Right?
Namînin, no, namînin.
They won't remain, no, they won't remain.
Wellah rast e.
I swear it's true.
Eger merîkî feqîra tedayî ye, pêçûye Xwedê re ser vê cejnê
kiriyê pê...
If a poor man is distressed, helpless towards God, for this
Eid he has done it with...
Qurbanê xwa kiriyê pê, mesela, tiştin ji qîçkê xora kirinê
pêşabûna.
He made his sacrifice with it, for example, bought things
for his children so they rejoice.
Her qîçkikî şokirin bide, bi hecikey e.
Every child you make happy, is like a Hajj.
Bi hecikey e.
True.
Is like a Hajj.
Wellahî xalo xêrxwaz hene, bi me ra tewasul kirin.
I swear uncle, there are charitable people, they contacted
us.
Piroka go amkanin, mê pênsed dular am bidin, am maşê mesela,
am maşê hino girêdin, maşê sêwiyay.
The story is that they said if possible, we will give five
hundred dollars, we will assign a salary for example, a
salary for orphans.
Malbatna sêwa deste da, go az kanim ji mada, am mê pênsed
dular bişînim, hawa şexsikî mra wa go.
Families with apples [poverty] in hand, he said if I can
from my side, I will send five hundred dollars, a person
told me this.
Şexsikî.
A person.
Şexsikî, mê pênsed dular ke bişîne.
A person, he will send five hundred dollars.
Elloh me'ek.
God be with you [him].
Û yekî din jî me ra derkat.
And another one appeared to us.
Go herin malbatek naxoş, go 'emeleta genda çok sid kelifê.
He said go to a sick family, he said the operations for the
children cost a lot.
Go am sta'ed mi ji hazur dularî heta bîst pênc hazurî bidim,
teklîfê wê 'ameletê.
He said I am ready to give from one thousand dollars up to
twenty-five thousand, for the cost of that operation.
Saeta genda xweş.
Bless their hearts.
Xwedê mezin e, mekrîmanj, dilbirehm e.
God is great, generous, merciful.
Û dilê xwo jî bnozîk e, dilê xwo bzuy însên dşewitê, xêrxwaz
têda pir nê wella.
And His heart is near, His heart burns quickly for the
human, there are many charitable people in it, I swear.
Rast e.
True.
Saeta gendiya xweş, û berdestê miriya genda gîne.
Bless them, and may it reach the hands of their dead
[ancestors as blessings].
Xwedê pêxember ji we razî bin.
May God and the Prophet be pleased with you all.
Erê.
Yes.
Teqsîr nakin.
They do not neglect [their duty].
Rind e, bota av tişta, 'amelyo pir rind e.
Good, for you this thing, the work is very good.
Xwedê pêxember ji we razî bin.
May God and the Prophet be pleased with you.
Xwedê wana bafqîne.
May God grant them success.
Xwedê qçkê, qçkê wana selîm bike inşallah.
May God keep their children, their children safe, God
willing.
Amîn, amîn, inşallah.
Amen, amen, God willing.
Inşallah, ka heval nû dê bime ra bin, emê noka lextane di
nav gund werê çêkin, saeta ta xweş xalo, Xwedê ji te razî
be.
God willing, friends stay with us, we will now make a clip
inside the village, blessings to you uncle, may God be
pleased with you.
Dê ka bime ra bin.
Stay with us.
Erê hevalno, gundekî pir xweş e, kîbar e.
Yes friends, it is a very nice village, elegant.
Mentîqê me pir fereh e.
Our region is very wide.
Wellahî ji Libnanê jî mestir e.
I swear it is even bigger than Lebanon.
Ha.
Awa Dêrbalûte ye hemberê me?
Is that Dêrbalûte opposite us?
Awa Dêrbalûte ye.
That is Dêrbalûte.
Erê, û yê jê wêda Xêmen?
Yes, and the one beyond that is Xêmen?
Xêmen.
Xêmen Dêrbalûte ne.
It's Xêmen, Dêrbalûte.
Ewe de maxferê Tirko ye tîxê yon.
That over there is the Turkish outpost, their border.
Xerbi wê va?
To the West of it?
Û şerqî wê jî, viderê Mehmudiye ye.
And to the East of it, right here is Mehmudiye.
Mehmudiye.
Gundê Mehmudiye ye, ew darê... merxê têdane.
It's the village of Mehmudiye, those trees... there are
juniper trees in it.
E hemberê me jî Dêwa ye.
And opposite us is Dêwa.
Dêwa?
Dêwa ye, Dêwê Xerbî ye awa.
It is Dêwa, that is Western Dêwa.
Dêwê, welle dûr e.
Dêwa, wow it is far.
Dêwê Xerbî ye.
It is Western Dêwa.
Eywa.
Yes.
Û şerqî wê dere, gewr dikê, ew jî Dêwê Şerqî ye.
And to the East of it, you see the white spot, that is
Eastern Dêwa.
Çend mal dorda hene.
There are a few houses around there.
E şerqî wê Qulkê ye.
And to the East of it is Qulkê.
Awa Qulkê ye?
That is Qulkê?
Erê Qulkê ye.
Yes, it is Qulkê.
Vêra dibên Qulkê ye?
They call this place Qulkê?
Qulkê ye.
It is Qulkê.
Wê gundî mezin kîdere lê?
Where is that big village then?
Hawa Celamê ye.
That is Celamê.
Celamê.
Erê.
Yes.
Eywa.
I see.
Hawa Celamê ye, hawa Qulkê ye, hawa Dêwê Şerqî ye, Dêwê
Xerbî ye, Dêwa ye, Mehmudiye ye...
That is Celamê, that is Qulkê, that is Eastern Dêwa, Western
Dêwa, Dêwa, Mehmudiye...
Û vî jî xêmê Mehmudiye ne.
And these are the tents of Mehmudiye.
Erê.
Yes.
Maşallah, mentîqe mezin e, mezin e, havalno.
Mashallah, the region is big, big, friends.
Mezin e.
It is big.
Kake Xelîl, em malbatê bavê te, te ye?
Brother Khalil, are we at your father's family home?
Teb'en, aw têdaye, 'esker têdaye, nal mole.
Naturally, he is in there, the soldier is in there, curse
the home [joking about disorder].
Li mol bû, emê têketana hewşê, me ye ter hewş jî teswîr
kira.
If he was at home, we would have entered the courtyard, we
would have filmed the courtyard too.
E mirîşk nal mole, em nikanin dhewşê kevin.
The chickens curse the home [run away], we can't enter the
courtyard.
Li mol bime, e izn jê bipro, emê dhewşê ketana.
If we were at home, we would ask permission, we would have
entered the courtyard.
Bjûz jin minê xol mol bin.
Perhaps my uncle's wives are at home.
Erê wellah. Ka bme ra bin, em derbas jêr bin.
Yes indeed. Be with us, let's go down.
Erê hevalno.
Yes friends.
Teb'en em mole Ebu Îbrahîm ne.
Naturally, we are at Abu Ibrahim's house.
Bofkê Xelîl.
Khalil's father.
Xwedê 'emrekî dirêj pê de, saeta gende xweş.
May God grant him a long life, blessings to them.
Em dçûn mol, wellah ew jî bsidfê em rastî duso hatin, go î
lginda, am hatin.
We were going home, by chance we met again, he said he is in
the village, we came.
Me go em silavke pê dinê.
We said let's greet him.
Kake Xelîl, em lmolbata we ne.
Brother Khalil, we are with your family.
Bofkê te, me go em silavke pê dinê.
Your father, we said we will greet him.
Ehlen we sehlen, serî serê çavê me babo, ehlen we sehlen
bwatini we, ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome, you are most welcome on our eyes [very welcome]
father, welcome to your coming, welcome.
Saet xweş.
Blessings.
Wece xweş.
Your face be good [Bless you too].
Xolo, maşallah ez nû vgindê we gerîm, gind pir gindekî
kîbar, xweş bî.
Uncle, Mashallah I just walked around your village, the
village was a very elegant, nice village.
Xolû miro tarîx nehewl don.
The uncle didn't try to give history [earlier].
Yanî pir xweş bî, me hejê bon.
Meaning it was very nice, we liked it.
Navê gundî me ye, maşallah pir xweş e, yanî evê xozî, cewî
gende, ji dar berî gende, je gîda yanî pir xweş e, ya ni
b...
The name of our village, Mashallah it is very nice, meaning
the houses, the atmosphere of the village, the trees of the
village, everything is very nice, meaning with...
Ewe îctîma'î.
The social aspect.
Xweş e gundê we?
Is your village nice?
Xweş e gundê we.
Our village is nice.
Cima?
How?
Xolo berê rind bî, noka rind bî?
Uncle, was it better before, or is it better now?
Serkî da, berê rind bû.
In one way, before was good.
Berê.
Yes.
Before.
Yanî berê, em bêjin çû qîmetê ev zonîn, yanî çûndin hatin
hebu, hevdu ihtiram dikirin, der dikirin.
Meaning before, let's say they knew the value of this, there
was visiting, they respected each other, visited each other.
Noka jî em bibêjin, ne zêde waye em bibêjin.
And now let's say, it's not much like that, let's say.
Kêm biye.
It has decreased.
Û em bibêjin, yanî...
And let's say, meaning...
Çû dibê?
What happens?
Berê dçûn cem hev, dihatin, witu nîne, noka jî dar nîn, yanî
berê dil ki pak dabo.
Before they went to each other, they came, it's not like
that [now], now there is no door [open], meaning before
there was a pure heart.
Eywa.
Yes.
Dihatin xema xelkê, ev lê ab did ra wandin.
They came [shared] people's sorrows, this one running to
that one.
Yanî wekî dibêjin, ji hev ra wextî bîn, dan dikirin, ge
didogrin, vî vêr dogrî, dkenî, hew jî vêr dkenî.
Meaning as they say, for each other when they were... they
paid attention... if this one grabs, he pulls, that one also
pulls.
Dketin gozinca bhevda ra.
They entered into struggle/links with each other.
Î noka jî, ekteriyetên bu meslehet yanî.
But now, the majority has become for self-interest, meaning.
Meslehet.
Self-interest/Business.
Meslehet e yanî.
It is self-interest, meaning.
Rast e.
True.
Ha, xolo te...
Ha, uncle you...
Te mentîqe xweş dîtî ye, tu çûye Ewropa jî, te gerî ye?
You have seen nice regions, have you gone to Europe too,
have you traveled?
Welle mentîqa me cenet e.
I swear our region is paradise.
Cenet e, ne wey?
Paradise, isn't it?
Mentîqekî pir xweş e.
It is a very nice region.
Yanî em bibêjin mentîqe, yanî av heye, dar hene, hewa heye.
Meaning let's say the region, meaning there is water, there
are trees, there is air.
Kaniya avê.
Springs of water.
Kaniya avê heye.
There are springs of water.
Çem heye.
There is a river.
Çem heye, gî heye, yanî mentîqa pir xweş e.
There is a river, there is everything, meaning the region is
very nice.
Yanî milletê Ewropa me liva gere?
So the people of Europe should come back here?
Milletê Evropa, gerek neşkinin gî werin.
The people of Europe, they should all break [leave] and
come.
Xweş bî, mentîqe xweş bî hevalno.
It was nice, the region was nice friends.
Erê, mentîqe xweş e.
Yes, the region is nice.
Çiqa bibê, oxê mero ser ba ye.
No matter what, a person's nature is on the wind [air].
Erê.
Yes.
Yanî çiqa herî dero, ti dgi nîzîkê dikî, bînî gendê tê mero.
Meaning no matter how much you go out, when you get close,
the scent of the village comes to the person.
Nefesê...
The breath...
Wero vê derê bêje. Xweş dibe.
Come and say it here. It will be good.
De ca silavekî jî bişîne ji şebab û bura û xûşk û birayê me
seyr dikin.
Come on, send a greeting to the youth and brothers and
sisters watching us.
Welle ez silavê li gişya dikim.
Well, I greet everyone.
Wegerin ser cîwarê xwe, mentîqê xwe.
Return to your homeland, your region.
Û Xwedê sihetê xweş bide gişya de.
And may God give good health to everyone.
Wekî din, eşrefî me ji gişya ra hene.
Other than that, we have respect for everyone.
Ê pêk nîn e, silavê te pêk nîn e.
It's no problem, your greeting is no problem.
Kekê Xelîl silav gihiştê. Baş e?
Brother Xelîl, the greeting reached them. Okay?
Ew silavê te li ser çava.
That greeting of yours is upon my eyes (You're welcome).
Gotina te hene ti têkî bikî?
Do you have any words to add?
Te jî xweş.
You be well too.
Erê hevalno, emê li vîderê vîdyo xwe xîtam kin cem Apo
Ibrahîm, seeteke hindik xweş.
Yes friends, we will conclude our video here at Uncle
Ibrahim's, a nice short time.
Kekê Xelîl şaşbûn maşbûnê me heye hûnê qisûrê me efû kin
hevalno.
Brother Xelîl, if we have any mistakes, forgive our
shortcomings, friends.
Taben vîdyê me jî ekserî ge efewî ne.
Of course, our videos are mostly very spontaneous.
Emê li vîderê xîtam kin. Di yê ro xelekek din inşallah emê
werin bal we, nêzîk da.
We will conclude here. Another day, another episode, God
willing, we will come to you soon.
Like like follow. Gulek gulek xatira we.
Like like follow. A flower a flower, goodbye.
Qusûrê me hejî winê efû kin. Belkî me şaşbûn ji kiri bî winê
efû kin.
Forgive our shortcomings too. Maybe we made a mistake,
please forgive.
Şaşbûn tinne ne, seeteke xweş, çavê we gişya maç dikim.
There are no mistakes, a good time, I kiss all of your eyes.
Spas dikim.
Thank you.