Milekî vî gundî eyn wekî vî darê...
One side of this village is just like this tree...
Ev qorî wek qorî wek çiye?
This teapot is like a teapot like what?
Qorî me zrêqa wisa...
Our teapot is shiny like that...
Asaso sî zrêqaye.
Basically, its shadow is shiny.
We'be me ji we re heye, ver heta dewletî der va.
We have [news/talk] for you, go until the state outside.
Are, walla maşallah tejî biya gelekî dwa şin, dwa şin.
Yes, by God, mashallah, you have also become very followed,
followed.
Walla sê sado min dayê qîs ke u lo u xo...
By God, three hundred I gave for it, measure it and...
Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike de.
May God prolong your life then.
Ji dehê heta deh û pêncî, deh.
From ten until ten-fifty, ten.
I sêrek?
Is it a quarter?
Belê.
Yes.
Merheba ji were hevalno, siba we gîyo bi xêr. Em hatin hûru
vîdyoyekî xweş kîbor.
Hello to you friends, good morning to you all. We came today
[to make] a nice, decent video.
Vîdyoyê me jî, hûru em li gundê Xelêrê ne.
Our video today, today we are in the village of Xelêrê.
Are, emkê darbazî gundê Xelêrê bin, emkê teswîr kin.
Yes, we will pass into the village of Xelêrê, we will film.
Maşallah gundekî xweş e.
Mashallah, it is a nice village.
Are, ka bi mere bin vîdyoyekî xweş kîbor, nav gundê Xelêrê
emê were teswîr kin.
Yes, so stay with us for a nice, decent video, inside the
village of Xelêrê, we will film for you.
Bîr mekin te'lîqê we mero pir bin.
Don't forget, let your comments be many for us.
We kî dibê saeta gîyo xweş, kesê ji mero te'lîqê xweş
dişînin, çavê gîyo maç dikim.
As they say, health to you all, [to] those who send us nice
comments, I kiss all your eyes.
Mihemed tu tiştekî dibêjî?
Mohammad, do you have anything to say?
Merheba hevalê me, we çun e, îşê we çawa, siheta we çawa,
inşallah gî rind û rehet ne.
Hello our friends, how are you, how is your work, how is
your health, God willing you are all good and comfortable.
Ere îro dîsa em hatin vîdyoyekî xweş kîbor çêkin.
Yes, today again we came to make a nice, decent video.
Bîr mekin ji mero laykê û îştîrakê pêdinê û muşarake kin
hevalê xwe, ehbabê xwe gîyo.
Don't forget to give us a like and subscription, and share
it with your friends, all your loved ones.
Heta sefha me tîşkî bilind bibe û saeta we gîyo xweş.
So that our page rises a bit, and good health to you all.
Are hevalno, saet xweş Mihemed.
Yes friends, good health [thanks] Mohammad.
Livro gundê Xelêrê, maşallah gundekî pir xweş e megû.
Today the village of Xelêrê, mashallah it is a very nice
village as we said.
Av jî heye, gundê Xelêrê av jî heye.
There is water too, the village of Xelêrê has water too.
Xelkê piro bîrê avê lêxistî li vî gundî.
The people have dug many water wells in this village.
Are çîçkê gundikî kortê daye, bes xweş e, gundekî xweş e.
Yes, it's a bit of a village situated in a hollow, but it is
nice, it is a nice village.
Nav mar bin heta tolyê, inşallah ew vîdyo be ecibînin.
Stay with us until the end, God willing you will like this
video.
Oo xelkê piro bîrê avê lêxistî.
Oh, the people have dug many water wells.
Are noko jî me gundê Xelêrê xelas kir.
Yes, now we have finished [filming] the village of Xelêrê.
Ezê inşallah be izna Xwedê, Xwedê teqaza nede, ezê vî gundî
Keferşîlê jî vîdyoyekî têda çêkim.
I will, God willing, by God's leave, if God forbids any
accident, I will make a video in this village of Keferşîlê
too.
Bi xwo Keferşîlê ne mezine.
Keferşîlê itself isn't big.
Inşallah Xwedê yesirand, ezê gundê Keferşîlê daxim.
God willing, if God makes it easy, I will upload the village
of Keferşîlê.
Bi sawirînim, hêlqê... hêlqê du yê vêra ezê gundê Keferşîlê
daxim.
I will film it, episode... as part two of this, I will
upload the village of Keferşîlê.
Miletê gundê Keferşîlê, milo li me baskinin.
The people of the village of Keferşîlê, don't let them be
upset with us.
Hêlqê du yê vêra emê daxin.
We will upload it as part two of this.
Slav û rêzê me ji miletê... vê gundina hard gora hene.
Our greetings and respect to the people... of all these
surrounding villages.
Ser serê me, ser çavê me, çûçik mezin.
On our heads, on our eyes [you are welcome], small and big.
Are hevalno li vê derê jî me dest pê kir.
Yes friends, at this place too we have started.
Li vê derê jî bîrê avê lêdixin, bu sehrekê gi bihare.
At this place too they are digging water wells, for a bit of
spring planting.
Wadiye, bîrê avê çok so lêxistine milet.
It seems, the people have dug water wells very much.
Av li vê gundî pir e.
Water is abundant in this village.
Are.
Yes.
No şoş e, ev tiştî wano şoş e.
Now it is glass [smooth], this thing like that is glass.
Rast e wadiye, herre gi çû berdanê ser rê ke, tay milet
mokîna ke çû têre herin werin?
It is true, it seems, they let all the mud go onto the road,
so how can people's cars go back and forth?
Are wî bîrê lêdixin lêxin, saeta wa xweş.
Yes, let them dig the wells, dig, good health to them.
Bes vê heriyê ê vê derê... cifloq e.
But this mud of this place... is slush.
Hîşta miletê me pir şolê şbîna dikin.
Still our people do a lot of arbitrary work [without
planning].
Xendek xwo çêke.
Make your ditch.
Xendek xwo çêke, yo jî wekî zrîbê okey çêke wano, milo av
bearikê herre binî zeytûna.
Make your ditch, make it like a drain like that, so the
water flows down to the bottom of the olive trees.
Pa em bînê ser rê ke de, mokîna dişemite...
But don't bring it onto the road, the car slips...
...herre bî.
...it becomes mud.
Nexweş e.
It's unpleasant.
Pak bîn, pak bîn rinde.
Keep it clean, keeping it clean is good.
Pak bîn tişkî pir rind e.
Keeping it clean is a very good thing.
Ne emkê bes hema emkê îxo bikulin, emkê xelas kin û yalla.
Not that we will just boil ourselves [get agitated], we will
finish and let's go.
Çi dibê milo bê, no, ne wanoye.
Whatever happens let it happen, no, it's not like that.
Amkê qîmetê mentîqê xwo zanibin, qîmetê cografya xwo
zanibin, ha no mentîqa pir xweş bîye, kîbor bîye.
We should know the value of our region, know the value of
our geography, look now the region has become very nice,
very decent.
O xoluy hewşê termîm dike.
And the uncle is restoring the courtyard.
Saet xweş! Saet xweş!
Good health! Good health!
O hefarok li derana jî lêdixê, bîrê avê.
Oh, the excavator is digging there too, water wells.
Bi vê gundî de du hefara lêdixin avê.
In this village, two excavators are digging for water.
Wadiye o...
It seems oh...
...hefarok.
...excavator.
Are hevalno vî derê darek tîye heye, ev daro jî pir emrê xwo
kevnare.
Yes friends, in this place there is a mulberry tree, this
tree is also very ancient in its age.
Miletê vê gundî ê naske vê darê.
The people of this village know this tree.
Dorik pir kevnare. Li vî derê jî...
It is a very ancient tree. And in this place...
Sarinc heye.
There is a cistern.
Ev sarnco jî kevnare.
This cistern is also ancient.
Seke kevirê ginde.
Look at the big stones.
Avo cîyê avê ye, sarnce.
This is a place for water, a cistern.
No hevo gerek mero wano dûrê pak bîtin, termîm kiro.
Now this, one should have kept around it clean, restored it.
Ma'nî heywano, ma'nî milet.
For the sake of animals, for the sake of people.
Ev kevro jî şûni bêzing e, bêzing. Dîdinan ser dêv e, gişk
evir çêkirne.
This stone is also the place of a sieve, a sieve. [Like]
teeth on a mouth, all made of stone.
Vro jî cîkî çêkirina ma'nî dewar der têda vexwe, bes gi xera
kirne.
Here is also a place made so cattle can drink in it, but
they have ruined it all.
Mekanî ba mero çêkro wano pak, dûrê çêkro.
The place was good, one made it like that clean, fixed the
surroundings.
Miletê vê gundî ê bota, ê vaxora, heywanek ba, xerîbek ba, ê
vaxora, rind bî, tiştek rind rind e.
The people of this village would come, would drink, if there
was an animal, a stranger, they would drink, it was good, it
is a very good thing.
Gerek milet bixwo o no wa bike, milet bixwo no bavdo, havdra
alîkar ke çêke.
The people themselves should do that, the people themselves
should run [to help], help each other to fix it.
De yalla xêrxwaz hene ê çêkin.
Come on, there are charitable people who [will] fix it.
Miletê me bi xêr û bereke ye, teqsîrê nakin.
Our people are full of goodness and blessings, they don't
fall short.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Çawikî xweş e.
A nice view.
Teb'en vî derê seba saet teqrîben dehane, deh siba ne, em
derketin.
Of course, at this place, the morning time is approximately
ten, ten in the morning, we went out.
Are.
Yes.
Maşallah çi hewş difir da girtine.
Mashallah what a courtyard they have enclosed around.
Benî Adem erê hibo me hylkeka xwo bi vê darê va çêkro.
Son of Adam [Human], yes there was, we made an episode of
ours by this tree.
Mago ben hibo mero hylkek xwo li vir va çêkro.
We said there was a band/tie, one made an episode here.
Di xorê lêxistî.
It [the sun/weather] has struck the soil.
Dorik rind e. Rind e işta cîyê xwo rind e, işta çîçke wano
kevir darn e.
It is a good tree. It is good, its place is good, although
it has some stones [around].
Pak bibe, oo, hewl bike wekî kursîyo çêke xora bironê rinde.
If it becomes clean, oh, try to make it like a chair to sit
on, it's good.
De, wekî îstîrahekî ye wano.
There, it's like a rest stop like that.
Seke xwo.
Look at yourself.
Cama hewş li Efrîn, bîna or.
The courtyard group in Afrin, building walls.
Mago hewşo bikrin, bikrin, bikrin... kesî çê nekir. Nekirin.
We said buy courtyards, buy, buy... no one did. They didn't
buy.
Hewş noko her hewşek çar pênc hezar ketî ser.
Courtyards now, every courtyard has gone up four or five
thousand [price].
Le, ne der rind bîn, der rind bîn, der çê bîn, noko milet wa
hewşo dikre.
Man, if the places were good, if the places were good, if
the places were built, now people are buying those
courtyards.
Hewş buha bîne, ard buha bîne.
Courtyards have become expensive, land has become expensive.
Ke, emkê ki konibin bikrin?
So, how will we be able to buy?
Em ma çoq so gû werin bikrin, meşarî'a va kin, oo, buha
dibê.
We said so much "come buy, do these projects", oh, it
becomes expensive.
Hûru mero çêke ji siba çêtir e, hûru mero bikre ji siba
çêtir e.
Today if one builds it is better than tomorrow, today if one
buys it is better than tomorrow.
Te me'me bin barê rind bî û barê wano arzan bî.
Don't wait for the load to be good and the load to be cheap
like that.
Eh, badê çi.
Eh, after what.
Le?
Right?
Maşallah hewşek xwo xweş e, e çêkirî.
Mashallah it is a nice courtyard, the one built.
Hevalê min nîzîk be, hevalê min nîzîk be, kûçik tê ê wek.
My friend get close, my friend get close, the dog is coming
like that.
Gel, gele, gel, gele.
Come, come, come, come.
Kûçik nexazorin e.
The dogs are not aggressive.
Oo, mêrek baqoxa vê xistine, ardê xwo av dide.
Oh, a man has planted beans [vegetables] here, watering his
land.
Wadiye?
You see?
Are gundikî kortê daye, bes avê xwo heye, gelek bîr li malê
giyo heye bîr.
Yes a village situated in the hollow, but it has its water,
there are many wells at all the houses, wells.
Arê ha vana vî derî jî, me got orta gund e.
Yes, here as well, we said it is the middle of the village.
Dorek li vî derî çêbûye, li vî derî bîrek a avê heye, û
temdîd kirine.
A roundabout was made here, there is a water well here, and
they have extended the pipes.
Ha ev jî wekî mektebekê çêkirine... bixwînin ser... ev çiye
evro?
And this, they built it like a school... read on it... what
is this now?
Navenda... nîra niştimanî.
Center... Nira National.
Çiye?
What?
Navenda nîra niştimanî.
Nira National Center.
Hmm. Xora ciyê alcabê jî çêkirine, yanî qicika... qicikê
gund.
Hmm. They also made a place for games, meaning for kids...
the village kids.
Ha vî li vî derî hewşekê jûr bigire ha.
Here, take a shot of this yard up there.
Hêşînahî heye.
There is greenery.
Lo Erebî me tene, Erebî me min. Ez xwendinê nizanim.
Hey, don't speak Arabic to me, Arabic to me. I don't know
how to read.
Me got qicika bişînin mektebê, hem ew bikin.
We said send the kids to school, let them do that.
Lo lo tu ji min xilas nabî, ti kê tima resmî ware.
Hey, hey, you won't get rid of me, come take a picture.
Dilê min foka tima resm rabikim.
I want to take a picture over there.
Li vî derî hema... ro li vî derî jî hema ji te xilas nabim.
Heke de werim resm bikim.
Here... even here today I won't get rid of you. Come let me
take a picture.
Ha valî me o vî hewşê bigire, vî malana.
Here, take this yard for us, these houses.
Jûr du hewşê kevnar hene ha, gellek far e ha bin.
Up there are two ancient yards, look how wide they are.
Em ê nuke... ganibin em ê hilkişin jûr.
We will now... maybe we will climb up.
O vî malana bigire.
And take these houses.
Cewî gund e, xweş e, sibê xweş e, sibê jî hez dikim sibê û
roava.
The village atmosphere is nice, the morning is nice, I like
the morning and sunset too.
Seke ne sibê denê cew hênik e, hesî çîk o, hesî dîk o, ona.
Look, in the morning the air is cool, sound of birds, sound
of roosters, like that.
Çok xweş çêke.
Make it very nice.
Ehe! Ta eskirî.
Oops! You slipped.
Ehe. Maşalla wo.
Wow. Mashallah.
Xwedê miletê me mehfez bike.
May God protect our people.
Viro jî lawik ne bî mere... lawik bimer o ba maye li vî
helkê da ye kêf kir o.
Here too the boy shouldn't... the boy died... the wind is on
this side, he enjoyed it.
Heta min miş hema ku derkavin teswîrê dibê... bi be rehet
bin.
Whenever I... just appear in the picture, he says... be
comfortable.
Min go na te xora li makînê rûn... lê rûniştî te xora
rûniştî, dibê na ez rehet dibim. Fiqêre.
I said no, you sit in the car... you are sitting, sit down,
he says no I get comfortable. Poor guy.
Wiy vî derê şikeft pirr ne, gundekî kevnar e. Ku şikeftê
kifar e ne.
Wow, there are many caves here, it's an ancient village.
Those are caves of infidels [ancient people].
Miletê vir jî gidi şikeftê dibî wextê.
The people here also go to the caves at times.
Gundê kevnar, bilind e.
An ancient village, it is high.
Walla vî derê zift kirine.
Wow, they have paved this place.
E yoo şoşke ye, çêbûye zift bi cê ye, çêbûye ge ye çêbûye.
Oh no, it's a dirt road, it's okay, asphalt is in places,
it's okay, good it's okay.
Avrêko hecer çêkirine ha. Wile.
They made a stone water gutter here. Wow.
Malek ra jûr e.
A house up there.
Seke vî şarana çîçkê ona fere ne, rind e ne.
Look, these streets are a bit wide like that, they are good.
Gund ne hem darin, çûne... dîwarê xwe danîne ser rêkê.
Not all villages are like this, they're gone... they put
their walls on the road.
Yanî tenê makîneyek... nikanî tê re herê.
Meaning only one car... cannot go through.
Dibên şola bustik mezî dabe.
They say let the job give a span more.
Fere be kîlo rêk fere be. De makîne rehet tê.
Let it be wide, let the whole road be wide. So two cars can
pass easily.
Erê hevalno vî gundî... dora sed... topon sed malî ye.
Yes friends, this village... around a hundred... exactly a
hundred houses.
Haf jî gundê jî tabîe nahîya Efrîn e.
This village also belongs to the Afrin district.
Hember me jî Maratê ye, Maratê li geçê din e.
Opposite us is Marate, Marate is on the other side.
Paş me jî Cûqê, Cûqê li paş me ye.
Behind us is Juqe, Juqe is behind us.
Haw ne hewşê xwo nad ber avdodanê, çîçkê ji avdê dûr ne.
Look, they don't give their yards to irrigation, they are a
bit far from water.
Gundekî xweş e, îşta çîçkê kûrt e.
It's a nice village, still a bit short [undeveloped/small].
Erê me go vî gundî... tabîe medîne Efrîn e, Medîne, E Efrîn.
Yes we said this village... belongs to the city of Afrin,
City, Yes Afrin.
Bajarê Efrîn.
The city of Afrin.
Em dibên nahiye, Efrîn ne nahiye. Medîne ye.
We say district, Afrin is not a district. It is a city.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Hesî çûk û çoksora tê... li vî sibê.
Sound of birds and red-beaked birds comes... in this
morning.
Rind e, saet xweş e. Maşalla.
Good, the time is nice. Mashallah.
Ave ne va hofa gund e.
This is the slope of the village.
Hacî yaba hew dikî bi sehet û wext bi sehet bî.
Haji father, doing well, be healthy and time be healthy.
Siwîk.
Light [Easy].
Li vî derî jî em hatin cem şebaba, li vî derî şebab di
şixilin.
Here we came to the guys, here guys are working.
Ka em jê pirs kin hela şixil çu ye û meîşet çu ye, çu derbas
dibe.
Let's ask them how the work is and how the livelihood is,
how it passes.
Çi korî dikin.
What work they do.
Maşalla maşalla, ser xêrê be, ser xêrê be.
Mashallah, may it be blessed, may it be blessed.
Tebena ev jî celbê çêkirine, çîmetî sipî lêxistine.
They made this tiling too, put white cement on it.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Hello.
Welcome.
Pîroz be, xanî pîroz be.
Congratulations, congrats on the house.
Wala yê ehbabekî me ye.
Well, it belongs to a friend of ours.
Ehbabkî ye?
A friend's?
Xalnêrî. Rifat.
From Xalnêrî. Rifat.
Ticcarî zeytê ye.
An oil merchant.
Xwedê rizqî gundê bişîne. Tu ji vî gundî ye?
May God send sustenance to the village. Are you from this
village?
Na, ez ji Kurzêlê me.
No, I am from Kurzêlê.
Kurzêlê Cumê?
Kurzêlê of Juma?
Li ba Efrîn?
Yes.
Near Afrin?
Eyo.
Yes.
Me canixê me jî Kurzêlê ye.
My in-laws are also from Kurzêlê.
Îdrîs loyê Ebû Mehmûd.
Welcome.
Idris son of Abu Mahmoud.
Ehlen wa sehlen, nas dikim.
Welcome, I know him.
Tu nas dikî?
You know him?
Erê, ehbabê me ye.
Yes, he's our friend.
Bacanixê min e.
My brother-in-law.
Û çu derbas dikî, çu dişixilin, û zirqê dikin bes?
And how do you pass time, how do you work, and do you only
do plastering?
Bes zirqê û telbîsê û blokan.
Only plastering and cladding and blocks.
Korî we, korî we çiye?
Your work, what is your work?
Korî me zirqê esas.
Our work is plastering mainly.
Esasî zirqê.
Mainly plastering.
Ê çuwe te, te çu dîtine korî zirqê te...
So how is it, how do you see the plastering work...
Wala heye, şikê taib e yanî.
Well it exists, it's a bit tiring, you know.
Taib e, çetîn e ne?
Tiring, hard right?
Çuwe meîşet çuwe, yomîye çiqas yomîye amil?
How is the livelihood, how much is the daily wage, daily
wage of a worker?
Yomîye amil deh dolar, dwazdeh pênc dolar, haseb yanî.
Daily wage of worker is 10 dollars, 12, 15 dollars,
depending.
Haseb şixul erê. Yê ber destî zirqêçî bişixile.
Depending on work yes. The one working as an assistant to
the plasterer.
Deh û pênc dolar tê pêncîdî. Pênc sedî tirk.
15 dollars comes to 500. 500 Turkish.
Erê, deh û pênc dolar yomîya amil e, tê pênc sedî tirk.
Yes, 15 dollars is the worker's wage, comes to 500 Turkish.
Rind e, pênc sedî tirk yanî yek pê di eyîşe malekê, bes e,
yekî dike evîlokê.
Good, 500 Turkish means one can live on it for a household,
enough, one manages a family.
Bes garekî hîn be, lehne amil jî gî pirr radibin.
But he must be skilled, because workers all demand a lot.
Na weye? Tiştî paron.
Is it not so? Money stuff.
Çokse bibê meilim nabe kî amil... e ra dibê ye zûr li ser
amil e.
If he becomes a master, a worker can't... yeah he says the
pressure is on the worker.
Garek em maaşê amil rakin bi bîst dolar kin.
We should raise the worker's salary to 20 dollars.
Erê.
Yes.
Bîst dolar be, amil ra, mûntaz e.
If it's 20 dollars, for the worker, it's excellent.
Mûntaz e erê.
Excellent yes.
Xwedê rizqî we bişîne.
May God send you sustenance.
Vî zirqê we, metr bi çiqasî dikişînin?
This plaster of yours, how much do you charge per meter?
Metr bi sê dolara.
Meter for 3 dollars.
Metr? Metr merebe'?
Meter? Square meter?
Metr merebe'.
Square meter.
Metr metre, bi sê dolara.
Meter meter, for 3 dollars.
Kelbîş jî, kelbîş jî bi du dolara şixil im.
Roughcast too, roughcast for 2 dollars I work.
Temam şixilî pak e ne, du dolara.
Okay clean work right, 2 dollars.
Şixilî pak.
Clean work.
Hûn derin kî dera ne?
Where do you go?
Kî dera, kî dera.
Anywhere, anywhere.
Kîj wa xwest hûn derin, telefon wa dikin hûn derin.
Whoever wants you go, they call you go.
Erê telefon li me dikin em derin.
Yes they call us we go.
Kîj wa kî min nahîyê gîyê bigere.
Whoever... from the whole district calls.
Em digerin erê.
We tour yes.
Sere çavan, hewalgê bigere.
You're welcome, tour everywhere.
No no pir mantiqê me da şixil pir biye.
No no, lots of work has happened in our region.
Erê şixil pir bûye hemdûleh.
Yes work has increased thank God.
Labet meşarî ava dikin, na?
Of course they are building projects, right?
Noko şixil... xwo şixil mantiqê Efrînê da pir bûye.
Now work... actual work in Afrin region has increased.
Beh re şixil zêde bûye.
Work has increased a lot.
Şixilî, e bi şixil e, li kî derê be bi şixil e.
Work, yeah with work, wherever it is there is work.
Merî kî feqîr û kof e her e bi şixil e. E sinea' dest da
hebe yê bi şixil e.
A person who is poor... goes to work. If he has a trade in
hand, he works.
E sinea'î dest nebe mala malê bigere istî mal şixil.
If he has no trade, look for house work.
Şixil ji kotiye.
Work is everywhere.
E ew ne şixil e hetanî nîr û xav kir zotir şixil tine.
If that is not work, until he sweats, there is no work
sooner.
Hetanî xav rabe nîrû bê, yekî bi şixil tine, na wye?
Until sweat rises and force comes, one doesn't work, isn't
it so?
Bes merî xîret ê, sibê zû rabe, saet şeş ne heft ne.
But a person of zeal, gets up early morning, 6 or 7 o'clock.
Rast e.
It's true.
Xwedê rizqî gindê bişîne.
May God send village sustenance.
Emîn.
Amen.
Merî şaxil xwedê jê hez dike.
God loves a working person.
Rast e.
True.
Saet a we xweş.
Have a good time.
Xatira te.
Goodbye.
Kûrekî pir rind e, serkeftin be ji we ra.
A very good boy, success to you.
Ere ew jî xaletî min... te got navê te buçîk?
Yes this one is my uncle... you said your name little one?
Ebû Yûsiv.
Abu Yusuf.
Erê.
Yes.
Kurzêlê, binêre ji Kurzêlê.
From Kurzêlê?
Kurzêlê, look from Kurzêlê.
Serçavên me ne.
You are welcome.
Te çi silavê dişînî ji milet ra, kesê te me seyir dikin.
What greetings do you send to the people, your relatives
watching us.
Walla e silavê miletê gî miletê da giroyê...
Well greetings to all the people, to the people in the
group...
Her kes were vegera gundî xwe, bajarê xwe, welatî xwe.
Everyone should come return to their village, their city,
their country.
E çend xwasin miletê me gî vegere welatî xwe.
How much we want all our people to return to their country.
Inşalla, inşalla. Dema zurûf ne sihet bîn inşalla yê ten ten
yê vegerin.
God willing, God willing. When circumstances are not good,
God willing they will come, they will return.
Welat xweş e, mantiqe eman çêbûye, tişt tine, noko alem gî
tê malê xwe, şixulê xwe, meselen şixul pir bûye.
Country is nice, region has become safe, nothing bad, now
everyone comes to their home, their work, for example work
has increased.
Emîn te nebî.
If there was no safety.
Emîn te nebî hereket tune bû.
If there was no safety, there would be no movement.
Ere rast e.
Yes true.
Heta çawere xwarin verşotî bî, noko derxistî meydanê têt
şixulandin.
Even the guarded food was hidden, now brought out to the
square is being worked.
Ere giewaye. No ew ro eman tene be, tinê wîr parê xwar nake.
Yes that's how it is. No that day if there is no safety, no
one eats money there.
Tine kes nikare bişixilîne.
No one can employ.
Bes eman çêbî, elhemdila şixul pirr biye, milet vedigere ji
xurbê, na wye?
But safety happened, thank God work increased, people return
from exile, right?
Lê.
Yes.
Inşalla, inşalla. Mantiqê me pirr xweş e.
God willing. Our region is very nice.
Wala... Andorê ji me xwestine.
Well... they asked for Andorê from us.
Ne? Andorê vîdeo ji me xwestine.
Right? They asked for a video of Andorê from us.
Nefş... ti ji Kurzêlê?
Same... you are from Kurzêlê?
Kurzêlê, bes Andorê rûniştî.
Kurzêlê, but residing in Andorê.
Andorê. Hmm. Maşalla.
Andorê. Hmm. Mashallah.
Lo xaletî... vî gundî da ez behs dikim şikeft têde pirr ne.
Hey uncle... in this village I mention there are many caves
in it.
Bes bêle, yanî gundekî kevnar e?
But tell me, is it an ancient village?
Aqa emrê vî gundî yaqe çarsed, pêncsed sal e.
Brother, the age of this village is about four hundred, five
hundred years.
Gundê me Kirmanc û Gowan e?
Is our village [made up of] Kurds and Gowan [tribe/locals]?
Belê.
Yes.
Avaye, pêncsed sal, şeşsed sal em zanin, bes...
It is built, five hundred years, six hundred years that we
know of, but...
Nûxîn ji me jî...
The new generation among us also...
Hene, hene teyîd...
They are there, there is confirmation...
Ee, behsa hezar sala dikin.
Eh, they are talking about a thousand years.
Erê welle.
Yes, really.
Ee, dereca rolikê şimikê nefesa mi qut bî.
Oh, the steepness of this slope cut my breath short.
Ha mala Rifetê Xelnêrê?
Is this Rifat Xelnêrê's house?
Rifetê Xelnêrê ha va ne. Maşallah hewşek gundî pir kîbar e.
Rifat Xelnêrê is right here. Mashallah, it is a very elegant
village courtyard.
Mewqiyê xwe şêrîn da ye.
It is in a sweet [nice] location.
Hav zifta kê çêkir ji we ra?
Who made this asphalt for you?
Hav zifta, welle li ser hesabê xwe çêkirin.
This asphalt, well, they made it at their own expense.
Li ser hesabê xwe çêkirin?
They made it at their own expense?
Miletê gund... Belê, miletê gund...
The people of the village... Yes, the people of the
village...
Miletê gund, na?
The people of the village, no?
Gund tev da iştîrak kirin, rêka gund çêkir û zift kirin.
The whole village participated, they fixed the village road
and paved it.
No welle kîbar e, gundiyo. Gundekî pêşketî ye.
No really, it is elegant, villager. It is a developed
village.
Ee, pir gunda dîtin, şar'a, kerpîçê xwe danîne ser rêkê. Rêk
wilo teng...
Uh, I have seen many villages, the streets, they put their
bricks right on the road. The road is so narrow...
Na ma şixulê wan çi ye?
No, what kind of work is that of theirs?
Milet hevdu xeniqî, ee?
The people are suffocating each other, eh?
Tê rehet avê vedixwin.
You can drink water comfortably [because neighbors are so
close].
Rehet çayê ba apê Elî vedixwin.
They drink tea comfortably at Uncle Ali's place.
Muxtarê gund girêdayî... cîran û...
The village Mukhtar is connected... neighbors and...
Ee hevalo, darê masebûkrê xwe cem teh, wa bike cem tek, wele
makîna xwe înare jor.
Hey friend, gather your [unknown plant/wood], do it like
this, really bring your machine up.
De!
Indeed!
Ee we, noka me sekinandî, makîna gund kelager da re, bes
gundê hene, na wene.
Uh yeah, now we stopped, the vehicle circled the village,
but the village exists, or it doesn't.
Na, rast e.
No, that's true.
Saeta be, miletê gundê Xelnêrê xweş, ewdire hore kirine.
Cheers to you, the people of Xelnêrê village are nice, they
have cleaned up nicely here.
Muşareke kirine, ew çêkirine. Rêkek xwe ziftê çêkirine.
They participated together, they made this. They made an
asphalt road for themselves.
Ji gund ra teb'an, ji xwe ra çêkirine. Xweş.
For the village obviously, they made it for themselves.
Nice.
Welle, ez zanim, ew şikatê vê gundî pirr in he?
Well, I know, there are many caves in this village, huh?
Şikat pir, ber gund...
Many caves, before the village...
Ew kevnar e, kevnar e.
It is ancient, ancient.
Erê, her qelbi gundî da şikat hene... heqa... tina kûk,
tina, sed şikat vê gundî da heye.
Yes, in every heart of the village there are caves...
really... up to the peak, up to... there are a hundred caves
in this village.
Sed?
A hundred?
Sed şikat heye.
There are a hundred caves.
Maşallah, wadiye? Dibê sed şikat vê gundî da heye.
Mashallah, is it true? He says there are a hundred caves in
this village.
Gundekî pir qedîm e.
It is a very old village.
Na?
Really?
Sed şikat...
Yes.
A hundred caves...
Şikat xwande, adeta hewşê ye.
The cave is read [counted], it's like a custom of the
courtyard.
Yanî her malekê, şikatek xwe heye.
Ah!
Meaning every house has a cave of its own.
Her malekê şikatek xwe heye?
Every house has its own cave?
Ê, berê... tiştek zanim, digotin milet, miletê kevnar tim
diçûn li... li kuderê rûdiniştin?
So, before... I know something, they used to say the people,
the ancient people always went to... where did they settle?
Ava kuderê habû diçûn xwe... nêzîk dikirin. Kaniyê... kaniyê
vê gundî heye?
Wherever water was, they went... they got close to it. The
spring... does this village have a spring?
Habû berê, pir zeman da habû.
There was one before, a long time ago there was.
Pir zeman da habû. Em nehiştine, bes habû, dibên kaniyê vê
gundî da habû. Wekî şikeft hebûn, kanî jî tê da heye.
Really?
Pir zeman da habû. Em nehiştine, bes habû, dibên kaniyê vê
gundî da habû. Wekî şikeft hebûn, kanî jî tê da heye.
A long time ago there was. We didn't catch it [live to see
it], but there was, they say there was a spring in this
village. Since there were caves, there is also a spring in
it.
Erê, û gelek jî, leynî gund, kurte de gelek heye, ekîd
wextîna av tê da diçû.
Yes, and a ravine too, alongside the village, in the
depression there is a ravine, surely at times water flowed
through it.
Erê, her gund jêkî... wekî ka...
Yes, every village from a... like where...
Maratê...
[Place name/Marate]...
Kaniya xwe habû, şikatê xwe pir in. Xêra... yanî gund qedîm
e, yanî alem dihat hewş tunebûn berê, şikata da rûdiniştin.
It had its spring, its caves are many. Goodness... meaning
the village is old, meaning people came and there were no
courtyards before, they lived in the caves.
Şikat çêdikirin, der dikirin, tê da rûdiniştin.
They made caves, excavated them, and lived in them.
Rûniştina şikatê hênik e.
Living in a cave is cool.
Noka ên hewa, beradaye.
True.
Now the air conditioners, it's useless [compared to caves].
Hewra hênikî yê dide.
It gives a cool breeze.
De seeta te xweş.
Cheers to you.
Tu ser çava hatî, spas dikim.
You are welcome [upon eyes you came], thank you.
Welle mentîqe xweş e. Ha binê?
Really the area is nice. Look here?
Mentîqa 366 gund in, ef şox e.
The region has 366 villages, this is the charm.
No, xusûsen adimê cewê sibê, onot robî, hefsî çûko, hefsî
dîko...
No, especially a person in the morning weather, the smell of
the sun, the sound of the birds, the sound of the rooster...
Her kes darê karê xwe. Pir cewekî xweş e.
Everyone is going to their work. It's a very nice
atmosphere.
Noka sibê rabî pyalek qehwekî vexwî, molî dinê dike.
Now if you wake up in the morning and drink a cup of coffee,
it's worth the wealth of the world.
Wana seeta gundê xweş, welle cihê xwe pir kîbar e, welle
mewqiyê xwe pir rind e.
Theirs is a nice village time, really their place is very
elegant, really their location is very good.
Xwedê rizqê gundî bişîne, xwedê mehfeze ke.
May God send sustenance to the villagers, may God protect
them.
Îşalla gişt kûva bin, hewşê hawa çêkin, hewşê pak û kîbar.
God willing they will all appear [prosper], build courtyards
like this, clean and elegant courtyards.
Şimik çêdime, perê xwe çêkin, û vîn jî ya xwe ona çêkin, na
we?
I'm making slippers [idiom?], let them make their money, and
build their vision like this too, isn't it?
Rast e.
It is true.
Şikatek li vir da ye. Şikatê xwe jî gelek kûr in, kûr. Binê,
hember me, vro, derana, gişt şî ye.
There is a cave right here. Its caves are also very deep,
deep. Look, opposite us, over there, the slopes, it's all
shaded.
Têbê derana jî sarnîc hene.
You'd say there are cisterns on the slopes too.
Oho, di geliyek da hene.
Oho, they are in a valley.
Bile, bile wextîna, av li vir da dikişî.
Indeed, indeed at one time, water flowed here.
Golê vê gundî tinen in, çi ye?
There are no calves/flocks in this village, what is it?
Fa, milet gişt çûyî karê xwe, gişt nava milkê xwe, ye gişt
çûne şixulê xwe.
So, the people have all gone to their work, all into their
property, all have gone to their jobs.
Şebab jî li vir da şixulin. Na ji vir, na?
The young guys are working here too. Or not from here, no?
Ji qerzêlê ne.
They are from Qerzel [neighboring village].
Îna kesek hebe, ona me ra bigere nava gund, e pir xweş bû.
If there was someone, to walk around inside the village with
us like this, it would be very nice.
Ser dîroka şikata, daro, maro ra hewal dano.
To give information about the history of the caves, trees,
and such.
Hêdî bajo pîse.
Drive slowly, it's bad [the road/bump].
Recal e.
It's a man/pedestrian.
Xeletî me, dibê sed şikat heye. Rast e welle.
By my mistake [expression of surprise], he says there are a
hundred caves. It's true really.
El kuderê dinêrim, şikeft tê da ne.
Wherever I look, there are caves in it.
Bavê min, çi ye?
My father, what is it?
Çelek me ra ona habo.
A jackal [or partridge] was there like that for us.
Çelek me ona habo, ruyê me kê şîr be mala kê da.
A jackal was there for us like that, may our face be
white/milk in whose house.
Milo te'l me, boxar ona.
My shoulder is bitter [sore], [unintelligible] like that.
Or lab nêçîrvano.
[Unintelligible - likely referring to hunters].
Ewe ew darda xûçkê çatin e, dige xizmet eke, çêl midelel me.
Yes, those trees are hard/tough sisters, it needs service,
[unintelligible].
Ev jî camî ye. Bi şik, ne?
This is also a mosque. I suspect, no?
Hee!
Tiştek pir ecêb e.
It's something very strange.
Kaskê vê gundî xwe lê niştî, li heyfê niştin e, em jî tim e
lê rûniştin heyf ko.
Someone from this village settled here, they settled in
pity/regret [perhaps referring to a difficult spot], and we
are always sitting in it, what a pity.
Welle em çûn jûr, wî hewşo hindî... welle ceb hewşo kîbar
çêkirine.
Really we went up, that courtyard is so... really they made
a very elegant courtyard.
Bes milet tinen e, milet. Xa miletê vê gundî da biyo xew
kiriye, çûye saet...
But there are no people, people. Either the people in this
village have gone to sleep, gone for hours...
Al bajarê kûk hez nakim. Na...
I don't like the city at all. No...
Bêjer, serokê me senedekî anorin. Nefesa min o tê da ye.
Driver/Speaker, our leader brought a document. My breath is
in it.
Înî xelk jî dare ser şara'ê reîsî, hewşo dikir, dibê em li
şara'ê reîsî bî.
Look at the people on the main street, making a courtyard,
saying let us be on the main street.
Tîtîta mokîna, cir cira mokîna...
The honking of cars, the screeching of cars...
Sere te diçî, diêşî.
Your head goes, it hurts.
Wane no seh xidra, bîkova digerin, ban dikin, aqil serî mero
dare.
Those looking at green, walking in nature, calling out, it
takes the mind from a person's head [in a good way].
Hêdî hêdî bajo.
Drive slowly, slowly.
Min taqî nekir.
I didn't verify/follow it.
Em li vir da vegerin.
Let's turn back here.
Ev der sînorê gund e.
This place is the border of the village.
Ee... merheba, merheba hatina we ji gundê Xelnêrê ra.
Uh... hello, hello and welcome to the village of Xelnêrê.
Ez navê min Şîlan Hesen, û ez qîza Ebû Rênas im.
My name is Shilan Hesen, and I am Abu Renas's daughter.
Ee...
Uh...
Silavê min ji wara heye, vir heta... dewletî derve.
My greetings are for them, from here until... foreign
countries.
Are. Tu silava li apê xwe nakî?
Yes. Won't you say hi to your uncle?
Apê xora, silava li apê xora noşînî?
To your uncle, won't you send greetings to your uncle?
Baye apû, bay baba.
Bye uncle, bye daddy.
Are, evana li vir jî, em malê... awe ne, Ebû Rênas.
Yes, these here too, we are at the house of... that one, Abu
Renas.
Ma qehwek gund ve xwar, xwedê jê razî be, xwedê emrê gi
dirêj bide, silavê me ji qîçka gund ra hene, li derve.
We drank a village coffee, may God be pleased with him, may
God give him a long life, our greetings are to the little
girl of the village, outside [abroad].
Ji vir da em silav dikin, heta Ewropa.
From here we send greetings, all the way to Europe.
Çavê we maç dikim.
I kiss your eyes.
Û bimara bin jî, noka lextana xweş kîbar, emê dakevin malê
qoş û ji jêr jî wara teswîr kin.
And stay with us too, now nice elegant moments, we will go
down to the beautiful house and film for them from below
too.
De baybay ke, baberê me, eynî teswîr ke.
Come on, say bye-bye, facing us, film the same way.
Bay!
Bye!
Vêra ewreqê gundê zû çêke, ma neyê zû bicemtekîne.
There you go!
Prepare the village papers quickly for this one, so she
doesn't get snatched up quickly.
Raşik biye li gunda, raşik biye.
Isn't that right?
She has become tanned in the village, tanned.
Mla re çişke bêjer, mla no sipî bibî.
Just a little bit speaker [driver/talker], let her not
become white.
Xwedê mehfeze ke. Tu dixwînî?
May God protect her. Do you study?
Erê.
Yes.
Ti çendê?
Which grade are you in?
Ez sisê ye.
I am in third.
Sisê ye? Tu şîr kaslan î le şatire?
Third? Are you a lazy lion or smart/active?
Şatire.
Smart/Active.
Ekîd.
For sure?
For sure.
Ê, xwedê te bêle, xwedê te mehfeze ke.
Eh, may God leave you [spare you], may God protect you.
Îşalla tu gûla gûla arê, canbapî xo gînê.
God willing you are a rose of roses, you will reach your
side/goal.
Tu gîj canbapî xo, cudu bîr meke.
When you reach your side/goal, don't forget Cudi [maybe a
name/place].
Tim deqa deqa vêre telefonê danke. Tamam?
Always call here minute by minute on the phone. Okay?
De baybay ke, baberê baybay ke.
Come on say bye-bye, say bye-bye to the front.
Bay baba.
Bye daddy.
Bay.
Bye.
E. Navê apî te çiye?
Uh. What is your uncle's name?
Amu Henan.
Uncle Henan.
Kaka Henan silavê me jêra hene.
Brother Henan, our greetings are to him.
Bay bay.
Bye bye.
Ko amu bûs ke ko, ko. Ko bûs ke.
Come kiss uncle come on, come on. Come kiss.
Ko mla amu bûs ke ko. Ko bûs ke.
Come on let's kiss uncle come on. Come kiss.
O xwedê baybay ke baberê de.
Oh God, say bye-bye to the front, come on.
Ono ono de.
Like that, like that, come on.
De baberê baybay ke ono ono. De.
Come on say bye-bye to the front like that like that. Come
on.
De Cudû ra bayke, Cudû ra. De.
Come on say bye to Cudu, to Cudu. Come on.
Tu gûla gûla ye.
You are a rose of roses.
Sey dike, fey dike. Maşallah, xwedê bêle.
Looking, paying attention. Mashallah, may God spare
[him/her].
Îşalla... mezin bibî, tiştekî bibî, îşalla.
God willing... grow up, become something, God willing.
Hav lewha jî... yekî lê ser ke, me'ne gundî zanibin.
This sign too... fix one on it, so the meaning of the
village is known.
Me'ne gundî zanibin.
So the meaning of the village is known.
Mero te'lîqa duyozmîş kin.
Let people write comments [unintelligible].
Henan, Kaka Hemûdî avê hewş a waye?
Henan, Brother Hamoudi, is this your courtyard?
Birakî me Henan, avê hewş a waye?
Our brother Henan, is this your courtyard?
Kole xoro xedra ne xo çandî, o...
He planted his own green plants/flowers all by himself,
oh...
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Were hewşê gundî gi darxînin.
Come, let's bring out [show] all the village courtyards.
Mamoste Henan!
Teacher Henan!
E, Mamoste Henan, ser serî me.
Uh, Teacher Henan, upon our head [welcome].
Çi bokî yenik te, hewşê wa çi bokî yenik te, ox!
What a nice smell comes, what a nice smell comes from your
courtyard, oh!
Ya selam.
Oh peace [wow].
Hêê!
Hee!
Sake balkonê xo fereh e, pir rind e.
Look, his balcony is spacious, very good.
Yak baqil e, xwedê jêra bêle. Wele.
He is a smart one, may God spare him. Really.
Bay.
Bye.
Saet xweş xal, xwedê şta razî be. Saet xweş.
Good times uncle, may God be pleased with you. Good times.
Me go maşalla av hebê wadiyê xizmet ke, hena rind gristîbin
maşalla.
I said, mashallah, if there is water and the valley is
served well, look how well they have grown, mashallah.
Heye? Rind bîne. Maşalla. Tebe'en hîn ne wext e, ê bibê, ê
dest pê bibê ê sor bibin.
Is there any? Show it well. Mashallah. Of course, it is not
the time yet, it will happen, it will start to turn red.
Xweş e xalo? Şêrîn e ne? Hena rind e. Of!
Is it good, uncle? It is sweet, isn't it? Look, it is good.
Oof!
Ev wa çi çandî ye? Cercîr e? Eva cercîr e. Ew jî ne'neh ne.
What have you planted here? Is it arugula? This is arugula.
And those are mint.
Xalo ev çi wa çandî? Tirp in ev no? Ew tirp in. Ew jî silk
e, sapanax e? Ew jî bacanê reş in.
Uncle, what are these you planted? Are these radishes? Those
are radishes. And that is chard, spinach? And those are
eggplants.
Lo av hebê, çi biçîne ê derkevê. Zêdetir hişk bî.
If there is water, whatever you plant will come out. It was
mostly dry.
Xalo ev portqol e? Portqol e. Ah bes sêr ay? Maşalla wele
heye. Binêr.
Uncle, is this an orange tree? It is an orange. Oh, but look
at that? Mashallah, by God, there is fruit. Look.
Me he xalo xatir jê xwest û. Çîçkê av bî, nikanî... xirabî
nikanî mer derket o, mişîklet nîne.
We said goodbye to the uncle. Since there was a bit of
water, you can't... it's not bad, one can't get out, no
problem.
Em jî li vê derê, ê mala qewşon e? Ê mala Mihemed wan o.
Brahîm e? Çan mal li wan e li vê derê. Tebe'en berî gund e.
And here we are, at the Qewsho family's home? Muhammad and
his family's home. Is it Ibrahim? There are several homes of
theirs here. Of course, it is before the village.
Emê bê hewşê na, rind derxîne.
We will come to the courtyard, no, film it well.
Me xalo pirs kir, dibê vê derê av pir e. 100 metrî, 125
metro av derdikeve. Kîbar e. Avê xwe rind e. Zûr bibê.
We asked the uncle, he says there is plenty of water here.
At 100 meters, 125 meters, water comes out. It is great. Its
water is good. Turn (the camera) around.
Wo wo wo yekî rol derî û di jur girtî ye. Em jî bigir, we
dikinê jur. Em dikinê jur nîzik bikê.
Whoa, whoa, whoa, someone has closed the remote door inside.
Capture us too, we are going inside. We are going inside,
zoom in.
Eyê! Wele ceurik jî hene.
Oh! By God, there are puppies too.
Vê hewşê jî hecer çêkirina o. Bi hecer çêkirine vê hewşê.
Ok, ekî de meyrê xêrê. Vê hewşê...
They have made this courtyard with stone. They built this
courtyard with stone. Okay, someone is coming to welcome us.
This courtyard...
E baxoxan dişixulin, xelk zeytûnan av didê.
The gardeners are working, people are watering the olives.
Nîzik bikê.
Zoom in.
Maşalla, maşalla heye, eva hejîr nîne çiye? Me go eva hejîr
nîne?
Mashallah, mashallah there is, isn't this a fig tree, what
is it? I said isn't this a fig?
Êe stêrk têdane. Gi sor bûne lê? Bes sor bîn zanibe bixwe.
Yes, there are starling birds in it. Have they all turned
red? Once they are red, know that they are edible.
Wele maşalla tijî bî ye, geleka dowaşin dowaşin. E hebes e
tebe'en.
By God, mashallah it is full, many are hanging down, hanging
down. It is a dense bunch, of course.
Bixwe. Maşalla. Le nav bîstanê, lekê derê ne.
Eat. Mashallah. Inside the orchard, look where we are.
Birjî mekteb e. Mekteba vê gundî ye.
Up there is a school. It is the school of this village.
Tino? Le hê?
Tino? Over there?
Çi hewş nê!
What a courtyard!
Wele maşalla zeytûnê reş bîne. Ewna wextê wane nise...
By God, mashallah the olives have turned black. It is their
season now...
Wana sêrek reş bûye. Hêj sêrek. Wana qolu pir reş bîne
cemaet, xêr e?
Some of them have turned black. Just a few. Uncle, they have
become very black, folks, is it good?
Ê temam sêrek kir. Negr, ne sale xwe ye.
Yes, okay, it produced a few. Don't record, it's not its
year (off-year for olives).
Xalo merheba iştêre.
Uncle, hello to you.
Ehlen w sehlan.
Welcome.
Xalo te nas dikin ebû çîk?
Uncle, how do we address you, Abu what?
Ebû Yûsif.
Abu Yusuf.
Ebû Yûsif? Nav bixêr?
Abu Yusuf? Your name, with blessings?
Mihemed, Mihemed Qewşo.
Muhammad, Muhammad Qewsho.
Mihemed Mihemed Qewşo.
Muhammad Muhammad Qewsho.
Maşalla xalo wele cemaet tebîeta gundî ya pir xweş e.
Mashallah uncle, by God folks, the nature of the village is
very nice.
Xweş e rê.
It is nice indeed.
Bîrê avê jî cemaet hene, bîr pir ne.
There are also water wells folks, there are many wells.
Bîr pir kûl o ne.
There are many wells everywhere.
Salê du hezar deha min vê şûnê mektebê da hukmetê.
In the year two thousand and ten, I gave this land for the
school to the government.
Te teberu' kir?
You donated it?
Erê.
Yes.
Wele sehetxweş.
By God, well done (bless your health).
Eyna ew şûnê mektebê o te bî, te dayê?
That implies that the school site was yours, and you gave
it?
Erê erê.
Yes, yes.
Ev milkê ewa ye giştik ewa ye?
Is this property yours, is it all yours?
E min e, e min e.
It is mine, it is mine.
Bereket çiqas o ew?
How much is the blessing (size/trees)?
Wele sê sed dar e, me dayî qîsko û lawko.
By God, there are three hundred trees, I gave them to
relatives and sons.
Wele!
By God!
Me tiştek xorê nehêştî.
I didn't keep anything for myself.
Xwedê emirê te dirêj ket te bî.
May God give you a long life to see it.
Beskê mi jî ne ji bo sinfê helhelketi û rezîl serseme. Xwedê
star ke. Xwedê sitara xwe li giya ke.
But I am not of the class of the frivolous and disgraceful
people. God forbid. May God protect everyone.
Silavê me qîçka xalo ra hene, li her derekê. Li Ewropa hene
qîçkê te?
Our greetings to the uncle's daughter, wherever she is. Are
your daughters in Europe?
Beskê min el Ewropa ne hene.
Only my people are not in Europe.
Bir ne?
Are they gone?
Giştik bir ne.
Everyone is gone.
Silavê me ji gindiyo ra hene. Te qîmetê kolî xwe jî zanibin
maşalla o... hesibî gî yê kirîye qîsko, lawko.
Our greetings to the villagers. You knew the value of your
pile (wealth/land) mashallah... you calculated it all as
belonging to relatives and sons.
Hê qizix çine lawk çine.
Oh, what is a daughter, what is a son (meaning they are
equal).
Lê xalo... neha milet, milk nade meselen qîçko. Heta nebe
ber mirinê. Ne mero zîbelok e rinde.
But uncle... nowadays people don't give property to, for
example, daughters. Until they are near death. It is better
not to be a miser.
Qîçik êkê çiwext bibe milkşab bibe? Golbû?
When will a daughter become a property owner? (When she is
old/hunchbacked?)
Milkûrem îş nabe. Gelek, emirê me...
Inheritance doesn't work (that way). Many, our age...
No, spas, saetxweş.
No, thanks, bless you (declining something offered).
Gelek emirê mero gîşt pêncî, çelî, mero milk le hevak e?
Many people reach fifty, forty, should one leave property
for that time?
Me'nî pê şa bibin ne?
Meaning, let them enjoy it, right?
Ez hefteyek'm noko.
I have been [doing this] for a week now.
Maşalla xalo, li te bî, li no ke.
Mashallah uncle, may it be yours, don't do that (don't work
too hard).
E eşqara tu şixulim nav zeytûna, li wir, li wir, ez hereketê
xwe dikim.
Ah, openly I work among the olives, here and there, I keep
my movement up.
Lê hereket jî dewrana dilî zine.
Indeed, movement keeps the blood circulation going.
Erê yek 'ospiskî' jî me xwar.
Yes, I even took an 'Aspis' (Aspirin/medication).
Wele?
Really?
Herê temam emrê min im.
Yes, okay, it's my age.
Wox!
Whoa!
Xalo jî xalo sahib kêf e o. Lê merî sahib'il kêf, ew e,
cêmore jî o xalo.
The uncle is also a man of pleasure (good mood). But a man
of pleasure is that, he is generous too, uncle.
Wele camêra.
By God, generosity.
Ne?
No?
Bixodê tim pîs e.
By God, [being miserly] is always bad.
Tu ne cêmor ba te milk dida qîçko?
If you weren't generous, would you give property to
daughters?
Tu şerm e, çar pênc mokîna hewarê daskirin. Hêwar, ahbab,
miletî.
It is shameful, four or five machines (cars) stopped for
help. Neighbors, friends, the people.
Maşalla xwedê emirê te dirêj bide te.
Mashallah, may God give you a long life.
Dû du mokîna sekinî bûn.
Two, two cars had stopped.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Du niştin, se'et deh dudu nebî cîranî me telefon kir wara
min bibe.
Two sat down, it wasn't ten or twelve o'clock, our neighbor
called, come take me.
Wele brawu! Xalo ev cem... ev zinin wextê xwe derbas dikin.
By God, bravo! Uncle, this group... these guys know how to
spend their time.
Wextê derbas kim belê.
I spend the time, yes.
Maşalla xalo te çi teqawid ra çandî çiye?
Mashallah uncle, what have you planted for retirement?
Ji malê ro, qîçik tîn diçine, e dilok min êşînin. Xwedê
ştara bî.
From the house, the daughters come and go, and my little
heart hurts. May God protect.
Te xora çandî, pîre wextê wa ta.
You planted for yourself, old age is your time.
Xalo no ez hes dikim te çîçak çandine, te hûn tişt çîçako jî
hez dikê?
Uncle, look, I feel you planted flowers, do you also like
things like flowers?
Um Kelsûm dibê: "Idḥak lil dunya, tiḍḥaklak". Eva kelamê Um
Kelsûm e.
Umm Kulthum says: "Smile to the world, and it smiles back at
you". This is the word of Umm Kulthum.
Wux qurbanê şûre bim. Eger xalo ne...
Oh, I sacrifice myself for that advice. If uncle...
Ya ni dinê te xweş kir xweş e, te pîs kir pîs e.
Either you made the world good and it's good, or you made it
bad and it's bad.
Pîs e, nawaye?
It's bad, isn't it?
Ê xêr û şer, em ê xêrê bikin, emkê şer û pîs kir.
Eh, good and evil, let us do good, why should we do evil and
bad things.
Xwedê yuno... kêfê bi te bide, xwedê emirê te dirêj bide, tu
tim wina bi kêf bê, û tu tim wina hebe.
God like that... may He give you joy, may God give you a
long life, may you always be joyful like this, and may you
always exist like this.
Xwedê şta razî be babo, xwedê qis'kê wa giya bê.
May God be pleased with you father, may God be with all your
children.
Xalo tu çi silavê dişînî ji miletro?
Uncle, what greetings do you send to the people?
Silavê mi ji miletî Kurd gîro heye, û ji miletî aleme gîro
heye bi xêr û selamet e. Wux! Selametî ya dixwazim. Wux!
I have greetings for all the Kurdish people, and for all the
people of the world, with goodness and safety. Wow! I wish
for safety. Wow!
Wekî din em kê bin, em çi derd... Selametî ma fehm kir, fehm
kir, ma fehm nekir...
Otherwise, who are we, what pain... We understood safety,
understood, if we didn't understand...
Zêdetir em hinda bîn.
Mostly we will be lost.
Emî hinda bûn. Em jî û xêrî me jî.
We were lost. Us and our charity too.
Erê.
Yes.
Ser serî min ser çava.
You are welcome (on my head and on my eyes).
Serî ta sax bê, xwedê şta razî bê. Xalo jî maşalla tebîetek
xweş çêkirye vê derê, çîçako, bîstan çandî.
May your head be healthy, may God be pleased with you. The
uncle also, mashallah, has created a nice nature here,
flowers, planted an orchard.
Erê. Xalo wele cemaet zeytûn pir reş bîne, ka hevalê mewer
lê bigre. Wer ba wer. Oh. Tebe'en sal a xo ne... mane?
Yes. Uncle, by God folks, the olives have become very black,
come my friend, film this. Come here come. Oh. Of course, it
is not their year... right?
Ne sala xo ye na, vê dan me ham av didê şuxulîne. Maşalla. E
were hevalî me fonş bigre were.
It is not their year no, this time we are watering and
working on them. Mashallah. Come my friend, take a wide
shot, come.
Ka lê bigre la? Wele xalo têbê zêyt lê gerî ye?
Film this here? By God uncle, look, oil has formed in it?
Têtê zêtê çûz... eweh wena biko...
Look at the oil... like that, do it like that...
Em tên nik kî, bo heta em bixwin.
Who are we coming to, so that we can eat.
Nan pêş te ne, tu çawa dixwî bixwe.
The bread is in front of you, eat however you like.
Xalo Cemal o, sahibê kêfê xalo.
It is Uncle Jamal, a man of pleasure, uncle.
Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike.
May God lengthen your life.
Spas dikim, sax bî.
Thank you, be healthy.
Were xalo, were.
Come uncle, come.
Eyn e ka?
Where is it?
Vele?
Really?
Ohx.
Ooh.
Xalo bîra te çend metro kûr e?
Uncle, how many meters deep is your well?
Sed û pêncî heşt metro.
One hundred and fifty-eight meters.
Sed û pêncî heşt metro?
One hundred and fifty-eight meters?
Heştê metro ava, heftê metro qulabî, zelzalê da heqî mûbela
xera kirin.
Eighty meters is water, seventy meters is casing, the
earthquake truly damaged it badly.
Eyn e ka bismillah.
Here it is, in the name of God.
Eger meriv damîş bû, çetinî û êşeka...
If a person gets accustomed to difficulties and pain...
Zû... te qezenc mîş kî.
Quickly... you gain from it.
Te damîş êşeka nebû, zor zehmetiyek nebû, te kî giyê
biderdî.
If you didn't get accustomed to pain, didn't have great
hardship, you would burst at a straw.
Lê te kî derdê?
But you will burst?
Te kî biderdî bira viharî.
You will burst, brother...
Yanî dogê em divir da man, em zor zehmetî pir dî.
Meaning the time we stayed here, we experienced a lot of
great hardships.
Lê?
Really?
Yanî em hatin, dihatin vir bi tirs.
Meaning we came, we used to come here with fear.
Seet çêl meriyê bata...
At forty hours a person would...
Roj roja çêtir dibê.
Day by day it gets better.
Çêtir dibê.
It gets better.
We de herêm da ne?
In that situation, right?
Yanî... hekê bêjim çi, miletê kî...
Meaning... if I say what, a nation that...
Xalo bîra te av çend înç niha?
Uncle, how many inches is your water [output] now?
Înç nîvî bike teqrîben.
Make it an inch and a half approximately.
Ava înç nîvî bike. Etabî lêxistî hana ye ava te?
Water, make it an inch and a half. The pump hitting it is
like this, your water?
Maşallah hana jî hebe...
Mashallah, if it is like this too...
Ê hana jî hebe nîmet e, hana bîst û çar saeta hebe nîmet e
na we xalo?
Yes, if it is like this it's a blessing, if it is like this
for twenty-four hours it's a blessing, isn't it uncle?
Ê saxlem.
Yes, absolutely.
Heştad heta pênc nîva, ez ser taqa şemsiyê dixebitînim.
Eighty to five something, I run it on solar power.
Heştad heta pênc nîva te ser taqa şemsiyê dişixulînî?
Eighty to five something you run on solar power?
Yanî tekalîfê xwo tinî, mazot, der...
Meaning you have no expenses, diesel, money...
Na, na, na. Heta...
No, no, no. Until...
Bê ceefa ye.
It's without trouble.
Heta didim meriyan, didim xwa, cîranê xwa, gî pê av didim
zeytûna.
I even give to people, give to myself, my neighbors, I water
the olives with it all.
Welle. Xwedê jê razî be, seheta te xweş.
Really. May God be pleased with you, health to you.
Yanî feyd dikin werin bixwazin, ez dibêm werin avê bibin,
min xelas kiriye.
Meaning if they benefit let them come and ask, I say come
take water, I have finished.
Welle.
Really.
Xwedê ye, rizqê ruxa bibin, hekê paşê disa av da.
It is God, let them take the sustenance of souls, if later
it gives water again.
Xwedê jê razî be, rind e, rind e.
May God be pleased with you, good, good.
Veku jê naxwim, mixara ker nistexel.
Like I don't eat from it, ... [indistinct Arabic phrase].
Ee, maşallah cemaata milûxiyê werin ha. Xalo milûxiyê çawa
dîtî? Xalo tu naxwî milûxiyê?
Ee, Mashallah the Molokhia group come here. Uncle how do you
see the Molokhia? Uncle you don't eat Molokhia?
Ez kok jê hez nakim, naxoş ti be.
I don't like it at all, it becomes unpleasant.
No?
Bes ez diçînim ji qicika ra, ba...
But I plant it for the little ones, father...
Jê hez dikin?
They like it?
E pir jê hez dikin. Li min nayê, li me'dê min nayê.
Yes they like it a lot. It doesn't suit me, it doesn't suit
my stomach.
Ewa?
Is that so?
Ez li Misrê jî, me'dê min ji milûxiyê levket.
Even in Egypt, my stomach got upset from Molokhia.
Welle?
Really?
Li Misrê bûm. Çûn milûxiyê danîn ser tawlê, min jî got çiye
ev? Got da milûxiyê ammî.
I was in Egypt. They went and put Molokhia on the table, I
asked what is this? He said this is Molokhia uncle.
We kî hana metat jê hevedikşî. We kî henê, tûnî xwa, ew jê
hevedikşî.
Like this rubber it stretches. Like that, its slime, it
stretches out.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Wey çawa de me'dê min milûxiyê levkeve... Li Qahîra li
Misrê.
Oh how my stomach got upset from Molokhia... In Cairo, in
Egypt.
Kaka ev bîstana te çandî ye... û bes hana tu xora xizmetê
dikî, me'nî malê ne?
Brother, this garden you planted... and just like this you
serve yourself, meaning for the home right?
E malê me, heq qicika...
Yes for our home, right of the small ones...
Ê te pir çandî ye?
But you planted a lot?
Ê temam, berka min çar mal in.
Yes okay, in my responsibility are four households.
Aaa çar mal in?
Aaa four households?
Ê ê...
Yes yes...
Tu pêkwanî hana, tu îdare dikî, tu kanî?
You manage like this, you administer, you can?
E lê em av, dix avê berdidinê û semad... ji e'cûl mesin
zibilê deweran em dikin, avê berdidinê.
Yes but we water, give water to it and manure... from the
calves, big livestock manure we use, give water to it.
Hasa me jî lê naxim.
I don't even use chemicals on it.
Rind e, seheta te xweş. Xwedê quwetê bide.
It's good, health to you. May God give strength.
Naxweşî nake, saxlem.
It doesn't cause illness, healthy.
Welhemdulila siheta ma rind noka.
And Alhamdulillah our health is good now.
Hemdula, Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike de, hemdula.
Thank God, may God lengthen your life too, thank God.
Sax bî, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Be healthy, may God be pleased with you.
Maşallah. Wadî ev ne ye xalûnê? Ev lîmon le bigir?
Mashallah. Is this the valley uncle? Take this lemon?
Me dar av reşand.
We sprinkled water on the trees.
Dilê min ket vê darê hana gile tenê xwo, bes hîn zû ye?
My heart fell for this tree like this all alone, but it is
still early?
Ma kî dinê, dest pê bikin ne?
Others in the world, let them start right?
Yekî deh he? Adeten tê çinînê?
Is it the first of the tenth? Usually it is harvested?
Yekî deho na?
First of the tenth, right?
Em şanzdê şino bar e.
We are at the sixteenth... [referring to date].
Yekî da û yeka, tê biçinî... dogê zeytûna rind girtîbe.
First of the tenth and first, you harvest... when the olives
have caught well.
U negirtîbe?
And if they haven't caught?
Bes sêrek be têkan zû biçinîn de weşînin derdixin.
But if it's sparse, the ones quickly harvest and shake and
take out.
De û pêncî deho û derna ne?
The tenth and fifteenth of the tenth and around there right?
Yanî yekî deho da û heta de û pêncî deho.
Meaning from the first of the tenth until the fifteenth of
the tenth.
I sêrek.
The sparse ones.
Belê.
Yes.
Lê hindik ma.
But a little remains.
Xêr...
Good...
Erê ev al no, li vê derê jî em li mala xalo ne.
Yes this side too, here we are at uncle's house.
Erê.
Yes.
Em gihîştin dawiya vîdyoya xwo, inşallah vîdyoya me jî be
ecibînin.
We reached the end of our video, hopefully you like our
video too.
Bimînin di xêr û xweşiyê da.
Remain in goodness and happiness.
Na we xalo?
Isn't it uncle?
Belê.
Yes.
Wekî xalo gotî bimînin di xêr û xweşiyê da.
As uncle said remain in goodness and happiness.
Û inşallah vîdyo kî din xweş kîbar, emê werin daxin.
And hopefully another nice lovely video, we will come and
upload.
Û inşallah me teqsîr jî nekiribine.
And hopefully we haven't been negligent.
Me teqsîr kirine jî, bikun wîneyê qusûrê ef bikin, le yê
vîdyo meke efawî ne.
Even if we have been negligent, forgive the fault in the
picture, make the video spontaneous.
Na we xalo?
Isn't it uncle?
Hawa xoşik e.
The air is nice.
Tiştêd efawî.
Spontaneous things.
Efawî.
Spontaneous.
Hawa xoşik e.
But it's nice right?
The air is nice.
Hana bi bernamî, cû der, wer ber, ser, ti dicirifî ecem şaş
bû, şaş nebû.
Like this with a program, go out, come in, on, you get
confused, whether it was wrong, or it wasn't wrong.
Çê dikim.
Spontaneous.
I make it.
Çê wana çêtir e.
Like that is better.
Erê. Ka bimarim vîdyo kî din xweş kîbar.
Yes. Let me end another nice lovely video.
Inşallah emê werin nêzîk da daxin. Bay bay.
Hopefully we will come soon and upload. Bye bye.
Ser serê min, ehlen wesehlen.
On my head, welcome, welcome.
Gula gula babo.
Goodbye father.