Gule de bêje Gule, aaa, heya heya...
Gule, come on say Gule, aaa, heya heya...
Kê? We kêm ma Azad gotiye kê, evê tarîx xwendîye.
Who? It almost left Azad said who, she has read history.
Em hemî nizanin em ummî ne, evê tarîx xwendîye, maşellah lê
ke.
We all don't know, we are illiterate, she has read history,
say mashallah to her.
Wele mase te hene...
By God, you have tables...
Xwişkê xwarziyê me wîne bura, rinda navê, bura xweşe, de bes
e xeytem, kamerê xwe çatekin.
Sister, bring our nephew here, is he good or not, he is
happy, enough my sister, turn on your cameras.
Kê? Na gumrîk nîne bura. Nebî Hûrî.
Who? No it's not Gumrik brother. It's Nebi Huri.
Nebî Hûrî ne Elemdar e li Sûriyê.
It is Nebi Huri, not Elemdar in Syria.
Wisa ekelî girim. Maşellah de kilamekê çi dikî pêde mere...
Like this let me take a shot. Mashallah, come on sing a song
or something...
Wele dilî wa min nayê ez, îştev mace were heval da. Nebî
hûrî. Wer wer têkeve wer, ho wer têkeve.
By God, my heart is not coming to this... come to my friend,
Nebi Huri. Come, come, go in, come, oh come, go in.
Xwişk û kekê min. Ev he ye anî kirrî li vî derê, em kê
farûcekî vira derjêkin...
My sister and brother. There is this, we bought it here, we
will slaughter a rooster here...
Roj baş hevalno, xwişkno û birano, em hatin. Me wera go...
me Gumnîkê sewirand, me wera go em kê herin cîkî din.
Good day friends, sisters and brothers, we have come. We
told you... we filmed Gumnik, we told you we will go
somewhere else.
Em li vir hatin, Nebî Hûrî. Li vî derî em kê çend laxtan li
vir çêkin, û em kê dekevin jêr jî. Em kê kin jêr jî an e, û
cisr jî hene, emê pêş we kin.
We came here, Nebi Huri. We will take a few shots here, and
we will go down too. We will go down there too, and there is
a bridge too, we will show you.
Erê vîdyoyê Gumrîkê min helqe baş çêkir, min go manî pir
dirêj nebe. Neka hûn dikarin vîdyoyê Gumrîkê jî sêr kin, me
ecan vî derê pêş we kin.
Yes, I made a good episode of the Gumrik video, I said so it
wouldn't be too long. Now you can also watch the Gumrik
video, we will show you here now.
Arê noka em kê laxtan ji xwişkê me yê kîbar ra vir çêkin.
Bes vî derî ekseriya pir xirab e, de em hal hazir in em kê
noka pêş we kin. Ha Xecê tu tiştekî nabêjî?
Yes, now we will take shots for our kind sister here. But
most of this place is in ruins, so we are ready now, we will
show you now. Ha Xeje, don't you have anything to say?
Erê hevalno noka bi mara bin... xeta taliyê vîdyo... bîr
mekin layk û îştîrakê pêl din û te'lîqne xweş kîbar ji me ra
çêkin.
Yes friends, now stay with us... until the end of the
video... don't forget to press like and subscribe and leave
nice and kind comments for us.
Birano teb'en em li Kela in ha. Bere vê rê da gotin Kela
Nebî Hûrî, bes gellek xirab kirine, birano.
Brothers, of course we are at the Castle, huh. They used to
call this road Nebi Huri Castle, but they have destroyed it
a lot, brothers.
Noka emê herin derbazî mesreh bibin, zî sekên hela çûne ne
çûne, lenc me jî em vira da na hatinê, hîn em waz'ê vira
nizanin.
Now we will go pass the theater, to see if they went or not,
because we also haven't come here, we still don't know the
situation here.
Û paşê jî em kê derbazî Nebî Hûrî bin. Bi mara bin heta
taliyê vîdyo, û bîr mekin layk û îştîrakê pê din û te'lîqne
xweş kîbar yê xwe ji me ra çêkin, seet xweş.
And later we will also pass by Nebi Huri. Stay with us until
the end of the video, and don't forget to press like and
subscribe and leave your nice kind comments for us, well
done.
Arê hevalno, ev vî derê caran ez nehatime, ev a ewil car e
ez têm vî derê. Teb'en gundîyê Dêr Siwanê, carekê me xwestin
sewirandin, Dêr Siwanê.
Yes friends, I haven't been here before, this is the first
time I come here. Of course, the villagers of Der Siwan,
once we wanted to film, Der Siwan.
Bes vê gundiyê yanokirmancan... ev dît ber telê daye, carekê
me xwestin... erê carekê me xwestin du rîye na, rêkê gund da
nizanin di kîderê ra derin.
But this Kurdish villager... he saw it behind the wire, once
we wanted... yes, once we wanted two roads, we don't know
which road goes to the village.
Lenî wele ji çema piştî Dêr Siwanê ta vî derê wara nêzikî
heftê kîlometre heye. Û rêkê xwe jî pir xirabe ne.
But from the river after Der Siwan until here, it is almost
seventy kilometers. And its road is also very bad.
Teb'en we bajerî hemver me, bajerî Tirkiyeyê ye, kîderê ye
ez nizanim. Kilîs e, kîderê ye ez nizanim... Ooo bînaye
gihane in te.
Of course, the city opposite us, is a city of Turkey, where
it is I don't know. Is it Kilis, where it is I don't know...
Ooo, buildings have reached you.
Sekine ev ê gundê kî li koka e... kirmancan. Gundikê li
deryan e.
Wait, which village is this at the roots of... the Kurds. It
is a village by the sea.
Bes ev gundan navê gund da ez nizanim. Navê gund me re yê
ezmûş kin, kesê zanê ev gunda kîderê ye, kesê xastê me re yê
ezmûş kin.
But these villages, I don't know the names of the villages.
Let them test the names of the villages for us, whoever
knows where this village is, whoever wants let them test us.
Rêkê gundê jî dikirin ji kîderê ye em nizanin, emê pê
bihelin inşellah... Emê xwe pê bigihîninê.
We don't know which way the road of the village is made
either, we will learn it hopefully... We will reach it.
Erê huro, vîdoyê me ha noye. Me go bes cewlek em bixwazin.
Yes guys, our video is here. We said let's just take a tour.
Em cewlek bixwazin... ko em bi hev ra... em derbaz bin, em
tiştan pêş we kin.
Let's take a tour... so together we... we pass, we show you
things.
Yo jik av rabe nebe ne. Wê runiştin e, cîkê yo ji habe ne.
Were rûnê e bino we da, ob e bi e.
Also get up from the water, let it not be. Let it be
sitting, also a place to have. Come sit at its bottom, let
it be a tent.
Mor e, tiştek yo ji ha be... Were e bino wada bikeve.
It's an ant, something also to have... Come sit under it.
Bîne ef derya canê, işte gihê serî ne. Bes ekterî gundî
xirab in.
Look at this dear sea, here it reached its end. But most
villagers are ruined.
Maşallah lê. Omrê xwe pir kavin ware... Weleh nizanim,
kêjanê çêkirîye.
Mashallah to it. Its life has been very long... I swear I
don't know, who made it.
Yûnan çêkirîye, Sûrî çêkirîye, Frensî çêkirîye? Kê çêkirîye
ez nizanim.
Greeks made it, Syrians made it, French made it? Who made it
I don't know.
Lenî min naxwandiye jî, Maşallahû.. Bes bokê hênik, xweş
heye li vî derê.
Because I haven't read either, Mashallah... But the wind is
cool, nice here.
Mor, yojk mor e habin. Lenî ew salk baran der pir ne, û
haşayêş jî pir re.
Ants, also ants are having. Because that year rain is very
outside, and insects are also very outside.
Merokê hişk xwabo. Manî moro... we nigê xwe ça kir winke
pîşê xwe bin ir, nînî morî ga wî nate.
The guy was sleeping dry. So the ant doesn't... he did his
leg like that, put his front under, look the ant's ox
doesn't come to him.
Ha bilî mar vê laxtê vir bigir, mete.
Let me take a shot of the snake here, aunt.
Qurban textê taybanî ye, gelî... lo însanê berê gihê emlaq
bin, cebbar bîn.
May I be a sacrifice to your special throne, valley... the
old people used to be owners of property, they were giants.
Yanî sekine, bi çi tertîbê kevir gihakê bân neke... E kevrê
ha cab ref'e o hapî noçe xê ref'e tenê bin.
I mean wait, in what order the stone weeded doesn't shout...
This stone has shouting, lifting, oh happily didn't lift to
be alone.
Ev kevrên we, çu rakirin ban e? Gelî gih wusa wekî kapkan jî
gih kirin av, divê zîrav e û paşê ji qolingan manî avdi
bigir e.
These stones of yours, how were they lifted up? People who
were also doing it in water like traps, it must be thin and
later also from digging so that it holds.
Seke gih cîk çin a ez nizanim. Çêkirina maşelah çiqanter in
em.
Wait what place is that I don't know. Mashallah they made it
how big are we.
Sa kakevirî waznê gindê tûnê ka heye.
Watch a stone has a ton weight of a village.
E no ka yekî rabe wer hano, çi e dizane be? Dizane...
Is there anyone right now to get up from here, what does he
know? He knows...
Tu tiştekî vira? Loe mê dike, beba, tiştek vira...
Do you have anything here? Look he is looking, dad,
something here...
Gûmgûmik a.
It is a lizard.
Ka vira bêje baba gûmgûmik. Ew... More? Yeşla... em kevrê
bavê ne.
Tell dad here lizard. That... Is it an ant? Let it be
alive... let's throw the stone.
Bê kê mor e... îşte heywanat pir ne.
Look who's an ant... Look there are many animals.
Hedî ye? Ha bi lemin wano laxtû kê liver waji lebigirla...
Hodiye...
Is it calm? Yes let me take a shot here at the liver too...
Is it calm...
Ev e masreha me. Ev o berê masreh bi. Cih rûniştinî bî.
This is our theater. This used to be a theater. It was a
sitting place.
Ecêb we da dawan dikirin le... îctîma bî... Belkî ciyê
mûsare'eyê be li vî derî.
Strangely they used to shout... it was a meeting... Maybe
it's a place for wrestling here.
Cîyê mûsare'eyê bi, na na, mi bihstî.
A place for wrestling, no no, I heard it.
Li vî derî berî wilo ko rudiniştin, mûluk... me mûluk ro
rudiniştin...
Here people before used to sit like that, kings... we kings
used to sit...
Ecêb ciyê mûlukê kî derê ye? Le jûr ê. Gerek li himberî ba.
Curiously where is the kings' place? It is up. It should
have been opposite.
Lê.. ber hember ew kû rûdiştin, mûsera wî dûçûn ewda...
But... people were sitting in front, its wrestling was going
on in them...
A nizanim, cam xuwat bi hemis, xeriyat dike. Da ekîd bilible
wina ye.
Oh I don't know, maybe my glass was all, it makes fun.
Surely it is true.
Yo ji cihê heflat o bî. Maşallah.
Also its place was celebrations. Mashallah.
Lê kevrî gundih ha na.. weh.. kevr ha na mar ko nayê, termîm
kê.
Look the village stone is not... wow... the stone is not
coming snake doesn't come, termim does.
Yanê kevrî... rafo hebê. Kevrî meselen ê din ê ketin e, moko
wano li cî yê din wera bivînê.
Meaning the stone... its shelf is there. the stones of for
example the other ones fell down, you will see them in other
places.
Seke we te dît çi menzerê çê kirin e... E hên... Ci tertîbî
kirin e ev...
Look, you saw what scenery they have made... Hey... What
arrangement they have made this...
Barê ber ço daxişî... înçu kirin, enêzanî. Noka... ketiye.
They dragged it in front... what did they do, they didn't
know. Now... it has fallen.
Ev cî ye. Tabin yozel ser hay e... yozel ser hay e.. bes
hapê nizanima.
This place. Of course it is fast on top... it is fast on
top.. wait to fly I don't know.
Seke gih zexrefe kirin e. Yevne çi se sol şağlin yane evna,
vê zexrefne gah çi kirin e. Vî harketne? Hebne?
Wait, people have done graffiti. What these people did for
years, these graffitis people have done what. These
movements? Are they?
Beba... go vira yê vir e. Heye... Zaxlî...
Dad... he said he is here. There is... Smart...
Ha seke... te nedît ev zexrefe go çawa çê kirine? Vane...
Look... didn't you see this graffiti how they made it?
See...
Seke... gilek nexşe çê kirine. Bes a ew.. ne şuxulê a
weye... Bi destan vano çênabe...
Look... people have made a lot of patterns. But that.. is
not your work... By hand it didn't use to be...
Gellek belê çerxê we kirine pê çi we kirine ez nizanim. Çi
alet heta vira anîn bi hafrînê? Gih nîzama derexistin... Lê!
Really it is clear people have turned the wheel I don't know
what they did with it. What tool did they bring here to dig?
They didn't know it came out... Look!
Ev e... Seken ser giyaye... Çi qas zexrefiye têda ye, cîkî
mezin e.
It is this... Look at the grass... How much graffiti is in
it, it's a big place.
Çiqas sol û çiqas av tê da derbaz kirine... Hatiye vî wî
cîyî da. Qicikê me jî çû ne.
So many years and so much water was passed in it... They
came to that place. Our little one has also gone.
Qicikê me li vî derkî li meser dakê... ko yek ji wî be em
gundiyê...
Our little one stays at this place at the camp... where is
he going to say we are a villager...
Musa ho bilis te na luwe derke. Dey çepke din maro... Na
wilo... Te hemşaya din dît mûsare'e wele.... Ko kes da ne...
Musa oh close to you he doesn't go out. Come on run where
they went... He is a flute... Did you see the other neighbor
wrestling.... Look there is no one...
Gazo elî wî yê da dixin. Vi ne maşellah, Çimen zere çiqen e
her zexre fena tê da hane.
They put gas of Ali in it. Look mashallah, The grass in it
how much it is every graffiti in it.
Eqliyê me ra xwedê be. Vê ne, hê... Tab'en evnok derece ne.
May God give us intelligence. Look at this, hey... Of course
those are steps.
Ciyê xwendiyê maroyekî yê... Arê kê ye? Wekê mû'ezet
gotiyê.. Kê tarîx xwendiyo, em nizanin em ummî ne.. Evê
tarîx wî xwendiyo.
The reading place of a guy... Yes who is it? As mu'ezet
said.. Who read history here, we don't know we are
illiterate.. She has read its history.
Mirov... hawêldar... ev derî va ez ê çi bim... Wele ewil car
ez têm asê vîdyo bibînim. Rom. Ektarî go rom çêkirî e.
A man... around here... this place I will be what... By God
this is the first time I come to see a video like this.
Romans. Most said Romans made it.
Rom çêkirî e, bes êsa vîdyo de bînim... Bes ez nizanim çî
ye, li cî ye.. Lenî em tarîx naxwendiye. Ev jî elim gerakê
erê. Marvê zike, manî çiye ba çi dikirin da vir da.
Romans made it, let me see the video now... But I don't know
what it is, in the place.. Because we haven't read history.
This is also knowledge. The man asks, what was it, what were
they doing here.
Milet çû derbaz dikir liwê vî derê.. Lê! Evane.. Sekin wakî
kûrsî yane. Da wî kûrsî ya mûlukey... E kûrsî melekî ye..
Weke... nîştinê. Heyo xulam.. newa divin...
The nation went passing through this place.. Look! These..
Wait like chairs. The chair of kings... The chair of an
angel.. Like... sitting. Come oh slave.. they don't go...
Filmek jî habî digo, "emruka mewlay". Bi! Temaşê kin. Qurban
ev çi qel e..
There was also a movie saying, "your command my lord". Come!
Watch. May I be a sacrifice what a fortress this is..
Sako vê darê çi qê kirine... Çiqas hazar sal emrê gundî...
emrê vê darê. Seke gî şûna xê eştin û çûn.
Wait here what did they do to this tree... How many thousand
years is the villager's life... the life of this tree. Look
they left their traces and left.
Însana berê jî çi tişkê aw bîn digot em kê bimirin, em kê
herin.. Em dîsa vejîn..
The people before used to say whatever thing was there we
will die, we will go.. We will be reborn again..
Serê xwa gen, dikiran ev dîwaro, em nîşan daynin ser û mehnî
teq ra biftilno derin serî xwa bibin... Nizanim çi tiştekî
sêx kirinê, çûn, xilas. Ta were de em...
Turn their heads, they did this wall, we put signs on it and
so it explodes and they will go to their heads... I don't
know what they did, they left, finished. Let's come here...
De hal e. Dinyayek boş e. Hemî ji zimanê xweş e, seke eva ji
derecek hendî ne terê hil dikşîne jor.
Look at the state of things. It's an empty world. Everything
is from a sweet tongue, look at these huge stairs, pulling
the train up.
Milet livê derbas dibe, milet wê derbas dibe.
People pass from here, people pass from there.
Lê her derîyekî da, derece hene.
Yes, at every door, there are stairs.
Seke her mobnê derîkî derece têra çêkirine. Ma nê milet...
Look, at every building's door, they have made stairs. So
that people...
Dorte dorê cumhûr rûniştin.
The crowd sat all around.
Mel'eb noko çênekirine?
Didn't they build stadiums now?
Lê, mel'ebê noko çênekirine, fıkra jı wê mesrehê birine.
Yes, they haven't built stadiums now, they took the idea
from that theater.
Ava tertîbê...
This layout...
Tertîbê mel'eba çêkirine.
They made the layout of stadiums.
Seke meqe'îd nê dor têra mirov lê rûniştine. Mel'eb naha
wanê ye, milet gel hev dore we ne.
Look at the seats all around where people sit. The stadium
is like that now, people are all around it.
Ev fıkra jı wê mesrehê birine.
They took this idea from that theater.
Pir tişt heye, o hewlî me dorçerma he bigere.
There are many things, let's look around us.
Ecewek pir xweş e.
It is very beautiful.
Naha heram e ev kafir noko ava nabînin e, benasin e.
It's a shame that these infidels don't see this now, they
recognize it.
O kursîkî livir jî, ew jî kursî melîk o çi ye. Ew jî yek
livir jî... bılınd e, bılınd e.
And there's a chair here too, is it a king's chair or what.
There's another one here too... it's high, it's high.
Eha...
Aha...
Oho.
Seke eva wekî mesrah a ye. Li vê derê jî wekî hewşo ne. Go
hewş tê çêkirine, o rola jor a e se paştev e wer.
Look, this is like a theater. And here it's like a
courtyard. They made a courtyard, the upper part is this,
look at the back.
Ekîd vê derê wextî...
Surely this place, in the past...
Wextî vê derê wekî bêjer, begind bigind, qesir bî...
In the past, this place was like a stage, very big, it was a
palace...
Li vê derê qehreman derdixistin e, melûk didîtin, dihatin vê
derê, milet.
They used to bring out heroes here, the kings would see,
people would come here.
Berê miletê berê jî diçûnê li dor o dorê rûniştin.
People from the past would also go and sit all around.
Wer em ke noko da kevin jêr jî. Maşallah.
Come, let's go down now. Mashallah.
Wer, wer, hawlî min binere.
Come, come, look around me.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Menteqeyek mam mezin a, mezin a maşallah, serî ke yek têne.
It's a very big area, it's huge mashallah, they come one by
one.
Taba li vê derê bi dûr va nêzîk e, ew gund o jî di binê telê
da ye.
Of course, this place is both far and near, that village is
also under the hill.
Haa, wer.
Yes, come.
Wadiye. Çi tertîbê kafir kiriye evde, maşallah. Xwexwo
bilind e bilind e.
It's a valley. Look at the setup the infidel made here,
mashallah. It's really high, it's high.
Min go çiqas bilind e, a sere herem tiştek pê nebe.
I said it's so high, maybe there's a sanctuary on top.
Lanî sê sed metreyan e.
Meaning it's three hundred meters.
Ya xudê... Maşallah.
Oh God... Mashallah.
Seke wekî girtîgehê jî çêkirine.
Look, they made it like a prison too.
Lê gelek qenter hene... Tiştê ana meriv lê ser dikî...
Yes, there are many bridges... You look at these things...
Tiştê ana kafir meriv lê ser dike... Diçe bi hezar salan paş
de...
You look at these things the infidel made... You go back
thousands of years...
Tu dibê eceb bere çawa bûn, çawa dikirin çawa nedikirin...
You wonder how they were before, how they did things, how
they didn't do things...
Lê ev noko.. Ne ev fîlm naha ne. Wa nê çêdibe, fîlmê wan e
temsîl dıkin çêdikin, yanî nefs wekî noko ye...
But this now... These aren't movies now. That's how it
happens, they act in their movies, meaning it's exactly like
this now...
Ho ho. Qelibê wer e ye. Seke qop a, qopê bawobê gind e.
Ho ho. Look at the mold here. Look at the arch, a huge arch.
Seke di vir o da ku derece ne, di vir a diket e. Medxalê
gind e.
Look, from here where the stairs are, it went in here. The
entrance is huge.
Seke ew hêl e. Maşallah.
Look at that side. Mashallah.
Welle ewel car e têm vê derê.
Truly, this is my first time coming here.
Ez ser televîzyonê dibînim. Berî vê jî me dît cihê ku em
hatin em gihîştin derên din.
I see it on television. Before this too, we saw places we
came to and reached other places.
Dinya germ bû û der bû, me nekanî ba ti tişt nê...
The weather was hot, we couldn't go to anything...
Te dît xelk tê xwarê siyah e, nê.
Did you see the people coming down for tourism, look.
Keft e ke.
Look there.
Me pir ew kir, xaye mişkîle go ew bin e... xerab bin...
We did a lot of this, but it's a problem that this is
ruined.
Gelek... Ohoh li ba gind... Pir nivîs jî li ser heye.
Very... Ohoh next to the huge... There is also a lot of
writing on it.
Em nizanin bixwînin, em nivîsê jî nizanin bixwînin go ecnebî
ye...
We don't know how to read, we can't read the writing because
it is foreign...
Oh.
Erê ew li nê vê derê jî jêr e, binê kelê.
Yes, this place is below too, beneath the castle.
Taba zikriyate go li vê derê hene, kesî noko ta vê derê
nîne. Ew baş e kela qatê banê.
Of course, there are memories here, no one comes here now.
It's good, the top floor of the castle.
Ecewek pir xweş e livirê.
It's very beautiful here.
Çi can e lo? Hey hey...
What a beauty, man? Hey hey...
Lê kafir bi kafirin.
But the infidels are infidels.
Berê, inson ê berê go diçûn e kî derê...
In the past, people from the past wherever they went...
Cîhekî tê ra li kon, te dît? Insonê berê...
See this place? People of the past...
Cîhê bilind lê diçûn wê derê rûdiniştin... Maşallah.
They used to go and sit in high places... Mashallah.
Wek ewê gotî tebarek el-rehman...
As he said, blessed is the Merciful...
Ev xêr bereketa, ev xêr bereketa me ye. Ebo maşallah.
This blessing, abundance, this is our blessing and
abundance. Oh, mashallah.
Gijgijka erdê derdikeve, wadiye... ev ê em bixwîn lê.
Grass grows from the earth, there's a valley... we will read
this.
Şekê baxim... Av o ti be xwarin saqî ye. Pok e binê.
Look at the garden... The water is drinkable. The bottom is
clean.
Îsal, îsal xwedê baran xweş bûn, dîg diro ava çêkir e...
This year, thank God the rain was good, it has created
water...
Kanîk e li kî ye, seke di vir o di vir o... Seke wer,
were...
Look at the spring, right here, right here... Look, come,
come...
Maşallah. Ev nîmet e naha temam pê ne...
Mashallah. These are blessings, perfectly...
Menteqe a xêr o bera e seke rûyê behrê va roxê derdikeve,
yek e li wî cî.
A region of blessing and abundance, look at the surface of
the sea coming out on that side, it's one in that place.
Çend qulika derketin e, gelek yek.
Several holes have appeared, many of them.
Taba her cîhekî tije ye ava boş e, noko havîn e, ew tije
hişk dibin, ew e çem o robar in.
Of course, everywhere is full of empty water, now it's
summer, they completely dry up, these are rivers and
streams.
Ew noko yî ken dê xwo ra we derxê malê dinê di ke, te dî.
Now people get their money out of the world from it, you
see.
Berî vê hişk bin, derw pir xweş e.
Before they dry up, it's very nice.
Kesê hatî vê derê, hewlî min li vir biger e.
Anyone who has come here, let them look around with me.
Kesê hatî vê derê, ta'lîq da min re binîse, kî hatî ev
zikriyat li vê derê dîtiye, me re yazîmiş ke.
Anyone who has come here, write to me in a comment. Whoever
has come and seen these memories here, write to us.
Ha qeçkê me jî xwarê çûn e, ê yer rûniştin e...
Yes, our girls also went down, they went and sat down...
Maşallah... hey tûzike hene mendez...
Mashallah... there are some watercress here...
Hindikero çîn ro. Te dî, çi berxek e.
Some gather it. You saw, what a beautiful place.
Tabi ev der, ev kes nîne wey kanin werin vê derê jê re
rûnin.
Of course, this place, there's nobody here, they can come
here and sit.
O noko di vê derê te dî cihê rûniştinê hene mirov di xwe re
tiştek çêke...
Now, as you see, there are places to sit here, one can
prepare something for oneself...
Pir nê... qet ne xêçek xwe re di bilîzin.
Many... at least people can play a bit.
Ecew e pir xweş e.
It's very beautiful.
Tabi berî vê derê ge oda dor bîn... xerob bîne.
Of course, before this place used to be rooms... it's
ruined.
Wa di e, hewlî min li vir biger e.
You see, look around with me here.
O tûzikê mendezê maşallah ez ê kem. Werin tûzikê mendezê
bibînin.
O watercress, mashallah, I will pick some. Come and see the
watercress.
Jin in e... jin jî tûzikê mendezê hez dikin wî netê xwe me
dît vê derê.
It's women... women also like watercress, we saw their
situation here.
Eceb inê di avê de mar hebin. Ez ê henekok bikim.
I wonder if there are snakes in the water. I will joke
around a bit.
A masî cûçika çi ji? Ê welle ev masî ne, ho.
Are there little fish or anything? By God, these are fish,
here.
Welle masî ji tê hene lo, masî hûrik... Ê masî mezin e.
By God, there are fish in it, little fish... Yes, a big
fish.
Ê... beqeranî masî hûrik av jî hene.
Yes... there are little frogs and little fish too.
Nê çengê xwe re xwarinê nînin, naha biçarbondo.
No, they haven't brought their food, no let's look.
De seze ev e kem. Ê gelek cîhek xweş e.
Come, I'll do this. It's a very nice place.
O masî giha wa.
O the fish arrived.
Îîî!
Eeee!
Em qanûnî bigirin. Eceb mar hebin mar.
Let's legally catch it. I wonder if there are snakes.
Wele nêwêrim, av pir sar e. Pêçî cûcik min in.
By God I don't dare, the water is very cold. My little toes.
Mirov ji destê heywanata, ev der e ka avî nîv darar e, lanî
mirov tirse ke mar û dar a hebin.
One is afraid of animals, this place is full of water and
trees, so one is afraid there might be snakes and things.
Ooo maşallah.
Ooo mashallah.
Gî dar di nav de ne, mêze ke dar gî dorhêla in e.
There are trees in it, look, trees are all around.
Ê. Werê avê heye, ew jî ew wer e wera. Maşallah av çi qas
boş e.
Yes. Come see the water, come look over here. Mashallah, how
abundant the water is.
Ev hawil nabîne. Cîhek pir xweş e. Wekî ew gotî wê derê
binêr.
Look at this around you. It's a very nice place. As he said,
look over there.
Ez dı şevtiyam ev xeyalat nabin e ez da şevtiyam...
I am burning, these thoughts are not coming to me, I was
burning...
A taştan ew dibînim, pirca serê min pê ve sekinî, ez ê dîqe
dîqe vîdyo werim... ha... wer bin.
I see those things, the hair on my head stood up, I will
come minute by minute in the video... yes... come.
Hıı. Ew nîmet o te dî we ey... masî jî hene.
Yes. Those blessings... and there are fish too.
Şeref nîne hene. Seke nîmet o, qeçikek têne xwarinê da
bilîzin.
Honestly, there are. Look at the blessings, the girls come
to play while eating.
Hatine û li vir rûniştin. Xwe re xwarina xwe xwarin û zibalê
xwe jî gî li vir eştin.
They came and sat here. They ate their food and threw all
their garbage here.
Miletî Efrîn... Miletî Efrîn xewyî tiştek wisa nakin.
The people of Afrin... The people of Afrin don't do such
things.
Gı qeyna ji baxistanê ne... Baxistanê natên cema.
Maybe they are from the gardens... the gardens don't gather.
Miletê Efrîn, iştê vî dîtin, vîdyoya min sêr kir.
The people of Afrin, seeing this, watched my video.
Cîhekî xweş e dibînin, diçin cîhekî dimînin. Ema ez wê
dikim.
They see a beautiful place, they go and stay somewhere. But
I do that.
Noko ev mesele helwe... Niha hema çi... Nîvê nêzikî wê
derê...
Now this issue... Now whatever... Near there...
Jı darikî dûr ve ye, dıhatin, werin cem zibala wan û nîviyê
dimaş e.
It is far from the tree, they came, come to their garbage
and half is left.
Gerek in zibala xwe çê nekin û nanî xwaro bibin çiqin derkî
nava reşîkî bişewtînin.
They shouldn't leave their trash and they should take the
eaten bread and burn it somewhere in the bushes.
De ev derece ne ema te maşallah ev nîmet o, welle nîmet in.
So these are stairs but mashallah these blessings, by God
they are blessings.
Vê dor o cîhekî wekî kaniyan e. Eh eh... Maşallah...
Around here is a place like springs. Eh eh... Mashallah...
Çi tûzik mendez, pir e vira, tiştek nevira nîne.
There is so much watercress here, there is nothing missing
here.
Wile ew kîjan mandik in, ne ewin...
Oh, which mandik are those? They are not the same...
Ewin wile...
That is them, by God...
Mandika darê wê ditiyê...
The wood of the mandik is inside...
Kaniya...
The spring...
Darê wê bi xwe ye. Bes kûr e.
Its wood is its own. But it's deep.
A cewwek pir xweş e. Bi Qur'anê Ezîm.
A very nice atmosphere. By the Great Quran.
Bes tiştek... Ji camêr ra, av hetanî li derê... pir dûr e.
Just one thing... To the man, the water until the outside...
it's very far.
Erê wele.
Yes, indeed.
Oho... tûzik e.
Oho... it's watercress.
Xalo mandik nîne...
Uncle, there is no mandik...
Merheba... tişkî bi me dîna.
Hello... show us a little.
Ev koma te ye.
This is your group.
Ya selam.
Oh, peace.
Xalo bi kilê mezin e...
Uncle, with the big pot...
Maşela evîne rind in.
Mashallah, these are nice.
Tabi te wexta dît, kûkê hilnekê.
Of course when you find it, don't pull the roots.
Ew bes te bi qerçînê... wekî dîsa şaxek bide.
Just cut it off... so it gives a branch again.
He ye...
Yes it is...
Evîne rind in... Naka nanek xwa... dimso lêl e, dimsa bacana
lêl e...
These are nice... Now a good bread... with molasses on it,
tomato paste on it...
Çêçekî tu havê lî xwe, bi pîvazek hişk û dirûmkekê bixwe
malê dinyêye bike.
You add a little taste to it, with a dry onion and a bite to
eat, it's worth the world's wealth.
Yanî tu kûk, çîçek, xwarina ne... daştî jê bîne bi nanî, ti
sî têr bibe... ti kanê ti weke din bixwe...
I mean you, root, flower, food... bring it from the plain
with bread, you get full... you can eat whatever else...
Xalo mandik nîne...
Uncle, there is no mandik...
Mandik heye, jêre ewe. Av kûr e anez ûrîm xwe têkime.
There is mandik, it's down there. The water is deep,
otherwise I would go in.
A kincên min wê şil bibin.
Ah my clothes will get wet.
Ew xweş hilwe, deke kilê.
That is nice, put it in the pot.
Kûr e kûr. Mera tamtîkê çê ke.
It's deep, deep. Make a tamtîk for us.
Tamtîk bi çilo çêdibe?
How does tamtîk get made?
Ê tamtîk bi vî çê nabe?
Can't tamtîk be made with this?
Ew mandik e mandik.
That is mandik, mandik.
Av ê mandik e na?
Is this mandik, no?
He.
Yes.
Ha... ew mandik e. Hey... lêvî me kef didan ho.
Ah... that is mandik. Hey... look, they were foaming for us.
Teqe tima werî vir o... Milet qeçikên xwe jî wê bînin vir
têkevin e?
You should always come here... Will people also bring their
girls here to get in?
He?
Huh?
Qeçikên we jî ewê dikanin werin vir... Hizê naka warin...
laxtê xwe çêkin... ez ê jî warim çêkim.
Your girls can also come here... Let them come now... make
their portions... I will also come and make it.
Nere vir ha... vê meke... Maşela.
Look here... don't do this... Mashallah.
Te dît kaniyek li vir jî heye. Kaniyek ava ye.
Did you see there's a spring here too. It's a water spring.
Tedi qeçik li vê derê jî heye... ew qeçik heye.
Look, there's a girl here too... there is a girl.
Bes binihêre.
Just look.
Maşallah. E qeçikên xelkê xwe re hatin vir in.
Mashallah. People's daughters came here.
A maşallah amo menzerek xweş e. Cewwek xweş e vî derî.
Mashallah, uncle, it's a nice scenery. It's a nice
atmosphere here.
E avê wê li vir re hat... maşallah. Seleten Nebî.
Its water came through here... mashallah. Blessings on the
Prophet.
Tadi çi menzere ye... menzerek xweş e. Qeçek li vir dikin e.
Did you see what a scenery... a nice scenery. Girls are
doing it here.
Lê em jî mat in ho. Em nizanin vir bîra me mest dike, weke
çi mesel ye na.
But we are also amazed, look. We don't know, it intoxicates
our minds here, what kind of situation it is.
A cewwek pir xweş e. Bes tesbîtat li vî derî garak e.
A very nice atmosphere. But determinations are necessary for
this place.
Oho... vê derê gelek cî runiştin e, ev xetên çîçekên vê derê
wê mezin bibin, dar bibin. Ehê... pir xweş e.
Oho... there are many sitting places here, these flower
lines here will grow and become trees. Aha... it's very
nice.
Oho ev qeçek xwarê dikin e. Gelek qeçek xwarê dikin e. Kûr e
navika...
Oho, these girls are doing it down there. Many girls are
doing it down there. The middle is deep...
Ho wer e... wez çewa me wada?
Hey come... how am I in this situation?
Wez rind e? Evno jî mûtebeiynê min a na.
Am I good? These are also my followers, right.
Qîzno, bay bay kin. Ev se'eta gundiyan xweş e.
Girls, say bye bye. This time of the villagers is nice.
Xaltîk evno gî mûtebeiynê min na ew gî gundê yî teki mi...
Hûn naşorin we...
Aunt, these are all my followers, I am making a video of
all... Aren't you washing...
Ava zor e...
The water is strong...
Saet ew derê dî me ro, xaltîk. Qeçek xwe înîn vî derê em
rûkê xweş derbaz kin ne.
Watch that side of us, aunt. Bring the girls here, let's
spend a nice time, right.
Ew inakê xweş e... Ena milê neynin e, kê firsend e bê werin.
That is nice... They shouldn't be bothered, whoever has the
chance, tell them to come.
Were... Maşallah. Îsal te dît derê xêr û bêr pir e.
Come... Mashallah. This year, you see, there is a lot of
goodness and blessing here.
Maşallah. Tabî vir gî zeytûn e, zeytûn e u qeçek xwe
dikene...
Mashallah. Of course here everywhere is olive, olive and the
girls are doing it...
E li vî derê jî pismamên min ji Qestel Cindo ne... A ev derê
wî cewwê vir çewa ye?
And here are also my cousins from Qestel Jindo... Ah, how is
his atmosphere here?
Cewwê wê xweş e.
Its atmosphere is nice.
Xweş e, kîbar e na?
Nice, polite, isn't it?
A cewwe xweş e.
Yes, the atmosphere is nice.
Silavên min ji miletê Qestel Cindo ro... kûçik u mezin çavên
we gî maç dikim. E miletê Qestel Cindo ne?
My greetings to the people of Qestel Jindo... young and old,
I kiss all your eyes. Are you the people of Qestel Jindo?
Wele wîn miletin, em miletin...
By God you are the people, we are the people...
Em zehf kêfxweş bûn... kîlik ojî çi xweş rast hatin.
Maşallah, o xêr û bêr maşallah çiqas pir e.
We were very happy... how nicely we came across each other.
Mashallah, and goodness and blessing, mashallah, how
abundant it is.
Elhemdulillah pir e.
Praise be to God, it is abundant.
Bî çend sal tu nehatî vî derê?
For how many years haven't you come here?
Deh sal min nehat vî derê bîra.
Ten years I haven't come here, brother.
E deh sal tu nehatî vî derê... zêdeyî de sal min nehat vî
derê.
Ah, ten years you haven't come here... more than ten years I
haven't come here.
Wele em jî...
By God, us too...
E qeçek we rûkin, ev wextên xweş e, rûkek xweş e. Bes yek ev
gemara xwe paqij bikin.
Ah, let your girls show their faces, these are nice times, a
nice face. But just clean up this dirt of yours.
Maşallah ev der e...
Mashallah, this place...
Xaltîk ew gihîştin... em ew silavê... ew milet u tiştê din
jî ha ye.
Aunt, they arrived... those greetings... those people and
other things are there too.
Ew Amerîkî ye, ewrûpî ye... e reb e, a alem e silav pir ji
we re heye. Xwestekek ji islam re tiştek ji we ra ha ye.
They are American, European... Arab, all the world has a lot
of greetings for you. A wish for Islam, something for you is
there.
Silavê min ji bo gundiyê me, hevalê min u xaltîkên min rê,
biçûk û mezin çavên wan maç dikim emrên dirêj seyran xweş
in, na xaltîk?
My greetings to our villagers, my friends and my aunts,
young and old, I kiss their eyes, long life, picnics are
nice, right aunt?
Erê wele.
Yes, indeed.
Umrê we tê ne xaltîk, maşallah xwedê te da vir u maşallah te
dît wekî xweş e.
Your life comes, right aunt, mashallah God brought you here
and mashallah you saw it is nice.
Xwedê te da bîne, xwedê kêm neke birastî.
May God bring you, may God truly not make you less.
Maşallah, maşallah... bes xaltîk cî warê xwe pîs dikin ev
tiştên wa nînin...
Mashallah, mashallah... but aunt, they make their living
place dirty, these things shouldn't be...
Law em çi bikine... em çare nabînin. Emro gelek pir tiştin
kîbare...
Boy, what should we do... we can't find a solution. Today
there are many polite things...
Na dûr e Qestel Cindo, na dûr e?
No, is Qestel Jindo far, or not far?
Na dûr e... em nexweşin... amîn...
Not far... we are sick... amen...
Nîv saet tu digihîje derî?
Do you reach the place in half an hour?
Saeteke na...
About an hour, no...
Saetek e, na?
It's an hour, right?
Nêzîk e.
It's close.
Xaltîk evno ji Qestel Cindo hatin a. Digotin e saetek wext
digire, saeteke.
Aunt, these came from Qestel Jindo. They were saying it
takes an hour, an hour.
Bes rûkek xweş e, metel mabû bi vî cewweyî xweş, vî derî
dixwaze werê.
But it's a nice face, amazed by this nice atmosphere, wants
to come to this place.
Kî dare bê vir xwe nîşan bide. Ewqas kîbar e.
Who would come here and not show themselves. It's so polite.
Bir kûrê vir, wek qewtek dîke... ava navikê... ev çiya?
Bring the boy here, like a bump... center water... what is
this?
Ew paneşîr e.
That is paneşîr.
Wile min gotî belkî ev dar e... erê wele.
By God I thought maybe this is wood... yes, indeed.
Maşallah, ez fehm dikim ev mûtabeyî min e, ji gundê Arandê
ye.
Mashallah, I understand this is my follower, from the
village of Arande.
Silavên min ji miletê Arandê re ye, ê biçûk u mezin ev... e
dûre ji Arandê vir a?
My greetings to the people of Arande, to the young and
old... is it far from Arande to here?
Dûr e.
It is far.
Çend saet e tu digihê vî derê?
How many hours does it take you to reach here?
Me di duh de vir xew kir. Me li vê derê xew kir.
We slept here yesterday. We slept at this place.
We ji duh de vir xew kirî...
You slept here since yesterday...
Na ez nîvroj çûm, saetek me çû...
No, I went at noon, we went for an hour...
E ji we re saet e... tu bi motor hû tê. Motor saet e...
weqtek kin tu vê derê yî.
Ah, it's an hour for you... you came by motorcycle.
Motorcycle is an hour... in a short time you are here.
Ew kes yê ba xwe bînin vir. Kesî heye vir silavan jê re
bişînin.
Bring those people here with you. If there's anyone, send
greetings to them.
Silav dikim...
I send greetings...
A cewwek pir xweş e, na, cîhek xweş...
Ah, a very nice atmosphere, right, a nice place...
Xweş e bi rastî...
It is truly nice...
Ev av e, wekî ku me dît... av çawa xweş derdikeve, maşallah.
This water, as we saw... how nicely the water comes out,
mashallah.
Dîqet meke, bi hezaran sal e ev ava wî naşikê na... av germ
e bira. Ji ber vê yekê çêdibe.
Look carefully, for thousands of years this water hasn't
stopped, right... the water is warm, brother. Because of
this, it happens.
Xweş e na xweş e? Maşallah e...
It's nice, isn't it? Mashallah...
Kef xweş e... ev qezenc e... zehf kîbar e.
The foam is nice... this is a gain... it is very polite.
Kûr kûr e, ev ava çawa ji vir derkeve?
It's deep, deep, how does this water come out of here?
Ev av kûrahiya wê heye, kûrek mezin e...
This water has depth, it's a big depth...
Ava kûr e, ava xwe... me dît e.
The water is deep, its water... we saw it.
Ev der şev bu... wek navê wî bu...
This place was night... it was like his name...
Em xweş dikin li gundê xwe. Em miletê ev gund in wek şev bû.
E te dît... maşallah.
We enjoy ourselves in our village. We are the people of this
village, it was like night. Ah, you saw... mashallah.
Ev derî mûtebeyên min in. Gundî gişt in, milet... te dît we
ez wî xelkê silav nakim.
Here are my followers. All the villagers, the people... you
saw I won't ignore those people.
Bira, me ji Qestelê wext girtî...
Brother, we took time from Qestel...
Saet e ew der e?
Is it an hour there?
Saetyek wexta me girt... e nîv saet e.
It took us about an hour of time... well, half an hour.
Heta we hatî vî derê... bi motor hat, we bi motor hat saetek
tu li vir î.
Until you came to this place... came by motorcycle, you came
by motorcycle, in an hour you are here.
Ê maşallah, silav ji milet re be, em te naskirin tu kîbar
î...
Eh mashallah, greetings to the people, we know you, you are
polite...
Spas dikim... xweş e...
I thank you... it's nice...
De ma xweş e. Dor ber jî wina in.
Well, it's nice. The surroundings are like this too.
Hêşîn bûn e, pez, kela, hîn erê rind e.
It's green, there are sheep and things, it's really
beautiful.
Bihar e vira tenê bi kêf e, hêşîkayî be,
Spring here alone is enjoyable, when it's green,
bas e ev sal maşallah kaniya gelek dar e, dibîne zêde ye.
but this year, mashallah, the spring has a lot of water, you
see it's abundant.
Heye heznika xwe diqîm pir ne sar e. Teba kaniya ne, icbarî
kê ye av be.
I can feel it, it's not very cold. It's spring water, so
it's naturally water.
Ne nakin cem e. Cihê xwe rûne em heseb nakin wele, de şil
bibe.
No, they don't let me. Let's just sit down, we don't care,
by God, let it get wet.
De xwe bavê. Yaaa. Ehhh, rûyek gihalim.
Jump in. Ohhh. Ehhh, my face got wet.
Rûyê yên în e... bera mekin çi tenê... zehmet e pê.
The face... don't let it... it's difficult...
Cih tenê nîn e?
Is there no empty place?
Cih tenê ye.
There is an empty place.
Bes bes şer meşûkin me. Şukran!
Enough, enough, don't mess around. Thank you!
Vêce cihê heciz dikin?
Are you reserving the place?
Wele.
Yes, by God.
Li pêşda şabû tên cihê heciz dikin.
They are coming from ahead to reserve the place.
Yella!
Let's go!
Tu li hakê, wele kilam e.
You're there, let's sing a song.
Merheba. Merheba anse.
Hello. Hello miss.
Kake hilgirim, maşeallah!
Let me pick you up, mashallah!
De kilamê çika pê de mawa.
Come on, sing a song for us.
Gule, gule, gule, gulê min. Mervan ba min. Gule, ez bi te re
diçim...
Gule, gule, gule, my rose. Mervan is with me. Gule, I am
going with you...
Ka bûsek ke mi. Ka bûsek ke mi. Ka enşewa me diçap ke we ra.
Give me a kiss. Give me a kiss. Let's show this to them.
Maşeallah de kilamê gul e gul e. Hefiz kirî, gelek hefiz
kirî a.
Mashallah, she sang the song "gule gule". You memorized it,
you memorized a lot.
Te hîn çi dizanî kilama?
What other songs do you know?
Çi erebî? Kilame xaricî ye, de bêje mawa.
Which one in Arabic? A foreign song, come on, sing it.
La la la, binti flos. Bidha îdiye. Encema şehatetlib hekî.
La la la, binti flos.
No, no, no, the girl wants money. She wants an Eid gift. I
don't know what she's asking for. No, no, no, the girl wants
money.
Maşeallah, maşeallah, maşeallah, hêêêêê.
Mashallah, mashallah, mashallah, hey.
Ka bûsekî mi. Ka bûsekî mi.
Give me a kiss. Give me a kiss.
Maşeallah xudê emirke dirêj pê bide, bi aqil e, kilama gî
dizane.
Mashallah, may God give her a long life, she is smart, she
knows all the songs.
Musteqbel tu dixwazî tu bibe çî bî? Te textor bî an te bi
kilamê bêjî?
In the future, what do you want to be? Do you want to be a
doctor, or do you want to sing?
Kilamê.
Singing.
Kilamê? Merqa te qe ser kilamê ye, tu dixwazî kilamê dîn.
Singing? Your passion is singing, you want to sing.
Noka ha kî te terzûn da derxistin. Milet li me sêr dika, tu
dibêjî çî milet ra?
Now whoever put you on TV. The people are watching us, what
do you say to the people?
Tişt nabe.
Nothing.
Tu bay bay dikî?
Are you saying bye bye?
Erê.
Yes.
Tu ji wana hes dikî yê me sêr dikin? Pir lê hindik?
Do you love those who watch us? A lot or a little?
Pir. Bi layîk û iştirak mela xan...
A lot. With like and subscribe...
De wek wê bê, bê layk û iştirak...
Say it like that, say like and subscribe...
Maşeallah. Xudê belê. Te li wî sêr kî ne?
Mashallah. May God bless. Did you look at that?
Ê te lê sêr kî ev qanatê çî kî ye? Te lê sêr kî.
Whose channel is this that you are watching? You watched it.
Ev. Buhar Xweş.
This one. Buhar Xweş.
Buhar Xweş e. A yê te ko? A yên Efrîn se û şêst û şeş?
Buhar Xweş. And yours? Afrin 366?
Erê. Te lê sêr kirî yotobê? Erê.
Yes. Did you watch it on YouTube? Yes.
Maşellah, xudê we re wek bi hêle. Qîzkek bi aqil e.
Mashallah, may God protect you like this. A smart girl.
Ez te dekim derê? Erê.
Should I put you down? Yes.
Yella. Hay. Maşeallah. Xudê bi we rabe jivarû, xudê destên
we bi sere we bigre.
Come on. There. Mashallah. May God be with you, and may God
guide you.
Şîrîkê re bay bay ke, buharê re. Lî buharê sêr ke.
Say bye bye to the partner, to Spring. Look at Spring.
Qanata buharê lê sêr dikin. Qanata buhar na yewmiyatê xwe de
dixeyî. Sebira xwe biqeşko li ber te.
They are watching the Spring channel. The Spring channel
shows their daily lives. Have patience with yourself.
Ma go qaçik e xelkê biaqil e, xudê stara xwe lê bike yek
biaqil e, çi kilam o zanî, kilama gul e gul e.
I said this child is smart, may God protect her, she is very
smart, what songs she knows, the song is Gule Gule.
Guli, e gulê ma... nizanim çiye min hefez nekirî welleh min
hefez nekirî, asan tîk tok lê sêr dikim...
Guli, oh gul... I don't know what it is, by God I haven't
memorized it, I just watch it on TikTok...
Bes mi hafeZ nekirî, maşeallah hefiz kirîye.
But I haven't memorized it, mashallah she has memorized it.
Ez min ta mezin bibî te dixwazî çî bibî? Dibî yek kilamê
dem, mago textorbe derba dîn na... çi ecewb naye ewînar e...
I said when you grow up what do you want to be? She said I
will sing, I said be a doctor, she immediately said no...
what a wonder she loves it...
Maşallah. Milo dîlî wa mê na mî... îşte me cihê wê re hewal
da, nav bihurî.
Mashallah. I was talking to them... we arranged a place
there, with the flow.
Noka wê rin wê rin bi dar e... amî cih pêşva dikin, me'nî ê
nizanî wer e.
Now it will flow, it will flow to the tree... we are making
the place ahead, the meaning he doesn't know, come here.
Min li dîlî wame nanî.. nokoşî moknî giya ye na.
Maşeallah... peq peqa ewê ko a.
I was looking... now we are here... grass everywhere.
Mashallah... the bubbling of that water.
Hehê! Saat xweş.
Hey! Good hours.
Maşallah. Lê ji aran de je xarikîn dikirî bo milet e lê. Dûr
e iştê o diwê dido me we tê na...
Mashallah. People are coming down from the top... It's far,
there are two of us...
Xelî kon hala bicî wahed bikûn meho minfax.
Let's see if someone comes with a pump.
Tekerê wê ra do qatiye?
Is the tire double-layered?
Di qomên fextera ye? Mago wele min tuneye gelek bimir e
bilana rîko de darim gerk ha hûyî nê..
Is it torn? I said I swear I don't have it, it's very worn
out, I'm waiting on the road, I must inflate it..
Te dît çi ecwe me pêş wa kir? Ecwe xwaş e noka hem jûr ji
wero teswîr kin.
Did you see what atmosphere we created? The atmosphere is
nice, now we will film from the top too.
Obo!
Oh boy!
Maşellah heval no gel e millet...
Mashallah friends, there are a lot of people...
Millet hatine jor, li avê xwe pir pak e, binê jê guh qiym û
qiym, ba's yanî ba'sin e.
People have come up, the water is very clean, clear from the
bottom, enough, I mean it's enough.
Pak in e, o milet ev hew e her derêkê rûniştî ye. Xwe dikin,
ho, maşellah, wa di biniya binî xuya têt.
It is clean, the people have settled everywhere. Doing their
things, oh, mashallah, it's flowing clear from the very
bottom.
Tediye? Gelek qiym e.
You see? Very clear.
Maro ko anî li ve hawiyê rûniştiye bas te vê hawiyê
rûniştiyî te nikane devê xwe derkeve ber avê...
A man came and sat on this side, but you sat on this side,
you can't open your mouth in front of the water...
Yo hestire di jîre yo tike jûr herre. Secce cihê me noka
seyrana dîl e vire avê me hiwê kende...
You either slide down or go up. The place for our picnic now
is here, near the water...
Werin ha vîlyomê were. Oooh qale rayil e ko tediye qale
jûra.
Come on, come this way. Oooh how nice, you see, it's nice up
there.
Maşeallah... ajo yek pir xweşa! Me'nî hest naket çi.
Mashallah... it is a very nice atmosphere! Meaning he
doesn't feel anything.
Sa ke... tale talê ge ni ov ev div e dore... heta cêr ov,
cêr jî milet ev ê çûne bin doro rûniştine şebap xwe fer
dikin e.
Look... from top to bottom, water is all around... even
below, people have gone to sit under it, guys are spreading
out.
Ajwak pir xweş e... ev şelale ye ev me seyran dikin li vir
hember me ne av e bi dar e jêr...
It's a very nice atmosphere... there's the waterfall, we're
picnicking here right across from it, the water falls
down...
Tebî'an ew du rûne şemsê ge qad kirina hinî de şixul in...
Of course they cut off some of the sun to work...
Ne wa be ser sî pir bî... te vê derê yek dor hanîn ye ko te
xwe bin de se sî ye.
Otherwise there would be a lot of shade... here you can put
a circle to sit in the shade.
O nahasi ro xwe roxuye ... inuq wî kende bibî hek iz zehmet
bibe,
They are just enjoying themselves... it's a bit difficult
like this,
Noka dinê çikê germe qo yil e da mûtin e ... li kende milat
ew ere zehmet bibe.
Now the world is a bit hot... It will be hard for the people
here.
Sa ke. Wî dar e çoxse avê xwe pak e o bîn e ... de diyo? Paq
qiym!
Look. From this tree, the water is very clean, look... you
see? Clean and clear!
Av hebe heyat heye... heyat ji avê ye...
If there is water, there is life... life comes from water...
Min go av tune be heyat jî tuneye. Oo lê keyfê xwe dike,
keyf.
I said if there is no water, there is no life. Oh, enjoy it
yourself, fun.
Lê... Teba marke li ser we rûniştiye maro xwarê li vir
rûniştiye bo xê xê ser î kendo.
Look... Of course, some people sat up there, and those
sitting down there eat from the bottom.
Û paşê ro çêke dinê hîngî bî te xwe de avê de pîr xweş bî...
And below, wait a bit for the world to cool down, dip
yourself in the water, it's very nice...
Bas ayn hatine haş piçûkê xwe bin tim awetê mi dikin...
But they came with their kids, they complain to me...
Hoş piçûkê xwe bîn em bernadîn nê, milet xwe di binî dara we
re ne kin..
They brought their kids, we brought them, don't let them go
near the trees...
Li vir der jî ye ne... mektû e... miş tişt ev e dûr e na...
Here too it is... restricted... it's somewhat far...
Ya na xudê neke qazak bibe de wa unkel xobehayn keyfê wekî
we bernedîn kan çav wakin tîmê piçûk e piçûk e, zarok e xweş
amîne nizanîn.
God forbid if an accident happens, they come to me, they
look out for the kids so they don't fall, kids are small,
they don't know.
Paşê lome dikin bofko nav evê we de bibe, mmm.
Then they start complaining if they fall into the water,
mmm.
Ar e heval no em evê derkê jî am hatin gîştin pir e...
Yes friends, we came here too, there are many...
Pir e we pirro bernem wextek e savurun we ro.
The bridge, we'll film the bridge down there.
Mugu wextkê bere mes ev ra em hatin jor... li her derî milet
e ye. Mashalla... ajwa pir xweş a!
I said before we went down there... we came up... there are
people everywhere. Mashallah... the atmosphere is very nice!
Ah ... gidare derana ... ah erê ... herin qu tek e navê ...
no.
Ah... there's a path there... ah yes... they're hitting the
water... no.
A we re ko çûçk e û wî ... wirtê qan da kever dûr e ... çi e
a ne ke vere ok je çû ye a çêç kə karkurte xwe pir bi yê
Here a little one and... below the cover far from here...
under the cover, it fell down, her clothes got very wet.
Na çima tu ne me re lexistî a dayik te bi ba, hîna mi kiribû
we wîna ... qirika wî bar kir, çi xezeb dikî mi canê...
Then he got angry at me... she got wet... I said I didn't do
it... look at this place!
Haha wekî hanko cîgî bibî mlîm way! Ajway e pir xwaş e
slatenabe.
It's a very nice atmosphere, blessings upon the Prophet.
Qîçikê me yê lî kû der kîha ket e kîn avê? U lî ko kelyo
bend we kîn.
Where is our little girl, did she fall into the water? Cover
it well with tape.
A naxoşe we lawê la taba milet li gî dor o heya .. nî .. dor
ha bono dor hebûn e milet a hîn bî.
Let me tell you... of course there are people from all
around... yes... there were people all around.
Tabî dê re kê sak re kex jishke av.. bro jishk doxre ya.
Look at this path... brother, it's a straight path.
Bas evê li ti tek ebî evwelîtî li diq sha.
But at first you go down, at first you slide.
Maro celbeg bi xwe nî lîkrû .. eyqas bo û Mashaala.
We brought a rope with us, look at it... it was nice,
Mashallah.
Hawaja gam otin me dîrs wan e sawe ron dem difre. Tim pir ek
li derî wî dizî ay te bîn.
Look, we brought a lesson, we were filming, we were turning,
full, many at his door... you see.
Milet hatiye der an û milat gî kursî xwe kirse xwe - karsi
yo xlkn no vi ove khol rnısht n.
People have come here, people have brought their chairs -
brought chairs for this water to sit in.
Çi keyf lo. Kemiya avê re rind e, rind e, maşallah pir e,
hobi ko veqana yê di ro e tî di yo.
What a joy. The quantity of the water is very nice,
mashallah, it's abundant, you see... a good amount is
flowing over it.
Kemiye rind te ser. Yê hahî yayle jêr jî bigire.
Oh, taking the one below too...
Were. Were, me qîçka kiş ke ser tabê, noka kende bîkizê mebe
maqişka malî raylqîn e.
Come on. Come on, don't pull the girl to the edge, now if
she falls it will be difficult, that girl sitting on the
rail...
Ay lo mî keyf diki. Em qûçk bîn. Em qîçk bîn, em qîçk bîn,
me çoxse...
Hey, don't make me fall. Let's be little... we were little,
we were kids, so beautiful...
Me tiştek nizanî, ne xwem, ne xeswat,
We didn't know anything, neither talking...
kesî lê me adeb nediqir e yane...
no one judged us, you know...
Me çi jî diqir, af fî ma'fî bî, em noka mezin bîn e.
Whatever we did, we were forgiven, now we are grown up.
Noka ha wa ke qeder ecew bî, e qîçk bîn me diko tu sax ke
mezin...
It was nice at that time, we were kids, they told you to act
like a big person...
Am mezin bûn jî, am di xwe nas kir, am bi tev li nav
rûvîyan, qeçkan, lixwe am çûçik.
Even though we grew up, when we became self-aware, we were
all among foxes, girls, and we were kids ourselves.
Eştê... çûçikena rinde. Heyata xweda jî dar bi dar bê, xêre,
xema tîne nî, qisawet tîne nî... ta efo, efo.
Well... being a kid is good. In your life you go from tree
to tree, thank goodness it doesn't bring sorrow, it doesn't
bring worries... you just say sorry, sorry.
Ji me çî mesela, yek îşkî bike dibê qeçik e lo jehde bige.
For us, if you do something they say he is a kid, let him
be.
Mero mezin bê jê, şta kê hesabî tişta bike qisawet pir
dibin, ha wisa ha wilo.
If a grown man does something, calculating things, worries
increase, yeah, like that.
Erê ev holê, ava wuderê... ava jî bin erdê derdikeve...
Yeah, it's like this, the water here... this water comes out
from under the ground...
Gelek, av bî, qerimî bî. Vêderê jî germika, ava xoyna wekî
wuderê ye.
It was a lot, the water was very cold. Here is the warm
spring, the water of this place is like the water over
there.
Sekê, ecêb tenik e wî manê. Yanî zor pir qerimî bî.
Look, it's strangely thin, I mean. I mean it was very very
cold.
Binêre goqoyme tebîen goqoyme ha... dîtîye? Vira jî qeçikena
halemîye ha. Goqoyme...
Look, we jumped, naturally we jumped, look... see it? Here
the kids are swimming too, look. We jumped...
Ji qeçika ra pir rinde. Bes tişte, dorê wê hakême niçîçik
evê derê...
It's very good for kids. But the thing is, its
surroundings... I will dig a bit here...
Te hato jêrde, heto sedî meydonka derê...
You came down, down to the middle of the field...
Ha cîwek pir xweş e, eha.. qeçik nafetisin. Wêderê qeçik
nafetisin.
Yeah, it's a very nice place, here.. kids don't drown. Kids
don't drown there.
Yenî lawtina cam qeçkê xwe be jî adî ye yenî, te kîlekî
rine, devkî xwe de rine, adî ye.
I mean, even if you are with your kids, it's normal, I mean,
you can sit on the side, sit at the edge, it's normal.
Yanî na kûre, qeçik pê da narin, alçoq e.
I mean it's not deep, kids won't step into it, it's shallow.
Are wele, wooooh... ya selam ya selam... maşella.
Yeah by God, wooooh... oh my goodness, oh my goodness...
mashallah.
Ne me, me ezelî kirin, eqilê min giş şilpilik kirin, xayiyê
min ha xayîyê min ha.
We moved them out... oh we made everything soaking wet, oh
man, oh man.
Me şil pil kir in, hal binêre ez zirarê bi xwe dikim.
We made it soaking wet, look at the condition, I am doing
damage to myself.
Ez zirarê bi xwe dikim belkî lokal makîna me, makîne
biqemirine...
I am doing damage to myself, if the local machine gets wet,
our machine will burn out...
Bes, teslîm.
Enough, I surrender.
Erê ev holê, me vira jî qolo pir kir. Vira mesmeke ye, ez
nizanim berê mesmeke ye.
Yeah, this is how it is, we also dug a hole here. This is a
fishery, I don't know if it used to be a fishery.
Ev derê jî... mesmeke, çar nûh masî têdan e. Çar nûh. Yê
karp e yê reş e...
And this place... is a fishery, there are four types of fish
in it. Four types. Carp, black ones...
Yenî berê vî awatin xwe çeda dikirin. Ha gilê pilçikik we de
din tê de... a.
I mean, before they used to throw this in and make them.
Look, they throw a little piece of mud in it... yeah.
Gûl jî fer e ye û av jî, j'ava pak jî jûr de dikeve ser.
The pool is wide, and water, clean water falls on it from
above.
Mero çengilê xwe werê çêkê. Jîna, zêtena senara niqmişa û
minêştîrî ma pisêr.
A person should prepare his hook. We came, we don't have a
hook to drop and we buy, it doesn't matter.
Zixare, zixare.
It's small, small.
Zixare? Dibê çûçik e ne, xalo dibê...
It's small? He says it's a kid, uncle says...
Erê ev derê, xalo dibê berê ev mesmeke ye vir.
Yeah here, uncle says it used to be a fishery here.
Mesmeke yî Corciyawa bûye. Masîyê kîrniya e, mezin derxistin
e.
It was a Georgian fishery. They took out big carp fish.
Iqçîq e ne. Dibê di madê mezin dibin, dibin weznê gende du
kîlo. Di madê dibe du kîlo.
They are kids (small). He says in two months they get big,
they reach a weight of about two kilos. In two months they
become two kilos.
Eceb eyma hûr hane e. Hemî noko çen lextik a wera jor jî
çêkin. Teba milet ji ro heto jor rûştî...
It's strange, we have these details. They are all making
some parts up there now too. Of course, people from down to
up...
Têl jî vira va nêzîk e, helo imê jî de rexs e, kêfa, helo
imê bikêf e.
The wire (border) is also close here, look, we are also
dancing, joy, look we are joyful.
Ha ha ha milet ronîştî heto jor. Têl jî weleku himber me ye
bi cîkî gindî xwe tê. Têl hember me ye nêzîk e.
Hahaha, people are sitting all the way up. The wire is also
opposite us, coming to a place like this. The wire is
opposite us, it's close.
Mave, mave. Maşella.
Let it be, let it be. Mashallah.
Erê ev holê, li vê derê jî am giştin... vira... gelîyê horî,
gelîyê horî.
Yeah, it's like this, and here we have all arrived...
here... at the Horî valley, Horî valley.
Erê am giştin vira. Hema nuko laxtoke di do yê vira jî
çêkin.
Yeah, we arrived here. Right now they are doing some things
here too.
Û amê xatirê xwe ji wa bixwezin. Vê em rawestiyan, rê dûr e
û dinya jî germ e...
And we will say goodbye to you. We stopped here, the road is
long and the weather is hot...
Me kêm nekiriye, em gêj bîn wele.
We didn't fall short, we got dizzy, by God.
Lê rind e. Menteqe honex... av be. Milet xwêr tê seyranxwe,
rind e. Çi hebe rind e, çi hebe rind e.
But it's good. The area like this... with water. People come
here for picnics, it's good. Whatever there is, it's good,
whatever there is, it's good.
Wer wer pê bika we. Ho, wer tebika we.
Come, come, step on it. Oh, come step on it.
Bes vine, bes vine.
Enough of this, enough of this.
Wê min... ho ro, ho ro avîyê. Namsiz bûyê.
Oh man... look, look at the water. It became ungrateful.
Erê hevalo li vê derkê jî em geştin taliyê vîdyoyê xwe.
Yeah friends, here we have also reached the end of our
video.
Înşella wê vîdyoyê me bi ecibînin. Berê me xelqe di berda
gelek çêkiriye.
God willing you will like our video. Previously we have made
many episodes.
Ena hacet kî yana ez ge yê waro pêşkêş kim.
There's no need, I will present it like this.
Xelqe, bere jê me eşta wido xestiya û kunê herin lê seyir
kin û xelqê... yê wisa tişkin li ser kin.
Episodes, previously we wanted it like this and you can go
and watch it and the episodes... you can do something like
that on it.
Teqsîr, meqsîr hebî yane qisirê me ji ef kin. Horo vîdyoya
me hona bî cevlata em derdixin in.
If there were any shortcomings, I mean forgive our faults.
This was our video, we take tours.
Ma gû mile ho rû vîdêyo me jê tebî'a be ono seke tiştê xwêş
ma pêşwekirin...
I said our video is natural, like this, look at the nice
things we presented...
Ba maro bî duso vîdyokî xwêş û kîbar e me wer in nêzîk da
dax in.
Let's see, with another nice and elegant video we will drop
by soon.
Û kesê gund ji maxwastine ji, unê li me biburin, înşela
nêzîk da amê wa rû bibexşin in.
And anyone who wanted their village from us, please forgive
us, God willing soon we will grant it to them.
Erê wela, di maşela dest me rî ya wû da'wato dar o ...
fersend naketi me go am herin gunda teswîrê xweş bikin.
Yeah by God, mashallah we have a lot of work and wedding
invitations... we didn't get the chance to go and film the
villages nicely.
Ma gû hor am derkevin barî, xelkê ma ona der e Heleb...
We said let's go out at least, our people are there in
Aleppo...
De sere sol ma wo ke, neqilket te ca, me, da wê ra ji ma go
arî, no maşe...
At the beginning of the year we moved to that place, we said
we would help, it didn't happen...
Erê welah ho şit çiqta mirov dimirin, barê însanî bere na
dimirin. Am mirov xu da dibin heştê nut...
Yeah by God, look how many people die, they didn't use to
die like this in the past. We reach eighty, ninety...
Am derbîst yik mirî. E nukar... deh salî, pênc salî, da pênc
salî.
We passed one dead. Now... ten years old, five years old,
fifteen years old.
Çiqte milet dimire... No gundê ma de, berekat çend in, am
dibin bareket d... bî çend gundê ma, bî çar-pênc. Ser hev
de.
So many people die... In our village, how many blessings
there are, we say blessing... it was how many in our
village, it was four-five. Consecutively.
Ser hev da. Da'wet û qeleng û şahî, heflet o... Xwedê rehma
xwo l' giya ki, cîyê wa cinet be.
Consecutively. Invitations, dowries and joy, parties... May
God have mercy on them all, may their place be paradise.
Dê rîko me giyê... Erê wela horî wîdyo ho na bî. Qisûrî me
ji efo kin.
This is everyone's path... Yeah by God, this was our video
like this. Forgive our faults.
Wîdyo me go afo yi, da... çe wê we giyê maştikî, bay bay.
I said our video is a pardon... whatever it is... bye bye.
Wele ko îqra biriciyal ey, ev qebir o...
By God, look they read on the men, this is a grave...
Erê hevalno, lê vê derê jê, xwarinek min.. ha e... ont
kirîye, lê vê derê.
Yeah friends, here too, I ordered.. yeah.. some food, here.
Emkê farûca wera derjekin, me farûc unt kirîye.
We will prepare chicken for you, we ordered chicken.
Awê ra dibên seeta gindê xweş, Xudê... onte dilê gindî
beke...
For this they say beautiful hours, may God... fulfill the
wishes of the village...
Û Xudê bereketê balokê... rehme l'miriyê gindî bin je...
And may God bring blessings... mercy upon the dead of the
village too...
Erê. Ê dû... non bî, non bî. Û farûc o. Unt kirîye... Ekê...
bale kê.
Yeah. Those two... it was bread, it was bread. And chicken.
Ordered... We will... distribute it.
E m' gu em vê ra derjekin, le vera bar zewiya Şêx Reşîd,
uh..
I said we will put it out here, here by the shrine of Sheikh
Rashid, uh..
Xudê qebûl ke. Xudê berekatê belav ke.
May God accept it. May God spread blessings.
Erê, xwarinê min îştar, wun ona amkê noko la we k'mer a
derjeke.
Yeah, my food is ready, now we will put it out for you here.
Ko... me nexwî dernekeve begere.
Because... it won't come out if we don't eat it, turn it.
De temam ko bi mero be, mulo derjekin mehnê xûn dernakive.
Ok then, if you're a man, put it out so blood doesn't spill.
Erê havolo lêvî derkê jî, teben xwarinek me naye... vi derê
mero taboro' kir.
Yeah friends, here too, of course we have some food... here
someone donated.
Am kê... nonê balo kin.
We will... distribute the bread.
Û amkê çend farocaji derje ke.
And we will take out a few chickens too.
Amkê da daw beş farujaji amki le feqira balaken.
We will distribute ten, twelve, fifteen chickens among the
poor.
Erê ever dibim saetek hendi xweş, xwedê bereketê balav ke.
They call this beautiful times of the village, may God
spread blessings.
Mexne xwarinek hendiye, awê... onda keriye, ku balave kem.
Meaning it's a food of the village that they ordered. I will
distribute it.
Ami wer dibin saetek hendi xweş, xwedê bereketê belav ke...
We call this beautiful times of the village, may God spread
blessings...
Xwedê miroziya dile wi ji beke. Wû xudê qebûl ke ji. Wo be
ber desta meriya wejî gene.
May God fulfill his heart's desire. And may God accept it
too. And may it fall into your hands too.
Ami noko naniya xwe belaken. Ari woro ber game ma.
We will now distribute our bread. Yeah, wait in front of our
step.
Sibe duje eza kî evira be Şêx Reşid cî, piştino azki firo...
Tomorrow I will be here at Sheikh Rashid's place, afterwards
I will...
Sibe de ji ez kê vêre ber Şêx Reşîd cî. Badîn a, ez kê firo,
de pênc faroj e, akê darce kim, akê belov kim.
Tomorrow too I will come here by Sheikh Rashid. Afterwards,
I will, ten, fifteen chickens, I will put them out, I will
distribute them.
Kese ku xwarina wî nagihê ye. Milû wêjî weke da bi xêra
gindê yê bî. Seta gindiya xwaş.
For anyone whose food doesn't reach them. Let them also do
it so it is for the charity of the village. Beautiful times
of the village.
Û dîsa em dibin Xwedê bereketê belav ke. Nozlo, wer nozlo,
wer.
And again we say, may God spread blessings. Nozlo, come
Nozlo, come.
Teba ev nan e, nan.. e, her yekî du rabta ne. Wêre, bi rê ve
ne hewaş, hawaş.. hi.
Naturally this is bread, bread.. yeah, two wraps for each.
Come, carefully, slowly, slowly.. yes.
Bigre eva na, matev e.. male we yê, yê weş. Ev na yê male we
yê.
Take this, this is for all.. for your house, okay. This is
for your house.
Evê ji bibe mela ofîna şert... Çar rabta he... Ev ne. Haa.
Take this one to the office's house as a condition... Four
wraps here... This one. Yes.
Wev jî bibe mala xalî Mehma. Û ve jî wêre bibe mala metê
Nisrî.
And take this to uncle Mehma's house. And come take this to
aunt Nisrî's house.
Wanê jê, heşet, yêş, yêş... ewa! Nin ne di bin en! Min ba
nakirin mi go?
Those too, slowly, slowly, slowly... hey! Bread shouldn't
fall! Didn't I call out and say?
Havoyê jê bibe mola... mola Ezîz ro. Von e jêr.
Take this one to... Aziz's house. Down there.
Ew lawe kê ye? Ee... ware evo ê Fatmê di ye, he Fatmê di ye.
Whose boy is that? Uh... come, this is Fatme's, yeah
Fatme's.
Xwedê bereketê balo ke. Un ce noko bibin jêr ew biki...
May God spread blessings. You guys take it down now and do
that...