Ka ev çiye? Ji me ra li ser vê bêje.
What is this? Tell us about this.
Heva hekîb e, vêra dibên hekîb.
This is a saddlebag, they call this a hekîb.
Ka ev çiye? Ji me ra li ser vê bêje.
What is this? Tell us about this.
Heva hekîb e, vêra dibên hekîb.
This is a saddlebag, they call this a hekîb.
Ka ev çiye? Ji me ra li ser vê bêje.
What is this? Tell us about this.
Heva hekîb e, vêra dibên hekîb.
This is a saddlebag, they call this a hekîb.
Ax em ketine derbaz nake, mala Xalû li kîderê ye?
Ah, we entered a dead end, where is Uncle's house?
Ew mala jêr.
That house down there.
Ew mala jêr?
That house down there?
Kîderê ye Xalû?
Where is it, Uncle?
Erê hevalno, em hatine mala Xalû, livê derê Xalû sê qîzkêt
xwe hene, Xudê jêra bihêle.
Yes friends, we have come to Uncle's house, here Uncle has
three daughters, may God preserve them for him.
Qîzkêt wî jî her sê moaq in. Her sê.
His daughters are all three disabled. All three.
Xalû, lawik hene te?
Uncle, do you have a boy?
Yek e.
There is one.
Ew jî wusa ye?
Is he like that too?
Ew jî kûyt e.
He is also disabled.
Yanî çar ta hene, her çar ewha ne?
Meaning there are four, all four are like that?
Erê. Sê qîzik û lawkê.
Yes. Three girls and the boy.
Weleh gune ne. Yekî..
By God, it's a pity. One...
Erê erê, weleh gune ne.
Yes, yes, by God it's a pity.
Erê hevalno, qîzika nikanin pirr derkevin, qîzik ciwan e,
nabe derkevin.
Yes friends, the girls cannot come out much, the girl is
young, it's not appropriate for them to come out.
Erê, weleh wilo ye.
Yes, by God it is so.
Na, her male, her.
No, just stay home, stay.
Lêka li hember me ne, em naxwazin pirr nêzîk bikin, yanî ew
ne gune ne jî, me'nê gundî ye..
Look, they are opposite us, we don't want to get too close,
meaning they are innocent too, it's the village custom...
Sê qîzik û lawkî, evna moaq in. Xudê emrê Xalû dirêj bike.
Three girls and a boy, these are disabled. May God give
Uncle a long life.
Xalû, tu çawa îdareyê li van mesref dikî lê?
Uncle, how do you manage the expenses for them?
Lawo de hişta, bi te'bê xwe ne, bi milkê xwe ne.
Oh son, let it be, it's by my own effort, with my own
property.
Îdare dibe terê wana?
Is the income enough for them?
Lawo de hişta, îdare, hemkî dibrin îdare, gunkî Xudê emrê...
îdare nakin de ha...
Oh son, let it be, managing... we just get by, servants of
God... if we don't manage then what...
Rêve diçin? diçin taran waran?
Do they walk? Do they go here and there?
Na na, nikanin herin.
No no, they cannot walk.
Nikanin?
They cannot?
Li erdê mal in ha.
They are [crawling] on the ground at home like that.
Fuqara.
Poor things.
Deko, lawik çûye ber... derketiye derve belkî.
Look, the boy has gone to... has gone outside maybe.
Xudê emrê te dirêj bike, Xalû.
May God prolong your life, Uncle.
Erê hevalno, inşallah kesê xêrxwaz hebin, me ra tewasul kin.
Tabean reqemê mi jî li ser e, reqemê mi l'jûr e.
Yes friends, God willing, if there are charitable people,
contact us. Of course, my number is on it, my number is up
there.
Kesê bixwaze, bi Xalû ra alîkar be. Tabean Xalû dengê xwe
digihîne milet. Miletekî xêrxwaz.
Anyone who wants to help Uncle. Of course, Uncle is raising
his voice to the people. A charitable people.
Xalû dengê xwe bilind ke, milet ra ê, hîta seyr kin.
Uncle, raise your voice, so the people... so they can watch.
Ê, tu zanî...
Eh, you know...
Hişta vî miletî... ewî gundo... ta'bî gundo, mesrefê gundo,
tiştekî, şixul nînin.
Leave this people... this village... the struggle of the
village, the expenses of the village, something... there are
no jobs.
Em nakin navê... weke lawik û pîrekê wî çûne aforê katin,
aforê qatîkin.
We don't mention the name... like the boy and his wife went
to the harvest, to do the harvest.
Çûne aforê zeytûna?
They went to the olive harvest?
Ê, aforê zeytûna.
Yes, the olive harvest.
Erê Xalû dibêjin jinik û lawik va jî çûne aforê zeytûna.
Yes, Uncle says the wife and the boy also went to the olive
harvest.
Me'nî şixul tina ye, me'nî xizmet, vê keçiknoka... vê
keçikno jî...
Meaning there is no work, meaning service... these girls...
these girls too...
Xudê jê razî be, mezin e jî, bîlyo ne, emrê gende teqrîben
bîst hene ne?
May God be pleased with them, they are big too, grown up,
their age is approximately twenty, right?
Ser bîsta ra ne.
They are over twenty.
Ser bîsta ra?
Over twenty?
Deşallah kesê xêrxwaz hebe, me ra tewasul kin. Tabean reqemê
mi mewcûd e, kesê bixwaze xêrek xwa bike, em kanin dîsa
werin xûb mala Xalû gînin.
God willing, if there is a charitable person, contact us. Of
course, my number is available, anyone who wants to do a
good deed, we can come again and bring them to Uncle's
house.
Ser çava, ser çava.
You are welcome, you are welcome.
Wate jî xweş, û inşallah, em naken gelek biçin teswîr kin,
ji ber ku, Xalû naxwaze ew bikin.
The situation is good, and God willing, we won't go in to
film much, because Uncle doesn't want to do that.
Yanî, ser çê, ciyê kimsûra ye. Em naxwazin ew bikin.
Meaning, upon [my] eye, it's a place of women/privacy. We
don't want to do that.
Hilqe hona bî. Bi me ra bin dîsa. Videokî xweş û kîbar.
Let the episode be like this. Stay with us again. A nice and
neat video.
Emê noka werin, ew bikin, parçê hîdê emê werin teswîr kin, û
zotir emê xatirê xwe ji wa bixwazin, bi me ra bin.
We will come now, do that, we will come film the other part,
and soon we will say goodbye to you, stay with us.
Yalla, spas dikim.
Okay, thank you.
Tabean terbê gundî jî, livê derê ne.
Of course, the village paths are also here.
Xalû, divê rê darê meydanê ne? Rê çûyîna meydanê?
Uncle, you say this road is to the square? The road going to
the square?
Erê rêkî darê meydanê ye. Ê!
Yes, it's the road to the square. Yes!
Hew jî rê be, hewa?
Even if the road is... like this?
No no, ev rê kimin e.
No no, this road is a trap [very bad].
Hew jî tê be, ew kirî ye?
Even so... is it done?
Na erê erê.
No, yes yes.
Welleh, qirêj e.
By God, it's dirty [rough].
Xudê emrê ki dirêj pê de, Xudê emrê ki dirêj pê de.
May God give [you] a long life, may God give [you] a long
life.
Hewayê kû tê de darê meydanê?
The air that comes in the square?
Ez teryê çûme, teryê çûme.
I went earlier, I went earlier.
Tema, tebîetek pirr xweş e.
Look, nature is very beautiful.
Erê de hişta, mi çî ji te ra ne, ka ke.
Yes, let it be, what should I [say] to you, look at it.
Hewayê kû hatbû, kû derê? Hatbû bibile?
The air that came... where? Did it come to Bibile?
Welleh, yek pirr gund hene di kefê me, wellehil 'ezîm.
By God, there are many villages in our mind/list, by God the
Almighty.
Hin êr bi dilî me ranadixîn, hin miletî gundo jî êr bi dilî
me ranadixîn.
Some don't lay the ground to our liking, some village people
don't lay the ground to our liking (don't welcome us).
Wellehil 'ezîm, tiştekî min noka dişewite, sok memê... ew
kirî.
By God the Almighty, something inside me is burning now,
look at... that thing.
Or bizike me kat.
Turn us around [to the driver].
Jêr, hewşêt wa pirr ne, welleh hêli jî heye.
Below, their courtyards are large, by God there is a nest
too.
Maşallah, hewa hênik e.
Mashallah, the air is cool.
Hew hewşên kene, rat wi... ortê do.
These are their courtyards, right in... the middle.
Hêşta vala ye.
It's still empty.
Her dûr e, bi dûr e.
It's still far, it's far.
Erê hevalno, livê derê jî em li mefraqê Mamola ne, cambê
darê, vê tebîetê.
Yes friends, here we are at the Mamola junction, the side of
the trees [forest], this nature.
Erê gundî Bililko jî, hûnê qusûrê 'af kin. Gundî Bililko me
pirr nekane bisawiranda.
Yes, the village of Bililko too, you will forgive the fault.
We couldn't film the village of Bililko much.
Ama kin nehebin, ê kimsûra bîn, me nekanî teswîr kiro.
There were no places [to film], they were private [women's
area], we couldn't film.
Û rêka xwe jî pirr çetin bî, ge xarabe bî, ge herrî bî jî.
And their road was very difficult, very ruined, very muddy
too.
Inşallah emê wara bi 'ewdînin.
God willing, we will return to you.
Ezê noka, ber vê me ba rac û kirî, ya kî ba rac û arim.
I will now... [turn back/face the slope].
Miletî gundî Bililko qusûrê 'af kin, me nekanî gundê we rind
teswîr kiro. Hûnê pirr qusûrê 'af kin.
People of Bililko village, forgive the fault, we couldn't
film your village well. You will forgive the fault very
much.
Rêk çetin bî, kesî me ra amakin hawal nadin. Milet me digot
wara em kê derkab in, me ra hewal din, dar biken.
The road was difficult, no one gave us a place or
opportunity to talk. We asked people to come out, talk to
us, do something.
Ê milet, pirrek naxwaz darkev e, me jî naxwaz em gundya
ihrac kin.
Eh, the people, many don't want to come out, we also don't
want to embarrass the villagers.
Me'ne we merno jî, wanê me ra derkatin e.
Meaning, [regarding] those men too, the ones who came out to
us.
Kesê dogze gundya ra alîkar be.
Anyone who wants to be helpful to the villagers.
Tabean, giniyê xwa jî çakir istim Xalû.
Of course, I heard his condition too, Uncle.
Kesê dogze vê ro, tabarru' ke, reqemê mi l'sar e, kanin me
ra tewasul kin, û bicavî xwa, ez ê xwa pî ginî me.
Anyone who wants to donate to him today, my number is on
[the screen], you can contact us, and with your own eyes, I
will bring you there myself.
Ya herom, sê qîzik û lawkî ne, avna, na mezbût ne, mo'aq ne.
It's a tragedy, three girls and a boy, these, they are not
healthy, they are disabled.
Xudê emrê kî dirêj pê de, Xudê jê razî be.
May God give them a long life, may God be pleased with them.
Bi me ra bin dîsa, videokî xweş û kîbar, emê wara inşallah
doxîn. Gul e gul e.
Stay with us again, a nice and neat video, we will show you
God willing. Bye bye.