Te çi got beg? Belkî ehlê sirkê zone bin?
What did you say, sir? Maybe they are vinegar people?
Em hatin vê derê masiya... em bûn narinde, em kovan bûn
narinde... em kovan û xirab bikim.
We came here for fish... we became [narinde/pomegranate], we
became sad [narinde]... let me be sad and destroy it.
Bûm narinde, narinde... Heta marê weyî dibêji, hoto bikun
emrê name...
I became [narinde], [narinde]... Until the snake preaches to
you, [unintelligible]...
Lo milet çi tîtir tune ye... vî wextî... vî davî... vî deran
da.
Oh people, there is nothing else... in this time... in this
era... in these places.
Rojbaş hevalno, xwişkno, birano. Çûne? Şolê şîwa rind be?
Good day friends, sisters, brothers. How are you? Hope your
affairs are good?
Erê hevalno, hûru vîdyoyê me, em hatin Efrîn.
Yes friends, our video today, we came to Afrin.
Vîdyoyê me jî em hûru hatine, em kê werin gundê 'Enderê bi
sewirînin.
For our video today, we came here, we will go film the
village of Andara.
Erê, gundê 'Enderê jî gundekî pir xweşik û kîbar e cîmaet.
Ez jê maq westîne.
Yes, the village of Andara is also a very beautiful and nice
village, folks. I missed it.
Lê nî mentîqê me ra cû hoda, gelek berf e.
But in our region regarding the weather, there is a lot of
snow.
Berf pir e li manikonê têketê gunda. Dinya jî bûye xuyzik...
wê derê tenikonê têketê gunda.
There is a lot of snow at the corners of the village
entrances. The weather has become misty... at those places
at the village entrances.
Lê vira cema mentîqê Efrîn jî çîçke berf haliye, ê em magu
em han vir teswîr kin.
But here, dear folks, in the Afrin region only a little snow
is left, so we said let's come film here.
Bi me ra bin vîdyokî xweş û kîbar, emê na were nav gund
teswîr kin.
Stay with us for a nice and lovely video, we will go film
inside the village.
Ti şaşbînî maşbînê me jî hene û yine pir qusûrî me efû kin,
vîdyê me ekserî ge efewî ne. Mazên gotinê te hene?
We have some mistakes and errors, forgive our many
shortcomings, our videos are mostly spontaneous. Mazen, do
you have anything to say?
Sibe we bi xêr hevalê me, hûn çûne, şîwa çûye, sihet çûye?
Good morning our friends, how are you, how are things, how
is your health?
İnşalla bê rind be, bi has bin. Erê îro jî me berê xwe da vî
gundî.
God willing you are well and happy. Yes, today we headed to
this village.
'Enderê, em kê derbasî zindê 'Enderê bin. Bi me ra bin.
Andara, we will enter the vicinity of Andara. Stay with us.
Vîdyekî xweş û kîbar e em çêkin. Û bîr mekin me ra layk û
îştîrakê pêkin û teelîqne xweş û kîbar binivîsînin.
We will make a nice and lovely video. And don't forget to
like and subscribe for us, and write nice and lovely
comments.
Erê, hûru baharxweş jî me ra derketiye. Baharxweş jî me ra
hatiye.
Yes, today the nice spring weather has come out for us too.
The nice weather has come for us.
Erê, erê berf me ra teswîr dike.
Yes, yes, filming the snow for us.
Me go miş hema gilxana, em kan kişan gundî.
We said... [unintelligible]... let's go to the village.
Me go ox nebî miş hema 'Enderê... 'Enderê vî derê wehîd berf
tûne ye. Bes sar e welle.
We said hopefully Andara... Andara is the only place here
with no snow. But it is cold, by God.
Cewo mentîqê me bigrin hoda? Dadê ser wê derê gelek berf e.
How did they capture our region...? Dad/Brother, up there,
there is a lot of snow.
Gelek berf e. O Efrîn e, em ber me ya.
It's a lot of snow. That is Afrin, in front of us.
Tebeen 'Enderê jî ji Efrîn va ne dûr e. Nîzik e. Sê çar
kîlometre ne?
Of course, Andara is not far from Afrin. It is close. Is it
three or four kilometers?
Erê welle. De anca sê çar dên berf dar be hale. Em were dîsa
derbasî gunda bin.
Yes, by God. So there are barely three or four grains of
snow left. We will enter the villages again.
Bes seke mentîqê me. Maşalla, salek xêr bîr e.
But look at our region. Mashallah, it has been a bountiful
year.
Îsal ekîd xêr e. Yanî berfê lê kir, salê hacer.
This year is definitely bountiful. Meaning, it snowed, a
solid year.
Berf jî rind e, ana dihelê... yavaş yavaş erd bî melhem.
Bira em ber me ge bextewar nîza, ge qit kirin.
Snow is good too, now it melts... slowly the earth becomes
ointment/healed. Brother, in front of us, they seem very
happy, they cut across.
De ko em herin nav gundî... 'Enderê. Ko bi me ra bin
hevalno.
So let's go into the village... Andara. So stay with us
friends.
Erê hevalno, me dest pê kir vî derê.
Yes friends, we started here.
Dinya çîçke ne sar e, millet gi di hundurê da ye, pir sar e.
The weather is a bit... no it's cold, the people are all
inside, it is very cold.
Selam aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Wa aleykum selam.
And upon you peace.
Şukran, ya'tîk el afye.
Thanks, may God give you health.
Maşalla gundekî kîbar e.
Mashallah, it is a nice village.
Erê hevalno, berê qenaya avê jî ji vira tê hat.
Yes friends, look, the water canal also came through here.
Gundekî xweş û kîbar e. Bere işte... gunahkî me dît, av ji
vira dihat.
It's a nice and lovely village. Look here... it was a pity
we saw, the water used to come from here.
Vê milletê vî gundî kêf dikir. Pe milkê xwe av didan dag
dikirin.
The people of this village used to enjoy it. They used to
water their property and irrigate.
Erê welle, ev der jî... Ev der e berê gelek gulê avê bî,
kanî bî.
Yes, by God, this place too... This is the place where there
used to be many water flowers, it was a spring.
E kanî jî hişk bîye.
And the spring has dried up.
Ne me go şta... cefaf çêbî... e... pir kanî hişk bûn.
Didn't we say... a drought occurred... uh... many springs
dried up.
Vê derê berê kanî bî, tije av bî. Belkî ehlê sêrkin zanibin.
This place used to be a spring, it was full of water. Maybe
those watching will know.
Em dihatin vê derê masiya jî... Me masî digirtin, yek... Av
nema.
We used to come here for fish too... We used to catch fish,
one... There is no water left.
Erê welle. Viro berê gelek dar bûn, av bî...
Yes, by God. Here used to be many trees, there was water...
Milet dihat xwarinê, sîyahê.
People used to come to eat, for tourism.
Ev tebîeta vê gundî ye. Maşalla... teben ev gund jî me...
yanî meşhûr e.
This is the nature of this village. Mashallah... of course,
this village of ours too... meaning, it is famous.
Kerzêlê, Basûtê... bi aliyê bîstana da... hêşînayî da, pir
hêşînayî diçînin.
Kurzêlê, Basûtê... towards the orchards... in the greenery,
they plant a lot of greens.
Gundekî mezin e. Erê welle. Ne herim e vê ava li vê derê
hişk bî.
It is a big village. Yes, by God. It is a pity that this
water here has dried up.
Erê welle. Seh ke ho ho çiyayê mezin berf e. Bes vê derê
kurt e, halî ye.
Yes, by God. Look, look, the big mountain has snow. But here
it is low, it is empty.
Erê welle, çok dilê mi ber dişewite. Xelkê ji Helebê, ji
dera dihatin vê derê zîyara.
Yes, by God, my heart burns for it a lot. People from
Aleppo, from places used to come here for visits.
Bin vê derê gelek dar bûn, av pir bî, xelk dihat xwar û
rûnişt seyrana.
Below here there were many trees, water was plentiful,
people came to eat and sit for picnics.
Me go deh salê baran moran ne lê ke, av... wane bi kaniya
were... Erê welle.
We said [even if] for ten years rain doesn't fall, water...
would come from the springs... Yes, by God.
We dîna... gelek dar... gelek darê silf hebûn, gelek dar
bûn. Milet tê lê sêrke wînê zanibin.
You saw... many trees... there were many cypress trees,
there were many trees. People who come to look will know.
Hişk bî. Mantiqa... 5 salan şûnda çû.
It dried up. The area... went back 5 years.
Me go 5 salan şûnda çû.
We said it went back 5 years.
De şolê dîsa wekî berê biftile...
So that the situation turns back like before again...
Mişkila dar neman. Dar hebin, cew pak dibe, telewus cew pak
dike... ba tê... yanî rûtûbet çêdibe.
The problem is no trees remain. If there are trees, the
weather becomes clean, it cleans the pollution of the
weather... wind comes... meaning humidity is created.
Noka ecêbî xê dora diçîne. Darê merxê darê... wê darê merxê
delê... ewî cazibîye dikişîne dê li ewr dar çêbibin.
Now strangely [it] plants around itself. The pine tree...
the heart of that pine tree... it pulls attraction, clouds
will form at the tree.
Cew pak dike... ba tê... yanî rûtûbet çêdibe, dê lê baran
lêke.
It cleans the weather... wind comes... meaning humidity is
created, rain will fall on it.
Berê ez radibûm ser gundê Hisênmiderî, wane ewr xetimî bî li
gundo da.
Before I used to get up above the village of Hisênmiderî,
the clouds were thick in the villages.
Kurta da. Ê noka jî ewê merxana tenê ne. Ê çibîye? Ez sibê
radibim qa cinsî xerbî tê ne.
In short. And now too those pines are alone. And what
happened? I get up in the morning, as if a kind of western
dust comes.
Berê ge xerbî bî wekî ewra, ser gund dapo dasekinî. Xêr e ge
dar wa dike, dar dikişîne. Gelek qal bûn, merx bûn.
Before when it was western wind like clouds, it stood
covering the village. It is good when trees do that, the
tree attracts. They were very thick, they were pines.
Kanî hişk... û neha jî şta... bistanê da ne... çilî daro ge
weşîye... hêşînayî kêm e. Erê welle.
The spring is dried... and now too... in the orchard... the
appearance of the trees has faded... greenery is less. Yes,
by God.
Ecêb kî bi şev hatim vê kaniyê, mi çend masî jî derxistin.
Strangely when I came to this spring at night, I took out
several fish too.
Weh! Gelek masî wane tê de bûn.
Wow! Many fish were in it.
Cihê kî rêkê ziftê ji me ra çêkin, rêkê ziftê çêkin, îşaretê
çêkin, îşaretê mirûr çêkin...
Where they make asphalt roads for us, make asphalt roads,
make signs, make traffic signs...
Lê? Me'ne hadîs çê nebin. No. Cema'et mentiqa me pir hadîs
çêdibin, xêr e?
But? So that accidents don't happen. No. Friends, in our
area many accidents happen, what is wrong?
Îşewda Xwedê heye tina dajo.
By God's will, there is, he drives fast.
Îşewda Xwedê heye tina dajo, ê qçkê hûr dajo.
By God's will, there is, he drives fast, the small kid
drives.
Emrê... di bin hivde salî re qedexe ye. Li Ewropa di bin
hijde salî şofêrtiyê bajo.
Age... under seventeen years old is forbidden. In Europe
[one must be] under eighteen years old to drive.
Lê? Cema'et hana paş direksiyon daxwîna tê.
But? The group here comes behind the steering wheel while
blood is boiling.
Lê? No, zift pak çêbibe, îşaret çêbibin.
But? No, if the asphalt is made clean, signs are made.
Me'nî milet zane be, ê pir xweş bibe.
Meaning if the people are knowledgeable, it will be very
good.
De înşallah ew jî çêbe.
So God willing, that will happen too.
Ê dîsa... ew bibe.
And again... let that be.
Miletî, paşî em kerman, cem cebar ne, em ê wekî berê bikin,
em ê ji berê rindtir bikin înşallah bi izna Xwedê.
The people, afterwards we represent generosity, with the
restorers, we will make it like before, we will make it
better than before, God willing, with God's permission.
Tebe'en, em kê bi hev de henek, em kê hev de pîs nekin.
Of course, let's joke with each other, let's not make each
other look bad.
E ne ekî bibin wele... heva rind û heva ne rind e... işte...
Let's not be like... well... good with each other and bad
with each other... you know...
E bibim ne rind e, e tu bibî ne rind e, ew be ne rind e, de
tîr em ta'v de em xera bin. Bes em kê, işte hev de musameha
kin, em kê...
If I become bad, and you become bad, and he becomes bad,
then completely we will all be ruined. But we should, you
know, tolerate each other, we should...
İşte bidestî hev de bigirin, em kê kelek hev de sekinin.
You know, hold each other's hands, we should stand beside
each other.
Musameha rind e. Wa zanî?
Tolerance is good. You know?
Lê? Noka ez çoxsê bibim hevo ne rind e, ekî min bibim ne
rind e, ekî min xera bikim. Bibim ne rind e, ne rind e.
But? Now when I become bad with this one, my side becomes
bad, I ruin my side. If I become bad, it is bad.
Bes nê çoxsê ne rind be, ekî bim nê rind e. Ez ê bim rind e,
me'nî...
But if the time is bad, let me be good. I will be good,
meaning...
Em destê xwe bidestî hev kin, em dîsa wek berê biftilin...
Let's join our hands together, let's turn back to how we
were before...
We em hey... dinya çi ye? Dinya boş e. Dinya boş.
And we hey... what is the world? The world is empty. The
world is empty.
Emrê me giş çend sal in? Em çend sal in ji heyatî dijîn? Em
giş bîst pênc salan ji heyatî xwe dijîn.
How many years is all our age? How many years of life do we
live? We all live twenty-five years of our lives.
Pirs kin, ew çend salan ji heyatî xwe dijîn.
Ask, how many years of their lives do they live.
Însan çend salan dijî? Heftê sal, şêst pênc sal.
How many years does a human live? Seventy years, sixty-five
years.
Ê... xeyo heftê sal. Jê sî pênc sal şev e. Te heyat nedî, te
xew dikir.
So... let's say seventy years. Of that, thirty-five years is
night. You didn't see life, you were sleeping.
Ewa şev tî. Ma sî pênc sal te.
That one is gone as night. Thirty-five years remain for you.
Jê... ji yeksaliyê heta dav pênc saliyê tu sinêt mironqa, te
heyat tişt fehm nekirî?
From... from one year old until fifteen years old, you are
in the age of adolescence, you haven't understood anything
of life?
Te heyat tişt fehm nekirî, teyî bê dinya ne hesiyayî.
You haven't understood anything of life, you haven't sensed
the world without [experience].
Ma çoxso? Ma dav pênc sal te.
What remains? Fifteen years remain for you.
Wê dav pênc sal no jiy e, heta te bi heyatî dinyê da 'almî,
heta te bi... bi lezzetî dinyê da hesî...
Those fifteen years aren't just that, until you learn about
the life of the world, until you... sense the pleasure of
the world...
Bikon te zewicî, te qçik, ew bîn û xem û qiswet... çûyî. Te
dav pênc salan ji heyatî xwe dijî, bîst salan.
Because you married, you had kids, those brought grief and
worry... gone. You live fifteen years of your life, twenty
years.
Ha o çi ye? Nîvî te bi xewê derbas dike. Bi şev.
Ha, what is that? You spend half of it sleeping. At night.
Ribik jî te... çûçik e, te nizanî. Lezzetî dinyê te nizanî.
A quarter of it too you are... small, you don't know. You
don't know the pleasure of the world.
Heta mero we'î dibe jî, qorqa bikon emr namîne.
By the time one becomes aware, it's over because no age/life
remains.
E welekin, gerek em... destê xwe bidestî hev kin, û em ji
hev hez kin, em hev de tena nekin.
But however, we must... join our hands together, and love
each other, let's not distress each other.
Em... em bê rind e. Rind e. No bê me bê ez ê bêjim emrî vî
gundî milyonek sal e. Ez no bim sed sal e.
Let us... let us be good. Good. Now without us, without me,
I will say the age of this village is a million years. I
won't be [here] for a hundred years.
Bajarê min e, gundê min e, axa min e.
It is my city, my village, my land.
Kelha Basûtê... Aviyona jî tivê 'endar e ha.
Basute Castle... This building too is ancient, ha.
Bere ge tiştê aso rî tê da bî... e... kûlana derkirin, ge
xirabiyê. Bere ge tiştê aso rî tê da bî.
Let there be some historical things in it... uh... they made
holes [excavations], some destruction. Let there be
historical things in it.
Ere wele.
Yes, by God.
E wele, şore mi şaş û milo bibin şaş, û milo te'lîqa da
yazmış kin, teke dogrî dan dikim ya xar dan dikim.
Oh God, don't take my words wrong and don't misunderstand
me, and don't write in the comments, whether I am speaking
correctly or speaking crookedly.
Arê a bi emr çûçik me, bes a bi... kohl, malor û pir
rûniştime.
Yes, I am young in age, but I have sat a lot with... elders,
wise people.
Ma... ma şûr jê birin e, ma aqil jê girtin e.
We... we have cut off the rashness from it, we have taken
wisdom from it.
Oh, em daran gundo geryo.
Oh, we walked around the village trees.
Yî emrî xwe heyştê kiye, yî emrî xwe nod kiye.
The one who made his age eighty, the one who made his age
ninety.
De marara û hewal didin, işte...
So they give us companionship, you know...
Ay Semo!
Oh Semo!
Tabîetê Efrînê, Basûtê.
The nature of Afrin, Basute.
Ava sar, hewa hênik.
Cold water, cool air.
Ay Bavê Reco!
Oh Father of Reco!
Ev welat no... vî darê işte 'ndar e ha...
This country now... this tree, you know, is ancient, ha...
Vî darê 'ndar e.
This tree is ancient.
Ev çi 'ndar e!
How ancient this is!
Bimar o bin, vîdukî den xweş, kîbar.
Stay with us, a nice, gentle video.
Em ê wara bisewirînin.
We will film for you.
La nî bê gund o bi xwe çûçik e, ne mezin e.
No, look, this village itself is small, not big.
Arê. Ma vîdu dirêj bikro, e hono bî.
Yes. We made the video long, let it be so.
Tebe'en silavê min ji miletê vî gundî ra hene, çûçik mezin.
Şoşbîn ji hene win ê qusûrî me efû kin, çavê we gîya maç
dikim.
Of course, my greetings to the people of this village, small
and big. The cheerful ones are there too, you will forgive
our shortcomings, I kiss the eyes of you all.
Hez kin, hev de hez kin, hev de hez kin, û qîmetê hev de jî
zane bin.
Love, love each other, love each other, and know the value
of each other.
Xwedê we gîya biparêze, Xwedê we gîya mihafize ke.
May God protect you all, may God preserve you all.
Û Xwedê le... dilê we gîya kêfweşkirin bide, û ne kevin bar
destan.
And may God give joy to the hearts of all of you, and may
you not fall under [someone else's] hands/control.
Maşallah miletî me cebar e.
Mashallah, our people are resilient/restorers.
Xwedê ji gîya razî be. Miletî me pêşketî ye. Wez dibînim, ez
o li vîdyo seyr dikim, î heye î mendes, î heye î şifêrê
teyare...
May God be pleased with everyone. Our people are advanced.
And I see, I am watching the video now, there is one who is
an engineer, there is one who is a pilot...
Î heye î qadî, î heye î muhamî. Maşallah rind e. Seta we
xweş.
There is one who is a judge, there is one who is a lawyer.
Mashallah it is good. Health to your hands.
Lê? Xwandin rind e. Zimanî xweş... a hemşî ye.
But? Education is good. A nice language... is everything.
Yekî came hebi, yekî ne mezbût bi...
Someone had a glass [metaphor], one was not strong...
Yanî 'albarekê bi.
Meaning he was a simpleton.
Ma digot di heyatî însên da çi xweş e? Ma ra hewal da... ew
ji nizanî ho, dîn bi, gênda aqil xiro kiriye.
We used to ask what is good in a human's life? He gave us
company... he didn't know either, look, he was mad, he had
seemingly lost his mind.
Ma digot çi xweş e di heyatî însên da? Digot di heyatî însên
gî da... ziman.
We used to ask what is good in a human's life? He said in
the whole life of a human... language.
Ziman xweş e.
Language is good.
Me digot xêr e?
We used to say why/is it good?
Digot... ziman... gîtî ne. Ziman perotî ne. Ziman...
He said... language... is belonging. Language is
feathers/wings. Language...
Heyat pir xweş e, yanî ziman ehemşî ye di heyatî însên da.
Ziman... ziman ciyê îxtiram e, ciyê giye. Ah avo.
Life is very good, meaning language is everything in a
human's life. Language... language is the place of respect,
place of everything. Ah, like this.
Lê? Zimanî ta xweş be, milet maro îxtiram dike, parê maro
hene.
See? If your language is good, people respect us/one, one
has money.
Şor... tekî da çû jî, te qit bi, şorê ta dimaşe.
Word... even if you went into a corner, you were cut off,
your word/speech walks (is effective).
No, el vî darê min a ne rind bim, kasek no de min. Bes a...
ze'rî mi xweş be, u a zimanî mi xweş be...
Now, at this tree if I were bad, no one would come to me.
But if... my appearance is good, and my language is good...
Axo kê bigirim, ê bidestî min bigre. Zimanê mero, perê mero
ne.
Whomever I catch/meet, he will take my hand. One's language
is one's money.
Lê? Îş... îş para berîkê mida heben? Ne hewa.
But? Work... is there money/work in my pocket? Not like
that.
Alan! Alan! Alan! Kida? Kida? Oh meyrê min jiy hat. Ware.
Merheba, merheba.
Alan! Alan! Alan! Where? Where? Oh my man also came. Come.
Hello, hello.
La sorim şêkim kerem ke cem Axa.
Abdulaziz, greetings.
No I swear I am a Sheikh, please come to the Agha's place.
Tu te nas nekir bi motorê?
You didn't recognize yourself/me on the motorcycle?
Yo, sorim şêkim kerem cem Axa. Çend ro berê... Axa ne li mal
e.
No, I swear I am a Sheikh, please come to the Agha's place.
A few days ago... Agha is not home.
Ez zanim te televîzyonê wîna...
I know, on the TV like that...
Ez te nas dikim tey... tey Efrînê, tey hemî cîya.
I know you, you are of... you are of Afrin, you are of all
places.
Mulo bimîne zikr e.
Let it remain a memory.
Gundê Basûtê... Berê Serê Solê me ber... esas telefon bikim,
telefon girtî ye, ez û hemî em çûn e.
Basute village... Towards Serê Solê we went... actually I
was going to call, the phone is closed, me and everyone we
went.
Kowa, ma rind cema kir?
Where, did we gather well?
Wele ez jî, a kê arim hat, a ntorê teswîr kir, wez kê
têkavim... a kê em malê boconixê xwe, cem Idrîs.
By God I too, I was coming to come, I filmed the waiting, I
will enter... we will go to the house of my cousin, to
Idris's place.
Yekşî dermayê, we derî vekir.
Someone remained outside, you opened the door.
Ere, le Efrîn ras mo hat. E me go emê 'andarê xilas kin emê
herin darbece cem bin. Ma vo nêzîk e, qirzêlê o vo.
Yes, from Afrin the road came. And we said we will finish
the ancient [sites] and we will go there to be with them. We
are near, that is Qirzel.
E kundo, yanî Basûtê ne foid e. Du kîlometre ne.
Eh man, meaning Basute is no distance/benefit. It's two
kilometers.
E wara em çayekê vexwînin, da ro, hon tim digerin şol û...
So come let's make you drink a tea, give it, you are always
traveling, work and...
Xol, am... am tebî'etê piş milet kin.
Well, we... we show the nature to the people.
Te bi miletî me ra dibê çi? Te çi silavê dişînî?
What do you say to our people? What greetings do you send?
La wile miletî me...
No by God, our people...
... çi têrt tê ne, yaw welle. Vî de vî de ra de.
...what a satisfying rain, oh God. Through here and there.
Xêr inşallah xêr, rind e ser vî miletî ya Rebî.
Goodness God willing goodness, may it be good for this
nation oh Lord.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Xêr rind e elhemdu lillah.
It is good goodness, praise be to God.
Cem wa çû ye kuderê bavo?
Where has the river gone, uncle?
Cem e, qepat e.
It's the river, it's closed (covered).
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Ew gi berf e, girtî ye.
That is all snow, it is blocked.
Elhemdu lillah.
Praise be to God.
Berf jî çi dibe? Yavaş yavaş dihele, di nêv rê de diçe erdê
ne.
And what happens to the snow? It melts slowly, soaking into
the ground on its way.
Yanî ji baranê çêtir e.
Meaning it is better than rain.
Xêr e, xêr e. Çol û çiya xêr e.
It is a blessing, a blessing. The wilderness and mountains
are blessed.
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Ê me go Cem wa ye, berf helî ye ne av e, em herin vira.
So we said the river is like this, the snow has melted, it
isn't water (flood), let's go here.
Yanî gundê Cem e gi bixwîzik.
Meaning the river village (area) is all slippery mud.
Mokinê ta here, av gi helî ye, tenê ew rê bimeşe.
Do not let it go, the water has all melted, just let it flow
in the path.
Dişimt e.
It is slippery.
Dişimt e, xêr e welle mokinê.
It is slippery, it is a blessing by God, don't let it go.
Mero çi bike de.
What can one do.
Wa tiştek çandiye îsal?
Have you planted anything this year?
Erê, ma heşawîş çandî ye, heşawîş...
Yes, we planted greens, greens...
...ne mane?
...not left?
Mebes berdaye?
Did you give up the greenhouse?
Erzan e, nayê firotan.
It is cheap, it doesn't sell.
Erzan e na?
It's cheap, isn't it?
Ademim xidre erzan e, îne noka.
Man, vegetables are cheap, look at it now.
Xidre erzan e welle, nayê firotan.
Vegetables are cheap by God, they don't sell.
Aa melfûf e, na melfûf... pîşkê heşawîş.
Ah cabbage, no not cabbage... a bit of greens.
Bexdenûs e, cercîr e, mecer...
Parsley, arugula, ...
Tişt nîne.
There is nothing.
Tirp in.
Radishes.
Mesrefê xwe nîne.
It doesn't cover its cost.
Em ê tirp bidin hewa, wereqe tûr.
We give radishes away for air (for free), a sack for a
banknote.
Tûr?
A sack?
Tûrî tirpa wa qisû.
A sack of radishes is that much.
Xas çandine, nayê firotan.
They planted lettuce, it doesn't sell.
Xas çandine, no te firotan na?
They planted lettuce, it doesn't sell, right?
Eslen şansê bacanaxî te ye.
Basically it is your brother-in-law's luck.
No?
Bacanaxî min vî di neqilê de diçî... naqil kî çû, necihîn,
di neqilê jî vêra difeşile.
My brother-in-law goes in this transport business... the
transport went, didn't succeed, and in transport it fails
too.
Xasê xwe gaho nabe... me go bifiroş bifiroş... ba bin, tewre
bibe wereq e.
The lettuce doesn't form heads... we said sell, sell... let
it be wind, let it all turn to leaves.
Xas bibe wereq e.
The lettuce turns into leaves (bolts).
Axayê mero çi bike de.
Oh man, what can one do.
Em bi vî derê bibînin inşallah.
Hopefully we will see this place (prosper).
Met ke vî derya.
Praise this place.
Meşî, selametan.
Okay, stay safe.
Vêga ma motor teka temo kirin, ma hejî pakînek bibra.
Now he has turned off the motorcycle, he should have taken a
clean path.
Sehet xweş herin.
Good health, go.
Erê hevalno, em li vî derê gihîştin taliya vîdyoya xwe.
Yes friends, here we have reached the end of our video.
Hêvîdar im vîdyo kî din xweş, kîbar, em ê werin... inşallah
wisa bikin.
I hope for another nice, decent video, we will come... God
willing we will do so.
Sehkin xelkê dar gi qut kirine...
Look, people have cut down all the trees...
Dar gi qut kirine, hişta... î heye, qut dikin, ke... tiştê
hişîn nehêlin biçînin.
They cut down all the trees, still... there is this, they
cut, that... they don't let green things grow.
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Birevin!
Run!
...Ew ê kûçikê xwe nedaye lotikê...
...He hasn't given his dog to the tumble... (unclear
idiom/joke).
Are are. Beqe, xwîn hate, xwîn hate.
Yeah yeah. Look, blood came, blood came.
Erê welle, hevalno...
Yes by God, friends...
Teb'en ji Basîtê ye. Ji Cem a Basîtê ye.
Of course, this is Basuta. This is the Basuta river area.
Miletê Basîtê jî pir zerxweş in û pir mişterem in. Bixêr û
bêr e.
The people of Basuta are very pleasant and very respectable.
It is bountiful.
Kirzêlê jî wane. Kirzêlê jî wane.
Kerzele is the same. Kerzele is the same.
Gi di milkê xwe de dişixulin, bi xop xop.
They all work on their own property, very hard.
De bimînin seata we xweş, û vîdyo kî din xweş, kîbar.
So stay well, until another nice, decent video.
Em ê inşallah werin doxin.
We will God willing come again.
Mekanî, helqokî em li nav Kirzêlê çêkin.
A place, an episode we will make inside Kerzele.
Em ê werin Kirzêlê jî bisewirînin.
We will come and film Kerzele too.
Lenî seat bînê didu, Cem in.
Because it has been two hours, at the river.
De yalla, seata we xweş.
Come on then, have a good time.