Waren, kesê li Helebê, kesê li dera, waren gundê xwe şên
bikin.
Come, those in Aleppo, those outside, come and enliven your
village.
Gundê Elbîskê... gundê me qehreman cîhanê.
The village of Albiske... our village is a hero of the
world.
Gunde wa wekî dibê... Gundî Elbîskê tima bû tebîetê, ناحiya
Rajo ye.
Your village, as they say... The village of Albiske has
become nature, it is in the Rajo district.
Xwe çêl pênc mal, tû ne gundî tenê.
It has forty-five houses, there is no village like it.
Çil pênc mal manî çi? Manî xêr çinîn.
Forty-five houses, what does it mean? It means planting
goodness.
Manî çûka têra, manî tebîra, manî însên...
It means birds having enough, it means interpretation, it
means humans...
Dibe hûn rêvîk çûn, hûn vê tiştî bixwên.
Perhaps you have gone on a journey, [but] you crave this
thing.
Dibe ev kilîla Kurdistanê ye... Navê wana lêkirine "Kilîla
Kurdistanê".
Maybe this is the key of Kurdistan... The name they gave it
is "The Key of Kurdistan".
Gundê me qehreman cîhanê ne, bi şiklê giştî.
Our village is a hero of the world, generally speaking.
Dîkan divê gundî da tune ne. Derdê tiştê xwe ji Rajo tînin.
There are no shops in the village. They bring their
necessities from Rajo.
Merheba hevalno, dîsa em hatin û hûrxwî vîdyoyeke xweş û
kibar.
Hello friends, we are back again today with a nice and grand
video.
Vîdyoya me jî îro em li nahiya Rajo...
For our video today, we are in the Rajo subdistrict...
Tevayî... em ê hinke dakevin gundê Elbîskê wara teswîr kin.
Generally... we will go down a bit to the village of Albiske
to film.
Erê, tebîeta gund pir xweş e. Me hez kir gotina te heye?
Yes, the nature of the village is very nice. We wanted to
[ask], do you have any words?
Sibeha we bi xêr hevalno, çawanin, baş in? Îşalla hûn gir û
rihet bin.
Good morning to you friends, how are you, are you well? God
willing you are healthy and comfortable.
Erê dîsa em îro hatin warê vîdyoyeke xweş û kibar.
Yes, today we came again to the location of a nice and grand
video.
Bi me ra bin, em derbasî gund bin. Bi dilekî xweş û kibar.
Be with us, let us enter the village. With a happy and grand
heart.
Em dest bi vîdyoya xwe bikin.
Let us start our video.
Ka bi me ra bin em ê dest bi vîdyoya xwe bikin. Gundê
Elbîskê... gundekî pir xweş û kibar e hevalno.
Come be with us, we will start our video. Albiske village...
it is a very nice and grand village, friends.
Erê, mewqiyê gund... Ev çiyayê hember me, çiyayê Tirkiyê ne,
evna.
Yes, the location of the village... These mountains opposite
us are the mountains of Turkey, these ones.
Ooo bajarê Tirkiyê jî xuya dikin ji me va. Yûlçatê, giş der
me va xuya dikin.
Ooh, and the cities of Turkey are visible to us. Yolçatı
[village], they are all visible to us here.
Erê.
Yes.
Wexta mewsîma tirê, wexta mewsîma hejîra ye... qortal xêr
dibe.
It is the time of the grape season, the time of the fig
season... the potholes are getting bad.
Erê.
Yes.
Wexta her tiştî ye, wexta gûza ye jî. Gûz, behîv.
It is the time for everything, it is the time for walnuts
too. Walnuts, almonds.
Welle maşalla bayî viderê tê me hey.
By God, mashallah, the wind here is hitting us.
Yanî çiqas dinya germ be, wer viderê, bayî xweş e.
I mean, no matter how hot the world is, come here, the wind
is nice.
Xêra pêşiya wê vekirî ye.
Because its front [exposure] is open.
Ji çiyayê Gewr va dikşîne.
It pulls [wind] from the Gewr mountain.
Erê hevalno, eva tebîeta gundê Elbîskê ye.
Yes friends, this is the nature of the village of Albiske.
Lê sêr kin heta toliya vîdyoya me.
Watch until the end of our video.
Înşalla evê vîdyo bi hecibînin, pir xweş e.
God willing you will like this video, it is very nice.
Bi elimim gundo, bi elimim cografya gundo bi elimim.
Let me learn the village, let me learn the geography of the
village.
Gundê Elbîskê li kû dikeve. Tenê rêka mero di gundo dikeve,
mero...
Where the village of Albiske is situated. Only one's path
falls into the village, one...
Tişta gundê fêm bike, manî mero zanibe.
[Should] understand something of the village, meaning one
should know.
Mero menteqa xwe, cografya xwe zanibe, rind e.
One should know their region, their geography, it is good.
Welle viderê jî hewş pir xera bûne.
By God, the courtyards here are very ruined.
Welle viderê jî pir xera bûye.
By God, this place is also very ruined.
Welle bê bismila kesek tê tunde.
By God, there isn't a single soul in it [It is completely
deserted].
Bûş e.
It is empty.
Ne qope ne tiştek.
Not a dog [living creature], not anything.
Feqîro milet... miletê çûne. Milet jî hebe, gundê xwe waha
dibînin, dilê xwe pê bişewitînin.
Poor nation... the people have gone. Even if the people
exist, seeing their village like this, they burn their
hearts for it.
Hûn nuyî vîdyoyê dibînin, tu çi dibêjî?
You are seeing the video now, what do you say?
Ne li ser sucdê ne hatine.
They are not on the register [deed/record].
Gundê me xera nebe.
May our village not be ruined.
Gundê me wekî bajar e.
Our village is like a city.
Mero derê mala xwe berda, êke xera be.
Once one leaves the door of their house, it will surely be
ruined.
Gere malê mero talan kir.
They must have looted one's house.
Hêşîn bibe.
Let it be green [revived].
Çiqas malê mero rind be, hefta ketê, her e, wêran e, ana
teyîrat pir çêdibin.
No matter how good one's house is, if seven [years] pass it,
go, it is desolate, now many changes happen.
Gûz...
Walnut [trees]...
Te xêra tiştek nexoş e, teban e.
It is not a good thing, it is tiring.
Na herim û vê gundo waha nebe.
I won't go [and let] this village be like this.
Erê, miletê gundê Elbîskê.
Yes, people of Albiske village.
Ev dara, ekîd zîkretê wa giyan li ber vê darê hene.
This tree, surely all of your memories are by this tree.
Silavê min ji miletê gundê Elbîskê ra hene, tevayî.
My greetings go to the people of Albiske village, all of
them.
Waren, kesê li Helebê, kesê li dera, waren gundê xwe şên
bikin. Gundê wa wekî dibê...
Come, those in Aleppo, those outside, come and enliven your
village. Your village, as it is said...
Milet pir tê tune. Yanî hene, milet tê heye bes ekterî mala
gi xera bûne, kes nawotî.
There aren't many people in it. I mean there are some, there
are people in it, but most of the houses are all ruined,
nobody is living [in them].
Waren hewşê xwe çêkin.
Come fix your courtyards.
Çiqas bikun bin vê kevirî rûniştine, bin vê darê rûniştine
ooo...
How many brides have sat on this stone, sat under this tree,
ooh...
Zîkretê giyan li ber hene gundê Elbîskê.
All of their memories are here in the village of Albiske.
Tebîeta vir pir xweş e, mi pir eciband. Her gundek, ser
gundekî ra, gundê me Kurmanca...
The nature here is very nice, I liked it a lot. Every
village, above another village, our Kurmanji villages...
Dadî ye? Çiqas gundekî na nuke çiqas xerabe ye.
You see? Look at a village like this now, how ruined it is.
Bes dîsa, ebi malê dinyayê nadim, cem û hana ye, ez pir jê
hez dikim.
But still, I wouldn't trade it for the wealth of the world,
it is [dear] like that, I love it a lot.
Tebîeta gunda, derê gunda, ana bin vê darê... yeke çawqê xwe
çêke, bi malê dinyayê dike.
The nature of the villages, the surroundings of the
villages, now under this tree... if one fixes their
corner/spot, it is worth the wealth of the world.
Çawqê xwe çêke, ana dewarek te hebe, ana berda viderê na
xera pey hev bibe.
Fix your corner, now if you have a livestock animal, now
release it here so it doesn't get ruined one after another.
Rind e.
It is good.
Pir mantiqa xweş e. Ev dara jî emrê xwe kevnar e.
It is a very nice region. This tree is also ancient in its
age.
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Erê erê, hene bes e. Na wena, wisa de.
Yes yes, that is enough. No not like that, give it like
this.
Abo te vê mektebê bîne. Erê, heva mekteba vê gundî ye.
Abo, show this school. Yes, this is the school of this
village.
Mekteb jî xirab bûye. Çiqas zarokên vî gundî li ber mektebê
hatine kirin. Çok seqa, çok jî li ber mektebê hatine kirin.
The school has been ruined too. So many children of this
village were raised in front of this school. So many cold
[days], so many [people] were raised in front of the school.
Çend mal ba derketin hene? Hew jî mirin, gundî...
How many houses have left from here? They also died, the
villagers...
Erê hevalno, li vê derê jî em hatin... Em teb'an gundî
'Elbîskê ne.
Yes friends, we came to this place too... We are, naturally,
in the village of Albiske.
Li mala birayê me, bavê Mesûd, em rûniştin... me got em
îstîrahetê kûçik li vir bikin.
We sat at the house of our brother, Masoud's father... we
said let's take a small rest here.
Û niha jî, em ê çend pirsan ji Ebû Semîr bikin, ser vê
gundî, dîroka vê gundî, û çiqas niştecîyê gund hene.
And now, we will ask Abu Samir a few questions about this
village, the history of this village, and how many
inhabitants the village has.
Merheba Ebû Semîr.
Hello Abu Samir.
Ehlen, ehlen we sehlen bi Efrîn Sê, Şeş, Şeş... ferman.
Welcome, welcome to Afrin 366... at your command.
Ebû Semîr, tekî... çend gotinê ser vê gundî mere hewal de.
Niştecîyê xwe kîne? Çiqas in? Be kêjan malbatê tê naskirin?
Abu Samir, give us a few words about this village. Who are
its inhabitants? How many are they? By which family is it
known?
Gundî 'Elbîskê te got teb'an nahya Reco ye. Bi xwe 45 mal di
vî gundî da ne. 45 mal ne.
Albiske village, as you said, is naturally part of the Rajo
district. There are 45 houses in this village. 45 houses.
Hew 45 malna, hinek jî li vê derê hene, î halê hazir li vê
derê hene, 17-18 mal li vê derê ne.
Of those 45 houses, some are here, at the present moment
they are here, 17-18 houses are here.
Ê sekanî noka î hazir li vê derê ye. Û ma tebeqa hinek li
Helebê rûniştine, hinek çûne Ewrupa.
The inhabitants present now are here. And the rest, some
settled in Aleppo, some went to Europe.
Teb'an me ji ber vê... siyaset kişand. Siyasetî gund me
kişand. Waqaî gund me kişand.
Naturally, we... politics pulled us away because of this.
The politics of the village pulled us. The reality of the
village pulled us.
Ê aîlê li vê derê, gundî 'Elbîskê bi xwe mûsema wekî gotî...
xê nav lê kirin 'Elbîskê. 'Elbîskê.
The families here, Albiske village itself is named... as you
said... how it was named Albiske. Albiske.
'Elbîskê bi xwe, ewil mal hat li vê derê rûnişt. Di berî vê
bi 50 salî, 60 salî.
Albiske itself, the first house came and settled here.
Before this by 50 years, 60 years.
Heft gundê 'Emrîkan... la eqel en 60 sal, 70 sal e.
The seven Amrikan villages... at least 60 years, 70 years
[old].
Ê ewil aîle, kewno li vê derê rûniştî, mala 'Elbîskê bûn. Wê
me'nê yê... gundo lê kirin mala 'Elbîskê.
The first family, since they settled here, was the Albiske
family. In that meaning... they named the village the House
of Albiske.
Ebû Semîr çiqas kîlometre ji Reco dûr e?
Abu Samir, how many kilometers is it far from Rajo?
Deh kîlo hene. Deh kîlometre ji nahya Reco dûr e.
There are ten kilos. It is ten kilometers far from Rajo
district.
Deh kîlometre ji nahya Reco dûr e gundî 'Elbîskê.
The village of Albiske is ten kilometers far from Rajo
district.
Û... aîlê, em dîsa tewdîhek biçûçik li ser aîlê ê di vê derê
rûniştine. Me got mala 'Elbîskê yek.
And... the families, let us give another small clarification
on the families that settled here. We said the House of
Albiske is one.
Mala Binbiş, û Mala Mihekê.
The House of Binbish, and the House of Mihekê.
Bi vê sê aîlana tê naskirin?
Is it known by these three families?
Teb'an, ev gund bi vê sê aîlana tê naskirin.
Naturally, this village is known by these three families.
Ê dîsa em ê bên... tewdîhan tiştin din... meşahidê me, em
biçin ser vê gundî haysa...
And again we will come... [give] clarifications on other
things... our viewers, let us go up on this village like
this...
Li ser te'lîqê xwe me rêj mîş kin, em ê gerin, buhara xwe
kin û tewdîhan dîsa bidin.
On our slope/hanging place we will focus, we will walk, have
our spring [picnic], and give clarifications again.
Sahet xweş Ebû Semîr, melûmatê me pir xweş û kîbar in.
Health to you Abu Samir, our information is very good and
noble.
Erê, bes sikanî gund hîştan... me got mal pir xirabe ne,
yanî milet... va nagere.
Yes, but the village inhabitants still... we said the houses
are very ruined, meaning the people... are not returning.
Ektirî xelkê Helebê ne. Û înşallah gey biftil wara mala xwe
û e çê be û e ji berê şêntir bibe înşallah.
The majority are people of Aleppo. And God willing, may they
eventually return to their homes, and it will be fixed, and
it will be more prosperous than before, God willing.
Û de ka em ê ro bin jî... em ê lextanê xwe jî dîsa wara
çêkin.
And come let us go down... we will make our clips again
there.
Erê hevalno, li vê derê jî hake tişkî we bibînim.
Yes friends, here too I will show you something.
Li vê derê jî, a binêrin çiya heye. Heva kevir e, bi xwe,
bin û jûr.
Here too, look there is a mountain. This is rock, itself,
bottom and top.
Teb'an javde... av dikişîne... zewadî ye?
Naturally from there... water flows... is it a valley?
Heva zeman da, av dikirine. Bilxur dikirin vê derê, û heva
jî tim ba didan. Pê dertin.
In the past, here, they utilized the water. They made bulgur
here, and here they always winnowed it. They processed it.
Bilxur, genim... elmûhîm tiştê xwarinê gilê dixistin.
Bulgur, wheat... anyway, they put food grains [here].
Nîsk... darox gilê... nîsk jî pê hûr dikirin.
Lentils... threshing grain... they also ground lentils with
it.
Tim hona dû rav da... e hinek dik ber didanê çe... û tim ba
didan... bi vayê.
Always like this down the slope... they would release some
[grain]... and always winnow it... with the wind.
Ba didan, ê kevir jî yona li hevdû dihat, hûr dibû.
They winnowed, and the stone would come together like that,
it would be ground.
Heva lê. Kevnar e, emrê vê jî kevnar e.
Here it is. It is ancient, its age is also ancient.
Heva jî dorka Kurdistanê ye?
Is this also the map/shape of Kurdistan?
Kilkê Kurdistanê ye na?
It's the tail of Kurdistan, isn't it?
Erê. Hevalno heva... dibê heva Kilkê Kurdistanê ye. Nav wan
o lê kirine, Kilkê Kurdistanê.
Yes. Friends this... he says this is the Tail of Kurdistan.
They named it "The Tail of Kurdistan".
Erê hevalno, heva şta... ev gundo, tebî'eta vê gundî hwana
ye.
Yes friends, this is as... this village, the nature of this
village is like this.
Me got kok daw heşt mal di vê gundî da hene. Yanî pir kes na
weti. Bi xwe 45 mal ne, bes daw heşt mal jî hene.
We said there are some eight houses in this village. Meaning
not many people are there. There are 45 houses, but only
eight houses are [occupied] there.
Vê gundî jî şta... bi karaz o ye, bi karaz o ye, henar ne,
tirş e, simaq e. Gundê me Kurmancan honane bi şiklê 'am.
This village too... is [known] for cherries, for cherries,
pomegranates, sour [plums/fruit], sumac. Our Kurdish
villages are like this in general.
Erê. Dikan di vê gundî da tinene. Daren tiştê xwe ji Reco
tînin. Erê. Dikan tinene. Saman di vê gundî da tinene.
Yes. There are no shops in this village. They bring their
things from Rajo. Yes. No shops. There are no supplies in
this village.
Ho wextê henarê jî kê bibe ho.
Look, the time for pomegranates will come soon, look.
Hevalno werin hejîra.
Friends, come for figs.
Me got wextê hejîra ye? Ha... ha... binêrin... werin da pir
ne ho.
Did we say it is time for figs? Look... look... look here,
there are many, look.
Destê min nagihîyê.
My hand doesn't reach it.
Wey, destê min nagihîyê wella.
Oh, my hand doesn't reach it, by God.
Werin dilê wa kê te ra, hûn kê bixwin werin. Ebû Semîr henke
binîvîne de.
Come, whoever desires it, whoever wants to eat, come. Abu
Samir is down there.
Henke binîvîne de...
He is down there...
Teb'an hejîr... edetê me gundê me Kurmancan...
Naturally figs... the custom of our Kurdish villages...
Berê... kalê di berê... nav milkê xwe de diçandin... ser
riya de diçandin.
In the past... the elders of the past... planted them within
their property... they planted them by the road.
Xêrî çin, bixwe û dua li wî mirî bike.
[So that] passersby go, eat, and pray for that dead person
[who planted it].
Ne were bike û satilê xwe tijî bike ba hejîra berfşê.
Not to come and fill your bucket so the figs run out.
Niha hejîr... hejîr came buhanek e... niha hejîr bûye bi
pere. Kîlo bi sê dolar.
Now figs... figs have become expensive... now figs have
become for money. A kilo for three dollars.
Xelas... em derbas bûn...
It's finished... we passed by...
Em ê hinekî daji hejîrê xwe bixwin...
We will also eat some of our figs...
Weka şita fehm dikin...
As you understand...
Vê hejîrê no em dixwin, ekîd em helal dikin.
These figs we are eating, surely we make it halal [we ask
permission/blessing].
Taybetil ser çi helal dikin... helal dikin.
Specifically on what we make it halal... we make it halal.
Ez helal dikim... yanî xalû...
I am making it halal... meaning uncle...
Erê, ez ê vê hejîrê noka helal kim. Ebû Semîr jî min ra wal
de, ez ê kê çû helal kim.
Yes, I am going to make this fig halal now. Abu Samir is
here with me, I will go make it halal.
Temam. Dê ma em merî misilman... her yekî misilman hedîsek
hene...
Okay. Since we are Muslim people... every Muslim has a
Hadith [saying]...
Rebb... hedîsek hene tê da hewşî helal kirin.
Lord... there is a Hadith wherein the courtyard [eating from
the garden] is made halal.
Ma ev hedîs noka çi ne? Ku hemû şêniyê xwedê ra izin bira...
î nizane...
Now what is this Hadith? That permission is given to all
God's creatures... he doesn't know...
Me'ne am zanibin, tekê hejîrekê teraste hat, tiştek teraste
hat, te jê xwar, çi tûne helal e.
Meaning we should know, if you come across a fig tree, or
come across anything, and you eat from it, there is no
issue, it is halal.
Di hedîsê de heye tê zekirkirin dibê: "Men zere'a zer'en fe
ekele minhu teyren ew insanen ew behîmeten we îlla kane bîhî
sodeqe."
It is mentioned in the Hadith, saying: "Whoever plants a
seedling and a bird, or a human, or an animal eats from it,
it is regarded as a charity for him."
Yanî, hem mileta me, edetê me pirr hene, teqlîdê me pirr
hene, her yekî baxçak zeytûn ku diçand...
Meaning, our people as well, we have many customs, we have
many traditions, anyone who planted an olive orchard...
Hesren... ekê du dar hejîrê sê dar hejîrê biçîne...
Exclusively... he would plant two fig trees, three fig
trees...
Me'ne çi? Me'ne xêr û çin.
Meaning what? Meaning good deeds and such.
Me'ne çûka, têra, me'ne tebîra, me'ne însên, dewarê rêwîk
çû, ew ê tiştî bixwe.
Meaning for birds, wild doves, nature, humans, a beast or a
traveler passing by, they would eat that thing.
Me'ne Rebbel Alemîn xêr û bereketê de zeytûnê ge jî.
Meaning the Lord of the Worlds puts goodness and blessing
into the olives as well.
Temam. Noka jî em ê çi bikin, em ê de'wa li xalû bikin.
Okay. And now what will we do, we will pray for the uncle
[owner].
Wekî dibê, megû se'et xweş e, se'eta gundê xweş, xwedê rizqê
gundê bişîne.
As they say, the time is pleasant, the time in the village
is pleasant, may God send provision to the village.
Û nanê rehmetî jî be, xwedê rehma xwe lê ke cihê xwe cenet
be.
And may it be a mercy for the deceased too, may God have
mercy on him and may his place be paradise.
Me xalû... me pênc şeş hejîr te xwarin, helal ke.
Uncle... we ate five or six of your figs, make them halal
[forgive us].
Kerem kin, serçava.
You are welcome, with pleasure.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Erê ev wa loma hejîrê xwe jî li vir xwarin.
Yes, here, we ate our figs here too.
Em gihiştin dawiya vîdyo xwe, se'eta we xweş. Xwedê ji we
razî be.
We have reached the end of our video, have a good time. May
God be pleased with you.
Bîr mekin te'lîqên xweş, kîbar me ra binivîsin û em jê
kederê daxwazin.
Don't forget to write us nice, kind comments and we will ask
for [prayers] from there.
Erê, na waye em ê li berqewar man e... Ebû Semîr tê dibê çi?
Yes, it's not over, we are remaining under the sun... What
do you say Abu Samir?
Em daxwazin tewdîhek bidin hecêr em pê bidin muşahîdê xwe û
mutabe'înê me.
We want to give a clarification just to inform our viewers
and followers.
Lî enû ewîn mustehel ne, mutabe'înê me, Efrîn sê sê sê şeş.
Because they are deserving, our followers, Afrin 3336.
Çi pir mustehel ne. Birê delal em li kîderê ne?
They are very deserving. Dear brother, where are we?
Noka em li muselles kin in. Ev musellesî ve dere, sê rêk tên
ser hevdu.
Now we are at a triangle [intersection]. This triangle is
here, three roads join together.
Em li ber meferqa gundê 'Elbîskê.
We are at the intersection of 'Elbîskê village.
Ava gundê 'Elbîskê, ova hilekşa 'Elbîskê.
That is 'Elbîskê village, this slope is 'Elbîskê.
Vê derê, vê rêkê dize têra devera Cengê.
Here, this road goes towards the area of Cengê [Rajo].
Gundê Cengê, giya heşda mal e. Cengê û Reco.
The village of Cengê, it's totally eighteen houses. Cengê
and Rajo.
Û vê dengê ra jî diherin 'Edema. 'Edema.
And this side goes to 'Edema [Adama]. Adama.
'Edema. Lê li vê derê çi heye? Bira dostû, li vê derê goleke
heye...
Adama. But what is here? My friend, there is a pond here...
Ko wermê lê bigre.
Let the camera capture it.
Bîra min bîne. Ev gola mileta, vê sê gundan çêkirî.
Remind me. This pond of the people, these three villages
built it.
Vê sê gundan xêra vê golê çêkirin. Wextê nebû.
These three villages built this pond as a charity. [In a]
time when there wasn't [water].
Av li vê gundê welatî tûne bû. Pir kêm bû.
There was no water in these villages/country. It was very
scarce.
Dewara xwe... qantirê xwe qebat... dewarê xwe...
Their cattle... maybe their mules... their cattle...
Ê batan li vê derê, ava vê derê, vê sê gundan, dihatin li vê
derê av didan.
The threshers here, the water here, these three villages
used to come here and water [their animals].
Lê dabara xwe li vê derê dikirin.
But they made their living [sustenance] here.
Bere, gû gol hebin.
Indeed, there were ponds.
Lê her gundekî golek xwa hebû.
But every village had its own pond.
Lê tetewra çêbûyî paşê dewletê bîr kolan derxist millet jî
îstîfade dît, elhemdulîlah.
But development happened later, the state dug wells and
brought [water] out, the people benefited, thank God.
Erê, se'et xweş Ebû Semîr.
Yes, pleasant times Abu Samir.
Bûrin, kerem kin.
Excuse us, please [come in].
Lê noka em daxwazin, em kê vîdyokî din, yekî pir xweş, yekî
rind delal, gundê 'Edema em kê werra bisewirînin.
But now we want to film another video for you, a very nice
one, a beautiful good one, the village of Adama.
Ew helqek başqe ye.
That is a separate episode.
Erê heval no, ka bimînin se'eta we xweş, em ê helqeke jî li
gundê 'Edema çêkin, bes em ê dû vê helqê ra em ê daxînin
înşallah.
Yes friends, stay tuned, have a good time, we will make an
episode in the village of Adama too, but we will upload it
after this episode, God willing.
Ka bimînin, se'eta we xweş.
Stay tuned, have a good time.