Heta dar û ber di dinê heye, mantîqa vir xweş dibe.
As long as trees and nature exist in the world, the
environment here will stay beautiful.
Hemî guhdarvanên vîdyoyê me, silav ji Ebû Henan ra, heta
bajarê Viyanayê, Nemsa. Û ji xelkê Fikrat ra, û Mehmel ra,
silavên me ji we re hene heta Rûsya.
To all the viewers of our video, greetings to Abu Hanan, all
the way to the city of Vienna, Austria. And to Fikrat's
family, and Mehmel, our greetings go out to you all the way
to Russia.
Ka derbas bin, qada rastî bigire û bişîne.
Let's pass by, please film straight and send it.
Silavê me ji Mistefa yî Henanî re bi umûmî. Silavên me ji we
re hene kekê Mistefa, tu hevalê min î, em gelek ji hev re
lîstan dikişînin û em bi hev re diaxivin.
My greetings to Mustafa Hanuni in general. We send you our
greetings, brother Mustafa, you are my friend, we send voice
notes to each other and we talk a lot.
Emmar Gocar, ser serê min. Emmar Gocar te we'dek daye sobê
bo me masî bigirî. Cihê ku min te masiyan xwaribû, biçe wî
cihî.
Ammar Gochar, you are on my head. Ammar Gochar, you promised
me a fish meal tomorrow. Look, Ammar Gochar, this is the
place where we ate the fish together, go there.
Xelkê Fikrat wekî te digot, silavên me ji te ra hene, eva
hewşa te ye.
Fikrat's family, as you requested, our greetings to you.
This is your yard.
Xweş e!
It is beautiful!
Xelkê Fikrat û em Memer, ev hewşa te ye. Çi hewşek kîbar e.
Xwedê rziqê gundiyan bişîne.
Fikrat's family and Uncle Memer, this is your yard. What an
elegant yard. May God bless the villagers' livelihood.
Esasî gund mala Omo ye, mala Omo. Ew diwêra kî ye? Xelkê
Fikrat û Mehmûd... ev e hewşa we ye, çi hewşek e! Çi hewşek
e rind û kîbar e. Xwedê rizqê we bide.
The core of the village is Omo's house. Who does that belong
to? Fikrat's family and Mahmud... this is your yard, what a
yard! What a beautiful and elegant yard. May God grant you
livelihood.
Ebû Henan birk e te ye eva birk, bes dîwarî te hedimî ye we
da leko, ev birka wê derê.
Abu Hanan, this is your pool. However, your wall has
collapsed over there, this is your pool right there.
Rojbaş hevalno, xwişkno, birano, û gişka guhdarên. Em îro
hatin bi vîdyoyek xweş û kîbar.
Good day, friends, sisters, brothers, and to all our
listeners. We have come today with a beautiful and nice
video.
Erê hevalno, vîdyoya me jî em hatine Gundê Omo. Nabe xal?
Temam.
Yes, friends, for our video we have come to the village of
Omo. Isn't that right, uncle? Alright.
Gundê Omo gundekî pir xweş e, cografiya wî gundî, milleta ku
tê da dijî pir xweş e, kîbar in, ekabîr in.
The village of Omo is a very beautiful village, its
geography and the people living in it are very nice,
elegant, and noble people.
Em ê noka bi hev re derbasî vî gundî bibin, vîdyoyek xweş
nava gund da çêkin. Cografiya vî gundî, milleta wî gundî
çawa radibin, rûdinên, çawa dijîn pêşkeş bikin.
We will now go through this village together and make a nice
video for you inside the village. We will show you the
geography of this village, how its people get up, sit down,
and live.
Ê esasiyê gund o kî ye? Tab'en xalê min Ebû Nîzar bi me ra
ye. Silah Reşo.
And who is the core of this village? Of course, my uncle Abu
Nizar is with us. Salah Resho.
Em ê pê re derbasî nav gund bibin û pêşî li me bike. Em ê
derbasî cem malbata bibin jî, em ê sualên xwe ji wan bikin,
pirsan ji wan bikin.
We will go into the village with him, and he will guide us.
We will also visit some families and ask them our questions.
Bi me re bin heta dawiyê, înşallah em ê vîdyoyek xweş we re
çêkin. Mafê xeberdanê yê te ye. Ser çava!
Stay with us until the end. God willing, we will make a nice
video for you. Now, the floor is yours. At your service!
Rojbaş xal û xwarza, heval û bira. Hevalên me çawa ne? we
baş e? we sax e?
Good day, uncles, nephews, friends, and brothers. How are
our friends? Are you well? Are you healthy?
Înşallah hûn giş digel hev baş in. Canê we di rehetî de ye.
God willing, you are all doing well together and living in
comfort.
Erê wek ku me got, em gundê Omo ne, em ê derbasî gundê Omo
bibin. Bi me re bin heta dawiya vîdyoyê.
Yes, as we said, we are in the village of Omo, and we will
go through the village of Omo. Stay with us until the end of
the video.
Înşallah vîdyoya me hûn ê pir jê hez bikin, bi ecibînin.
Bîra xwe mekin like e û iştirak û te'lîqne xweş û kîbar ji
we binivîsin, kusur efû bikin.
God willing, you will really like and appreciate our video.
Do not forget to like, subscribe, and write us nice and kind
comments, and please forgive our shortcomings.
Bi me re bin em niha derbasî gundê Omo bibin.
Stay with us, we will now enter the village of Omo.
Saeta we xweş xal, Ebû Nîzar. Erê hevalno milletekî gundê
Omo re... çûçik mezin, ez çavê gundê Omo giş maç dikim.
Silavên me ji Ebû Henan re jî hene, ji xelkê Fikrat re jî
hene, li bajarê Rûsya, silavên me ji wan re hene û çavê
gundê Omo giş maç dikim.
Health to you, Uncle Abu Nizar. Yes friends, to the people
of the village of Omo, young and old, I kiss the eyes of
everyone in Omo. Our greetings also go to Abu Hanan, to
Fikrat's family in Russia, our greetings to you. I kiss the
eyes of everyone in the village of Omo.
Bi me re bin û noka em vîdyoyek xweş gund da çêbikin. Xal,
te tiştek digot tu bêjî?
Stay with us as we make a beautiful video in the village.
Uncle, did you have something to say?
Welleh gotina min, silav û rêz ji we re. Hûn bi xêr hatin,
gund geş bû bi hatina we, em kêfxweş bûn ku hûn hatin.
Silavên me ji her yekî gundê Omo li Ewrûpa re, silav û rêz û
hurmet ji wan re hene. Ehlen û sehlen... bi xêr hatine we.
By God, my words are greetings and respects to you. Welcome,
the village has brightened with your arrival, we are happy
you came. Our greetings and respects to everyone from Omo
village in Europe. Welcome, we are happy to have you.
Allah yselmek, silavê te gîhîştin. Yê gund rast e rast ji te
re silav dikin... Xwedê emrêk drêj bi te bide...
May God bless you, your greetings have reached them. The
people of the village directly send their greetings back to
you. May God grant you a long life...
Em te xwere aciz dikin ku tu tiştên gund, kîdera wî, dîroka
wî pêş me bike. Xwedê ji te razî be. Saeta we xweş bî. Te em
gelek xwaş kir, we rû xwaş av kir...
We will bother you a bit to show us the village, its places,
and its history. May God be pleased with you. Health to you.
You made us happy and refreshed us...
Ez ê bêjim Xwedê emrekî drêj bi te de... û em noka... em bi
hev re derbas bibin, xal Ebû Nîzar di gund re pêşiya me
bike... tiştên xweş pêşkeşî me bike.
I say, may God grant you a long life... and now... let's go
together, Uncle Abu Nizar will guide us through the
village... to show us beautiful things.
Ka em bi hev re derbas bin... Bir!
Let's pass by together... Walk!
Erê hevalno ji vê derê em me dest pê kir, em ê niha bi rê
kevin. Gundekî pir xweş e û kîbar e.
Yes friends, we have started from here, we will now hit the
road. It is a very beautiful and elegant village.
Evê derê projeyek çêdikin, hewşekê digirin, xwedê rziqê
gundiyan bişîne.
They are building a project here, enclosing a yard. May God
bless the villagers' livelihood.
Em lê mêze dikin... welleh qalibên kevir e! Çi hecer e!
Paqij e. Ev dîwarê kî ye xal?
Look at this... wow, stone molds! What stone! It is clean.
Whose wall is this, uncle?
Ev qelbeyê dîwarê Heco ye, Fîrasê... Ebû Fîras.
This is the wall of Heco's yard, Firas... Abu Firas.
Xwedê rziqê wî bide.. hewşa kê wisa we ye...
May God bless his livelihood... and all the villagers.
Hewşa... Ebû Velîd e, û Hecî Cemal.
This is the yard of... Abu Walid, and Haji Jamal.
Maşelleh kîbar e hewşek kîbar e. Ev hewşa kî ye?
Mashallah, it is a nice and elegant yard. Whose yard is
this?
Eva... mala Mixtar e. Miktar Qasim, miktar Qasim e.
This is... the Mukhtar's house. Mukhtar Qasim, it's Mukhtar
Qasim.
Maşelleh gundekî xweş û kîbar e.
Mashallah, it's a beautiful and elegant village.
Ev der jî malên Mela ne. Ev hemî naskirî ne hevdû. Ev der
hewşa Mehmûd... ev hewşa Miste.
These places here are the houses of the Mela family. They
are all known to each other. Over here is Mahmud's yard...
this is Miste's yard.
Xwedê rziqê we bide!
May God grant you livelihood!
Mezinê gund e ev a mala Xalê Remzî ye? Ewe hewşa ewe mezinê
gund e?
The elder of the village, is this Uncle Ramzi's house? Is
this the yard of the village elder?
Remzî Reşo ye ewe. Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide wê. Eva mala
Hemdî ye. Eva hewşa Hemdî ye.
That is Ramzi Resho. May God grant him a long life. This is
Hemdi's house. This is Hemdi's yard.
Erê hevalno, ka az bi xal Nîzar derbas bibim... ka em li
sekinînê mêzekin... Ka wateya van çiye xal te got ev çiye
bîra te?
Yes friends, as I walk with Uncle Nizar... let's look at
this spot... Uncle, what does this mean, what did you say it
was?
Xalî te digot eva seha gund ye ne?
Uncle, you said this was the village square, right?
Eva seha gund bû wextê, erê.
Yes, this used to be the village square back in the day.
Bes eva çi bî... çi... tu dikarî bêjî qebr e ...
But what was this? Like a grave...
Eva bilxur bû. Berê milleta gund bîlxurê xwe dida
kelandin... wextê hat kelandin, milleta gund dihat ser hev
didan sekinandin..
This was for boiling bulgur wheat. In the past, the village
people would boil their bulgur here. When it was boiling,
the villagers would gather around.
Şahiyek çêdibû gund giş ddor digirt... dordor... ewe temaşe
dikirin di vî wextî de bilxur xwe çêdikir...
It would become like a celebration, the whole village would
surround them... they would watch as the bulgur was being
prepared.
Hertişt dida ... teva hevbûn gund... wexta mala filan bilxur
li hev dixist, yek dida hev... em digotin bilxurê wî gundî
bûn, yê xwe... hevdû dihiştin. Temaşe dikirin yê bi hev r
alîkarî kirana tişte wey dî kîbar. Em gundî bûn teva hevdû
kirin.
It was a celebration. Everyone gathered around. When
someone's family was boiling bulgur, everyone would come
together... people watched and helped each other out, it was
beautiful. We villagers did everything together.
Xal noka weş tişt nemaye, gund... tişt weh derketin... lê
xwedê, wextê berê xweş bû ye gundiyê hev di girtin... biratî
xwaş bî. Te tama xwe heye bîr dixe xwe de..
Uncle, now these things don't exist anymore, times have
changed... but by God, the old days were better, the
villagers supported each other... the brotherhood was
beautiful. It brings back memories.
Xal milleta wî gundî têkîliyek pir wek bûn. Weke we bûn. Wek
yek mabûn milleta gundê bi hevdûra bûn, destê hevdû di
girtin.
Uncle, the people of this village were very united. They
stood as one, the whole village was together, holding each
other's hands.
Tu yek wilo nîne ne. Ne gund giş didîtin hev r rudinştin kî
di nexweşiyê de ba bi wî r radibûn pêş wî diçûn... bi xwa
karên hev didîtin. Şîn bûn dawet bû... yê gund gund bi yek
bûn, milletek gund bûn em e bi yek bûn.
You wouldn't see anyone left alone. If someone was sick or
in trouble, they wouldn't leave them alone. If there was a
wedding or mourning... everyone stood together. The village
was one, we shared everything in brotherhood.
Saeta we xweş Ebû Nîzar. Erê Ebû Henan, wî... eva mihdera we
ye. Eva mihdera Ebû Henan e.
Health to you, Abu Nizar. Yes, Abu Hanan, wow... this is
your gathering place. This is Abu Hanan's place.
Tab'en eva hewşa te jî ye. Lê hê ava nebûye hewşa Ebû Henan.
Dîwar tenê lê çêbûne em nakin derbas binê ...
Of course, this is your yard too. Abu Hanan's yard. But it
hasn't been fully built yet, it is still just walls. We
can't go inside...
Noka wira em derbas dibin nava gundî.. geryanek gund...
dîtin a dîrokî ka binihêrin.
Now we will go further to see the history of the village...
a historical tour inside the village... showing the village.
Welleh baqî mabû. Gundekî dîrokî bîne ...
By God, it's beautiful, a historical video, a historical
village...
Temam ev derê jî deriyê kevin û xanîyê kevin jî vê derê ye.
Okay, here is the old door and the old house is also here.
Xwedê rizqê gundîya bişîne Xwedê feqîrîyê nede.
May God send the livelihood of the villagers, may God not
give poverty.
Erê maşallah ev e gundê we. Gundekî xweş e. Cografyayek pir
xweş e.
Yes, maşallah, this is your village. It's a nice village.
It's a very nice geography.
Ev e hewşa Mustefa ye ne? Elîyê Xalê Henîf.
This is Mustafa's courtyard, right? Eliyê Xalê Hanif.
Elîyê Xalê Henîf.
Eliyê Xalê Hanif.
Li Siûdiyê ye ne?
He is in Saudi Arabia, right?
Li Siûdiyê... Mustefayê Hanêni û emo.
In Saudi Arabia... Mustafa of Haneni and uncle.
Silavê me jê re hene, kakê Mustefa hevalê min e. Em çend
wexta bi hev re li Estenbolê digeriyan... me tekstîl
dikirin.
We send him our greetings, Brother Mustafa is my friend. We
were together in Istanbul for some time... we worked in
textile.
Gelekî bi rûmet e, gelekî hevalê te ye.
He is very honorable, he is a good friend of yours.
Erê. Ez pirr diçûmê... dema te digot ev kê ye, ev birayê kê
ye.
Yes. I went there a lot... when you said who is this, whose
brother is this.
Digot birayê Şêrîn e, Mihemed e...
He said he's Şêrîn's brother, it's Mihemed...
Ewa bi hev re esker bûn û... erê.
Ah, they were soldiers together... yes.
Tamam.
Okay.
Ev a hewşa Mustefa ye, emê kêlîkê şûnda herin ser xênî.
Me... ku kê vîdyo dît... di dîwarê gund de bigerin da...
This is Mustafa's courtyard, we will go on the roof in a
moment. So... whoever saw the video... let them walk around
the village wall...
Hewş a kê ba, çi çêkiriye, xwedê rizqê giya bişîne, silavê
me jê re hene heta Siûdiyê.
Whoever's courtyard it is, what they've built, may God send
everyone's livelihood, we send our greetings to him all the
way to Saudi Arabia.
E, tamam... birayê min...
Eh, okay... my brother...
Are tebîetkî pir xweş e. Oh...
Yes, it's a very nice nature. Oh...
Hela min divê hewşa wana nêzîk bikim piçekî. Bo nanî...
binihêrim ma...
Let me get a little closer to their courtyard. Let me see
for the bread...
Çi ba, kî nekile l'vir e heye. Walê kakê Mistefa hewşa te ji
ya gîya rindtir e.
Let's see what is here. By God, brother Mustafa, your
courtyard is nicer than everyone else's.
Cîyekî te pirr hênik e, xweş e. Lê zivistan giya şûnde...?
Your place is very cool and nice. But in the winter, does
the grass go away...?
Rind e.
It's good.
Xwedê rizqê gîya bişîne. Xanê wexta bîstê em, em hatin... ba
te... me tiştek bixwara?
May God send everyone's livelihood. Lady, when we came... to
you... would we eat something?
Erê wele.
Yes, by God.
Maşallah di vî gundî de jî av heye. Heq we ra... di kûlê.
Sed û pêncî metreyî av xwe de derketiye. Ava xwe rind e,
kîbar e.
Maşallah, there is also water in this village. Rightfully...
in the well. Water came out at a hundred and fifty meters.
Its water is good, it's elegant.
Ev malo gîya heye nê? Gîya, yê taqeta wî digêje...
Do they have grass in this house? Grass, the one who has the
power to reach...
Dibê 150 metrîye, maşallah ava bahr e.
They say it's 150 meters, maşallah it's sea water.
Eme 100 metre ye.
Ours is 100 meters.
Rind a.
Maşallah.
It's good.
Em... l'ber pê ra, heta sî dîne... Şaredarî av derxist. Ne
amade?
We... under it, until thirty... The municipality brought out
water. Is it not available?
Ne amade ye. Heta heştê mêtra çûn, subhanallah behr.
It's not available. They went down to eighty meters,
subhanallah, a sea.
Maşallah, xwedê rizqê gîya bişîne.
Maşallah, may God send everyone's livelihood.
Em... hema ra va raber... bo kî me re...
We... just right here... for who to us...
Erê, te berê digot riya Efrînê li ku derê ye? Çawa xuya
dike?
Yes, you were saying earlier where is the road to Afrin? How
does it look?
Riya Efrînê l'jêrî me ye. Çiyayê Kurmancî l'hember me ye.
The road to Afrin is below us. The Kurmanj Mountain is
opposite us.
Ên ha caran, hevalek me ye, ewa wekî...
The ones from back then, we have a friend, he is like...
Ên ha caran me berê, kokên wan wekî ên ha caran, me bar kir
û sekinîn... êna caran jî... birayê min... l'vî gundî jî, me
kokên wî berê safî kirin.
From those times we used to, their roots like those ones, we
packed up and stopped... those ones too... my brother... in
this village too, we cleared his roots before.
Weleh mentîqek xweş e, nîzamî çêkiriye. Pirr hewş kîbar e.
By God, it's a nice place, it's made systematically. The
courtyard is very elegant.
Va amarek e.
This is architecture.
Oho, ho, ho, maşallah, maşallah. Ev a, bi rûnî gund di binî
te ye.
Oh my, maşallah, maşallah. This, if you sit down, the
village is under you.
Çi bayekî hênik jî l'vir e. O, o, ev a, b'meyzekî... dît te?
There is also a cool breeze here. Oh, oh, this, if you
look... did you see it?
Erê. Hemû ro ser xanîyek...
Yes. All day on a house...
Hemû gundî dît. Heta gundê Şorbe xwînê. Cindirês... giya
dixwiye te?
Saw the whole village. Up to the village of Şorbe.
Cindires... can you see it all?
Şora Hawar e. Lê?
That's the conversation of Hawar. Right?
Kîbar e. Vaye bavê av e... av a... em diçin xwe sekinin. Baş
e?
It's elegant. Here's the father of water... water... we are
going to stand still. Okay?
Hevalê me l'xeta wekî pey te va... l'hewşê jî bikişîne.
Our friend on the line like after you... should also film in
the courtyard.
Xwedê rizqê gîya bişîne. O, qata sêyem jî l'vir e. Kîbar e.
May God send everyone's livelihood. Oh, the third floor is
also here. It's elegant.
Ê wilo heta kû derê diçe?
Up to where does it go like that?
Abû Mistefa, evî jî te dikşînim ha. Gundekî pir xweş e.
Abu Mustafa, I'm filming this one for you too. It's a very
nice village.
Tabîat...
Nature...
Maşallah.
Maşallah, erê gundekî kûçik e, bas gundekî xweş e.
Maşallah, yes it's a small village, but it's a nice village.
Hêşînahîya xwe jî, avê wê jî heye.
It has its greenery, and it has its water.
L'vê derê jî em hatine ser tirbê... Tirba gundiyan giş l'vê
derê.
And here we have come to the graveyard... The graveyard of
all the villagers is here.
Wara em ha ne... ser tirban in...
Come on, we are here... on the graves...
Xwedê rehma xwe li giya bike.
May God have mercy on them all.
Cîyê giyan cenet be.
May their place be paradise.
E...
Eh...
Ev evê kî ye?
Who is this one?
Evê Hecî Mihemed Alî ye.
This is Haci Mihemed Ali's.
Xwedê rehma xwe l'gîya bike.
May God have mercy on them all.
Amin.
Amen.
Emê ji gîyara Fatiheyek bixwînin.
We will read a Fatiha for them all.
Lê haya min jî nayê we?
Don't you guys realize that either?
Xwedê rehma xwe l'gîya bike. Cemaetî...
May God have mercy on them all. Community...
Ev... xelk... kal e, feqî, fî... ka, l'kû yê van e?
This... people... old, poor... where are theirs?
T'bê feqî li jêrî gundin a...
You say the poor are below the village...
Ebû Henan em hatine ser tirbana. Û me Fatihe jî gîyara
xwend. Xwedê rehma xwe l'gîya bike. L'xelkê... k'gî, l'vîr
ke? Are...
Abu Hanan, we have come to the graveyard. And we read a
Fatiha for everyone. May God have mercy on them all. To the
people... who, here? Yes...
Av na ne... tirbe na ne pern e, deh, pa û pêncak in l'vê
darê...
There are not... many graves, ten, fifteen of them are
here...
Te ba, dido kûçe ha nê...? Awa ne.
You know, there are two corners inside...? That's them.
Kêsê mirîyên xwa l'vê darê hebe... me ro yaziş biki, û de'we
biki.
Whoever has their dead here... let them write to me, and
pray.
Am, l'ser tirba na.
We are on the graves.
Xwede rahma xwa l'gîyo ka, dîyo jîneta ba.
May God have mercy on them all, may their place be heaven.
Miletê gundî hema, min wilo zikriyatê wan anî bîra wan. Çi
wext di rê ra çûne, hatine, ev e zikriyatê gîya ne, l'vê
derê.
The people of the village, I brought their memories to their
minds like this. Whenever they went on the road, came back,
these are everyone's memories, here.
Xelkê Fikrat... silavê me ji we ra hene.
People of Fikrat... we have greetings for you.
Ewa ez qêpaxim berta we kasetek na, berta şînim hewa qêpaxê
im na.
Let me record a cassette for you, let me send it, let me
record it now.
Kaste ay e, ecêb e.
A cassette is, strange.
Çû ye ava?
What is this?
Eva hewşa xelkê Fikrat e, wekî ku dibê, silavê me ji re hene
heta bajarên Rûsya.
This is the yard of the people of Fikrat, as they say, we
send greetings to the cities of Russia.
Malyê, malyê!
People of the house, people of the house!
Welleh qûlix jî ketiye.
By God, the service has fallen too.
Xelkê Fikrat, wekî dibêjin silavê me ji we re hene, ev jî
hewşek we ye.
People of Fikrat, as they say we have greetings for you,
this is also your yard.
Erê weleh ta we hebû em ê ji am tirsa ... ka we xanî, ka
we...
Yes by God, if you had one we would out of fear ... where is
your house, where are you...
Hewşek te kîbar heye. Xwedê rizqê we lê be înşeallah.
You have a beautiful yard. May God provide your sustenance,
God willing.
Qîz xalî me heye?
Do we have a cousin?
Qîz xalî te?
Your cousin?
Xwedê sitara xwe lê gîha ke û xwedê emrê we drêj ke.
May God place your shelter there, and may God lengthen your
life.
Ev lîmoya we li ber laxtokê hewşê ye ka em da binêrin.
This lemon of yours is by the wall of the yard, let's take a
look.
Welleh hewş kîbar e.
By God, the yard is nice.
Dorbera xwe jî pirr xwesik çêkirine, hîşînahîya xwe
xwendiye.
Its surroundings are also made very beautifully, they read
its greenery.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Am em ê mistehme.
We will use it.
Mamuste amal...
Teacher's work...
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Merheba mamoste! Tê meriv çawa... qey em dike saet xweş.
Hello teacher! How are people... let's have a good time.
Ê...
Eh...
De Helîn nede kan ...
Well don't give Helin a spring ...
Welle lakab tişt ... di qad da bas ah...
By God nicknames things ... in the field but ah...
Yelle em ê... em ê werne em avî wî jî noka bas em wê xelas
kin.
Yallah we will... we will come we will look at his too right
now but let's finish that.
Evo... ewe melet avo ...
This... that is the nation ...
Evo ebu niyat ... Molo ebu niyat ...
This is Abu Niyad ... Abu Niyad's house ...
Are.
Yes.
Molo ebu xelîl molo wî ne.
Ebu Xelil's house is not his house.
Are molo wî ye.
Yes it is his house.
Ma ewa wî molo abu xelîl ... anî bo wî ...
Is that his, Ebu Xelil's house ... he brought for him ...
Ev mo teye ebu xelîl.
This is yours, Ebu Xelil.
Xweyekî xerîb tine.
There is no stranger.
Evdel!
Molo Ebu Nîzar.
Ebu Nizar's house.
Eyo Ebu Nîzar.
Eyo Ebu Nizar.
Ere em am derbas bi we ne mo lê aw salih... mo aw nîzar.
Yes we pass by you, house of Salih... house of Nizar.
Maşallah wele hişînek lican teye ye...
Mashallah by God there is a greenery in you...
Maşallah! Ah! E qezincî kilîkê derê jî pir hez dikim eva
şexsîya min e.
Mashallah! Ah! I also really like the handle of the door,
this is my personal thing.
Merheba, merheba.
Hello, hello.
Çawa nî? Şikur halê wa weta wa xweş?
Hello.
How are you? Thank God, how is your condition, is your time
good?
Weleh elhemdulillah ...
By God, praise be to God ...
Maşallah eva nîşan e qencî u kêfa, welle pir xweştir e.
Mashallah this is a sign of goodness and joy, by God it is
much better.
Lê am niha we me mişmişa ... dixwa?
But now we ... eat apricots?
Lê em jê dixwin hene.
But we eat from them, there are some.
Xwedê rizqê we lê we bişîne. E em ne ... rûniştî ne.
May God send your sustenance to you. We are not ... seated.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Aw ev lîmoya li vir wî wî, de de nava hewşê am ... bigrin.
That, this lemon here, come on, in the middle of the yard we
... will record.
Wele bavkekî xweş û kîbar li vira te heye.
By God you have a nice and beautiful father here.
De herî dika bêje ...
Go and tell the shop ...
Ewe sefera...
That trip...
Eyo... Salih... aw...
Eyo... Salih... that...
Weleh maşallah!
By God mashallah!
Weke va gotî fış fış, mişmiş in ne?
Like he said fush fush, they are apricots right?
Fış fış...
Fush fush...
Fış fış ... mişmiş, maşallah wextê wî ye.
Fush fush ... apricot, mashallah it's its time.
Sêke gindor e... hertişt ev dera gund we ye hebe rinde...
welle maşallah... la lim anî...
Look it's a melon... everything here in your village is
nice... by God mashallah...
Lê ava kerez, ew ...
But this is a cherry, that ...
E kû ev firqeta wa yê dîn ... we min diyarî da wa wî... ava
hidiya min e...
That difference of your religion ... you gave me a gift...
this is my gift...
De va xurt e qaw e ...
Come on this is a strong guy ...
Ehê! Maşallah, maşallah.
Aha! Mashallah, mashallah.
Mo maqo ne digir e ?
Is the camera recording?
Qafê... me makîneyê da girtiye ... aw kopya ye ...
The head... we have recorded it in the camera ... that is a
copy ...
Maşallah sêke hinar e, darek femsiye ye, mişmiş e, pirteqal
e te çi diwaze heye ... gindor.
Mashallah look it is a pomegranate, it is a femsiye tree, it
is an apricot, it is an orange whatever you want is here ...
melon.
Gindor jî em gelek me rîsk e, mo wî çêla min re min bizaniba
wa min hebe ... mîrîşk min hebe, wele maşallah tîşt e kêm tu
yî ...
We also have a lot of risks with melons, if I knew I had a
cow ... if I had chickens, by God mashallah the only missing
thing is you ...
Pêça ava... bi kar kêm in ...
But these... are useful ...
E?
Eh?
Ta çêwe... çêwekî xwaştir in.
Until how... they are much better.
Maşallah maşallah!
Mashallah mashallah!
O! E ala evdê te jî we ye wa qey te min meşek jê kir...
Oh! This flag of yours is also like this, as if you made a
walk from it for me...
E wisa roşîn e ... ev bi gane wan rûniştin e ewa ... ere ...
It is bright like this ... they sat with them ... yes ...
Şeklê wî şîn e.
Its shape is blue.
Sêke tîşte weha bas bi e, tîştê xwe ye kêfa wî xwe hebe te
... tama we jî xweş be... ji wî kêfa xwe be... tîştê weha di
kêfê xwe re be.
Look if something is fine like this, your thing that you
have the pleasure of... your taste is also good... from him
it is with pleasure... such a thing should be with your
pleasure.
Le maşallah melhêçe wê jî yek e... cê ye...
But mashallah its saltiness is also one... it's a place...
Sêke darikek malê cê xwe jî çêkiriye ... nîbana te wî jî ...
dîtinî qêş in ...
Look he also made a stick of the house his place ... your
middle one too ... they are nice to see ...
Çend a mo vira wî weye ... me lîstiye divî me we ... em a jê
re em wî ...
How much is his place here ... we played we wanted to ... we
will for him we will ...
Me ji te qehwe te waq xwaş xwar waq...
We drank your coffee so nicely so...
E te qehwe xwe xwar qehwe ta wî xwaşe te tebîe ...
You drank your coffee your coffee is good you are natural
...
Erê evna lî vira jî... am awê vira jî teswîra xwe taqriben
li vir derbaz kin ...
Yes these here too... we will roughly pass our recording
here too ...
Am ata mo molo xolê abû Nîzar xwedê emirê we drêj be am na
nav bar mî dibe wele wa re bê ...
We came to the house of uncle Abu Nizar may God lengthen
your life we don't bring a load maybe by God they will come
...
E... min qehwe we pir vexwariye wele... tiştek min gelek di
we xwariye ...
Uh... I drank your coffee a lot by God... I ate a lot of
your things ...
Xwedê ji we razî be... sax bî gelek xêr û berek... we gundek
heye camêr in... ere... va jê bo we re di ... we nav
milletan ev şexîyetin xurt e... xwedê ji we razî be...
xatira we... siletî wa xweş...
May God be pleased with you... be healthy very good and
blessed... you have a village they are noble... yes... these
are for you in ... you among the nations have strong
personalities... may God be pleased with you... goodbye...
good health to you...
Bêriya te gencan e we ... wa tişt te wenda kir we ... wa
tişt te wenda... navî wa re.
We miss your youth ... you lost that thing ... you lost that
thing... in his name.
... Îbrahim.
... Ibrahim.
Silavê me ji Îbrahîm re heye, o Îbrahîm yav ez xete wî lî
Almanya yek e?
We have greetings for Ibrahim, oh Ibrahim yav I his line is
one in Germany?
Ere ere.
Yes, yes.
Silavê me ji te re hene İbrahim xelî. Hetanî wî we yê te ...
le va bas e wê yê ez te gundê ta kerb be ... we kî ta be ...
We have greetings for you Ibrahim uncle. Until him your ...
but this is fine I will be angry at your village ... whoever
you are ...
Nîzar... wî mizan... aw wî dalil... xwedê ta gel emrê te
drêj bike xwedê satara we lê be we re...
Nizar... he balances... he is proof... may God lengthen your
life may God's shelter be upon you...
Tabe'en le şahiyê der e, stran û dengbêj e û tenbûr lê
dixe... em ê kê derbasî mala mamoste Emar bin, ko em bi
hevra derbas bin.
Of course, outside the celebration, there are songs, a
dengbêj (singer) and playing the tenbûr... we will enter Mr.
Emar's house, let's go in together.
Maşelleh maşelleh maşelleh bismilleh bismilleh.
Mashallah, mashallah, mashallah, bismillah, bismillah.
Hele binere. Çawa ye evna? Erê.
Just look. How is this? Yeah.
Tije ye hele li evna.
It is full, just look at this.
Xêr û bereket li vir e, ha.
Goodness and blessings are here, see.
Mêro şerabê kê hînek xweş be.
Man, whose wine is going to be nice.
Me weha rago mala mamoste Emar.
We made our way to Mr. Emar's house like this.
Mamoste Emar. Merheba, merheba.
Mr. Emar. Hello, hello.
Selam e.
Greetings.
Xêr hatine. Tu çawa ye?
Welcome. How are you?
Selam e elhemdulillah, tu çawa ye? tu çawa ye?
Greetings, thank God, how are you? How are you?
Welleh elhemdulillah, me go em ê derbasî cem te malê bibin
jî.
By God, thank God, we said we will come inside your house
too.
Erê.
Yes.
Ka werin em bi hev ra derbas bin.
Come on, let's go inside together.
Maşelleh.
Mashallah.
Kibar e. Çiqas bi qîmet e.
It is elegant. How valuable it is.
Wê dîtî a gul bîna.
You saw that smelling rose.
Bayê wê pir rind e.
Its breeze is very nice.
Tabe'en wekî te zift e, min go hilkê weha ye. Erê.
Of course, since you are asphalt, I said its slope is like
this. Yeah.
Nêzîk e.
It is close.
Xelkê Fêkrat, hewşa xelkê Fêkrat jî ev weha ye. Dîsa silavên
me ji he re hene.
The people of Fêkrat, the courtyard of the people of Fêkrat
is also like this. Again, we have greetings for them.
Gundekî xweş e.
It is a beautiful village.
Ohoho çiqas dor ber l'vir e. Ev gihane va. Erê.
Oh, how many surroundings are here. It reached these. Yeah.
Maşelleh.
Mashallah.
Gundê, gundê... l'gundê xwe seyr kin o. Erê.
The village of, the village of... look at your own village.
Yeah.
Em berî vê jî meş û tişta, cihkî hatin, me helqa nika wê
derê çêkir. Erê.
Before this too, walking and stuff, we came to a place, we
made the episode near there. Yeah.
Yawaş yawaş min bi alîyê xwe da bikişîne bibe wî.
Slowly pull me towards yourself and take me there.
Maşelleh, maşelleh.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Erê ev hol ne li vir der e, em li mala mamoste Emar in.
Dengbêj e Emar Îbrahîm.
Yes, this hall is not around here, we are at Mr. Emar's
house. The dengbêj (singer) Emar Îbrahîm.
Dengbêjê kurda ye. Dengbêjê gundê Emo ye. Erê. Derê ji
şahiyê der...
He is a Kurdish dengbêj. The dengbêj of the village of Emo.
Yes. Outside of the celebration...
Dilê xelkê şa kirin di de. Nê we ye? Birê Emar.
Bringing joy to people's hearts. Isn't that right? Brother
Emar.
Rast e.
That is right.
L'vê derkê jî em ê ji xalo bipirsin, Ebu Nîzar, ser vê
gundî.
And right here we will ask the uncle, Abu Nizar, about this
village.
Ebu Nîzar me go merheba ji te re, em ê paşê herin dagerin
cem mamoste.
Abu Nizar, we said hello to you, we will later go back to
the teacher.
Ehlen w sehlen mîyet selame, ehlen bi hatina we.
Welcome, a hundred greetings, welcome to your arrival.
Sax be sihet xweş. Gundê Omo.
May you be healthy. The village of Omo.
Gundê Omo.
The village of Omo.
Me'nî çi ye nav lê kirin gundê Omo?
What does it mean that they named it the village of Omo?
Ev gundê Omo, ê li vir, ê eses danî, navê xwe Omo ye. Nav lê
dan gundê Omo.
This village of Omo, the one here, the one who founded the
base, his name is Omo. They named it the village of Omo.
Êwa.
Yes.
Lê bes e ser wê dînim te... yazmîş kirin e, Mezrea Sîno.
But just so I can put it on it... they wrote it down as the
Sîno Farm.
Ev berî vê, teqrîben, yanî bi sedsalî yan û, sê çar mal bûn,
nav lê dan Mezrea.
This before this, approximately, meaning about a hundred
years ago or so, there were three or four houses, they named
it Farm.
Temam? Jê re digotin Mezrea Sîno.
Okay? They called it the Sîno Farm.
Kê navê wê jî Sîno ye? Ev serekî navê kê ma ecêbe?
Whose name is also Sîno? This head, whose name is it, I
wonder?
Dê kî wê çaxê muxtar, ji mala Sîno bû. Jê re digotin Mhemedê
Sîno. Nav lê dan Mezrea Sîno.
Back then the mukhtar, was from the house of Sîno. They
called him Mhemed of Sîno. They named it the Sîno Farm.
Mezrea Sîno.
Sîno Farm.
Heta niha ew di xetê bofkî de jî Mezrea Sîno ye.
Even now, in the official records, it is the Sîno Farm.
Yanî jin mêr ê ava gund ki ne?
So who are the people of this village?
Ê esasê gund, mala Omo ye. Mala Omo. Û dudu werê kî têne?
The foundation of the village is the house of Omo. The house
of Omo. And who are the other two that come?
Du gundê werê mala Mhemedê Sîno ne, mala Hemdê ne.
The other two village families are the house of Mhemed of
Sîno, and the house of Hemdê.
Ev ji xaletiya me ne, mala Delo ne, ew jî xwarzîyê me ne.
They are from our maternal aunts, the house of Delo, and
they are also our nephews.
Ev qet nefsê eqrebê ne. Nefsê eqrebê ne.
They are all from the exact same relatives. The exact same
relatives.
Û mala Henî Silo. Ev ji xaletiya me ne.
And the house of Henî Silo. They are from our maternal
aunts.
Xalo, teqrîben çiqas hewş li vê gundî da ye?
Uncle, approximately how many courtyards are in this
village?
Şêst hewş li vê gundî da ye.
There are sixty courtyards in this village.
Şêst hewş. Xizmet çawa ye? Kehreba heye?
Sixty courtyards. How are the services? Is there
electricity?
Kehreba ke taqeyê şemsî ne.
Electricity is just solar energy panels.
Yanî kehrebaya din negihaştiye we hîna?
Meaning the other electricity hasn't reached you yet?
Na nehatiye. Û av gî bîr in, gişka bîr kolane. Li hewşê heta
xizane tenê ye.
No, it hasn't. And water is all wells, everyone dug a well.
In the courtyard, it's just to the cistern.
Berê tebe'en bîrek ê gundekî hebû. Di da heft gundan.
In the past, of course, there was one well for the village.
It provided for seven villages.
Erê.
Yes.
Boyê jê re ser rêya, cem mefraqa Kûkanê.
So for it to be on the way, near the Kûkanê intersection.
Îdî evana jî, we nê dît jî çet in vir e, we nê stîlam kir
derxistin. Bû vi tenê bîr maye.
So these too, since they saw it is difficult here, they took
it over and extracted it. It became that only this well is
left.
Eses, xebatê dikirin ewa... tu dibê rêxistin minazemat e
gelek çî ye av e bikin inu.
Actually, they were working... you say an organization was
organizing what exactly is to provide water.
Bo we zi'ênen... heft gunda. Te de da heft gunda.
To distribute... to seven villages. It was given to seven
villages.
Da di heft gundan da, di da her dên hecera e çûçik û dên
mezin.
It gave to seven villages, it gave to both the small and
large ones.
Gundî me, gundî Omo, û di da Kûkanê foqanî û tehtanî, û di
da Dargirê û Cûqê.
Our village, the village of Omo, and it gave to Upper and
Lower Kûkanê, and it gave to Dargirê and Cûqê.
Maşelleh rind e.
Mashallah, that's nice.
Xalo.
Uncle.
Firnê gundî we de heye?
Is there a bakery in your village?
Na.
No.
Jê tiştê we nanê xwe dikirin?
Where did you get your bread?
Berê, nan, esil de dikançî tînin.
In the past, bread, basically the shopkeeper brings it.
Mû'temedîn tînin.
The certified ones bring it.
Mû'temedîn tînin. Ne ku jî, esil de her tişt, em wele
ê'tîmadê xwe li ser ê'tîmadê tînin. Ne.
The certified ones bring it. Not that, basically everything,
we rely on the reliance. No.
Hêsan pirbî ye. Na?
Is it very easy. No?
Ne esil pirbî ye. Belê hêsîn kêm bû, xayo.
No, it's not basically easy. Yes, it was a bit less,
brother.
Niha henku tişt, inu, dikan jê de der e.
Now some things, well, the shop is out there.
Rind e. Welle gundekî xweş e mi cografya gund eciband, gundê
we hênik e jî.
It's nice. Indeed, it's a beautiful village, I liked the
geography of the village, your village is cool too.
Hênik e, gund mewqi'a gundî me jî.
It is cool, the village, the location of our village too.
Di ortê çiyayê Kurmênc de ye.
It is in the middle of Kurd Mountain.
Di ortê çiyayê Kurmênc de.
In the middle of Kurd Mountain.
Di ortê çiyayê Kurmênc de ye.
It is in the middle of Kurd Mountain.
Û ne, mesela heta de bal we de, pênc şeş kîlometre.
And not, for example until towards you, it's five or six
kilometers.
Heta çer e, pênc şeş kîlometre.
Until the pasture, it's five or six kilometers.
Heta derşewîn e, pênc şeş kîlometre.
Until the sheepfold, it's five or six kilometers.
Heta bal wî gundî der. Yanî em ortê mewqi'ê ne.
Until out towards that village. Meaning we are in the middle
of the area.
Ev mewqi'ê we tabi'î kî deran e xalo? Tabi'î Mabetan e.
Where does this location of yours belong to, uncle? It
belongs to Mabetan.
Tabi'î Mabetan. Nahiya Mabetan.
It belongs to Mabetan. The district of Mabetan.
Siheta te xweş e. Xwedê te razi be...
Good health to you. May God be pleased with you...
Ya ehlen û sehlen...
Oh, you are very welcome...
Kalê Omo bavkûl bîna te.
Grandfather Omo is an ancestor like you.
Efrîn di ...
Afrin in ...
Efrîn gundê we... emrê gund teqrîben çend sale e?
Afrin, your village... what is the approximate age of the
village?
Emrê gund teqrîben dused, hefte sale e.
The age of the village is approximately two hundred, seventy
years.
Dused, hefte sale.
Two hundred, seventy years.
Ê yanî teqrîbî... erê, tê pêşî mirov re hev didan derkê...
Yeah, roughly... yes, it comes first to people to build a
courtyard here...
Bo ku gund ê te gî hane.
So that your whole village is here.
Ê hinde, di bê we ha bi.
Yeah, somewhat, it should be like that.
Gundê maşelleh kî gî dika.
The village, mashallah, whoever builds it.
Ê hinde, e heta... dused hefte hay e gund. Temam.
Yeah, somewhat, eh until... the village is two hundred and
seventy. Okay.
Û tabi'î gund, gund jî meşhûr e, bi tebî'eta xwe.
And of course the village, the village is also famous, for
its nature.
Mesela, zeytûn in, rezen. Çelu ye...
For example, there are olives, vineyards. It is forested...
Gelekî cî te der e. Hejîr in... dar e. Tebî'etê gund erebî
ye bi giştî.
There are many places here. There are figs... trees. The
nature of the village is generally Arabic.
Bîstan û çandin henar hebûn ber ava. Bi giştî ew ne hiştin
diçandin...
There were gardens and planting of pomegranates before the
water. Generally, they didn't let them plant...
Hinar jî namîna ava zêr e ke... ava kêm bû ev zelorat û niha
di di gund...
Pomegranates also won't stay, water is gold... water has
become scarce, these difficulties, and now in the village...
Temam. Û gund eşqê qedîm e şikeftin... Mesela...
Okay. And the village is filled with old caves... For
example...
Di dere der hene kaf nêre der dibêjin kaf norin...
There are caves out there, they call them the light caves...
Û der erebê in kaf ereb der dibê kaf ta der... mala Hemdê ye
ê mala Hemîd Sîno heye.
And there is an Arab cave there, they say Arab cave, the
cave over there... there is the house of Hemdê, and the
house of Hemîd Sîno.
Evana şixulên kevin in, mala Elî Ereb di vir da ye... ew
tişt hate pirs kirine derkerê...
These are old things, the house of Elî Ereb is in here...
that thing was asked about, extracted...
Siheta te xweş e. Îca ev gund e, em dixwazin... em tabi'eta
vî gundî,
Good health to you. So this is the village, we want... we
want the nature of this village,
Cografyaya vî gundî, em pêş miletê xwe da pêşkêş bikin.
The geography of this village, we present it to our people.
Gundê mirov Kurmanc da nas kirin... em gundî bi we re silav
dikin...
The Kurdish people introduced the village... we greet the
village with you...
Û gundê min... kî merya be, kesekî xerîb tune ye.
And my village... whoever the person is, there is no
stranger.
Rind e.
It is nice.
Te dît. Malbata mala Mihemedî Sîno... xalê gundî yê min in.
You saw. The family of the house of Mihemedî Sîno... are the
maternal uncles of my fellow villagers.
Em ji... eh wesas di gund e. Mala Omo ne.
We are from... uh the foundation is in the village. It is
the house of Omo.
Rabe, ewan bi mala Mihemedî Sîno ve, ewan mala Hemdê ve...
Stand up, those with the house of Mihemedî Sîno, those with
the house of Hemdê...
...Mala Silo ve... mala Delo ve, jin dan, jin girtin derket
in... kî xal û xwarziyê hev e.
...With the house of Silo... with the house of Delo, they
gave wives, took wives, it turned out... everyone is uncle
and nephew to each other.
Xal û xwarzî ye evna... silavê min... ji malbata... bi giştî
re ne.
They are uncle and nephew... my greetings... to the
family... to everyone in general.
Silavê me ji van malbatna re heye. Eşîretna bi nav kirine
gişka, xwedê sitare ser miletê me kurmanc re be, silavê me
li her çar perçan e.
We send our greetings to these families. The tribes that
were mentioned all of them, may God protect our Kurdish
people, our greetings are in all four parts.
Silavê me heçî ku guhdarî dike. Sihet xweş.
Our greetings to everyone who is listening. Good health.
Ehlen w sehlen. Bi xêr hatina we. Spas xweş heval.
You are very welcome. Welcome to you. Thank you, friend.
Sihet xweş. Mamoste Emar em vegerin cem mamoste Emar.
Good health. Mr. Emar, let's return to Mr. Emar.
Mamoste tiştek gotin, nake te di gotina nav kir, xêra te
fêda te xwedê...
The teacher said something, did not include you in the
words, for your goodness, your benefit, God...
Xwedê dest da be re.
May God give a hand to it.
Bira Emar.
Brother Emar.
Em di hatine der gundiyê wa de da. Û nas kirina tebî'et û
cografyayê em paş milet ê.
We came here to your village. And to introduce the nature
and geography after our people.
Silava tu peşan re ne, nasiyet di girtî milet e em... were
meşrû'e ava ke ava neke...
You are presenting a greeting, an advice you give to the
people is... come build a project, don't build...
Belkî bo wa temî te ser dilê wan re xweş bo.
Perhaps to make them feel good in their hearts.
Hêvî dikim piştî ku te xwest bê dar e cem mamoste Emar û
Îbrahîm... welle em ê gelek xwedî şeref bin.
I hope that after you wanted to come here next to the tree
with Mr. Emar and Îbrahîm... by God, we will be very
honored.
Meşrû'e jî wisa... yanî çêtir ciwantiya meriv e tê di. Yanî
gund. Gelek miro ava ke meşro'ê xwe.
A project is also like that... I mean, a person's youth is
better invested in it. Meaning the village. Build your
project with many people.
Cîkê malê xwe, cîkê warê xwe. Çiyayê xwe ke xaniyê bi... te
dît da erda xar. Çiyayê mala xwe...
Your home's place, your land's place. Make your mountain a
house... you saw he dug the ground. Your house's mountain...
Ciyê bav û kalê xwe bişîne... xaniyê nû şîrîne...
Send the place of your ancestors... a new house is sweet...
Na wey xaniyê... malê û bav û kalê wî şêrîn e ji wan...
No, its house... his home and ancestors are sweeter than
them...
Lênihêrin... na?
Look at it... no?
Zikrayatên mirovan tên di pirtûkan de ne.
People's memories come in the books.
Yek ser rûye. Xwedê rehma xwe lê bike ewa jî li Ewrûpa rehma
xwe lê bike welle, dewlet li ber be gund e.
One is on the surface. May God have mercy on him, also the
one in Europe, may God have mercy on him, by God, a state
should protect the village.
Miletê em gişt wê bişînin. Dîsa ez... ha...
We will send all the people. Again I... yes...
Da hazir dikin ten da gundê gundiyê min xwe şanaz dikin.
If they prepare to come to my village, they make themselves
proud.
Lê gundê bav û kal e, şêrîne, destên min nêzîk... dest
mal... noka tişte wele xêr o wê da em hêşiya nakin.
But the ancestral village is sweet, my hands are close...
handkerchief... now something, by God, goodness over there,
we will not leave it.
Elem gund bûn em di ênek da, min gî zarok, dîko wa nê xwar,
gî çoq o ez emrê min yanî ez wênek im.
We were the village world in a mirror, I said children, it
ate like that, all knees, my age, meaning I am a picture.
Her gund... erê dest mamoste bi qewlên mirova te ne di ke.
Every village... yes, the teacher's hand makes people's
promises to you.
Çetir e em wan tişt dikin mi. We toz e gî çik min paqij e
xalo e. Miha maşelleh... xwe wek mirî dînin inu...
It is better that we do those things. It's dusty, everything
is clean, uncle. Our sheep, mashallah... they set themselves
like the dead...
Bira Emar, em dixwazin... tu stranekî ji milet re diyarî
bikî.
Brother Emar, we want... you to dedicate a song to the
people.
Ez stranek weha dikim e... wekî dibên... yê weha bi dilê te
be.
I am making a song like this... as they say... one that will
be to your heart's liking.
Çî di dilê te da ne kîbar e. Dî me mirovek e nas kir di vî
emrî da ez re ne.
What is in your heart is elegant. We have known a person in
this life, I am not.
Ji heskirinên min re, l'Efrîn e, sê sêş eş we re dixim û ez
we ser bilind im we re bi stranê.
For my loved ones, in Afrin, three, three, six, I will play
for you and I am proud of you with the song.
Em li bendê ne te ji sêr dil çavan in em bîhnên xwe nû bikin
in, min bi te sirûdekî...
We are waiting for you from the bottom of our hearts, to
renew our breath, for me a song by you...
Gelek sipas Mela. Gelek sipas Mela.
Thank you very much Mela. Thank you very much Mela.
(Muzîk)
(Music)
Lê lê, lê lê lo.
Oh oh, oh oh.
Nizanim ev serê min ê jandêr çi ye.
I don't know what this aching head of mine is.
Lê lê, lo lo, nizanim ev serê min ê jandêr çi ye.
Oh oh, I don't know what this aching head of mine is.
Nizanim kincê kurdan dirr e.
I don't know, the Kurdish clothes are torn.
Lê lê lo, nizanim kincê kurdan dirr e, nizanim xumxuma gewre
ye lo lê.
Oh oh, I don't know, the Kurdish clothes are torn, I don't
know, maybe the gray jug is broken.
Min dêmê xwe fetiland, an te baş raşêkirî, li ser hekîmê
şukur te zemên e.
I turned my face, or you painted it well, thankfully you are
the doctor of the times.
Lê hekîmê zemên lê dinêrî, go law lo lo.
But the doctor of the times looked at him and said, oh boy.
Derdê te ne xumxuma gewre kurê dirê ye.
Your pain is not the gray jug or the torn clothes.
Derdê te li diyara çiyayê Kurmênc be,
Your pain is in the lands of the Kurmenc mountain,
Bere Mihemed koça giran e.
Since Muhammad's heavy caravan.
Ha ha, de başo, de başo.
Ha ha, come on fine one, come on fine one.
Lawo lo lo, de başo gencê min başo, siwarê min başo.
Oh boy, come on fine young one, my fine rider.
De başo, de başo, lo lo.
Come on fine one, come on fine one, oh.
Her bijî, dest sax bin.
Long live, bless your hands.
Guharê min çil xar bi dest e,
My earrings have forty beads on hand,
Zend û semra min rast e.
My wrists and arms are straight.
Guharê min çil xar bi dest e,
My earrings have forty beads on hand,
Zend û semra min rast e.
My wrists and arms are straight.
Eşqa dila mirin e,
The love of hearts is death,
Dil şikestî ne rast e.
A broken heart is not right.
Eşqa dila mirin e,
The love of hearts is death,
Dil şikestî ne rast e.
A broken heart is not right.
Wey yarê lê yarê,
Oh beloved, oh beloved,
Yar çi keko bihar e.
Oh brother, the beloved is like spring.
Destê xort destê min de,
The young man's hand in mine,
Ber bi çiyayê hawar e.
Heading towards the mountain of cries.
Ha ha, wey yarê lê yarê,
Ha ha, oh beloved, oh beloved,
Yar çi keko bihar e.
Oh brother, the beloved is like spring.
Destê xort destê min de,
The young man's hand in mine,
Ber bi çiyayê hawar e.
Heading towards the mountain of cries.
Wey yarê lê yarê...
Oh beloved, oh beloved...
(Instrumental)
Yara min tev şêrîn e,
My beloved is all sweet,
Ji çiyayê Lêlûn e.
From the mountain of Lelun.
Yara min tev şêrîn e,
My beloved is all sweet,
Ji çiyayê Lêlûn e.
From the mountain of Lelun.
Şikir da dilê min e,
Thank God she is in my heart,
Vê şekalê lon e.
In this form, oh.
Şikir da dilê min e,
Thank God she is in my heart,
Vê şekalê lon e.
In this form, oh.
Wey yarê lê yarê,
Oh beloved, oh beloved,
Yar çi keko bihar e.
Oh brother, the beloved is like spring.
Destê xort destê min de,
The young man's hand in mine,
Ber bi çiyayê hawar e.
Heading towards the mountain of cries.
Saet xweş mamoste, saet xweş, dest sax bin, Xwedê emrê te
dirêj bike dede.
Well done teacher, well done, bless your hands, may God give
you a long life, elder.
Mamoste, çend sal in tu bi vê karî dikî? Te ev tenbûre lê
dixe?
Teacher, how many years have you been doing this work?
Playing this tanbur?
Xwedê ev tembûre, heştê û çar, heştê û pêncan da min tembûr
lê dixe.
By God, this tanbur, I have been playing the tanbur since
eighty-four, eighty-five.
Di koma da, di daweta da, di tiştan da. Erê.
In bands, at weddings, at things. Yes.
We wê demê lê dixistin?
Did you play at that time?
Ê, me dest... 70, me dest pê kir. 77 ew bû min pêşî xwe re
da eskeriyê.
Well, we... I started in '70. In '77 I went to the military
first.
Yanî pêşî wê da kesî lê dixist tenbûr?
So did anyone play the tanbur before that?
Xwedê kesî nedi... na di kesî lê nedixist.
By God, nobody... no, nobody played it.
Yanî hûn bi hewa, hûn xwe bi xwe hîn bûn?
So you learned it by yourself, out of interest?
Ha wisa meraq e, meraq.
Yes, it was curiosity, curiosity.
Meraq! Te bê mamoste te lê dixist, ne?
Curiosity! You played it without a teacher, right?
Erê.
Yes.
Maşallah. Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike dede, em silav dikin...
Mashallah. May God give you a long life elder, we send our
greetings...
Mamoste, ev mitrib... kasetên te hene? An arşîvek we heye?
Teacher, do you have cassettes? Or do you have an archive?
Eh, me kaset... çar-pênc kasetên min arşîv hene weke stran.
Me qeyd kirin.
Yes, we have cassettes... I have four or five archived
cassettes of songs. We recorded them.
Wê demê çi klam, çi stran te lê dikirin?
At that time, what poems, what songs did you perform?
Tebîen, Şerê Mihemed Elî tê de ne, Şerê Hisênê Beto tê de
ne.
Naturally, the Battle of Mihemed Eli is in there, the Battle
of Hisene Beto is in there.
Erê, mamoste tê de ne.
Yes, teacher, they are in there.
Tu çend salî yî?
How old are you?
Şêst û pênc sal.
Sixty-five years old.
Maşelleh, emrê te xêr be.
Mashallah, may your life be blessed.
Di şêst-heftê salan da... tenbûrcî li cem we çend bûn?
In these sixty or seventy years... how many tanbur players
were around you?
Ê tenbûrcî, emrê tenbûrcî kêm bûn.
Well, tanbur players, the era of tanbur players was scarce.
Lê em miletê kurd bi xwe tiştekî wisa heye ku ev tûrasa me
ye.
But we Kurdish people ourselves have such a thing that this
is our heritage.
Tûras, belkî... tûras e me kurdan e tenbûr. Tenbûr bi xwe
tûrasê me kurdan e.
Heritage, perhaps... the tanbur is the heritage of us Kurds.
The tanbur itself is our Kurdish heritage.
Tebîen mamoste, dengbêjê vê gundî ye. Gundê Omo.
Naturally, the teacher is the singer of this village. The
village of Omo.
Saetên wî gelek xweş. Ev jî bi vî rengî xizmeta miletê xwe
dike.
Well done to him. He too serves his people in this way.
Herin ha, bi çend awayan xizmet dikin. Îro heye necar e,
saqfiya xelkê digire. Îro heye mesela tenbûrê lê dixe.
Look, they serve in several ways. Today he is a carpenter,
fixing people's roofs. Today, for example, he plays the
tanbur.
Saetên wî gelek xweş, xwedê jê razî be. Saetên we gişkan
xweş.
Well done to him, may God be pleased with him. Well done to
all of you.
Em pir kêfxweş bûn, em hatin vê gundî. Gundekî pir xweş e.
Miletê tê de jî xweş e, kibar e.
We were very happy to come to this village. It is a very
beautiful village. The people in it are also nice and
polite.
Silavên me ji miletê vê gundî re hene, çûçik, mezin, çavê
gişkan maç dikim.
We send our greetings to the people of this village, young
and old, I kiss everyone's eyes.
Saet xweş.
Well done.
Tiştekî din jî heye, mamoste, silavê min ji bo biraderan re.
Ji vir heta welatê xerîbiyê.
There is another thing, teacher, my greetings to the
brothers. From here to the foreign lands.
Û welatiyan, heval û cîranan. Silavên me li gişkan be, ji
mezin û qiseyan gişkî re.
And to the compatriots, friends and neighbors. May our
greetings be to everyone, to the elders and the young alike.
Xwedê emrê we dirêj bike.
May God prolong your lives.
Welleh, kake Mistefa, xalê Hanîf... mîna xizanê me ne,
maşelleh tam mîna çîçeka ye.
By God, brother Mistefa, uncle Hanif... they are like our
youth, mashallah, just like a flower.
Welleh min got wekî çîçeka ye.
By God I said he's like a flower.
Tiştên hûrik e. Çîçikên xwarinê?
He is small things. Food flowers?
Eceb em mezin dibin, em pê nahesin, em dereng dimînin.
Strangely we grow old, we don't realize it, we run late.
Me re şêrîn dibe.
It becomes sweet to us.
Me re şêrîn dibe ne?
It becomes sweet to us, right?
Bes dilê me nexweş dibe.
Only our hearts get sick.
Dilê, dilê mêra tirs, dilê hewî lo ye.
The heart, the fearful heart of men, is an empty heart.
Her bijî xalê. Saet xweş.
Long live uncle. Well done.
Çelkê dikin.
They are taking it.
Gelî xortan, xalê Fikret... Mihemed, ev hewş a te ye?
Hey guys, uncle Fikret... Mihemed, is this your yard?
Çi hewşek xweş te çêkiriye. Çi kibar çêkiriye. Xwedê rizqê
gundiyan bide.
What a beautiful yard you have made. You made it so polite.
May God give provision to the villagers.
Kilît... cam... min nizanî we wisa hewş kişandiye...
Lock... glass... I didn't know you fenced the yard like
this...
Erê. O hooo, li vir re lê bigire.
Yes. Oh hooo, film it from here.
Te dor û berê xwe weha girtiye...
You fenced your surroundings like this...
Weleh dor û berê mezin e, maşelleh... tije ye...
By God the surroundings are big, mashallah... it's full...
Tiyên xwe girê dane ne?
You tied your white birds, right?
Tiyên spî ye... kamil in.
They are white birds... they are mature.
Bes çûk dexe, çûk, çûkên kedî.
Just put some birds, birds, domesticated birds.
Ehe. Maşelleh ev kî ristek pêk aniye.
Yeah. Mashallah, whoever established this routine.
Min nedît... tu kîfa te? Ev çi hewşeke mezin e... min nizanî
tu li vir... hewş... tiştek...
I didn't see... what's your mood? What a big yard this is...
I didn't know you here... yard... something...
Welleh canê te... weha ye... Hingî diyar bû... helal ke lo
helal ke.
By God, your soul... it's like this... Since it appeared...
forgive me, oh forgive me.
Xaltî kerem ke, tiştekî wisa bay-bay ke... em weha wêne
dikişînin. Welleh hewşek wek gund e...
Auntie go ahead, wave bye-bye like that... we are taking
pictures like this. By God, a yard like a village...
Na çawa... we bîra hewşa xwe kiriye?
No, how... have you missed your yard?
Mirov ku ji hewşa xwe dûr be, zîhniyeta hewşê bi bîra mirov
dikeve... ditiqtiqe.
When a person is away from their yard, the memory of the
yard comes to mind... it ticks.
Dema ku tu diçûyî te çi dikir, te çi nedikir? Bi kîjan alî
de?
When you went, what did you do, what didn't you do? In which
direction?
Maşelleh, ev hewşeka mezin û kibar e.
Mashallah, this is a big and neat yard.
He... li vir wisa...
Yeah... here it's like this...
Av jî...
Water too...
Av di hewşa we da heye? Bîra avê ye?
Is there water in your yard? Is it a water well?
Erê rinde... bîr hebe bi wê hewşê weha re, mirov dikare
nexweşiyê ji xwe dûr bixe.
Yes, it's good... with a well in a yard like that, one can
keep illness away from themselves.
Wer em... xwarê de biçin?
Shall we... go down?
Wer em ji vê derê jî bigrin.
Come, let's film from here too.
Cihê we pir xweş e, weleh cihê gund pir xweş e.
Your place is very beautiful, by God the village place is
very beautiful.
Ho ho, maşallah. Ev dara hejîrê... darên fêkî. Fêkiyên xweş
derdixe...
Ho ho, mashallah. This fig tree... fruit trees. It produces
delicious fruits...
Cîran jî weha li pey in. Darê cinnetê ye ev dar.
Neighbors are also behind like this. This tree is the tree
of paradise.
Xwedê rizqê wan li wan bide.
May God give them their provision.
Welleh.
By God.
(Inaudible background talking)
Erê kekê Mistefa me hawşewa ne, can de am diko ta, ho hawşê
qoser ke, ho seke!
Yes brother Mustafa, we are in the courtyards, we will go
there, look at the courtyard of the Qoser family, look!
Erê... ho tê neh, sariyê dî ho...
Yes... look there is a well...
Sariyê çi ye ha, rind e.
It's quite a well, it's nice.
Şopa milet gelek ketiye warî. Erê.
The path of the people has turned to the ground. Yes.
Ho ev hewşe wa ye. Em kîne ko, hewşê Ebû Henon jî vira
bisewirînin.
Look, this is their courtyard. We will go and film Abu
Henon's courtyard here too.
Ebû Henon, silavek meş te re hene, lo ortê hewşê wa de.
Abu Henon, we have greetings for you, right in the middle of
their courtyard.
Em kîne ko derbazî hewşê wa bin.
We are going to enter their courtyard.
Werre... Ebû Henon...
Come... Abu Henon...
Ebû Henon maşallah mêwe te tiştekî qurix e.
Abu Henon, mashallah, your fruits are something beautiful.
Erê... Ev hewşe wa ye.
Yes... This is their courtyard.
Hewşê gundê vira bigr.
Film the courtyard of the village here.
Te bîra min e berê vira hinar dîn, dar mazî min bîn, ma
dihat in hinar dixwar in.
Do you remember, there were pomegranate and oak trees here
before, when we were small we used to come and eat
pomegranates.
Bî hat?
Have they come?
Bes bî yek ke.
Just do one.
Em nevê rûnin naha en, makîne ma bi gir.
We are not going to sit here now, film our car.
Erê Ebû Henon, em hatin.
Yes Abu Henon, we have come.
Erê... em kîne ko li çin serê xên e.
Yes... we are going to go on the roof of the house.
Ev hewşe wa ye.
This is their courtyard.
Wê ev lîmana xirto kê ji vir va jîyanê lê bigir e, Kîbor.
Film this life from this side too, Kibor.
Ev hewş malê Mihemed e, hem dî qelê hebû.
This courtyard is Muhammad's house, they also had a castle.
Erê... bin vir de tab'en ew e bi derece.
Yes... under here there are naturally stairs.
Lê çoxtê xeyrî ya. Ho...
But it has changed a lot. Look...
Werre bay bay ke, bay bay ke wa liko!
Come wave bye bye, wave bye bye to them!
Deko Mistef e, bay bay ke. Tiştî nîzîk bik min lo bay bay
ke.
Come Mustafa, wave bye bye. Zoom in on me a bit, wave bye
bye.
Ho Xalê Henîf yî li ko, ho cîronê wane, cîron.
Look, Uncle Henif is here, look he is their neighbor,
neighbor.
Bay bay... bay bay...
Bye bye... bye bye...
Maşallah welle mewqe xweş e, ho Ebû Henon mewqeyê hewşê te.
Mashallah, the location is really nice, look Abu Henon, the
location of your courtyard.
Avyê lê mî war rû'ir bi gir.
Come up here and film here too.
Ha, na na em nahaç e'f nînak in... Oh...
Yeah, no no we are not going to forgive now... Oh...
Vê malê nû bigir, ev mala kê ye?
Film this new house, whose house is this?
Em naha ketin be şor e ye, şorek dever de heye.
Now we have entered a path, there is a path here.
Welle pir de hatim ser vê xaniyê o bin e...
Well, I came to this house a lot before...
Vê hewşe nû nîzîk bik e avyî limina, na na dor şer meke bi
gire.
Zoom in on this new courtyard here, no no don't fight with
the tree, film it.
Se ke xudani bi tê ne...
Look, the owner is bringing it...
Dar bar e giçûbî na.
The trees and stones are small.
Ho war ro vir wero.
Look, come this way.
Hê... hê... hê çoxoço çêlek di vira de na.
Look... look... look how many cows are here.
Çoxoço wî wî, hê hê çoxoço çêlek di vira de na.
Look at this, look look how many cows are here.
Te xwe de te warkî sani
Bring yourself a bit...
Ho vî, vê hewşine gî ho bi gir e wer ro vir ro.
Look, film this courtyard too, come this way.
Weh, barê şoreyê xwey kê fere bî, di der bî tûçûk bî, me
dihat im vir.
Look, this path has become wide, outside it was small, we
used to come here.
Qen ne hun nê bî noko, gi bîn e dîyar, gi bîn e hewş.
It's good that you film this, everywhere you look are
courtyards.
Lê... Ebû Henon birk a te yev ho birk!
Look... Abu Henon, here is your pool, look pool!
Bes dîyorî taw o dare ha dî miye, ew birka we ye lik ho.
But look, there's a tree standing there, that is their pool
there.
Ha çaxê li sewrê nîştim e, mak a çaxê li sewra nîştim e
diderî hinara bî.
At that time I sat for the filming, when I sat for the
filming it was outside the pomegranates.
Birka xweş bî wî dare.
There was a nice pool by that tree.
Ho war ro vir wa jî lê bigire.
Look, come film from that side too.
O, wa mal no bigr e!
Oh, film those houses!
Hêy... Erê! Zikriyat e me çox se vir rone, kuçik bîn.
Hey... Yes! My memories are many here, we were little.
Kuçik bî min, am tê pni li dîv da hat în vî dar a...
I was little, we were running after it to this tree...
Maşallah! Tabi'î vî gindî xweş e, cuxrafiya vî gundî pirr
xweş e.
Mashallah! Of course this village is beautiful, the
geography of this village is very beautiful.
Bo kî hênik tê.
A cool breeze is coming.
Maşallah, haviş ek Kîbor ji de virde çêkirne, xwedê riziqê
gundîye bê şîn a!
Mashallah, what a huge courtyard they built here, may God
provide sustenance to the villagers!
Hewş a Kîbor di vir de je... hi...
The huge courtyard is here... yeah...
Erê, ew li vî darkî jî em li mala Xalê Henîf ne, em kê
xitamê xwe bi dîn.
Yes, from this place too, we are at the house of Uncle
Henif, we will give our conclusion.
Em gişt in tolîya wîdyoyê xwe. Wîdyoya me dirêj bî, bi
teqrîban pênca deqa.
We reached the end of our video. Our video became long,
about fifty minutes.
Teqsîr meqsîrê me hene, hun ew qisurê me jî 'ef kin.
We have shortcomings, forgive our flaws.
Seg mal der neket bin wê, leni wîdya me ektireyê ge 'ef
bûye.
If a dog didn't come out of the house... in our video it is
mostly forgiven.
Tabî dîsa em dibêjin silavê me, ji milletê vî gundî re hene.
Of course, again we say, we have greetings for the people of
this village.
Biçûk, mezin, çavê giya maç dikem. Silav ji Ebû Henon re..
Little, big, I kiss everyone's eyes. Greetings to Abu
Henon...
Heta bajarê Nemsa! U gundî lê nemçoy...
Up to the city of Austria! And the villagers...
Ji Xaltîka Fîkret re, û Um 'Emar silavê me ji wan re hene,
heta Rûsya.
To Aunt Fikret, and Mother Amar, we have greetings for them,
up to Russia.
Kes ev gund i çav ê giya maç dikem.
People of this village, I kiss everyone's eyes.
Emer Koçer! Ser serê min e, Emer Koçer ti ware ye... te dîsa
bo Moskow ye.
Emer Kocher! Upon my head, Emer Kocher, you are from here...
you went to Moscow again.
Emer Koçer hat cihkê mexreb e ro Moskow, xweş bî. Me kêf
kir, welleh ha ge dîsa bê...
Emer Kocher came, he went back to Moscow, it was nice. We
had fun, well, if he comes again...
H... xaltîka Siyon zêra... Em Resul silavê me ji Em Resul e
re jî hene.
Hı, Aunt Siyon Zera... We have greetings for Mother Resul as
well.
Welleh me'ezet e rind e, te wîne bîra ma.
Well, you have good honor, you remind us.
Sehhet xweş. Me'ezet e... em zakir kin dî... Em Resul silavê
me jê re jî hene.
Good health. It's an honor... we remember... We have
greetings for Mother Resul too.
Tabe'înê me ye.
She is our follower.
Got in wahene. Xalê Henîf, em berî kamerayê xwe digirin...
They said they are here. Uncle Henif, we are turning our
cameras...
Sahet te xweş Xalê Henîf. Em pir kêfxweş bîn bi wera...
milletê gundî wera xwe îkr kir...
Good health to you, Uncle Henif. We are very happy with
you... the village people treated us well...
Û em ji wan re, rihet bîn.
And we were comfortable with them.
Sehet we xwaş... ko vê ro bay bay ke in a... bay bay bi
qatira we..
Health to you all... let's wave bye bye from here... bye bye
to your mules...
Em ine ke laxtokê çindin jî wera ti kine. Bay bay... bay
bay...
We are going to put some cuts from here for you too. Bye
bye... bye bye...
Me bi muzîkê kin...
Put some music on for us...
Erê ev lîmana vê derkî jî, em diçûn mal, me xitam kirbû
vîdyoyê xwe.
Yes, from this place too, we were going home, we had
finished our video.
Tab'en vê derkê vira dibên zinara îneyê.
Of course this place here they call the Rock of Ine.
Erê zinara îneyê, li vê derê wa dibên.
Yes, the Rock of Ine, that's what they call it here.
Maşallah dorbir a qop er neh.. û av jî heye.
Mashallah, it's nice all around... and there is water too.
Li vê derê jî xalê tîkê min ji muhabetê ye, l'vê derê birkek
çêkiriye. Me'nê milet wêre seyrane.
And here my uncle is from love, he built a pool here.
Meaning the people come here for picnics.
Eee, welle di şoxile, herekat heye. Îneyê pir zehmet dibe.
Yeah, well it's working, there's movement. Ine becomes very
crowded.
Erê wa qe wara meq'ed... meq'ed jî gi çêkirne.
Yes like this, seating... they made seating everywhere.
Teba an na çêkirne. Yanê hin belaş na çêkirine.
Of course they didn't make them just like that. Meaning they
didn't make them for free.
Kesê kû ware, kesê kû ware wêne we ziftê we ware, win
gihştine zifte.
Whoever comes, whoever comes look, they come on the asphalt,
you reach the asphalt.
Win gihştine zifte, rêka terabiya ta ser til ro xwe berdi da
ta... Winkanin divê yolê ra jî werin li vê derê, li ber golê
avê.
You reach the asphalt, the dirt road goes until you let
yourself down... You can come through this road too here, by
the water lake.
Arê ew barakê xwe ya vî, cihê menqel e me şewi...
Yes look at his shed there, the place of our barbecue is
burning...
Kesê kû quştê xwe bixwaze, wer e, derbê k ew we derê diyî
ne.
Whoever wants their meat, come, immediately put the water
here.
Qanon ew menqal gî cehiz kirne. Meq'ed jî çêkirne wek dare
we.
They already prepared the barbecue by law/order. They made
seating like wood.
War am sê kin. Tab'en o wun kanin wek 'eyleyê xwe, xwe wura
wîn i vi dare. Li vi dare pişt ew çêkiriye.
Come let's look. Of course you can come with your family,
look here. Here behind they built water.
Ew maq'edê xwe guh na na.
They change their seating.
Cihokê, hesirê xwe dîni erde, rune, li derikê xwe a... cog
ze li ser meq'eda runi, bas wel eh mevre 'ecib im li ser
meq'edo.
It's a place, put your mats on the ground, sit, in your own
place... just sit on the seats, but wow I'm surprised by the
seating.
Pir Kîbor çêkiri ye... sateha gundi xweş e.
He built it very well... the health of the village is good.
Tiştekî wiha di mantiqe de hebe pir xweşe Kîbor a.
If there is such a thing in the region, it is very nice and
great.
Tab'en bi şave jî un kanin war in. Kehreb a qe çêkirne.
Lamba geş dikin.
Of course you can come at night too. They installed
electricity nicely. They turn on the lamps.
L'vê dere cema, aw diwore dera.
Around here they gather, water comes out there.
Aw eva dipişî we ro dara.
The water is coming down behind you.
O tevle ji hawir wera, ha qaçikek mo xwa kire.
And those tables around here, we made a small cut for
ourselves.
Ko wera avilimê we r a...
Come here, to this side...
Sa ke... Cugzê denav avê ro ronina, farq nake!
Look... just sit inside the water, it doesn't matter!
Taqet dere extiyar kera.
You can choose your place.
Se ke xweşik çêkiriye e, gine foka dar... lambe melevvîn
wexesniye, biy evarê cewê xa pir xweş dibe.
Look how beautifully they made it, above the trees... they
hid colored lamps, in the evening its atmosphere becomes
very nice.
Ti kanî d'vire da kevî... Tû qeçikê xwe evî warî ciyê xwe
pir xweş dibe.
You can go down there... You and your kids and this place
your spot becomes very nice.
Sê ke sersiyê xwe pira e, rune dite... de nav vî dere
rune...
Look its surface is wide, giving space... sit inside this
place...
Qen î mase ji habîn a. Te çengeli xwe ji ba bo ya na... Tame
care mase dat keme..
Good thing there are tables too. You leave your struggle
behind... I am putting down the table for a moment..
Te cengeli xwe ji çakiro, hema dar xist we, dî nî se
meqali...
You did your struggle, there is wood placed, sit by the
barbecue...
Ajweyek... pir xweş e.. sê ke...
An atmosphere... very nice.. look...
Wale ve ro, tişkê xo.. çakir bo n... çib i ya... req bi...
masî e ya n z nim... req e... a ha won ni reqi n
Wow here, a thing of his.. they made.. what is it.. it's
hard.. fish it is I don't know.. it's hard.. yes they are
hard.
Req jî tê hene.
There are hard ones too.
Ajiwayik pir xweş e. Sersiyê xwe... sê ke...
A very nice atmosphere. Its surface... look...
Hatok dare û dî nê ewi...
Up to the tree and gives it...
Mentiqa pir xweş dibe... mentiqa pir xweş dibe.
The region is very nice... the region is very nice.
Her der ek tiştiki wen e ba bi... rind e.
If every place is like this... it's nice.
Lo di mîra ko gind e.. milet baş de e'ciz e. Mara texile xwe
muxeyelê xwe li vê derê de ravi ne.
Among the people of the village.. the people get very tired.
A person comes and relieves their stress and imagination
here.
Qeçkê xwe, mare ti nî ve derê rawî in y... mara...
Their kids, a person comes to this place and rests... a
person...
Lê ev derê tam şeghal e, ji xwazê Êniwê werin, ji xwazê riya
Qadiyê werin.
But this place is very active, if you want come from Êniwê,
if you want come from the Qadiyê road.
Sêkin du rê bi hev re ne, ev cî we pir xwaş e.
Look, two roads are together, this place is very beautiful.
Hûn dikarin bi roj werin, bi êvarî werin, xwar rûnin.
You can come by day, come by evening, and sit down.
Ma go, di zivistanê giştan sar e, kes nayê, te dît sar tîr
derdikeve, de di vî alî re jî hûn dikarin werin.
We said, in winter it is cold everywhere, nobody comes, you
see the bitter cold comes out, well you can also come this
way.
Rêk diçe dariya da, da em herin hindava avê. Û çay jî li
hambar e, te dî ewê çayê.
The road goes through the trees, so we can go towards the
water. And the river is across, you see that river.
Wextê xwaş meriv konake vir çêke.
It's a beautiful time for one to build a tent here.
Arê hava jî, ev mabate, me di de go ev mabate, xortekî
mabate çêkiriye.
Yes this weather too, this place of conversation, we were
saying this place of conversation, a young man made a place
of conversation.
Em jî me bîstî wek rî, me go em carek ra derbas bin em aj wa
sê kin.
We also heard about it just like this, we said let's pass by
once and take a look at it.
Ma ne rinde, em hatin û em pêşnîyazî we jî dikin, em werin
li vê derê, qeçkê xwa bînin seyranê.
Isn't it nice, we came and we also suggest to you, to come
here, bring your kids for a picnic.
Dîyo de saetên we xwaş, û me vîdyo jî dirêj kir, me xatema
xwe da avê, li jêr gundê Êmû. Em hatin, me xwest pê vir jî
kevin, cem birakê min.
Well then, have a good time, and we also made the video
long, we ended up at the water, below the village of Êmû. We
came, we wanted to drop by here too, to my brother's place.
Saetên gundiya xwaş, her yekî tişkî wisa veke, çavê gundiya
xwaş bike, xwedê rizqê gundiya bişîne.
May the villagers have a good time, let everyone open
something like this, make the villagers' eyes happy, may God
send the villagers' provision.
Rind e, anha mantaqa me dibe mantaqa sîyahî ye. Yanî milet
yê înê di dera, Meydankê, Batmanê.
It's nice, now our region is becoming a tourist region.
Meaning people will come here, to Meydankê, Batmanê.
Ê no, ev derê hebe jî, li ziravekî hebe, binî gundê Êmû, ev
derê jî xwaş e, nêzîk e, av jî heye.
And well, if this place exists, if there is a stream, below
the village of Êmû, this place is also beautiful, it's
close, there is water too.
Saetên we xwaş, de bi me ra bin, em ê vîdyoyekî din ji bo we
xwaş, em ê wera bikişînin û nêzîk de em ê daqin.
Have a good time, well stay with us, we will shoot another
nice video for you, and we will upload it soon.
A de bi xatrê we. Werin vê derê ha. Werin. Yallah, bay.
Alright, goodbye. Come to this place, alright. Come. Yallah,
bye.