Ha hêştir, ha hêştir ferq... Taben mîrê kerr neçê dike, gar
min e, taze ne.
Ha donkey, ha donkey difference... Of course the prince of
donkeys doesn't do well, it's my turn, it's fresh.
Kê gulok ji min ra têke?
Who will give me a bouquet?
Maşalla ji vê gundî re. Wadi ye.
Mashallah to this village. It is a valley.
Binê tebîetê ginda.
Look at the nature of the villages.
Maşalla, hevo kenar e, hevo bilbil e, çi dengê xwe xweş e.
Mashallah, this is a canary, this is a nightingale, what a
beautiful voice it has.
Hev dare jî hem giştin mala xaltîkê.
These trees, too, we have arrived at Auntie's house.
Cam şabo bo... Carkî me qenat çêkiriye, me çîçkî dez tê çako
berdayo yale.
[Unclear]... Once we made a channel, we released a little
[unclear] into it.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Ev çiko, mroş tirmîşo?
What is this, a pear or something?
Weke me'zete.
It's like a goat.
Dû hemçûne gindekî...
Two like a village...
Hevo millet, bixo ge meyvan pirr danin gindo, em xoş
evdiravilda em darbas kevin nosta.
This nation, indeed there are many guests in the villages,
we [unclear] we will pass into the middle.
Merheba hevalno, siba we bi xêr, inşalla hûn rind in û rihet
ne.
Hello friends, good morning to you, God willing you are good
and comfortable.
Îro jî emê li Raco ne.
Today we are in Rajo.
Taben vîdyê me jî hûr, emê teqaz gundê Hecemala bin.
Of course, our video today, we will definitely be in
Hecemala village.
CEM AÎLET EMM MEHDÎN.
AT EM MEHDÎN'S FAMILY.
Emê darbas wê malbatê bin, û emê vîdyokî nû gundê Hecemala
wara çêkin.
We will visit that family, and we will make a new video for
you in Hecemala village.
Û emê darbas malê Em Mehdînê bin jî, hew jî Yûtyûber e, hew
jî qenatê wan jî heye.
And we will visit Em Mehdîn's house too, she is also a
YouTuber, they have a channel too.
Kasê dixwaze qenatê Em Mehdîn îştîrak ke.
Anyone who wants to subscribe to Em Mehdîn's channel.
Hevo qenata gundî ye, imkanin herin qenatê gundî jî îştîrak
kin, însanê 'eqba ger ne.
This is the village channel, it is possible to go subscribe
to the village channel too, they are good people.
Û vîdyê xwe jî xweş û kîbar ne.
And their videos are nice and elegant.
Walla ez mutabînê gund im û ez jî lê sêr dikim, Em Izzet bê
te min t'an.
By God, I am a follower of the village and I watch it too,
Em Izzet come here to me.
Siba we bi xêr hevalno, çawani başin, inşalla hûn gir bin
rihet ne.
Good morning friends, how are you, hope you are well, God
willing you are all comfortable.
Erê dîsa em hûr wara hatin, vîdyokî xweş kîbar çêkin, û
vîdyê me jî hûr mumeyez e.
Yes, again we came here today, to make a nice elegant video,
and our video today is special.
Emê herin cem aîlet Em Mehdîn.
We are going to Em Mehdîn's family.
Bi me ra bin, vîdyokî xweş kîbar emê wara çêkin, û taben emê
gund jî wara bisawirînin, Hecemala.
Stay with us, we will make a nice elegant video for you, and
of course we will film the village for you, Hecemala.
Bîr nekin me ra layk û îştîrakê pêkin û te'lîqna xweş kîbar
j me re binivîsin, û saeta we gelek xweş.
Don't forget to like and subscribe for us and write us nice
elegant comments, and have a very good time.
Erê hevalno, ka me ra bin, ez kê hediyekî biçûk vêra bibem.
Yes friends, stay with us, I will give a small gift to this
one here.
Guh ra em kanin, heke hediyekê vêra bibem. Erê.
Let's see if we can, if I give a gift to this one. Yes.
Erê hevalno, vî derê, Em Izzet evna ixtiyar kirin, ez
nizanim min di ecibîne ne ecibîne jî ez nizanim.
Yes friends, here, Em Izzet chose these, I don't know if I
like it or not, I don't know.
Hev zûqê Em Izzet e. Taben destoke.
This is Em Izzet's taste. Of course, hold this.
Emê vê banê vêra bibin.
We will take this vest here.
Taben heva min ecibandî bî, min ev ne ecibandî jî, ji ê qelb
şikî ye, min ewê me'nê nebir, emê van bibin.
Of course even if I liked this or didn't like it, since her
heart is broken [soft], I didn't refuse her wish, we will
take these.
Têkî...
Put...
Inşalla gulê gulê jî têda bixun, he?
God willing, may you wear it with joy, huh?
Têk tûr me ra, Ewîl?
Put it in a bag for us, Awil?
Erê, xîzê xokê me jî divê île mişebekekî bixwe.
Yes, our own desire/nature requires that we must eat a
mushabak.
Sibe mişebek xweş ne. Were, were, çend kîlo tera bibim?
Morning mushabaks are good. Come, come, how many kilos shall
I get for you?
Tu çiqasî divê bibe.
Take however much you want.
Kîloyê mişebeka bi heştê, heştê tirk. Taben mêrka neçê dike,
germ ne, taze ne.
A kilo of mushabak is eighty, eighty Turkish [lira]. Of
course the man makes them well, they are hot, they are
fresh.
Kê gulok ji min ra têke?
Who will put a piece for me?
Na, na, naxwazim.
No, no, I don't want.
Elî, Elî, ne xalî.
Ali, Ali, not empty.
Şukran, ya'tîk el afî.
Thanks, God give you health.
Ah, avna geytane ha?
Ah, these are from Geytane/Olive branch area?
Dilê xwe mişebeka dixwaze. Hîn dû dom rwa he dibê.
Her heart wants mushabak. She is saying [unclear].
Ala suhêla, xalî.
Welcome, uncle.
Şukran.
Thanks.
Walla maşalla tiştê, m'go maşalla tiştê xolû... a, pak e.
Êêê, çi sêv in e.
By God, mashallah the stuff, I said mashallah the uncle's
stuff... ah, it's clean. Eyy, what apples they are.
M'go çi sêv in e.
I said what apples they are.
Kêfî qabîne.
Enjoy them.
Şolî t'kê xona bibin?
Shall we take household items?
Mango le?
Mango too?
D'xwezê ke?
Do you want to?
Bibe, ke?
Take it, okay?
Maşalla tiştê xwa pak e.
Mashallah his stuff is clean.
Arzan ne ho, şebab. Cema'a xidra, fewakê bi şikl 'am arzan
ne.
They are cheap, guys. The vegetables, fruits in general are
cheap.
Mibareh xelqê sêvên qulol daxwistî.
Yesterday people asked for [unclear] apples.
Imkanin herin lê sêr kin.
It is possible to go watch it.
Ya aba...
Oh dad...
Maşalla çi sêv in.
Mashallah what apples.
Yek de... xalî ye, fuqara.
One more... it is the uncle, poor guy.
Temam, temam, m'le we ne.
Okay, okay, don't worry.
Yalla.
Let's go.
Erê hevalno, me îşê xwe Raco xilas kir, emê noka darbas
Hecemala bin.
Yes friends, we finished our business in Rajo, now we will
head to Hecemala.
Bi me ra bin heta nov Hecemala, vîdyokî xweş kîbar.
Stay with us until inside Hecemala, a nice elegant video.
Avo çarşiya Raco ye.
This is the Rajo market square.
Wadi ye çarşa, harekat pirr e, zehme ye.
It's a valley market, there's lots of movement, it's
crowded.
Si'ûd sîno.
[Unclear greeting].
Hela habîbî.
Hello dear.
Erê hevalno em giştin, vî derê, hembar Hecemala.
Yes friends we arrived, here, opposite Hecemala.
Emê l ser tirba ne, xwedê rehma xwa l miriyê we ke.
We are at the graves, may God have mercy on your dead.
Tabî'etek l vira heye pir xweş e.
There is a nature here that is very beautiful.
Erê hevalê min lê bigir gundê Hecemala.
Yes my friend, capture the village of Hecemala.
L hembar me ye.
It is opposite us.
Maşalla gundekî pir xweş î kîbar e.
Mashallah it is a very nice and elegant village.
Emê noka vîdyokî xweş nov wara nov gundê Hecemala çêkin.
We will now make a nice video inside the village of Hecemala
for you.
Taben emê darbas malê xaltîkê bin. Aîlet Em Mehdîn.
Of course we will visit Auntie's house. Em Mehdîn's family.
Em nîvanê gundin jî, emê nov gund teswîr kin û emê darbas
cem gundî bin.
We are in the middle of the village too, we will film inside
the village and visit the villagers.
Kasê dixwaze qenatê gund îştîrak ke.
Anyone who wants to subscribe to the village channel.
Havo qenata gundî ye ma wara go.
This is the village channel as I told you.
Emê rûpêl jî têkin ta'lîqê.
We will put the link in the comments.
Hew jî yomiyatê xwe çêdikin, vîdyê xwe pir xweş ne kîbar ne.
They also make their daily vlogs, their videos are very nice
and elegant.
Erê. Maşalla tabî'etê bigir, hevalê min vê tabî'etê bigir,
ooo were.
Yes. Mashallah capture the nature, my friend capture this
nature, ooo come.
Maşalla.
Mashallah.
Maşalla cewekî pir xweş e kîbar e.
Mashallah it's a very nice elegant atmosphere.
Vir kîdar e, hevalê min were vir la?
Where is here, my friend come here?
Hêêê! Biro bere û da bî çi bî? Îha...
Hey! Bro look if it was... what was it? Aha...
...me zor bî bere...
...[unclear] look...
Ox.
Oh.
Bere vê hewş bî, çûbî têbiyo fiqirtine.
Look at this yard, [unclear].
Çi tabî'etek xweş e l vî derê, hêêê.
What a beautiful nature in this place, hey.
Ooof. Çi çoxane, çoyê xwe çiqas tehm ne.
Ooof. What a [mountain/place], its river/tea is so tasty.
Wadi ye.
It is a valley.
Kivark tinen, am kivarka sêkin novê çovîre.
There are no mushrooms, let's look for mushrooms in the
grass.
Werin zû ya kivarka sêkin, werin.
Come quickly let's look for mushrooms, come.
Xayê baran nekatine, ka kivarkê kider kevin.
It seems it hasn't rained, where would mushrooms fall/grow.
Bere vê dogî ma çav sê kivark dikirin.
Look at this slope, my eyes were looking for mushrooms.
Cîckî çovîrê heşîn dayî vî derê. Ê dar keve.
A little green grass has appeared here. Hey come out.
De werin em darbas bin, em herin.
Come let's pass, let's go.
Bi me ra bin lextanê xweş.
Stay with us for nice moments.
[Music plays until end of video]
Hevalno fe'len fe'len ez her gundekî têm...
Friends, really, really, every village I come to...
...ez aşiqê gundo dibim. Maşalla ji vî gundî ra.
...I fall in love with the village. Mashallah to this
village.
Wadiye? Seh biken tebîeta gund e? Maşalla.
Is it a valley? Look at the nature of the village?
Mashallah.
Qurban bê kelem û wezin û er nabe.
My dear, without mud and slipping and [unclear], it won't
happen.
Hevalno emê yek hewşê jî nêzîk bikin, mala hewş gedar kevim.
Friends, we will zoom in on a courtyard too, let me enter a
courtyard house.
Maşalla rû germik e jî, seh ke ma em çileyê zivistanê ne.
Mashallah the weather is warm too, look, we are in the peak
of winter.
Gerek wekî noko berf bona, baran bona. Maşalla we bîn
tebîetê di, hevalno...
There should have been snow and rain like now. Mashallah
look at the nature, friends...
...hin vê darê, rûniştina bin vê darê malê dinyê dike.
...under this tree, sitting under this tree is worth the
wealth of the world.
Hene her wer, bindorê tîye, gund gund Hemzê Tado ye.
Look everywhere, it is the threshing floor [flat], the
village is the village of Hamze Tado.
Seh ke. Hevalno were. Tovek, de kevir qobîtî tono, e çox ser
rind bo.
Look. Friends come. [Walking sounds]. The stones... became
very beautiful.
Pencere heye o viderê.
There is a window over there.
[Whistling] Were were ba min.
[Whistling] Come, come to me.
Agle? Dedê hesê çûkê çox sono, hesê kîbar e. Dedê? Ber vê
darê kelm e? Ah.
Look? Uncle, the sound of the birds is very nice, a refined
sound. Uncle? Is it calm by this tree? Ah.
We heskirî? Çi rûniştin li viderê heye hevalno.
Did you like it? What a sitting area is here friends.
Maşalla, ev kenar e? Ev bilbil e? Dengê xwe xweş e.
Mashallah, is this a canary? Is this a nightingale? Its
voice is beautiful.
Hevalno rûniştinê viro, milkê m'li viro.
Friends, sitting here, is [worth] my kingdom here.
Er hewşê re nadin iştim, ekê tin betam minaf kelmê viro.
I wouldn't trade this courtyard... [unclear]...
Seh ke o no we. Ko were em hinek sa vê hewşê jî, were
hevalim were.
Look oh no wow. Come let's look at this courtyard a bit too,
come my friend come.
Maşalla, hevalno.
Mashallah, friends.
Hevalno me vê hewş no gî o nîzîk bike, milo mol mol... aw
bike.
Friends, bring this inside of the courtyard close, let it...
[unclear].
Gundekî kîbar e wela.
It is a refined village, by God.
Aleykumselam.
Peace be upon you.
And upon you peace.
M'go rêk fere ye, na fere ye, bira?
I said the road is wide, isn't it wide, brother?
Çawa? Rêk fere ye, fere ye.
How? The road is wide, wide.
Erê hevalno li viderê jî em gîştin mala xaltîkê...
Yes friends, here too we reached the aunt's house...
Jam şebab o. Erê. Em gîştin viderê. Keremkin. Şale.
Group of youth. Yes. We reached here. Welcome. Shall...
Elhemdulila ala selame. Wela maşalla gundekî wa ye, gundekî
kîbar e.
Praise be to God for safety. By God mashallah it is a
village like this, a refined village.
Gundê me ne, ber çê da hez dikim. Gundekî pirr xweş e.
It's our village, I like it very much. A very beautiful
village.
Teslîmbe. Kû... Elem. Ezê nokotê kem bira. Pêşî de herim.
Welcome.
Thank you. Where... [Unclear]. I will [unclear] brother. I
will go first.
Keremke. Bîrin darba... Taqok.
Welcome. Bring [unclear]... a cap/hat.
Wela bînîk xweş tê. Ez jî çiçeka hez dikim o.
By God a good smell comes. I also love flowers.
Wextkî aşiq çiçeka bibîm? M'go wextkî aşiq çiçeka bibîm car
kî me qenet çêkirî ye, m'çîçkê dest jê çiçeka berdayo wela.
Maşalla.
Was there a time I was in love with flowers? I said was
there a time I was in love with flowers, since I made the
channel, I gave up the flowers walah. Mashallah.
Ka de heşînahî. Hewşo heye vê. Xwalo ta heşînahî pirr
naçindî?
Look at the greenery. There is a courtyard here. Uncle you
didn't plant much greenery?
Heşînahî ye.
It is greenery.
Maşalla. Gilê spî, rind in. Gilê spî pirr bêhn didin. Hmm.
Maşalla.
Mashallah. White flowers are beautiful. White flowers give a
lot of scent. Hmm. Mashallah.
Wern evê gulê xemrî wadem hedîya. Ekê vê hedîyê bu wadem,
werim.
Come I will give this purple flower as a gift. I will give
this as a gift, I will come.
Ti sev xeyr hatî. Maşalla. Novî vê çî ye lê?
You are welcome. Mashallah. What is the name of this
man/dear?
Şebboy e.
It is Gillyflower.
Wala nizanim.
Huh?
By God I don't know.
Çîçek, bixwe heşîn dibin.
Flowers, they grow by themselves.
Ê çandin e, ê çandin e, bixwe heşîn nebûti.
They are planted, they are planted, they didn't grow by
themselves.
Êo.
Yes.
Maşalla. Wela.
Mashallah. By God.
Ewa jî leymûn e, ewa jî çîçek in e.
That is a lemon tree, and those are flowers.
Maşalla maşalla. Hewşê cem we gundo maşalla fere ne.
Mashallah mashallah. The courtyards with you villagers are
mashallah wide.
Êlê?
Really?
Gundê kîderê bijim em çûn... Gundê Qasim.
Which village should I say we went to... Qasim Village.
Her hewşekê, maşalla mokîne çido diftilen. Hewşê xo pirr
fere ne. Kerem. Gurim.
Every courtyard, mashallah cars turn in them. Their
courtyards are very wide. Welcome. [Unclear].
Erê hevalno, magû em gîştin mala aîlet... Îmadîn. Em gîştin
wi derê.
Yes friends, as I said we reached the house of the family...
of Imadin. We reached there.
Em nîvone gind in, emê qehwek xo vexwin istîrahe.
We are in the middle of the village, we will drink our
coffee [and] rest.
Emê... kî çîçkê behsê xolbir bibin û paşê ro emê lextanê
xweş dîsa nov gind wara temam bikin, b'mara bin o. Merin
tidera.
We will... [unclear] talk a bit and afterwards we will
finish our beautiful tour inside the village again, stay
with us. Don't go anywhere.
Talîqa wej mîşkin heta... fasil îlan o emê wara.
Don't forget your comments until... the break [and] we will
come.
Erê hevalno, livro... mala xaltîka me, mala... m'jontî? Vêra
dibên.
Yes friends, here... our aunt's house, the house of...
[unclear]? They call it here.
Û novî qenatê jî me hebarê wara wa gû... Aîlet Îmadîn Efrînî
ye.
And the name of the channel I told you before... Family
Imadin Efrini.
Qenatê gind o, wame rabet jî di telîqê kin wara. Kase
dixwaze iştîrakê qenatê gind e, ka her kesek ştarefê me
hare, ez çavê ginda maç dikim.
The village channel, and we will put the link in the
comments for you. Whoever wants to subscribe to the village
channel, whoever goes from our side, I kiss the eyes of the
villagers.
Xwedê ji wa razî be. U heleqê me li vê gindî ye.
May God be pleased with them. And our episode is in this
village.
Û bimar bin noko lextanê xweş emê nov gind wara çêkin, hin
vîdyû maxelo si nabe ye.
And stay with us now we will make a beautiful tour inside
the village for you, look the video is not over yet.
Me istîreheko çûçik bî, magû em xoltiqê jî bibînin em silav
kê pê bidenê.
We had a small rest, I said let us see the aunt too and
greet her.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Tab'an ez pirr kêfxweş dibim, ji xwe ez têm... cem gindîyo
ez pirr kêfxweş im.
Of course I become very happy, when I come... to the
villagers I am very happy.
Wekî dibêje ez gindîyo sipas dikim.
Like he says I thank the villagers.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Qenatê won jî kîbar e. Sato gindê xweş ew jî xizmet dikin.
Your channel is also refined. They also serve the beautiful
village hours [times].
Ser serê min ser çavê min Xwedê ji we razî be.
On my head on my eye [You're welcome], may God be pleased
with you.
Û erê hevalno li vê gindoy jî, magû... vê gindoy teqrîben
heftû pênc mal ne.
And yes friends in this village too, I said... in this
village there are approximately seventy-five houses.
Heftû pênc mal ne, tabî'ê nahîyê Raco ye. Pirr gindekî ne
mezin e. Bes tebîetê gind e, coxrafî gind e, pirr xweş e
kîbar e.
Seventy-five houses, belonging to the district of Rajo. It
is not a very big village. But the nature of the village,
the geography of the village, is very beautiful and refined.
Ma pir hez ji wan dikim bi rastî.
I really like them, actually.
Erê, ez... gundê navçê da pir jê hez dikim.
Yes, I... I love the district's villages very much.
Belê çiçike qelem, çiçike sist... Ne qelemê me jî dizanin,
giq û wiq dikirin darê bî.
But a bit [like a] pen, a bit slack... You know our pens
too, they used to creak and squeak on the wood.
Qelem hebûn? Hebûn ha, hînê xweş bû.
Were there pens? There were, huh, it was still nice.
Tebîet çiçike kêm civiya.
Nature was a bit less lush.
Belê tebîeta mantiqî ma pir xweş bî, hêşinayî pir bî, darê
me pir bîn.
But the nature of the area remained very beautiful, the
greenery was abundant, our trees were abundant.
İnşallah weke berê bibe, baran bibare, bereket bikeve.
God willing, it will be like before, rain will fall,
blessings will come.
Welle meydankê çandin, saeta gundê xweş.
By God, they planted the square, the time of the village is
nice.
Na na, xelk dıçinin noka, saeta giya xweş...
No no, people are harvesting now, the time of the grass is
nice...
Wextê adetê hebûn, bes baran lê kine.
There were times of custom, but the rain is scarce on it.
Lê şiqim... qelem zû şiqim didin. Timarê xwe bes bibin erdê
daben zû ew dibe.
But dry... stalks dry out quickly. Just take care of them,
put them in the ground, it happens quickly.
Me cotkî baran lê nekir. Şîret ser tiştekî lê nekir, ew
îştevam bû, adetê me bû.
We plowed [but] rain didn't fall on it. Advice didn't do
anything for it, that was the situation, our custom.
Welle bes hukm...
Well, just the rule...
De cefa wiha me ketina me ye, dew dê diê. Baran, tu baranê
lê nekir.
So such hardship is our lot, the buttermilk will come. Rain,
no rain fell on it.
Çunku baran lê kirî, me du pêrsîn kir, kanî baran? Me
sîtêrka avê...
Because if it rained... we plowed twice, where is the rain?
We [need] a water tank...
Weke me hemjî dikim...
I do just like us too...
Zivistane de be tu sîtêra avê bikire welle.
If it's winter, go buy a water tank, really.
De şolê Xwedê li vê, rehmê li vê miletî wer rehmê.
So God's work on this, have mercy on this nation, come
mercy.
Ana rehmetek çiçike bibare, vê miletî, yanî vê darberînê...
Let a little mercy [rain] fall now, [for] this nation,
meaning this forestry...
Feqîra welle milet cefaf e, tenîşkî bîn.
The poor people, really the nation is in drought, they are
thirsty.
Xelk heye sîtêra avê bi bîst û pênc dolara dikire, heyder...
There are people buying a tank of water for twenty-five
dollars, heyder...
Bîrgê heşgînî, bîr pir heşgînî welle.
The well is green [stagnant], the well is very green really.
Welle ezmok mekinê, yanî helo saeta milet bibe.
By God, don't test it, meaning now is the time for the
people [to suffer].
Wer avê tike vexwe tu bi bîst û pênc dolara tu bikire.
Come drink a drop of water, you buy it for twenty-five
dollars.
Sîtêrek bi bîst û pênc dolaro...
A tank for twenty-five dollars...
Mehe sê sîtêla tike bikire.
Buy three tanks a month.
Firaq û teşqê te heye, divê em fira û teşqê de bişûn.
You have dishes and basins, we must wash the dishes and
basins.
Dibê lê, dibê fira û teşqê de bişûn, yanî av nare.
It must be, it must be washing dishes and basins, meaning
water doesn't go [waste].
Tewekel bi Xwedê be, dinyaya me tenê ev nîne. Em jî wek
pênsîdî bihêzin.
Reliance be on God, our world is not only this. We are also
strong like the pensioners.
Çorsî pêncî pênsîdî ye, ew jî weye.
Four hundred fifty is the pension, that is it too.
Lê wek de çe, em av qinyat, ew nustemal nakin.
But how it goes, we don't use water frugally, we don't use
it [sparingly].
Dorê denke, em serf dikin.
Turn the tap, we consume it.
Lê berê nekê ne, tî we de teşta de bişon.
But don't do like before, you wash in the basins.
Xaltîkek silavkî bişîne ji mirat re.
Auntie, send a greeting to the people.
Erê cemaat, teb'en mêvanê me jî, aîlê, hew jî qanatê Efrîn
sêsed û şêst û şeş gund ne.
Yes group, of course our guests too, the family, and this is
the channel Afrin 366 Villages.
Hew jî bi efrîna, ehlen û sehlen.
This is also in Afrin, welcome.
Û her yekî teb'en mutabeînê me yî qanatê Muhîdîn Efrînî,
herin cem gundê, jêra îştîraq kin jî.
And everyone, of course our followers of the channel Muhidin
Afrini, go to the village [channel], subscribe to it too.
Û emê rabitê qanatê gundî jî daxin ser qanatê xwe, teb'en
heke jê me daxwaz.
And we will put the link of the village channel on our
channel, of course if he asks us.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Em ê wina daxin ser qanatê xwe.
We will put them on our channel.
Xizmeta me tîne.
It brings our service.
Erê, û her yek teb'en xwest wera cem me, ser ser û ser çavê
me, em ciyê wekî qebûl dikin.
Yes, and anyone of course who wants to come to us, upon our
head and eyes, we accept a place like [this].
Û nizanim ji berê da, kî tê cem me...
And I don't know from before, whoever comes to us...
Xwedê û pêxember ji we razî be miletî me.
May God and the Prophet be pleased with you, our nation.
Teb'en piştgirî we miletî me ye.
Of course, our nation is your support.
Bi desteka gundiya weke gotî, emê rabin inşallah, bi desteka
gundiya be.
With the support of the villagers as said, we will rise God
willing, let it be with the support of the villagers.
İnşallah, welle miletê me maşallah gib xêr û bêr e.
God willing, by God our nation, mashallah, is all goodness
and blessing.
Saeta wan xweş, kesê me seyr dike, kesê qenata me daam dike,
dişînin ji hev re.
Their time is good, those who watch us, those who support
our channel, sending it to each other.
Miletê me nav, em navek barê ne.
Our nation's name, we are carrying a name.
Hemdillah ji Xwedê re, em pêşketin noka pir çêbûye.
Praise be to God, our progress has become very good now.
Xwedê tu tengiya nede kesî.
May God not give hardship to anyone.
Em bi gundiya jî serbilind in.
We are proud of the villagers too.
Saeta wan xweş, kesê me seyr dike, kesê qenata me daam dike,
dişînin ji ewra.
Their time is good, those who watch us, those who support
our channel, sending it to others.
Û her yek jî tarafê me jî herê, qenata xwe, tîkê îştîraq ke,
çavê gindim maş dikim dîsa.
And everyone on our side too, go, subscribe to his channel,
I kiss the villagers' eyes again.
Bimara bin, vîdeoyêkî din xweş, kîbar, emê noka wera temam
bikin oh bikin.
Stay with us, another nice, elegant video, we will finish it
for you now, oh do it.
Cew hûr û germik û xweş e.
The weather is mild and warm and nice.
Mago cew germik û xweş e, em ketin hindirî, em çiçike
derkevin ber ro ye, mulo rû bime de.
I said the weather is warm and nice, we went inside, let's
go out a bit in the sun, let it shine on our faces.
Cewê derva pir xweş e kîbar, maşallah, mele... kûçik kûçik,
kerrin de maşallah.
The weather outside is very nice, elegant, mashallah,
ange... puppy puppy, look at them mashallah.
Maşallah, mala te ne spî boz e.
Mashallah, yours is not white, it's grey.
Hejî Mihemed, hejî kûçik pir hez dike.
Hajji Muhammad, Hajji loves dogs very much.
Lê berê ez aşiq kilîkê wî bûm.
But before, I fell in love with his tail.
Welle îşta min zenet berdayê.
Really, now I have given up the craft.
Lê em bîş nabe.
But we cannot exist without.
Wê bigire kilîk cem te enwa pir in.
Take it, the tails/types with you are many types.
Pir, xelkê didin ji cem min dibirin.
Many, people give, they take from me.
Te çi nûî dixwaze, goya fantoz.
What type do you want, supposedly 'fantoz' [fancy/strange].
Heîn hene lê?
Are there any there?
E welle hene, tek tek hîn mane.
Yes really there are, one by one some are still left.
De nî çiçike min sist kirî, mesele...
So look, I slackened a bit, the issue...
Di Youtube'ê da katî.
It fell into YouTube.
Lê, mecal tîne, mecal namîne.
But, there is no opportunity, no opportunity remains.
Du heyv... bêmî te dest hîn jî kilîkê ba didin, hîn jî ma ba
didin.
Two months... since your hand still wagged the tail, still
wagged us.
Hên ke berdayê.
They have given it up.
Hîn ke dinyayê da.
Still in the world.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Çi tebîetek xweş e, rûkanê germik xweş derketî.
What a nice nature, the warm sun has come out nicely.
Xweş e noda, erê canim.
It's nice here, yes my dear.
Sak bes heb, belo weşî o hevo.
Look, just look, that wild fellow is like that.
Ev hişîn tî ya.
This is a green one.
Are heval nûsak e.
Yes friend, it's a new one.
Vê kîlko, şeqam didê, di serî gindiro, serî belaro, gepek
hene.
This tail, he gives a slap/paw, rolling the head, shaking
the head, there are bites.
Hav gepeko bes ka çi sotale?
These bites, but look what a burning [taste] is that?
Go gîd welle hişî nator ne lê, bena.
Said go, really no mind in him, look.
Bixwe hişîn didê qurban, te Xwedê yî bimebîne.
Eat it, it gives green [vitality] sacrifice, may God make
you see.
Bixwe şeqam didê.
Eat it, it gives a slap/kick [strong taste].
Tu min nejo pepikê ketine çiçeka, çû ne zevî ne di, nizanim
acer e.
Don't tell me the feet fell into the flowers, went not into
the field not into, I don't know it's unripe.
Ev çiçeka maraş tirmişonî.
These flowers look like 'tirmishoni' [local plant name].
Tirmişo?
Tirmisho?
Weke me'zeta.
Like your appetizer.
Dû em çûn niza gindekî...
Yesterday we went, I don't know, a village...
Dû mizgîn... a we men...
Yesterday good news... ah yours...
Xaltîk dibê paf têneka bibin, em qey mîşê nebinin, mago no
şitilkê me din.
Auntie says don't puff [don't breath on it], let us not
become mice/flies, I said no, our seedlings.
Welle miji raş tirmişonî, cem malê xalê xwe, haw.
Really I also [like] black 'tirmishoni', at my uncle's
house, wow.
Lê, ne em di gunda digerin.
But, no, we are walking in the villages.
Are are.
Yes yes.
Yê em kîderê diçûn, dilê me dikeve çiçeka, me tînin.
Wherever we went, our heart falls for flowers, we bring
them.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Wera emê serxînin.
Come, let's climb up.
Xwezî wa etûn jî, ew kirne.
I wish those 'etun' [olives] too, they did that.
Lê.
Yes.
Û îbona paşê xê dikin, û hîdikirin.
And afterwards they make them good, and keep them.
Ev ne caîz e.
This is not permissible.
Em kî bixwin.
Let us eat some.
Maşallah, wer dilê wa etûno ra ye kî bixwin werin.
Mashallah, come, whoever's heart desires those olives, come
eat.
Heî se nekin, na min nedan ber ro ye, ta ro li we da.
Don't look at them, no I didn't put them in the sun, until
the sun hit you.
Du roj baran bî, zatan nedan ber ro ye.
It was rain for two days, anyway they didn't put them in the
sun.
Oox, çi tam didê, tam didê.
Ooh, what a taste it gives, it gives taste.
Xêr zeytûnê mantiqê başqane.
Goodness, the olives of the region are different.
We jî pêşwakin.
You guys welcome [them] too.
Fe'len gindekî xweş e.
Actually it is a nice village.
Welle kele mehderekî têre.
Really a fort of appearance is in it.
Mahderkî... seke bibin mekel, cem dorê jûr bibin, nov kelmû
lê?
An appearance... look at the place, be at the upper turn,
'Nov Kelmu' right?
Hawa derkê wisa.
That came out like that.
Nov kelmû.
Nov Kelmu.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Çi tebîetek xweş e.
What a nice nature.
Xolo, ji Reco va çend kîlometre dûr e?
Uncle, how many kilometers far from Rajo?
Pênc kîlometre nîv, pênc kîlometre nîv.
Five and a half kilometers, five and a half kilometers.
Are, are havalno Hecemalo, ji Reco va...
Yes, yes friends, Hecemalo, from Rajo...
Teqrîben qolû dibê pênc kîlometre nîv ne. Heta şeş
kîlometre, heta Reco nîzik e.
Approximately it's said to be five and a half kilometers. Up
to six kilometers, until Rajo is close.
Nîzik e.
It is close.
Min meşê pir... ew dê kûva diçûn da.
I walked a lot... where were they going there.
Pir xweş e, maşallah.
It's very nice, mashallah.
Cewekî xweş e.
It's nice weather.
Avelî ma avê hewşê no gida robigire mulo.
Look, the water of the courtyard didn't hold that much.
Milet lê seyr ke.
People, look at it.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Welle hewşê kîbar di vê gindî da hene.
Really, there are elegant courtyards in this village.
Se xelê af... xelê rind bûn.
Look at the people of Af... they were good people.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Xayo, çiçike tebîet kêm bî ye.
Uncle, the nature is a bit sparse.
Bere, dest qelemo tenekûnî divek çonoro lîkşêno.
Before, the hand of the pen shouldn't bend like that.
Lê bere qelem, ge bibîn dar, mezin bibîn.
But before, the grafts, they should have become trees,
become big.
E noka nemayî.
Eh, now none remain.
Lo çimo, miletî me jî noke, miletî me jî noka alimine ji
gundiya, alimine, hew jî jê dikin.
But why, our nation also now, our nation also now learned
from the villagers, learned, they also do it.
Wela?
Really?
Zanet kirend berme alimandin. Êzinga hewil kin.
They taught us the craft. They try for firewood.
Mago, miletî me jî alimiye ji gundiya, alimiye, hew jî noka
hil dikin êzinga.
I said, our nation also learned from the villagers, learned,
they also now gather firewood.
Me noka nokin êzinga, em belekis em xizmet dikin.
We don't do firewood now, we on the contrary, we serve
[maintain].
Welle pir gund hene hil dikin.
Really there are many villages that gather [cut down].
Noka fûcî çoyî belê, welle manteqa get, hebî sîtadoyî.
Now the barrel of tea yes, really the area is gone, there
was a citadel.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Mezin û cem her gund mobêrê me da, rîş hat...
Big and at every village beyond us, the beard came...
Heci heta derê xoyî tix heta ehmer bî.
Hajji, until his door... until it became red.
Welle.
Really.
Wana qit kirin.
They cut them.
Dewa pûza dî, kelemkê temam xoyî tê.
That snout saw, a cabbage completely comes to itself.
Jûr.
Up.
Darek beno vî werdo vî.
A tree of gum here, of that here.
Qit kirin.
They cut them.
E hişîn bidin, hişîn bidin, şolo e çê bibin, e çê bibin.
Eh, let them turn green, let them turn green, the work will
be good, will be good.
Tu çer we rîkê dikin ne?
You do it this way, right?
Aw rêko, dû xire derya.
That way, two rounds went out.
Daxwazê em sê sê herin.
The request is that we go three by three.
Welle gîş di moyî pûzî ye, fitilî mo pûzî.
Really all is in the snout [talk], twisted in the snout.
Bes şore, îşta bes gino bî, bokire gino e zût e sabixane.
Just talk, now just let it be big, tomorrow big will be
sooner than the past.
Tiş nabe.
Nothing happens.
O, avlî me avê vî darno jî bigir.
Oh, look, film these trees too.
Wadî ye.
It is apparent.
Çi tebîetek xweş e.
What a nice nature.
Îşta miletî gundo wekî çi korî bike, o darim bar pazê xo...
Now the village people, whatever work they do, oh trees load
his sheep...
Li gunda gerek her tiştek hebe.
In villages, there must be everything.
Gerek çêlê mera hebin, pazî mera hebe.
We must have cows, we must have sheep.
Mirîşkê mera hebin.
We must have chickens.
Bes tibî gundî, gike hebe.
But naturally for a villager, it must exist.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Welatî, helat.
Countryman, rise.
Ahlen, ahlen.
Welcome, welcome.
Bro, cemo a zeytûn hînane dicinîn?
Bro, are they still picking those olives?
Erê erê, em... azanim horko hatim, amolo dicinî zeytûn.
Yes yes, we... I know I came from there, they are picking
olives at the house.
Xolo, gundî ma molo...
Uncle, our village houses...
Xê nav lê kirin Hecemalo, xê lê nav lê kirin Hecemalo?
Who named it Hecemalo, who named it Hecemalo?
Lo da, dikavin dor, bofkolo de, welle ez nizanim.
Oh mother, they fall around, in the Bofko, really I don't
know.
Çi gundî wa çi meşhûr e, bi çi meşhûr e gundî wa?
What is your village famous for, with what is your village
famous?
O da îşta gundê cabarina, berê ge paz bûn, rez hebûn, cût
bûn.
Oh mother, now the villages of Cabarin, before there were
sheep, there were vineyards, there were pairs [plowing].
Bi kijan aîletê nos kirin Hecemalo?
Which family founded Hecemalo?
Aîlet hav, silav vê gindî dorim şti zoni ne?
The families here, greetings to this village, do you know
them?
Gî yek ne, gî yek ne.
All are one, all are one.
Yanî bi kijan malbetê nos kirin?
Meaning which family founded it?
Ka goy noko... noko dibên...
Well now... now they say...
Mesele, wo gê çer bûn, molê Qermo virde, molê Hecemî l'vir
de, molê Hewlîkê...
For example, they were grazing there, Qermo family here,
Hecemî family here, Hewlîkê family...
Ewa, sê aîle ne.
Yes, three families.
E.
Yes.
Silavê min ji vê sê aîlano ra hene, û miletî gundî, vê gundî
giyora hene.
My greetings to these three families, and the people of the
village, all of this village.
Hecemalo, çavê giyo maş dikim.
Hecemalo, I kiss all eyes.
Bes wek dorê zeytûna kitik yek e.
But like the olive trees, each one is unique.
Kitik yek e.
Each one is unique.
Lo bixwe milet, bixwe gi me ye, em pir dernayên.
Hey, the people themselves, all of us ourselves, we don't go
out much.
Em gundo, em xoşavtir hewl da, em derdikevin, em nos
derdikevin.
We in the villages, we try more pleasantly, we go out, we go
out anew.
Ne, zat Hecemalo gundî gimirî ye evnî.
No, actually Hecemalo village is lively.
Kesî xerîb têne.
Strangers come.
Maşallah, a wona hewş rind warda girtine. Esasê viro ma kin
e, ha ne?
Mashallah, they have enclosed those yards nicely. The
foundation here, don't do it, huh?
Hez û dero da sehî da hezê lê, bes avno.
Love and outside in the courtyard, love but these.
Hezê da tiş nebî cemaat.
In the love nothing happened, group.
Bes ê me çiçike kerpîç bî paqî, wek...
But ours was a bit adobe clean, like...
Kerpîç? Bûşe, lanî xêra menteqa cebelî ye, digre.
Adobe? It's okay, because it's a mountain region, it holds.
Bes gi reşî ye.
But all is black.
Reşî xo vekin.
Open the blackness.
Maşallah, rind e, gundî wa pir kîbar e.
Mashallah, it's nice, your village is very elegant.
Em çûn vê gundî jî, gundî kîderê avo?
We went to this village too, where is that village?
Çençaliya.
Chenchaliya.
Am çûn Çençalyo jî ma sewirand.
We went to Chenchalyo too, we filmed it.
Kelakê me ye.
It's our neighbor.
Çaqmoqo hene çûn?
Are there Chakmoqo, did you go?
Kîjan Çaqmoqê?
Which Chakmoqo?
Kelakê mavo.
Our neighbor.
Habî, bi gundo? Welle Çaqmoqê hîn am neçûne, ma têda xeleqe
çênekirî.
Is there, in the villages? Really we haven't gone to
Chakmoqo yet, we haven't made an episode in it.
Noko mi me'zetir, wagû amê xeleqok melwûr ay, amê çêkin.
Now excuse me, I said we have a full episode, we will make
it.
Jimo westin, bes î min nê, na westin.
From me take rest, but not mine, no rest.
Çax.
Time.
Çaxmoqê, Çaxmoqê mezin.
Chakmoqe, Big Chakmoqe.
Maşallah, ovînî nov çi kêfî sewr sa dikin ha?
Mashallah, the love inside, what joy they make, huh?
Xweş ono, hember mero.
It's nice like that, opposite to us.
Boyî gundo jî, boyî gundo tebîetî paq e.
The smell of the villages too, the smell of the villages'
nature is clean.
Boyî gundo pir paq e. Nawakî bêjêr me jêre.
The smell of the villages is very clean. Not like the
breathless ones down there.
Bêjêr dûyî mokîna û zamro û daro kulxonê.
Down there is smoke of cars and noise and trees of
factories.
Are, bes gundo ono, te sebêra bî, hisê dîko, mirîşko.
Yes, but villages like that, you wake up, sound of roosters,
chickens.
Lê, dewar jî hebe ono.
Yes, if there is livestock too like that.
Qewî xoşî vexe sibe, pir xweş e.
Very nice time in the morning, very nice.
Cewî gundo pir xweş e.
The weather of the villages is very nice.
Da welle, dewarî hey doşmiş kirî.
Yes really, the livestock has been finished.
Çêlê mera hebin, mirîşk hebin.
We should have cows, have chickens.
No, me'ney hewşî mero nevre, bahra doşmiş.
No, meaning our courtyard inside, the sea of milking.
Na de, maro bi gundî, garek gitışt li cem maro hebe.
No, man in the village, everything must be with the man.
Heta nan.
Even bread.
Hodo paramin...
Hodo paramin [Note: Likely a local nickname or
expression]...
Areyê hevalno, taben magot emê li ser pişta xwendinê, li vê
derê, wîr de gundê Hec Cemalo...
Yes friends, naturally it seems we will be [talking] about
education, here, over in the village of Haj Jamalo...
Silavê me ji wagî ra hene, çûçik mezin dîsa bibên...
Our greetings go out to you/them, small and big, once
again...
Navê herêta wî dimayî, emê herin darbazi wîr bin, emê vîdyo
xwe li wîr çêkin...
The name of that remaining area, we will go pass by there,
we will make our video there...
Û paşê ro emê berê xwe bidin mal dan.
And afterwards, we will head towards home.
Em xaltîkê re dabin, saeta te xweş...
We were with the auntie, may you have a good time...
Û xalo... saeta we xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be.
And uncle... may you have a good time, may God be pleased
with you.
Xwedê ji we razî be, bila evî jî werin cem me ser çava.
May God be pleased with you, let them come to us too, they
are welcome.
Wele em pir kêfxweş bûn.
By God, we were very happy.
Tu xêr hatî, tu bi xêr hatî, ser çava.
You are welcome, you are welcome, with pleasure.
We keyfa me anî, îftahîye, gerek îna xelê te ji vê rindtir
be.
You brought us joy, for the opening [intro], your uncle's
wife should be better than this.
Înşallah, înşallah... emê car kî din înşallah iyada kin, emê
werin.
God willing, God willing... we will visit again another
time, God willing, we will come.
Bi xatirê we, bi xatirê we, bi selametî.
Goodbye, goodbye, go in safety.
Em pir kêfxweş bûn, û emê noko vîdyokî xweş çêkin, bi me ra
bin, heta toliyê.
We were very happy, and now we will make a nice video, stay
with us, until the end.
Bi xatirê we, bi me ra bin.
Goodbye [to the hosts], stay with us [to the viewers].
Gul e, gul e.
It's a rose, it's a rose [expression of endearment/goodbye].
Erê cemaat, gundo pir xweş e, kîbar e.
Yes folks, the village is very nice, it's elegant.
Ê pirsgirêka me gundo, pirsgirêk me piçik heye.
And the problem of our village, we have a small problem.
Gerek rêkê me gundo, meselen neft xareta qîr biba.
The road of our village should have been, for example, paved
with asphalt.
Heger rê jî zift bana, yê pir xweş ba.
If the road was asphalted, it would have been very nice.
Dadbaxçeka girtî ye...
The kindergarten is closed...
Dergevanê wê xal e...
Its doorman is an old uncle...
Ser min da hawarî ye...
There is an outcry over me...
Dadbaxçeka girtî ye...
The kindergarten is closed...
Dergevanê wê xal e...
Its doorman is an old uncle...
Ser min da hawarî ye...
There is an outcry over me...
Kesek li canê min balî...
Someone is looking after my soul...
Tekîra xwe li sîngê min danî...
Put their dagger on my chest...
Kefen li canê min balî...
Wrapped a shroud around my body...
Tekîra xwe li sîngê min danî...
Put their dagger on my chest...
Taben ber me jî mekteb e, bes...
Naturally, in front of us is the school, but...
Magot mekteb girtine.
It seems they have closed the school.
Zarok tûne ne, naxwînin, eqle kirine.
There are no children, they aren't studying, they have shut
it down.
Derî raxistî da xwînin.
The door is spread open/broken where they study.
Dadbaxçeka girtî ye...
The kindergarten is closed...
Dergevanê wê xal e...
Its doorman is an old uncle...
Ser min da hawarî ye...
There is an outcry over me...
Lê maşallah dinya germeke...
Oh Mashallah, the weather is so hot...
Em nazanin seata xwe bixin, em nazanin xew kin...
We don't know whether to wear our watches [or clothes], we
don't know how to sleep...
Lê pir kes soba nakirî ye, yanî sarma tûne.
But many people haven't set up the stove yet, meaning there
is no cold.
Dinya sarma hîn pir çênebûye, ma sarma nayê...
The weather hasn't become very cold yet, the cold isn't
coming...
Kesek li canê min balî...
Someone is looking after my soul...
Baqurban Xwedê bike mazot biha ye... êzing biha ne... ew jî
li me xwedê rehmê bike...
My dear, may God help, diesel is expensive... wood is
expensive... may God have mercy on us regarding that too...
Feqara milet, guneh e.
The poor people, it's a sin [a pity].
Kefen li canê min balî...
Wrapped a shroud around my body...
Çi dî û ne dî...
What was seen and not seen...
Ez ê bimrim tu ne xeme...
I will die and you won't care...
Were, were... were Canfîda were... were, were, ta şînokê
were.
Come, come... come Canfida come... come, come, come little
one.
Ez nayêm lo.
I am not coming, oh my.
Were, were, were.
Come, come, come.
Areyê hevalno li vê derê jî em li mala...
Yes friends, here we are at the house of...
Mislimê Qermû ne, mala xalo, emê li vê derê ne.
Mislim Qermu, the uncle's house, we are here.
Ma atqava gundiya jî waha xwar...
The ancient structures of the villagers are standing like
this...
Kemkê noko warê hilweşin, ser pişta xênî, li dûr xwe agî
bigrin.
Soon now they will collapse, on top of the roofs, keep your
distance [take care].
Noko hevalî me warê lê, maşallah...
Now our friend is coming here, Mashallah...
Ê... tabîat jî tabîat e wex...
Oh... nature is nature, wow...
Hevalî me war silav ji we ra bigir, ji vî dema no.
Our friend, come send greetings to them, from this time now.
Vê dema no, hewşê me ne.
This time now, [these are] our courtyards.
Wadiyê hember me jî Gicoy e.
The valley opposite us is Gico.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Eh yekî hewş ro jur girtiye.
Oh, someone has enclosed the courtyard upwards.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Qurban te Xwedê bibe.
May I be a sacrifice to you, God.
Xelkê hîşta qorta zeytûnê xwe vadedin.
People are still pruning/harvesting their olives.
Xelkê mewsîm daşandin, qorta destvedanê kirin, ê vadedin
zeytûnê xwe.
People finished the season, they did the pruning work, they
are pruning their olive trees.
Ê çilê xwe jî giyî bişewitînin, ê zingê xwe jî peş dekin
tînin mal.
And they will burn all their branches/twigs, they are
gathering their firewood and bringing it home.
Ê hewşê no ta nîzîk kirin?
Did you bring these courtyards closer?
Hewşokî nîzîk kirin... Maqbaz jî dişixule, çuwal hindik mane
li pîşî maqbazê.
They zoomed in on the courtyard... The press is working too,
there are few sacks left in front of the press.
Çuwal hindik mane, maqbaz dişixule.
There are few sacks left, the press is working.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Qey ne boran moran kêle kir o? Wele feqîro.
Maybe the storm and weather destroyed it? By God, poor
thing.
Ox, ox...
Oh, oh...
Dinya ye.
It's the world.
Çû miletê me her yek bi welatekî ket.
Gone, our people each fell into a different country.
Belê gundo pir zehmet e...
But the village is very difficult...
Em hîviya eydê... eyda miletê Helebê da... datin cemaa
gund...
We wait for Eid... the Eid of the people of Aleppo... the
village community would come...
Her kes dihat gundê xwe, eyd û minasebat dihatin gund şên
dikirin.
Everyone would come to their village, for Eid and occasions
they would come and enliven the village.
Înşallah giyê biftilê wekê berê bibe, dîsa giyê biftilin
werin welatî xwe.
God willing, it will all return to how it was before,
everyone will return to their country again.
Emê eyd û erefat, emê hevdu bibînin.
We will see each other during Eid and Arafat.
Înşallah giyê wekê berê bibe... yo şêweş... î çîçikê av di
be... rindî milet va digere...
God willing, it will be like before... slowly... this small
water flows... the goodness of the people circulates here...
A maşallah, ev çi yazmîş kirî?
Oh Mashallah, what is written here?
Havalî me lê biger...
My friend, focus on it...
Ku avo... çûyî ezbenî?
What is that... where did it go, sir?
Tewekel tû elellah.
I have placed my trust in Allah.
Tewelet elellah, maşallah.
Trust in Allah, Mashallah.
Neh sed şêst û neh, û sê sed heştê û neh, hicrî ye ne?
Nine hundred sixty-nine, and three hundred eighty-nine, it's
Hijri [Islamic calendar], right?
Ew jî hewşka gavanor e.
That is the governor's [or shepherd's] small courtyard.
Li birca Belek...
At the Belek tower...
Li birca xalê min...
At my uncle's tower...
Birca Belek...
The Belek tower...
Birca xalê min...
My uncle's tower...
Li birca Belek...
At the Belek tower...
Birca xalê min...
My uncle's tower...
Birca Belek...
The Belek tower...
Birca xalê min...
My uncle's tower...
Bi birsiyare...
With a question...
Li halê min...
About my condition...
Ji xwedê bibe...
From God may it be...
Seza zalim...
Punishment to the tyrant...
Tu nekesî nî...
You are nobody [to me]...
Ji xwedê bibe...
From God may it be...
Li seza zalim...
Punishment to the tyrant...
Tu nekesî nî...
You are nobody [to me]...
Areyê hevalno, li vê gundiyo ne, hember me jî vêre dibên
Çaqmaqo...
Yes friends, in this village area, opposite us they call it
Chakmaqo...
Elqok min li vê gundiyo ne heye, gundê Çaqmaqo, nêzîk da emê
besewirînin...
I have an episode [planned] in this village, the village of
Chakmaqo, soon we will film it...
Yanî berga me ra namaye, qiçikê jî kê bar Helebê herin.
Meaning there isn't much left for our episode, a little bit
and they will go towards Aleppo.
Emê werin vî gundî bisewirînin.
We will come and film this village.
Çaqmaq...
Flint [or Chakmaq village]...
Barê min giran e...
My load is heavy...
Nika mi'd ger e...
Now it wanders with me...
Jar ke mîş te...
Once...
Hez kir yarê...
Loved the beloved...
Ez gunehme...
I am sinful [or a pity]...
Jar ke mîş te...
Once...
Hez kir yarê...
Loved the beloved...
Ez gunehme...
I am sinful [or a pity]...
Areyê hevalno li vê derê jî em gihiştin toliya vîdyoya xwe.
Yes friends, here we have reached the end of our video.
Emê noko bar mal da ren.
We are now going towards home.
Saeta we xweş...
May you have a good time...
Çavîkiya meş dekin, her kesî li me sêr dike, her kesî telîqa
me re nivîs kene, taben em telîqê we giya dixwînin...
We kiss your eyes, everyone who watches us, everyone who
writes comments for us, naturally we read all your
comments...
Telîqê we pir xweş in û kîbar in.
Your comments are very nice and elegant.
Wakî dibê...
As it is said...
Serkeftin be ji we ra, ji miletê me kurd gişka ra.
Success to you, and to all our Kurdish people.
Em îna ber vî me bar mal ne.
We are now heading home.
Bi me ra bin, dîsa vîdyokî din xweş kîbar.
Stay with us, for another nice and elegant video.
Emê werin nîzîk da axin. Me'ze gotina te hene?
We will come [upload] very soon. Muazzez, do you have
anything to say?
Areyê hevalno ez hêvîdarim vîdyo me aceb we di bê, û saeta
we giya xweş.
Yes friends, I hope you liked our video, and may you all
have a good time.
Û bîr mekin me ra layk û îştîrakê pê de ne.
And don't forget to give us a like and subscription.
Û herin cem qenatî Xalê Mehdî...
And go to Uncle Mehdi's channel...
Qenatî Gendozî bera îştîrak kin, û yozmîş kin min taraf
Efrîn 366, û saeta we giya xweş.
Subscribe to the Gendozi channel, and write "from the side
of Afrin 366", and may you all have a good time.
Saet xweş Muazzez. De bi me ra bin, vîdyokî din xweş kîbar,
saeta we xweş. Bye bye.
Good times Muazzez. Come stay with us, for another nice and
elegant video, may you have a good time. Bye bye.