Emrê min heştê sal e.
My age is eighty years.
Heştê sal e? Emrê te dirêj be înşallah xalê min.
Eighty years? May your life be long, God willing, my uncle.
Înşallah, Xwedê bela nede te gîdî.
God willing, may God not give you trouble, dear.
Amîn ya reb. Nexweşî şolê te nabe?
Amen, oh Lord. Is sickness not an issue for you?
Na elhemdulillah, nexweşî tune. Wa te zehmetî dît heştê
sal...
No, praise be to God, there is no sickness. You know, having
seen hardship for eighty years...
Yanî... nexweşî...
I mean... the sickness...
Ee?
Yes?
Me dît xwar, heta sê şev me dît xwar.
I suffered it, up to three nights I suffered it.
Ee.
Yes.
Bi şeş seata çûm fahsê, emna çûm fahsê.
For six hours I went for a checkup, indeed I went for a
checkup.
Eza... mesrefê min ê mezin bû.
I... my expense was big.
Bes min xwa xwa... xelas kir.
But I... saved myself.
Çawa xalû?
How is it, uncle?
Li vir jî Semîr berxê xwe ecibandiye wekî hûn dibînin, li
ber mal.
Here, Semir has also taken a liking to his lamb as you can
see, in front of the house.
Welle berxê te bêmale?
Wow, your lamb is something else (homeless/unique), isn't
it?
Berxê Elî... Berxê dudo çiqas çêkirine?
Ali's lamb... How much did the two lambs cost?
Ma van çehê berê didin ber, we dêr bo zikir?
Are they giving them this barley? Or will you turn it into a
remembrance?
Teba nebû, gundê Qûpê ye ew.
It didn't work out, this is Qûpê village.
Merheba ji we ra qenata Efrîn Vlog, em îro hatin vîdyokî
hecer, vîdyokî pir xweş û delal.
Hello to you Afrin Vlog channel, today we came for a solid
video, a very nice and beautiful video.
Ez birayê we Mesûd, û ev jî kekê Semîr, emê keda derbasî
gundê Qûpê bin.
I am your brother Mesûd, and this is brother Semir, we are
about to enter Qûpê village.
Hûnro halqê me li gundê Qûpê ye.
Today our episode is in Qûpê village.
Emê ecwayê gundê Qûpê seykin, ka bi me ra bin, heta toliyê
vîdyo.
We will observe the atmosphere of Qûpê village, stay with us
until the end of the video.
Derbas bin gundê Qûpê.
Enter Qûpê village.
[Music/Singing Starts]
Geryam ez hemî wara...
I wandered all the places...
Min pirsî çû xûna zozana...
I asked about the blood/lineage of the highlands...
Evîna te berda bû dil...
Your love had dropped into the heart...
Jêre nake tucar çare.
There is never a cure for it.
Axata zêr û cewhera...
The lady of gold and jewels...
Deşta mirgin tacê ser e...
The plain of death is the crown on the head...
Ava te paqij û kewsere...
Your water is clean and Kawthar (heavenly river)...
Her bihar bi nêrx û qîmet e.
Every spring is worthy and valuable.
Efrîna min... Efrîna min...
My Afrin... My Afrin...
Jan û êşa vê dilî...
The pain and ache of this heart...
Ejû zînim...
I live...
Tu şêrîn î... dermano vî dilî...
You are sweet... the cure for this heart...
Dermano vî dilî...
The cure for this heart...
[Music Instrumental]
Qurban bejna zeytûnê...
I sacrifice myself for the stature of the olive tree...
Rengê çavê esmer...
The color of the brunette's eyes...
Çiyayê Hawar û Lêlûnê...
The mountains of Hawar and Lelun...
Cîyê ez jê radigûrim e...
The place where I am raised...
Keziya pûra te meydan ke...
Let the braids of your hair make a field...
Biska berde şû dar veke...
Let down the locks, open the wooden combs...
Enya te kelat û sema...
Your forehead is a fortress and a sky...
Ser bilind û serfiraz ke.
Make the head high and proud.
Efrîna min... Efrîna min...
My Afrin... My Afrin...
Cewlê me li gundê Qûpê ye. Silav û rêz, her kesê ku vê
vîdyoyê bibîne, ji gundê Qûpê.
Our tour is in Qûpê village. Greetings and respect to
everyone who sees this video, from Qûpê village.
Em dibên silavê me ji were hene, em hatin nava gundê Qûpê
ne.
We say we have greetings for you, we have come into the
middle of Qûpê village.
Gundekî pir xweş e, gundekî pir delal e.
It is a very nice village, a very beautiful village.
Me vê derkê xalê min ma re, emê noka wane skerim bidin.
We found my uncle remaining in this spot, we will now give
him the microphone.
Xalê min merheba ji te re.
My uncle, hello to you.
Ser çava hatî, ser serê min.
You are welcome upon my eyes, upon my head.
Xalê min çawale te, rehet e?
My uncle, how is your condition, is it comfortable?
Xwedê rehetî bide te, ciyekî spas weş gî. Şîva bûn xêr, şivê
we li min, min bivê wekim. Milet girt tîje tîje dikin, şaş û
furekî webin înşallah.
May God give you comfort, a very thankful place. The dinners
were good, your dinner is on me, I want to do it for you.
The people held it full, doing it fully, may you be happy
and lively, God willing.
Saet xweş, Xwedê ji xalê min razî be.
Cheers/Bless you, may God be pleased with my uncle.
Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike.
May God lengthen your life.
Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike xalê min de.
May God lengthen your life, my uncle.
Ser çava.
upon my eyes (You're welcome).
Xalê min, emê du sê swalên ji xalê xwe pirs bikin.
My uncle, we will ask two or three questions of our uncle.
Fermo, ehlen we sehlen, ser çavê min, ser serê min.
Go ahead, welcome, upon my eyes, upon my head.
Ser çavê te sax bin. Xalê min navê te bi xêr tuke nasekrin
bidî?
May your eyes be healthy. My uncle, your name with goodness,
can you introduce yourself?
Navê min Mehdîn Mehemedî Mislim e, Mehdîn Mislim.
My name is Mehdîn Mehemedî Mislim, Mehdîn Mislim.
Mehdîn Mislim, ay ehlen.
Mehdîn Mislim, oh welcome.
Ay sehlen.
Oh welcome.
Mehdîn, me gote...
Mehdîn, we said...
Em jî ji gundê Baedîna, cîranê gundê Qûpê bûn, hûro.
We are also from Baedina village, neighbors of Qûpê village,
today.
Em cîranê hev in înşallah.
We are neighbors of each other, God willing.
Erê, emê hev nin, em cîranê hev nin.
Yes, we are together, we are neighbors of each other.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Xalo, lê emrê te bi xêr çiqas e?
Uncle, but how much is your age with goodness?
Emrê min şêst û heft.
My age is sixty-seven.
Xwedê emrê te dirêj xalê min de înşallah.
May God lengthen your life, my uncle, God willing.
Te jî înşallah, yê we.
Yours too God willing, yours.
Înşallah nexweşî tune be?
God willing, there is no sickness?
Welle nexweşî işta tewazim ro çûne û lingê min azê dore.
Well, sickness, my balance is gone today and my leg hurts
around here.
Xwedê saetê xweş bi xalê min de înşallah.
May God give good health to my uncle, God willing.
Te jî înşallah.
You too, God willing.
De xalê uda, hûro, noka tu kêj ma ra, ser gund, emê çika
swal nîşta pirs kin, tu hazir î xalê min?
So uncle over there, today, now you are with us regarding
the village, we will ask a few questions, are you ready my
uncle?
Bêje, ehlen we sehlen, ser serî.
Say it, welcome, upon the head.
Serî te sax.
Health to your head.
Wek ez zanim, ezê hewa bidim.
As much as I know, I will give (answer) you.
Erê, erê, wek tu zanî emê deng kin.
Yes, yes, as much as you know we will record.
Xalê min noka vîrye dibên gundê Qûpê.
My uncle, now here they say Qûpê Village.
Tab, xalo ev navê jikû hatiye xeberê te heye?
Well, uncle, do you have news/knowledge where this name came
from?
Xeber heye.
I have news (knowledge).
Kû we re hewal da xêra xwe?
Where did they give you the news, please?
A xeber heye. Navê yekî bû, jêre digotin Hemo.
Ah, there is news. It was the name of a person, they called
him Hemo.
Hemo, ey hewrdor gund hemû hatibûn Hemo bînin.
Hemo, oh all the surrounding villages had come to fetch
Hemo.
Navê gundê Hemo bî.
It was the name of Hemo's village.
Digotin em herin gundê Hemo.
They used to say "Let's go to Hemo's village."
Rabî...
He stood up...
Dewrê xwe hebî.
It had its era.
Hemo, Hemo per bî.
Hemo, Hemo was wealthy/capable.
Nan lî nan... Hemo emendî dewlemend bû berê qorciyê gund
radikirin... digeriya heştê ro li ser dikşand.
Bread to bread... Hemo was so wealthy, he used to collect
the village tax/guards... he wandered pulling it for eighty
days.
Rê digeriya heştê ro bî. Dibar xortikî gund radikirin... du
şi xortê dorê reş.
The road he wandered was eighty days. He raised the young
men of the village... two black-clad youths.
Cilê wî hebî qonîk, hem cû cîl bûn, çi xuşînî girtî bû xonî
çêdikirin.
He had conical clothes, they were also clothes, whatever
pleasure he held they made homes.
Navê xwa Hemo bî, û Qûpê di goşt di cem hebî Qûpê di goşt.
His name was Hemo, and he had a 'Qûp' (suit/coat) on the
meat (body), a Qûp on the body.
Qomci, qorcî girtibû, digotin em herin cem Hemo... ew Qûpê
di goşt hene... herin goşt bixwen.
He had taken the tax/leadership, they said "Let's go to
Hemo... those Qûp on the body are there... let's go eat
meat."
Ee.
Yes.
Yanî maneya nav li nav gundê Qûpê.
Meaning the meaning of the name is name of Qûpê village.
Çimkî Qûpê goşt cem hebî.
Because he had a Qûp (coat/suit) of meat (body).
Ew Qûpê di goşt hebi.
He had that Qûp on the body.
Yanî vê navaz jorda kişî.
Meaning this name was pulled from up there.
Jorda kişî... navê xwa Hemo bî.
Pulled from above... his name was Hemo.
Paşê nav li nav gundê Qûpê kir kirmancî.
Then they made the name Qûpê Village in Kurmanji.
Bi Erebî nav li nav Hemşelek.
In Arabic the name is Hamshalak.
Ee.
Yes.
Na ewa Kirmancî dibên Gundê Qûpê, demek...
No, in Kurmanji they say Qûpê Village, meaning...
Ji Qûpê goşt kişî?
Was it pulled from "Qûpê goşt" (Coat of body/meat)?
Ji Qûpê goşt kişî, û Hemo şelek li sojê nav çî.
Pulled from Qûpê goşt, and Hemo wore 'şelek' (pants) which
went into the name.
Orî xwa hekim bî.
He was a ruler of his area.
Qorcî tewr radikirin diqeribîn.
They collected the taxes completely, they approached.
Digo em kî de herin?
He said "Where should we go?"
Herin cem Hemo qûpê kînê, zikî xwa pir kin.
Go to Hemo of the 'Qûp' (coat/suit), fill your bellies.
Şelek ew dikşînin ew orcê wa digrin.
They pull the 'Şelek' (pants), they take that tax of theirs.
Nav li nav Hemşelek.
The name became Hamshalak.
Hemo şelek.
Dikşandin.
He was pulling (wearing) it.
Rast e, dogrî ye, saet xweş xalê min.
It is true, it is correct, cheers to you my uncle.
Ser çava.
You're welcome.
Xalê min... ewa bîdyoyî bî gundî... ser navê Hemo şelek
dikşandin.
My uncle... that was the beginning of the village... on the
name Hemo wearing 'şelek'.
Destpêkî ewa hatî.
That came at the beginning.
Paşê dewar goştê cem hebî.
Then he had livestock meat with him.
Kerge... kergê digirt, dikoştin... dewrê xwe hebî dibirin...
nas dikir Qûpê goşt.
The tax... he took the tax, they killed... he had his era
they took... he recognized the "Qûp of meat".
Qûpê di goşt cem hebî. Nav li nav gundê Qûpê jê.
He had the Qûp of meat with him. The name Qûpê Village comes
from it.
Erê rast e.
Yes, it is true.
Paşê bi Erebî nav li nav Hemşû.
Then in Arabic the name became Hamshu.
Hamşû?
Hamshu?
Hamşû.
Hamshu.
Bi Erebî Hamşû.
In Arabic Hamshu.
Ew jî ji nefsî wir da kişî?
Was that also pulled from the same root/place?
Hemo şelek dikşandin. Te fêm kir ne wey?
Hemo pulled (wore) 'şelek'. Did you understand or not?
Ji wir da ew jî kişî.
It was also pulled from there.
Ew jî ji wir da kişî.
That was also pulled from there.
Erê, wey saet xweş xalê min.
Yes, oh cheers my uncle.
Dê xalê min, bi xêr te xeberî te heye çiqas mal li gundê
Qûpê da heye?
So my uncle, with goodness do you have news how many homes
are there in Qûpê village?
Welle...
Well...
Sed û şêst mal e.
It is one hundred and sixty homes.
Sed...
One hundred...
Şêst mal.
Sixty homes.
Sed û şêst mal. Xwedê zêde bike.
One hundred and sixty homes. May God increase it.
Spas dikim.
Thank you.
Xwedê saetê xweş bide xalê min.
May God give good health to my uncle.
Te jî yê wa.
You and yours too.
De xalê min, gundê Qûpê...
So my uncle, Qûpê village...
Bi çi meşhûr e?
What is it famous for?
Em bibên...
Let's say...
Gundê Qûpê zêdetir meşhûr e... bi pêz meşhûr e.
Qûpê village is mostly famous... famous for sheep.
Ee.
Yes.
Dawar, dewarê xwe jî hene, û zeytûnê xwe jî hene.
Livestock, they have their livestock too, and they have
their olives too.
Berê gir, rez bîn. Paşê bûn zeytûn.
Before the hills were vineyards. Then they became olives.
Ee.
Yes.
Û milet pirtir rojê diçin ciyê îşin.
And the people mostly go to the workplace during the day.
Karê çolê?
Wilderness work?
Karê çolê. Îsa êzû waza dikin, kût kotînin, zeytûnî
daweşînin.
Wilderness work. Now they do this and that, they prune/beat,
they shake the olives.
Ya hezret, na em bibên gencî, di wirtî çê daye teqîben.
Oh Prophet/Sir, no, let's say the youth, they are mostly in
that place/situation approximately.
Ee, gencî...
Yes, the youth...
Pîşê xwe dest û pa rojî çoye.
Their profession/work is gone by hand and foot daily.
Erê.
Yes.
Yanî gundekî yeno... hami rûxweş e.
Meaning a village that is... all pleasant/welcoming.
Zirekî, reîsî bûn jîn jî kirin.
Cleverness, they lived like chiefs/leaders too.
Erê.
Yes.
Na xweş e, wek me dît, em hatin.
It is nice, as we saw, we came.
Gundekî pir xweş û delal e.
It is a very nice and beautiful village.
Xwedê saetê xweş bi miletê gundê Qûpê de.
May God give good health to the people of Qûpê village.
Û yêkî vê vîdyoyê bibîne em dibên silav û rêz, ji te ra.
And whoever sees this video we say greetings and respect, to
you.
Xalo te gotinî zêde hene?
Uncle, do you have extra words?
Ee, saeta te xweş. Xwedê ji we razî be.
Yes, cheers to you. May God be pleased with you.
Hatina we, qîmetê pêjî, bîst û pênc sal e wa te nebîm.
Your coming, the value of the arrival, it's been twenty-five
years I haven't seen you/this.
Ecab naze, we zewicîm, Xwedê qeçik dan me.
Yes.
No wonder/Amazing, we married, God gave us children.
Xwedê ji te ra bihêle.
May God keep them for you.
Dilok, dilok û xîzanî Xwedê dan min.
Heartbreak, God gave me heartbreak and family
(trouble/loss).
Xwedê ji te ra bihêle.
May God keep them for you.
Wekî din, gundî me ye... rehmetî bû.
Otherwise, she was from our village... she passed away.
Rehmetî bû?
Did she pass away?
Sere te sax.
She passed away.
May your head be healthy (Condolences).
Gî rehma, em gî hew nin.
All mercy, we are all together (in fate).
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Lê qeçikê, qeçikê min rehet radikevin.
But the children, my children sleep comfortably/are doing
well.
Ê mezin, sofî yek e, camok dixwînê.
The big one, is a Sufi/religious one, he studies university.
Rind e, zirek.
Good, clever.
Xwedê bi heqîne înşallah.
God grant him success God willing.
Xwedê bi heqîne, înşallah.
God grant him success, God willing.
Qîzkê bêjî, beşer du... yekê sol be qad digire.
As for the girl, humans... one takes the floor/area for a
year/time.
Înşallah der e, înşallah.
God willing it is a door (opportunity), God willing.
Xwedê gî bibe heqîne.
May God grant success to all.
Te jî ba heqîne ya reb.
You too grant success oh Lord.
Saetê te xweş xalo, em ro nîvanê we bîn. Em dibên saet xweş.
Cheers to you uncle, today we were your guests. We say
cheers.
Xwedê rehma xwa li xaletiya me ke.
May God have mercy on our aunt.
Xwedê rehma xwa li xolê te ke, nezi.
May God have mercy on your uncle/people, near ones.
Xwedê rehma li xolê gî.
God have mercy on all uncles/people.
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê ji we razî be, em cîranê kî rind bîn, eştê xo dîtin
bîn.
God be pleased with you, we were good neighbors, we had seen
their times.
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê rehma xwe li dê û bavê te ke.
May God have mercy on your mother and father.
Xwedê ji xalê min razî be.
May God be pleased with my uncle.
Cî xwa cenet be înşallah.
May their place be paradise, God willing.
Daragê me gî.
All of our departed ones.
Em gî veçin, gundê me, çar mal rehmetî bîn.
We will all go.
We will all go, our village, four homes passed away.
Erê, rast e.
Yes, it is true.
Xalo tu gotinê zêde hene?
Uncle do you have extra words?
Ee saeta te xweş, û Xwedê ji we razî be, Xwedê we bi heqîne
înşallah.
Yes cheers to you, and God be pleased with you, God grant
you success God willing.
Saet xweş xalê min, Xwedê emrê dirêj bi xalê min de
înşallah.
Cheers my uncle, may God give a long life to my uncle God
willing.
Te jî yê wa, ehlen we sehlen.
You and yours too, welcome.
De em dibên saeta gundê xweş, silav û rêz, ji malbatê gundê
giştîkora.
So we say cheers to the village, greetings and respect, to
the families of the whole village.
Yekê vê vîdyoyê bibîne.
Anyone who sees this video.
Ka em vîdyo xwe li gundê Qûpê hûro, em temam bikin.
Let us finish our video in Qûpê village today.
[Music/Singing Starts]
Qurban bum ez vê zeytûnê.
I sacrificed myself for this olive.
Rengê çavê... ez kuştimê.
The color of the eyes... it killed me.
Çiyayê Hawar lûle lûle.
Hawar mountain is full of twists and turns.
Dilêm ji jêla gorî me.
My heart is a sacrifice for it because of the embers.
Gazî û hawar tê meydan ke.
Bring the call and the cry to the square.
Bisk û baran şûdar veke.
Undo the wet locks of hair and rain.
Hêlîna te ke... asîman e.
Make your nest... [in] the sky.
Serê Bîlal û Hûrik e.
[On] the peak of Bilal and Hurik.
Afrîna min, evîna min.
My Afrin, my love.
Jan û êşa vê dilî.
The pain and ache of this heart.
Tu jîn î, tu şîn î.
You are life, you are greenery [vitality].
Hem derman û hem kul î.
You are both the cure and the wound.
Ev jî şebaka me ya derecê.
And this is our network of stairs.
Em hatin şikefta mezin, niha emê, inşallah emê tewaf bikin,
temaşe bikin.
We came to the big cave, now we will, God willing, we will
tour it, we will watch.
Manzereke, qantirmê xo pirna, ya pîroz, ya dîrokî ye.
A view, its archways are massive, it is sacred, it is
historical.
Kameraman tu dikarî nîşan bidî, binêre, kevirê kûlan çawa
çêkirine.
Cameraman, you can show it, look, how the hewn stones are
made.
Û hênik jî hênik. Maşallah.
And it is cool, so cool. Mashallah.
Ela mezinbûna vê derê, vê derê, ela yê vê derê dûçik
çêkirine.
Look at the size of this place, this place, look how they
made chimneys here.
Maşallah şiwir bigre.
Mashallah, take a shot.
Ne tenê derbasbûn e, derbasbûnekî dîrokî ye.
It is not just a passing through, it is a historical
passage.
Temaşe bikin, hunera destê Kurda li serê çiyayê Hawarê.
Watch, the art of Kurdish hands on the top of Hawar
mountain.
Hûn dibînin, qûpîyên mezin. Di vir de jî min got xezîneyê
tiştekî tişt têde heye.
You see, big jars. In here, I said, there is a treasury or
something inside.
Tişt çêkirine, hawar hawar, qûpîyên hindî dipirînê jî.
They made things, oh my, jars the size of huge vats too.
Eva metxalê xwe ye, tiştekî pir...
This is its entrance, something very...
Hawa gelekî, efrineke, kebireke, kûlan dinê, hewşa çêkirine.
The air is very... a creation, a stone, seeing the holes,
they made a courtyard.
Kefê hewşê.
The floor of the courtyard.
Galikê sefîl li vê derê, mirov çawa têhn vedide.
A humble mattress here, how a person rests.
Ala vê kevirê çawa anîne, çawa sekinîne.
Look how they brought this stone, how they stood it up.
Vê derê çêkirîye, xwedê zane radikirin, axa...
They made this place, God knows they were lifting, the
soil...
Cemekî noka dikelînin, hûn serê wî demê radikin.
Just as they boil chickpeas, you recall that time.
Ala werin, werin, mesada werin.
Oh come, come, come to the expanse.
Her tişt ciyayê cî çî ye ev?
Everything implies a place, what is this place?
Herçî vê derê, taq vekirine, ev taqna manê çine nizam.
Whatever is here, they opened arches, I don't know what
these arches mean.
Ropo, yek li vir, hember, ev de.
Look, one here, opposite, in this.
Livir jî Semîr berxê xwe ecibandîye, ellah bemol.
And here Samir has taken a liking to his "lamb" [likely
referring to an object or joke], God be praised.
Bira berxê te bamol.
Brother, may your lamb be praised.
Xêr e?
Is it good?
Kîjan berx? Tu dibê qey kuçikê gundê me te seh kir?
Which lamb? Do you mean the dog of our village that you
heard?
Lez de çiko guman tuye, lez de çiko, guman tuye.
Hurry up because you are suspected, hurry up because you are
suspected.
Tebe'en hevalê mînan, em cewleke xwe li gundê Qûpê temam
bikin.
Of course, dear friends, let us complete our tour in the
village of Qûpê.
Gundekî pir delal û kibar e. Gundekî xweş e.
A very beautiful and noble village. A nice village.
Silav û rêz ji miletê gundê Qûpê ra, yekê vêdê bîne, li
vêderê, li gurbetê dibe.
Greetings and respect to the people of the village of Qûpê,
to the ones watching this, here, or in the diaspora.
...Derman û hem kul î.
...Cure and both the wound.
Geryam ez di hemî waran.
I wandered through all the lands.
Min pirsî çû xûna zozana.
I asked about the blood of the high pastures.
Evîna te berda bû dil, min jêre nekir tu çara.
Your love had fallen into the heart, I found no remedy for
it.
Ax hatî sê roj û hewa.
Oh, three days and weather have come.
Deşt û merg hemû te jîn e.
Plains and meadows are all life because of you.
Bisk û baran şûdar veke.
Undo the wet locks of hair and rain.
Hêlîna te ke... asîman e.
Make your nest... [in] the sky.
Serê Bîlal û Hûrik e.
[On] the peak of Bilal and Hurik.
Afrîna min, evîna min.
My Afrin, my love.
Jan û êşa vê dilî.
The pain and ache of this heart.
Tu jîn î, tu şîn î.
You are life, you are greenery [vitality].
Hem derman û hem kul î.
You are both the cure and the wound.
Erê cemaet, vîdyoya me herû li gundê Qûpê ye.
Yes folks, our video continues in the village of Qûpê.
Silav û rêz ji gundê Qûpê ra. Miletni rind e.
Greetings and respect to the village of Qûpê. A good people.
Lê gund jî xweş e, tebîeta gund jî xweş e.
But the village is also nice, the nature of the village is
also nice.
Em dibên silav û rêz, xwedê sehta we xweş.
We say greetings and respect, may God give you good health.
Bê, miletê gundê Qûpê de, li vir dibe, lê li derva dibe.
Indeed, for the people of Qûpê village, whether here or
abroad.
De noka xalê me jî li ber rojê, emê çikin, vêra danikin.
So now, our uncle is also in the sun, we will go, we will
sit with him.
Êş û mara mûşareke ke, çike ser gund me ra deng ke, ka mar
bûn.
To share pains and wishes, let him talk to us a bit about
the village, let's see how they are.
Xalê merhaba ji te ra.
Uncle, hello to you.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Çawayî, tu rihet î?
How are you, are you comfortable?
Elhemdu lîllah, kêfa te xweş e?
Praise be to God, are you well?
Xwedê reheta te bide, înşallah, xalê min.
May God give you comfort, God willing, my uncle.
Xalê min ro, em mîvandarîyê te ne, qenata Afrîn Flo, vîdyo
me herû li gundê Qûpê ye.
My uncle, today we are your guests, Afrin Flo channel, our
video continues in the village of Qûpê.
Em dixwazin ji milet ra vîdyokî çêkin, vîdyokî xweş, li
gundê Qûpê.
We want to make a video for the people, a nice video, in the
village of Qûpê.
Ê heye li gurbetê, bîra gundê xwe kirî. Ne wane ye?
Those who are in the diaspora, miss their village. Isn't
that right?
Ew wilo ye.
That is how it is.
Ka dibê çi wekî yarab?
What does one say, oh Lord?
Ya na beşa rinde, xêr nîne.
Oh no, say it is good, is there no good?
Yê şiya me dikin, rind e, pîs e?
The thing we are doing, is it good, is it bad?
Na, bi şo rind e, xêr nîne?
No, on my honor it is good, why wouldn't it be good?
Tu yê tiştê wiha rind deynî ber wera, miletê xwe bibînî.
You are putting such a good thing before them, so they see
their people.
Meriyê mera hene, tişta, walah şirîn e, walah...
We have relatives, things, by God it is sweet, by God...
Yê gelek şirîn tir e.
It is much sweeter.
Erê, sehta her kesî xweş, işî rind eke. Ji me ra bibêje,
xalê min navê te bi xêr?
Yes, health to everyone, doing a good job. Tell us, my
uncle, what is your name please?
Ebdo Elî Yûsif im.
I am Abdo Ali Yusuf.
Ehlen wa sehlen xalê Ebdo.
Welcome, Uncle Abdo.
Ehlîn.
Welcome.
Xalê Ebdo, emrê te çiqas e, bi xêr be?
Uncle Abdo, how old are you, may it be blessed?
Xwedê rehetê bide, ez li ser 80 salî me.
May God give comfort, I am around 80 years old.
80 sal.
80 years.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bide, xalê min.
May God give you a long life, my uncle.
Xwedê rebe 'alema umeta Mhemed hemîyan.
May God, the Lord of the worlds, [give it] to the entire
nation of Muhammad.
Amîn ya reb. Lê xalê min, nexweşî şolê te hene?
Amen, oh Lord. But my uncle, do you have any illnesses?
Na elhemdulillah, nexweşî tenê... wey teze emrê xwe bûye 80
sal lê...
No, praise be to God, the illness is just... oh, well, the
age has become 80 years but...
Ya nexweşî...
Or illness...
...Hêlî xwedê nabe.
...Is not apart from God.
Elhemdulillah. Nexweşî diza me ta dîtî, navê zeytûnê
maşallah.
Praise be to God. You saw our disease [trouble], the name of
the olive, mashallah.
Erê, ew nexweşîya heba meqtelê, nexweşîya şekir û xwedê rebe
'alemîn... heba miratê nexweşîya hemu hal na maye.
Yes, that illness of the deadly pill/sore, the illness of
sugar [diabetes] and God Lord of the worlds... the damn
pill/sore, there is no condition left without illness.
Elhemdulillah, dîsa em hetadî tî, nav zeytûnê maşallah, hewa
jî pak tê ber bayê, hemdulillah şukur xwedê ra xalê min.
Praise be to God, again we have come, among the olives
mashallah, the air is also clean in the wind, praise and
thanks to God, my uncle.
De xalê min, em biftin ser meselê şikefta, em nav gund
digerîn, me şikeft pir dîn.
So my uncle, let's get to the subject of the caves, we are
walking in the village, we saw many caves.
Na yek na didu... tebîet pir ne.
Not one, not two... there are many in nature.
Lê hela evna kevndar ne? Zû ne? Tu kanî mera xeber de?
But look, are these ancient? Are they old? Can you tell us?
Ya evna... miletê vira, dibên Hecîko.
Oh these... the people of here, they call them Hecîko.
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Ta fêm kir?
Did you understand?
Û li vira, gel vira şikefto dibînî.
And here, with this place, you see the caves.
Rind.
Good.
Jêr, pişt şikefta nê.
Down, behind the caves.
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Ew bûn... ew bûn binê gundê Qîbarê... dibên Heyder.
They were... they were under the village of Qîbar... they
call it Heyder.
Dibên mala Heyder.
They say the house of Heyder.
Mala Ebdî Mehoko... mala...
The house of Abdi Mehoko... the house of...
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Evna... mala xalê biderê bûn. Gundê Elî Bolo.
These... were the house of the maternal uncle outside. The
village of Eli Bolo.
Gundê Elî Bolo.
The village of Eli Bolo.
Dibên vî gundê Elî Bolo.
They call this the village of Eli Bolo.
Aha.
Uh-huh.
Ev noka, vî derê da xanî, noka... vî... heta derîyê binî,
gundê Elî Bolo.
This now, in this place houses, now... this... until the
bottom gate, is the village of Eli Bolo.
Elî Bolo.
Eli Bolo.
Û de... ber û barê, dibênê Hemşelekê.
And so... the surroundings and front, they call it
Hemşelekê.
Hem gund da?
Also in the village?
Eh Hemşelekê.
Yes, Hemşelekê.
E, mabeyna genda da ixtîlaf çêbû, mezinê wan hev çêbû şer
kirin.
Uh, a dispute happened between the villages, their elders
had a falling out, they fought.
Çûn ber çoyê gewir.
They went before the stick of the infidel
[authority/foreigner].
Ber çoyê gewir.
Before the stick of the infidel.
Ber çoyê gewir de hatin ereba, Hemşelekê ereb in.
Before the stick of the infidel, the Arabs came, Hemşelekê
are Arabs.
Lê wuri jî heye Hemşelekê Ereb?
Is there also an Arab Hemşelekê there?
Hemşelekê Ereb in.
Hemşelekê are Arabs.
Malê Sebrî Yûsif... malê wa...
The house of Sabri Yusuf... their house...
Malê Sebrî Yûsif... dibên malê Heboke...
The house of Sabri Yusuf... they say the house of Heboke...
Navê wî gundî Xelek e, Xelek.
The name of that village is Xelek, Xelek.
Haho Sifî Pênc dê rênin.
Look, they will show Sifi Penj.
Erê.
Yes.
Bas avê va boşar dikirin, av kê bûn? Çûn ber çiya av da,
leqlek hatin rehmetî got Sifî Pênc...
When they were releasing the water, whose water was it? They
went to the mountain for water, the storks came, the late
one said Sifi Penj...
Sifî Pênc tirba mezin li wir e.
Sifi Penj is a big tomb there.
Sifî Pênc tirbe?
Sifi Penj is a tomb?
Sifî Pênc tirbe, mezin li wir e.
Sifi Penj is a tomb, a big one there.
Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke.
May God have mercy on him.
Îca ew dere rûniştin li wir. Av çûn û derket, em jî li vira
bûn.
So they sat there. The water went and came out, and we were
here.
Haho êdî 'Erfî Camiyê temam lê bilind, cihekî şirîn cî bû.
Look, then Arfi Jami was completely high up, it was a sweet
place.
Erê.
Yes.
Haho ew gund e Hemşelek e.
Look, that village is Hemshelek.
Yanî esasê gund ê me ne.
Meaning, the foundation of the village is ours.
Gund bi navê me ye, Hemşelek.
The village is named after us, Hemshelek.
Rast e.
That's right.
Dibên Hecîb e... meselen dibên Hesîko... dibên Mislim Lero,
malê miştê Hesîko wilo.
They say Hecib... for example they say Hesiko... they say
Mislim Lero, the house of Hesiko's people like that.
Erê.
Yes.
Sê gund bra gundê Elîkê bûn, rast dibêjim, Hecîba berê li
wir derê bûn eref axa.
Three villages were brothers of the village of Elike, I'm
telling the truth, the Heciba were there previously, Araf
Agha.
Mala Ehson Lero.
The house of Ahson Lero.
Erê.
Yes.
Paşê anîn girtin, mer'a bûn, girtin kirin Hemşelek.
Later they brought them and took them, they were pastures,
they took them and made it Hemshelek.
Kirin sê gund, kirin mer'a Hemşelekê.
They made three villages into the pasture of Hemshelek.
Erê.
Yes.
Nav yek e.
The name is one.
Kirin yek.
They made it one.
Erê rast e, sihet xweş xalê min.
Yes that's right, bless you my uncle.
Dê xalê min noka em bibin gundê Qûpê.
My uncle, let's turn to the village of Qupe now.
Naçe...
It doesn't go...
Qûpê jî ji Hemşelek e.
Qupe is also from Hemshelek.
Kî? Qûpê?
Who? Qupe?
Dibên gundê Qûpê, Hemqûp... ew jî brakê hevdin e.
They call it the village of Qupe, Hemqup... they are also
brothers of each other.
Ee.
Uh-huh.
Te bave serjiya heye didî? Dê bra çî dibên Şemdînê Ebdê...
You know the father of Serjiya? The brother, what do they
call him, Shemdine Abde...
Ebdê ji Hemşelek e.
Abde is from Hemshelek.
Erê.
Yes.
Yanî ev mer'a... sê aîle têkî nakevin.
Meaning this pasture... three families do not interfere with
it.
Bra hana dibên Şîmo, Hecîkê Şîmo.
That brother, they call him Shimo, Hecike Shimo.
Erê.
Yes.
Dê boro hewşê wî da, dibên Şêxê Elîkê... dibînin hawa qûl bi
dere.
Did you understand?
Hewşa wan qûl bi dere.
Their courtyard has a hole going out there.
Rast e.
That's right.
Dê xalê min, li gundê Qûpê noka em bibin... 'emrê xwe kevn
e, pirr e noka, bi vê wezihê ve gund da?
So uncle, in the village of Qupe, let's say... is its age
old? Is it a lot now, in this situation in the village?
Kevndar e, ne wye?
It is ancient, isn't it?
Gund... teqrîben...
The village... approximately...
Teqrîben erê.
Approximately, yes.
Erê... tike behs bibîne... sê sed salî heye.
Yes... if we discuss it a bit... it is three hundred years
old.
Sê sed salî heye.
It is three hundred years old.
Zivistan berê ew bûn... Tev bûn hewêl dikirin.
In winter, previously they were that... They were all doing
[unclear, possibly 'hawel' - moving/changing].
Rast e.
That's right.
Derman, merman çî me tne bûn.
There were no medicines or anything for us.
Hm.
Ax vedikolan... axê dikulan, dikişandin sivaq dikirin.
They used to dig the soil... dug the soil, carried it and
plastered it.
Dêr, û cî hawa qûb dida xwe digirtin.
The church [or place], and places like domes/caves, they
would occupy.
Hawa nê, eke haw bî, eke para lê bî da ketin jêr.
Like this, if it was like that, if it was back there, they
went down.
Haho malê he M'hemedê Henî, malê malê Heyder, malê Mehmûd...
Look, the house of M'hemed Heni, the house of Heyder, the
house of Mehmud...
Wana hew na hesiqandin e.
They were [unclear, possibly 'plastered/stuck'] like that.
Erê.
Yes.
Hawna da ketin jêr.
Like that, they went down.
Bes Hemşelek dista tenê di zemanê berzî... di şkeftin e.
But Hemshelek... only in the high times... it is inside
caves.
Erê di şkeftin e welle.
Yes, they are in caves, by God.
Bin boşî, hew cern o jî ê me ye, 'efşûr çêbûye.
Under the emptiness, that jar/basin is also ours, pressed
grapes were made there.
Do bofkên mey rehmê lê.
[Unclear, possibly regarding ancestors].
Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke.
May God have mercy on them.
Tike behs bibîne, baw gundo, yanî berê şkeft bûn, şkeftê xwe
li daxaz bûn, bê şkeft bûn yanî.
If we discuss a bit, look at the village, meaning previously
they were caves, they desired their caves, meaning they were
without caves [or distinct caves].
Erê şkeft jî hebûn, pirr lê ketine welle xalê min.
Yes, there were caves too, many have collapsed, by God,
uncle.
Ee malê miştê Hese, şkeftê xwe wû derê dijiyan.
Uh, the house of Hese's people, they lived in their caves
over there.
Bin 'efşûrê...
Under the grape press...
Rast e.
That's right.
Dê xalê min, hewşê Kevndar jêre heye, gelek qenter maye wna.
So uncle, there is the Kevndar courtyard down there, many
arches remain there.
Kû derê?
Where?
Li jêr.
Down below.
Haho wû da?
Look, over there?
Haho wû da esta ê malê Xelîlê Ehmed bûn.
Uh-huh.
Look, over there, those were the house of Xelil Ehmed.
Kevndar in, na wye?
They are ancient, aren't they?
Erê Kevndar e. Berê ew malê Xelefê Derê bûn, bi şkeftê xwe
heye.
Yes, ancient. Previously they were the house of Xelef Dere,
it has its own cave.
Di wû derê da ketin jêr.
In there, they went down.
Rast e.
That's right.
Paşê firûz Hesenê Emşê hebû, Behdîna bûn.
Later, there was Firuz Hesen Emshe, they were from Badina.
Ebrî ew riyê xwo ji Behdîna bûn.
[Unclear], their path was from Badina.
Ehsenê Emşê kirî.
Ahsen Emshe bought it.
Rast e.
That's right.
Ehsenê Emşê kirî, paşê...
Ahsen Emshe bought it, then...
Haro bîn noka.
[Unclear] now.
Erê, ka av e, kes nate tenê kevndar e.
Yes, well it's water [or distinct], no one comes, it's just
ancient.
E law qet ya xwo... Xelîl rehmetî bûn.
Oh man, not at all... Xelil was deceased.
Paşê frot bî wekê men, 'ereb.
Later it was sold like us, [to] Arabs.
Erê. Dê xalê min...
Yes. So uncle...
Ma rewal de te çi kar dikir berê? Te çi îş dikir? Te xwend,
te nexwend?
What work did you do as a kid back then? What job did you
do? Did you study, did you not study?
Noka berê...
Now, back then...
E, berê mekteb hebûn tne bûn?
Uh, back then were there schools or not?
No mekteb... çi dît?
No school... what did you see?
Gundê Dêvlîş, Dimilya, Gundê Qûpê, Sêvya, Gundê Kêlî bûn...
The village of Devlish, Dimilya, Village of Qupe, Sevya,
Village of Keli were there...
Ewan tenê, tenê mekteb, Gundê Badîna mektebek tenê bûn.
Those only, only a school, the Village of Badina had only
one school.
Hawî vî derê jê... di hatin Badîna.
From here... they used to come to Badina.
Di hatin Badîna.
They used to come to Badina.
Wî mektebê jor?
That upper school?
Erê mektebê jor.
Yes, the upper school.
Rast e.
That's right.
E paşê...
Uh, later...
Fitra kî ma...
A period remained...
Hafez El Esed teşlîm kir.
Hafez al-Assad took over.
Wexta Hafez El Esed teşlîm kir, ew sa'b gû... nûyî bîne.
When Hafez al-Assad took over, that difficult... was brought
new.
Go ev xelkê qîz brol berfê kune re Badîna?
He said, are these people's daughters and sons going to
Badina in the snow?
Çatne zûr e welle.
It is very difficult, by God.
Berf lê ket, berê ge berf bî, boş bî.
Snow fell, previously there was snow, it was abundant.
Ne wek noka bî, rift tne bî, rêk ne bûn.
It wasn't like now, there was no asphalt, there were no
roads.
Teftikê...
[Unclear, possibly fabric type]...
Hafez El Esed...
Hafez al-Assad...
Gote anî her gundekî mekteb kire dayê.
He ordered that every village should have a school put in
it.
Gote malê xwe derket, ji mektebê derket, were malê xwe.
He said leave your house, leave the school, come to your
house.
Wê go zehmet nêkêşîne.
He said so they don't suffer hardship.
Û jibo dere derket, he ne nêzîk e.
And getting out to there, look it isn't close.
Erê.
Yes.
Heta biro berfê, pêxwas, qetîk o ne ner e.
Even walking in the snow, barefoot, [unclear] is not
[unclear].
Neke zê çetin e, divê çûlê ra...
Don't do it, it is difficult, having to go through the
wilderness...
Erê...
Yes...
Gundê Dêvlîş, ba ewê Gundê Med, Dimilya, ewê bes...
Village of Devlish, regarding that Village of Med, Dimilya,
those just...
Gundê Qûpê, Sêvya, ew mektebek tenê bûn.
Village of Qupe, Sevya, they were just one school.
Bes mekteb. De naha ev mektebê gund, me tu na kevn e zêde,
ne xalo?
Just [one] school. So now this village school, we [think]
it's not very old, right uncle?
No ne kevn e.
No, it is not old.
Solê çend o da te bîreta?
In what year do you remember?
Sî û di... hefit û yeko... nimek haf...
Thirty and two... seventy-one... half [unclear]...
Şêst... şêst heştan derketim ji 'eskeriyê.
Sixty... in sixty-eight I came out of the military service.
Şêst heştan, erê.
Sixty-eight, yes.
Yanî tike behs bibîne...
Meaning if we discuss a bit...
Heftî û... salê...
Seventy and... the year...
Heftî û şeşan da, yan heft bû yan.
In seventy-six, or it was seven or.
Di heftî û şeşan da çêbî teqrîben.
It was built in seventy-six approximately.
Heftî û şeşan teqrîben çêbî.
Seventy-six approximately it was built.
Erê. Mekteb çêkirin.
Yes. They built the school.
Erê. Berî mekteb hebî noka go xolû qusrû 'of kirin din.
Yes. Before the school existed, you say uncle they were left
neglected/wandering.
Île to bî, her gundek île...
It was necessary to be, every village necessarily...
Bê 'alime, yozî û xondinê...
Without knowledge, writing and reading...
Êlaw xwedê île rind e.
Oh man, God knows it is better.
Noka wera kîk hebî bibînim, enizanim çi tê da ye. Meletî bê
jimarotî enizanim çi.
Now if there is a paper I can see, I don't know what is in
it. The nation without counting [education], I don't know
what.
Lê to kî 'ere, rî kî da 'ere, mesele...
But you know [a bit], you know the way, for example...
Xalo reqemê xalo ya ez nizanim.
Uncle, uncle's number I don't know.
Efî nizanim. Î, ya no bê 'elim, ya xwedê ne xwedê ye.
I don't know this. Yes, meaning without knowledge, oh God,
it is not godly.
Lê rind e, merov çi be 'alime rind e.
But it is good, whatever a person is [with] knowledge is
good.
Fîdel merov dibe.
One becomes a useful person.
Île fîdel merov dibe.
Necessarily one becomes a useful person.
Tabean tiştê rind merov dibe, ne ekîs.
Of course one becomes a good thing, not the opposite.
Erê.
Yes.
Tipçi, be 'alime rind e.
Medicine, having knowledge is good.
Fîdel ye. Lê xalê min, divir da em bibin miletê gundê Qûpê.
It is useful. But uncle, here let's turn to the people of
the village of Qupe.
Çi karî dike bi şeklê am?
What work do they generally do?
Berê, teqrîben... yanî...
Previously, approximately... meaning...
Erê, şêst, hefta... yanî...
Yes, sixty, seventy... meaning...
Berê gund çîl bûn. Çîl.
Previously the village was forty [houses]. Forty.
Pêş, vê deşta gir rez bûn, ne zeytûn bûn.
Before, this big plain was vineyards, they weren't olives.
Rez bûn.
They were vineyards.
Doxê ba av, dexl û dan dikirin, sindiq...
[Unclear] irrigated, they grew wheat and barley, boxes...
Dikirin mûy, dikirin dimiş...
They made hair [products], they made grape molasses...
Te se kir, gulî, pilî, pur, gur, lûk û de tê de hatin.
You watched, braids, [rhyming words], heavy, dense,
[unclear] came in it.
Toke hedîde titkî bî.
It was a sharp iron collar.
Le ber şûl gund daku...
Because of the village work so that...
Xalo, li ber xav dikirin, yanî çû dikirin, li wir xav
dikirin?
Uncle, did they do it raw [fresh], meaning how did they do
it, did they do it raw there?
Ê li wir xav dikirin, naxwe rêş...
Yes, they did it raw/fresh there, otherwise black...
Oxe ke tirê diçînî, dijiplanî, dikirin dimiş.
When they picked the grapes, trampled them, they made
molasses.
Kefî, awe dimiş dikelandin.
Foam, the water of the molasses they boiled.
Dîn o w erd...
Put it on the ground...
Mîj dikirin, awe... dikelandin, rê dixistin li erdê serjî
da.
They sucked it, water... they boiled it, poured it on the
ground in the washing place.
Digo miştoxa, tirê.
They called it 'mishtoxa', grapes.
Îlê?
Really?
Rast e.
That's right.
Hûr din, no me, berê...
Finely grounded, look us, previously...
Pez... û rez bî. Zeytûn hindik bûn.
Sheep... and vineyards existed. Olives were few.
Kêm bî berê?
Were they scarce previously?
Erê kêm bî. Yanî...
Yes, scarce. Meaning...
Deh mala, yanî sed zeytûn hebûn.
Ten houses, meaning there were a hundred olives.
Erê rast e.
Yes, that's right.
De deşta...
So the plain...
Dê dikirin genim.
They used to grow wheat.
Dikirin garis.
They grew millet.
Ta garis dît? Pembî?
Have you seen millet? Cotton?
Û dikirin pembî.
And they grew cotton.
Dê li vê deştê diçandin?
Did they plant it in this plain?
Îlê, li 'erdê xwo diçandin.
Yes, they planted it on their land.
Haman, xalo noka tişta tine, kêm e.
Same, uncle now things are gone, it's scarce.
Noka kêm, gi kirine zeytûn, a.
Now scarce, they made it all olives, see.
Tirê gubi zeytûn, zeytûn ne rez mir?
Grapes became olives, didn't olives kill the vineyard?
Zeytûn, bî zeytûn, tişt dî tin noka.
Olives, it became olives, there is nothing else now.
Tî bî zeytûn, zeytûn mezin bî, îna rez bi xû mir.
It became olives, olives grew big, so the vineyard died by
itself.
E re mezin bî, noka fêmî wan o berê rez bî.
Uh, it grew big, now their understanding [is that]
previously it was a vineyard.
Erê.
Yes.
Na we. E zeytûn gişt in.
Like that. Uh, olives are everything.
Rez bixû mir.
The vineyard died by itself.
Erê.
Yes.
Bi şiklê 'am.
Generally speaking.
Xwarin, ba xwarina me çîl bî.
Food, regarding our food, it was forty.
Ga bûn, ta ne, cot cotin.
There were oxen, right, pair by pair.
Bi şev, wextî noka...
At night, around this time...
Diçûn ser, diçûn dicêrandin.
They went up, they went to graze them.
Û tînan, siet hefta dikirin jût.
And brought them, at seven o'clock they yoked them [for
plowing].
Tê cût dikirin.
You were plowing.
Dê cût dikirin.
They were plowing.
Di draktor kêm bîn, ne wye xalo?
There were few tractors, right uncle?
Draktor qet çinebîn.
Tractors didn't exist at all.
No mentiqa tine bîn?
No, were there none in the region?
Mentiqa wilah req tine bîn.
In the region, by God, there weren't any hard ones
[roads/tractors].
Fitrakê tê...
A period came...
Digotin malê Henîf Axa, li firî ewê, li gundê Xelîl...
They said the house of Hanif Agha, over there, in the
village of Xelil...
Hinî zer e bîn, zer.
There were yellow ones, yellow.
Draktorê zer.
Yellow tractors.
Draktor qîl zer. Digo hebu malê Henîf e.
A big yellow tractor. They said it belonged to Hanif's
house.
Ee.
Uh-huh.
Paşê, fitrakê...
Then, a period...
Hin...
Some...
Xanam çû, ew derket, işe piçûkû zerî, digotin...
[Unclear], that came out, a small yellow thing, they called
it...
Birkiz.
Draktorê Birkiz. Begê heta noka hene xalo.
The Birkiz tractor. Maybe they still exist, uncle.
Yane bes yane.
Meaning just that.
Na, bes ne nefse wana ne.
No, but not the same as those.
Noka gund nebîne mûşî û wanî û...
Now the village shouldn't be [unclear, possibly Mitsubishi]
and such and...
Ewan, haw wa...
Those, like that...
Model pir derketin.
Many models came out.
Zîwanî zer...
The yellow Ziwani...
Ee.
Uh-huh.
Elê 'ereba hebîn. Yek wext, bizanim draktorê zer bîn.
The Arabs had them. At one time, I know they were yellow
tractors.
Erê.
Yes.
Paşê haw mûda hindo bî...
Then this fashion came...
Birkiz derketin. Pîşê qûsûrik û... ormîşê piçûk, wekî bê
şêmşûl a.
Birkiz came out. Short front and... small [unclear], like
without a hood.
Ee wekî şêmşûl.
Have you seen the Shemshul?
Uh, like the Shemshul.
Digotin Birkiz.
They called it Birkiz.
Noka ew mûda jî helo tê.
Now that fashion has also gone.
Dikirin e mûşî. Birkiz mûşî.
They made it [unclear type]. Birkiz [unclear].
Rast e.
That's right.
Noka 'alyat pir bîne, dinya pêşketî bûye, ne wek xolo?
Now machines have become many, the world has advanced,
hasn't it uncle?
Île xolo bêje tî tiştê...
Really uncle say [unclear]...
Û berê bes... berê çetin bî.
And before only... before it was difficult.
Bi palê... genim diçînîn. Warî doskî.
With laborers... we harvested wheat. Doski style.
Genim diçînîn.
Hm.
We harvested wheat.
Şexre...
[Unclear, possibly 'Sickle']...
Qatir tînan...
Mules brought...
Liyê didan zengelî vê diketin digot tilang û lang, tilang û
lang...
They hit the side, the bell fell on this saying 'tlang u
lang, tlang u lang'...
Dihat gund.
Coming to the village.
Bê deng qatir bi xwa kî zane...
Without sound, who knows the mule by itself...
Bê derê xwa bî, diçû ser bêderê disekinî heywan.
It knew its threshing floor, it went to the threshing floor
and the animal stood there.
Bi xwa 'alimî?
Did it learn by itself?
Erê doke 'alimî.
Yes, look it learned.
Rast e.
That's right.
E, berê got kumê sipî li bîn.
Uh, previously they said there were white caps.
Qor 'ewîl er... kum degiştî.
The first time [unclear]... holding the cap.
Digot tu çûyî mala dergiştî?
He said did you go to the house of the engaged one?
Kumê sipî danî serê xwo. Te got xulxulî ten...
He put a white cap on his head. You said [unclear]...
Na, ne me, ne ehdî walah xolo, bawer nake nakim tiştekî.
No, not us, not [our] era by God uncle, I don't believe, I
don't do anything.
Kumikî yano wekî aw bî.
A small cap, meaning it was like water [clear/white].
Kumê sipî çûk.
A small white cap.
Welle sipî bî?
By God, was it white?
Erê. Digot çûyî mala dergistiyê...
Yes. He said did you go to the house of the engaged one...
Kumek dayê.
She gave a cap.
Xolo, yanî wekî kamo bas, ard maldar kîsê kê têke?
Uncle, meaning like the land tax, into whose pocket did the
property tax go?
Walî, hew e xolo niho nîne.
By God, that is not around now, uncle.
Ê kê telaq dikir, kî hukim dikir?
So who was demanding it, who was ruling?
E kê telaq dikir? Mebe hukimê xolo meselen, hukim nakiye?
Who was demanding it? You mean the government, uncle, for
example, isn't it the government?
Axakî, mîrekî?
An Agha, a Prince?
Xweşe, elê bere walo bî, her hedê gundekî xwa hebî.
Well, back then it was like that, every village had its own
border.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Noko bere, hukimê dan şerîxwe, şarî şor merezê dan dûrê.
Now before, the government made its law, they kept the
saline land/city far away.
Erê.
Yes.
Şarî... şarî şor merezê.
The city... the saline city/land.
Erê.
Yes.
Hewa digote hukm, eşayerîne xwedî dîn e.
That, they called the government, the tribes are religious
(owners of religion).
Wekî Mele Henîf, wekî Mele Qate, wekî Mele Heskanî elî hem.
Like Mullah Hanif, like Mullah Qata, like Mullah Heskani,
all of them.
Ew na eşayerîne.
Those are the tribes.
Wan jî hukim da şerîxwe. Ew dikirin.
They also applied the Sharia law. They did it.
Şarî şor merezê dan me jî.
They gave us the saline land/city (difficult parts).
Rast e.
That’s right.
Digo şarî şor merezê darî bere nîxo, hewa ya eşayerî ye,
oxey.
He said the saline land is the wood of the front... that is
the tribal way, okay.
Hîşê Axa rind deqa li we dikir?
Did the Agha rule over you well?
E mela, e mela bilî reşîd e.
Oh Mullah, oh Mullah, except for Rashid.
Bî feqîra nedikir xolo?
Didn't he help the poor, uncle?
Feqîra ne... kî, kî xêrê li xo dîtiye?
The poor... who, who has ever seen charity for themselves?
Ewaye.
That is it.
Hemî, tişt milkê xwa ne.
All, things were their own property.
Ê wa ye.
That is it.
Wexta hat, mana, pêra we, ewa, hûn jî didîtirke.
When it came, meaning, after that, that one, you saw the
other one too.
Hûn li kêşê tirkê, ber çoyê darê gê xwa bîn.
You were at the Turkish struggle, under the stick of the
wood...
Gêyê malê, ê... teter bî.
The threshing floor of the house, uh... it was Tatar.
Oxa bîn.
They were Aghas.
Zemana Axa bî berê?
Was it the time of the Agha before?
E, zemana Axa bî.
Yes, it was the time of the Agha.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Dewir, ê Axa bî.
The era, was the Agha's.
Digote paz, yoz mîş dikirin.
He said the sheep, in the summer they milked them.
Her hewteha, bono, yo mîş dikir.
Every week, implies, he milked them.
Serî bide, wereq nîvêk didan.
Per head, they gave one and a half notes (money).
Li serê dewar ki wereq nîv kî?
Per head of cattle/threshing animal, one and a half notes?
Were, serê dewar, wereq nîv kî.
Yes, per head of cattle, one and a half notes.
Hukmet tîne, xolo, yanî mebet.
Was it the government taking it, uncle, meaning the purpose.
Na meşê.
No, the boss (Agha).
Xweş e, elêkî, wej mîş ki na, çêlo, rehet orê, foporê, ma
dida heqî rêke?
Well, regarding that, did he not milk/tax the cows, the
comfortable ones, the poor ones, did he give the right of
way?
Heqî esil, sole didan. Ma dida.
The original right/tax, they gave annually. He gave it.
Heqî, em bibên, rez daro xolo?
The tax, let's say, on the vineyards, uncle?
Digo rez, meselen, î pez jî waj mîş dikirin.
He said the vineyard, for example, even the sheep they
taxed/milked.
Deh bizin te hebana, quçanek didate.
If you had ten goats, he gave you a receipt.
Bota deh, bota heneke, dew yek man, dew didan, noko konekî
quçanek didan.
For ten, for some... gave ten, they gave ten, essentially
giving a receipt for a tent/family.
Îca deh jê dan e.
So, ten were given from it.
Dew didime, ya mîş kirine, hewa zêde dikir, sê wereq didan.
I gave ten, what was taxed, then he increased it, giving
three notes.
Ee.
I see.
Sole.
Annually.
Lê, ew dibêjinê.
But, they call it...
Ra ye, quçan kî hebî.
It's true, there was a receipt.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Em bibên xolo wekî çi, wekî ruxsetî mokinî noko.
Let's say uncle, like what, like a vehicle license now.
E we.
Yes, that.
Eyn wane.
Exactly like that.
Berê wane bî.
It was like that before.
Erê.
Yes.
Fîl.
Elephant (Wait/Actually).
Ew, wereq bîstê sêrê de xistine.
That, they imposed twenty notes on the head.
Serê çêlê?
On the head of a cow?
Çêlê.
Of a cow.
Didan.
They paid.
Sole.
Annually.
Yozmekî, we çêlê didan.
A fee, they paid for that cow.
Xolo li gund digeriyan, lê çi, gund bêle hebî?
Uncle, did they walk around the village, or what, did the
village have a guard?
Ee, tehsîldar dahat gund.
Yes, the tax collector came to the village.
Tehsîldar dahat gund, quç çi?
The tax collector came to the village, what receipts?
Rûdiniştin cem Muxtêr, û ban molo dikirin.
They sat with the Mukhtar, and called upon the houses.
Çend bizin te hene? Çend ga te hene?
How many goats do you have? How many oxen do you have?
Erê.
Yes.
Vî ya mîş dikir.
He taxed this one.
Sole, meselen pez.
Annually, for example, sheep.
Bîst dewar ser te hebana, bîst pênc dewar, na bîst pênc
dewar, quçanek da beliyê.
If you had twenty animals, twenty-five animals, no twenty-
five animals, he gave a receipt for the total.
Go seba, sed pênc ya mîş dikirin.
He said because, one hundred and five were taxed.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Çê wereq jê distandin.
They took notes/money from him for it.
Digo ta maxolîk bî.
He said it was a hassle/mess.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Daw demo çi, noko demek din e, dunya hedîs bî ye xolo.
That time is what, now it's another time, the world has
become modern, uncle.
E le?
Is that so?
Dunya rind bî ye, çîkî, em bibên, xola min noko gundê Qopê,
em bibên, berê, bava vî ketîna, bîr hebî?
The world has become good, somewhat, let's say, my uncle,
now in the village of Qopê, let's say, back then, did they
fall into... did it have a well?
Sernizîk, waderê tedî, wey binî tiron bise, digo did cer cer
têra dikirin, berê cer cer dikuton.
Near the top, around there, wait down there at the pump,
they said they used two jars/buckets, before they hit/filled
the jars.
Erê.
Yes.
He, û qatir dikirin e, bêder, yey tînan.
Yes, and they used mules, at the threshing floor, they
brought it.
Erê.
Yes.
Wê l'av veda xistin, ne bi çûn û me yî dît bîjî.
They put it in the water, not going... and we saw it too.
Çi xolo?
What uncle?
Îî, dikuton bidan qatirê.
Yes, they tapped/hit it for the mules.
Erê.
Yes.
Qatirê, cer cer, digotin cer cer, wer aweh bîn wekî.
The mules, jars jars, they said jars, they were like that
like...
Min nîvîsandin.
I wrote it down.
Wekî min.
Like me.
Nızra te ne be.
May your gaze not be (may you not be hexed).
Elmuhîm xolo.
Anyway, uncle.
E de.
Yes.
Cer cer pê dikuton.
They tapped/filled the jars with it.
O, hebî, digo derê bî.
Oh, there was, he said it was there.
U bo bîrê gelî.
And for the valley well.
Bîr... yanî em bibên li gund da çend bîr hebîn xolo?
Well... I mean, let's say, how many wells were there in the
village, uncle?
Di divîn.
There were two.
Bîra Pilingê li vira?
Piling well here?
Bava mi kir.
My father made it.
U bîra gelî.
And the valley well.
U dige.
And another.
Hecîk, o, afê Hecî ko çor bîr.
Hecîk, oh, Hecî's water... four wells.
Çor bîr.
Four wells.
Raj û berî tib raj û ginyê, heşt bîr têda bîn.
Up and below... up and the slope, there were eight wells in
it.
Digo tin bîra Elî Teybê keçê biro.
He said the well of Eli Teyb, oh daughter of the brother.
Hatine derê raj û binî rêkê.
They came out up and below the road.
Heşt bîr têda bîn.
There were eight wells in it.
Mela cûrê avê gotîn ê.
Mullah said distinct waters.
Hatto nîr, çêlî havîne av jê derdiketin.
Even until, forty days of summer water came out of it.
Yanî noko em bibên tîj mol, mela diçûy, avê xo jê bîrê tîna?
Meaning now let's say the whole house, Mullah went, brought
their water from the well?
Jê avê xo jî dikirin, pez jê av didan.
They did their water from it, they gave water to the sheep
from it.
Pez dewar av dida, e baxir den.
Gave water to sheep and cattle, oh bless you.
Bîra Elî Teybê.
Eli Teyb's well.
U bîra Sînê.
And Sine's well.
Deştî bolo, yek, yek, ana dare, digo Elî Teybê, bîna Elî
Teybê, ana, ana dare.
The upper plain, one, one, there it is, he said Eli Teyb,
Eli Teyb's well, there, there it is.
U yek jî li ê geçê navê destê nodan.
And one at the pass, didn't give a hand/help.
Digo tin bîra Sînê.
He said Sine's well.
Xolo li kinc, min, em bibên kinc li ser bîrê dişuştin?
Uncle, clothes, I, let's say, did they wash clothes at the
well?
Lê av tînan mal?
Or did they bring water home?
Elê, mesela digotin kutx xeya bî.
Well, for example they said the bucket fell in/was lost.
Diçûn kutxê.
They went for the bucket.
Keher, o, tîştî xwa, l'keherê dikirin.
Leather bag, oh, their thing, they put it in the leather
bag.
Diçûn kutxê.
They went for the bucket.
Pincî xwa dişûştin, evî xwa dişûştin, u teq l'keherê xwa
dikirin tînan.
They washed their herbs/vegetables, washed their this, and
filled their leather bag and brought it.
Kutxê, berê pir bîn.
The buckets, there used to be many.
Erê, eynen heta wextkî ji mabe.
Yes, exactly, until a certain time remains.
Digo tin bîra dîşko, hetto nîr, debdebî mehê, b'avê, bînî
dehrikî.
He said Dishko's well, until the yoke/limit, the drum of the
month, with water, brings to the surface.
Pa şerencî şabê tedîye, nav jêçî na da, av xul xul xul xul
xul derdiket derkî.
Then the waterwheel of Shabe is there, didn't give a
name/place, water gurgled gurgled gurgled coming out
somewhere.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Bas noko nemaye, qurban xwedê bim.
But now it's gone, I am a sacrifice to God.
Dahîşik bîne.
They were springs.
Erê, noko barxwa berda, noko şarincî, me meselen, gehişk
bîn.
Yes, now gave its load, now the waterwheel, for us for
example, they were springs.
Noko her maleke şarincî xwa heye.
Now every house has its own waterwheel/tank.
Lê bes xolo.
Yes.
But enough, uncle.
Her malik, şarincî xwa heye.
Every house has its own waterwheel/tank.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Wele xolo, wekî em zanin, berê cefo bî.
By God uncle, as we know, before it was hardship.
Karê wa dikir, noko mar... yanî mara firo neke, em nikin
bikin vî karî.
You did that work, now sna... meaning don't sell/blame us,
we cannot do this work.
Ne wane?
Isn't it so?
Çunkî, berêj noko rintir bî.
Because, before was better than now.
Sehî, em bibên dil paqij bî.
Correct, let's say the heart was clean.
Ya jî ew e da.
Or it is that.
Ya jî ehlaq da. Ehlaq mezin da.
Or it was morals. Morals were great.
Noko malikê.
Now a household.
Digotin vê çêlî, ho avîne, derê zê tê, de xwa.
They said this cow, well it's water, comes to the door, eat.
Her malikê, kulk de birjê ra, digo guneye.
Every house, poured a pot for it, said it's a sin.
Yanî cîranê xwa ra horê dikir?
Meaning they looked after their neighbor?
Lê de horê dikir.
Yes, looked after.
Ne minêrê xo cîranê xwa.
Not looking at themselves, [but] their neighbor.
Na cîranê xwa, ne ferq e.
No, their neighbor, no difference.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Yekî, jina xwa tîne bana, ji xwedê par tirs de xwar, mêr de
danê, digo tina ye vî.
Someone, brought his wife to the roof, ate a share from
God/fear, gave to the husband, said this is not his.
Tirê.
Grapes.
Raz.
Vineyard.
Îî kî tina bo, j'vî par tirs de xwar.
Yes, whoever didn't have, ate from this fear/share.
Digo, da gunaye qîtkî bî, wer ber devî bî, binerin, ber devî
bî, binerin.
Said, give, it was a sin, a tiny bit, gave to the mouth,
look, gave to the mouth, look.
U, meselen, qurban.
And, for example, sacrifice.
E.
Yes.
Îî hebî, wexa qurbanê heşt waraq bî, go ji xwa din, para
tina bî.
Yes there was, when the sacrifice was eight notes, said give
from yourself, share to the have-nots.
Îî tina bî.
The one who didn't have.
Îî tina bî, jî yî de par tirs de xwar.
The one who didn't have, ate a share from the other.
Digotin, me tin, yek, bira hebî, pîrek minî me.
They said, we don't have, one, had a brother, an old woman
of ours.
Digo, di teşti şîvê ne.
Said, send two trays of dinner.
Ru biştî te vayê, qurban nekirî.
Your face is roasted/sunburnt, didn't sacrifice.
Te ji birjê ro, wî ji birjê ro, wî ji birjê ro.
You pour for him, he pours for him, he pours for him.
Ji wî par tirs de xwar.
He ate a share/fear from him.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Qurbanê dikirin, ji wî par tirs de xwar, mîş, rez, tirê,
dimis.
They made sacrifices, ate a share from him, sheep/milk,
vineyard, grapes, molasses.
Dimis dekelandin.
They boiled molasses.
Dimşî xa dibir.
Took his own molasses.
Ta pale biçin o, ganim dibir.
Until the laborers went, took wheat.
Ta gariz biçin o, gariz dibir.
Until they went for corn/millet, took corn/millet.
Para tina bî.
A share for the have-not.
Qabala dikirin.
They made a contract/agreement.
Wa qabala bi çi xoşî ye.
That contract was with such joy.
Gab dişemilond, sê şemlo, du filonî, du filonî, berê
muhedder bî.
Measured the wheat, three measures, two such, two such, it
was previously determined.
Ganim dibir.
Took wheat.
Erê.
Yes.
Para tina bî.
A share for the have-not.
Tin bî xolo, em bibên.
There wasn't any uncle, let's say.
Berê ji noko rintir bî, em bibên merleqe hebî.
Before was better than now, let's say there was a
ladle/spoon (sustenance).
Te zanî xêr pir bî.
You know, charity/blessing was abundant.
Xêr pir bî, ne ke wadaî, em bibên mo kîno, teyaro filon, na.
Charity was abundant, not that situation, let's say like
now, airplanes so and so, no.
Berê, çi rind bî, merleqe yek.
Before, what was good, one ladle/spoon.
Cîran, li cîranê xwa da pirsî.
Neighbor, asked after their neighbor.
Brok, li brokê xwa da pirsî.
Brother, asked after his brother.
Elî.
Isn't it so?
Indeed.
Î noko ev tişta çikê kêm bî ye li nav me da.
Now these things have become a bit scarce among us.
Xêra her kes li xwa heyriye, yek.
Everyone is amazed/worried about their own good, one.
Dunya hedîs bî ye, bes çikê merleqe kêm bî ye.
The world has become modern, but the ladle
(sustenance/sharing) has become scarce.
Xwedê pir bike, û xwedê zêde bike înşallah.
May God increase it, and may God make it abundant, God
willing.
Efwan.
Excuse me.
Li ser hesobî eşîreta.
On the account of the tribes.
Gundî Dêvrîş.
The village of Devrish.
Tak merîk bîş.
Just one man.
Î din malê Omer tak merîk bî.
The other, the house of Omar, was just one man.
Her yekî lopikê xwa hebî.
Everyone had their own bite/portion.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Her yekî lopikê.
Everyone's portion.
Noko her yek bî, hewlok.
Now everyone has become... a crowd.
Pir bî ye.
It has become many.
Jî.
Also.
Berê jî xolo, em bibên, şorê bavkê şor bî.
Before too uncle, let's say, whose father's soup was salty
(who was tough/respected).
Horo, wekî terabîkêş da bûn.
Isn't it so?
Look, like they were weight-pullers (influential).
E, bîr in. Kerem ke.
Yes, they are wells/memories. Please (continue).
Tikê, tê virminde.
Single/One, come here to me.
Bavikê, qewl da te.
The father, gave you a word/promise.
Bo tewrî, ekem te dim.
For the seed/manner, I will give you the first.
Na be kes xwa mîşî veke.
Let no one open their mouth/interfere.
Şor şor bî.
The word was the word (salty/solid).
The word was the word.
Rast e.
That’s right.
Yekî bi tê ne.
One came alone.
Na bê, bibê xêra kê vî te dî bî ye.
Don't say, say whose charity saw this.
De noko ti nevirî şor kê bikî, berî te xêra me bî di nîv.
Now you don't dare speak a word, before you, our charity was
in the middle.
Emê xêra nola bikin.
We will do charity like that.
Rast e.
That’s right.
De xwedê merleqê pir bike înşallah.
May God increase the ladle (sustenance) God willing.
Ê weş.
Yes well.
Xwedê hez bike nola berê lê bî.
May God love/will it to be like before.
Heskirin tenê be, nola berê pî.
Yes.
May there only be love, like it was before.
Pîr û kal pîr û kal.
Old women and old men, old women and old men.
Rast e.
That’s right.
De xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te.
May God give you a long life.
Ee, xwedê rehmê li dê û bavê te bike.
Yes, may God have mercy on your mother and father.
Xwedê te bihêle bo me.
May God keep you for us.
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God keep you.
Gelî bînera.
Dear viewers.
Heta xelekek din, û bernameyek din.
Until another episode, and another program.
Emê li gel xolo xatira xwe ji we bixwazin.
Together with uncle, we will say goodbye to you.
Hûn bi xwedê bin, û xwedê li gel we bit.
Be with God, and may God be with you.
Keremkin temaşê klîpê bin.
Please enjoy watching the clip.
(Music playing)
Giryan êş e, hemî êş e.
Crying is pain, it is all pain.
Min tiv dî çû, xûn az da ra.
I saw the sun set, blood gave to...
Evîna te berda bû din.
Your love was released to the world.
Jêre ne kirtin çara.
They didn't find a solution for it.
Axatî zîr û je û here.
Lordship/Agha-rule goes under and goes.
Deşt û mirin te cinnet in.
Plain and death are your paradise.
Ava te paqij û kewser e.
Your water is pure and like Kawthar (heavenly river).
Her bosti bin axû...
Every span under the soil...
Axîna min
My grief
Evîna min
My love
Can û êşa vî dilî
The soul and pain of this heart
Te ji bîr nakim
I won't forget you
Tu şîrîn î
You are sweet
Hem derman û hem kul î
You are both the cure and the wound
Ax, hem derman û hem kul î
Oh, you are both the cure and the wound
[Mûzîk]
[Music]