Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Bi şewqa wejhê nûranî, şemsa edaletê danî.
With the light of his luminous face, he established the sun
of justice.
Maşallah ji navê Subhanî, Muhammed gula dunyayê.
Mashallah to the name of the Subhan (God), Muhammad is the
rose of the world.
Maşallah ji navê Subhanî, Muhammed gula dunyayê.
Mashallah to the name of the Subhan (God), Muhammad is the
rose of the world.
Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Yibo xwedawî can hilan, te'b û êş û ezyet kişan.
For the sake of the Divine he gave his soul, he endured
fatigue, pain, and torment.
Ashabê xwe li hevb ciban, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
He gathered his companions together, Muhammad has come to
the world.
Ashabê xwe li hevb ciban, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
He gathered his companions together, Muhammad has come to
the world.
Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Ilahî alem çi hal... [Lyrics fade into background noise]
Oh God, the world is in such a state... [Lyrics fade into
background noise]
Erê cimet, noka me mirîşk birin, teben me ye sefer e.
Yes community, now we have taken the chickens, of course, we
are on a trip.
Ev jî xwestekî ji bo jorê Tirkiyê, bîmarê tewasol bî.
This is a request from upper Turkey, a sick person contacted
[us].
Go wunê du mirîşka bibin ser tirbî Şêx Reşîd.
They said, "You will take two chickens to the grave of
Sheikh Rashid."
Wunê jarjî kin, Xudê qebîl ke.
"You will sacrifice them, may God accept it."
Dê noka em ken ser mezerê Şêx Reşîd dê Badîna.
So now we are heading to the shrine of Sheikh Rashid of
Badina.
Meşhûr e, gellek nas dikin. Xelkê alem tê ye mezerê.
It is famous, many know it. People from all over come to the
shrine.
Noka emê ji wara mezerê teswîr ke.
Now we will film the shrine for you.
Emê çîkê ser heyata Şêx Reşîd jî deyn kin, ka bimarê bin.
We will put a little bit about the life of Sheikh Rashid,
who he was.
Dê ev jî nav gund e, gundê Badîna.
And this is inside the village, Badina village.
Dinê jî pirr germ e Semîr.
The world [weather] is also very hot, Samir.
Erê weleh.
Yes, by God.
Dinê dikele hereret bîst... çil de dî ye.
The world is boiling, the temperature has hit twenty...
forty.
Yanî îson derava tine, bawer ke.
I mean, a person can't go out, believe me.
Gul berma rehana.
[Idiom: Flowers and basil have wilted] Meaning: It is
scorching hot.
Pirr germ e.
It is very hot.
Bes ez tibo maqal xro kirî ye, hema ber vê germê derketim.
I just prepared myself for the barbecue, I just went out in
this heat.
Bes hem ber vê germê derketine.
We just went out in this heat.
Dê me mirîşk kireyî, mirîşkî me çêkirin para.
So we bought the chickens, we prepared the chickens back
there.
Inşalla heta em dighên nefesim berra.
God willing, by the time we arrive, they won't expire [die
from heat].
Wa gundê Badîna ye. Slav û rêz ji miletê gundê Badîna ra,
tek tek, yek yek.
This is Badina village. Greetings and respect to the people
of Badina village, one by one, each and every one.
Ciyê rêz û hurmetê ne.
They are worthy of respect and honor.
Were xûşkê neşwiti.
Come [sister], don't get burned.
Noka em keherin ser tirba, mezerê Şêx Reşîd li wir e.
Now we are arriving at the tomb, Sheikh Rashid's shrine is
there.
Gerek qobî vekirî be, emê çîkî ji wara teswîr kin.
The dome should be open, we will film a bit for you.
Wa emê mirîşka jarjî kin, Xudê qebîl ke.
And we will sacrifice the chickens, may God accept it.
Ê niyet kirî, Xudê mirazê dilê gî gundî bike, Xudê mehfeze
ke.
The one who made the intention, may God fulfill the wish of
everyone in the village, may God protect them.
Xudê ji xişim û bela, bixebitîne inşalla, Xudê qebîlkar be.
May God keep them away from anger and trouble, God willing,
may God be the Accepter.
Slav û rêzê me ji te ra û ji aîla giştî ra.
Our greetings and respect to you and to the whole family.
Ciyê rêz û hurmetê ne.
You are worthy of respect and honor.
Dê noka me nêzîkî ser tirba kir, tirbê Badîna.
So now we have gotten near the tomb, the tomb of Badina.
Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Dunya kirye nûr û şewqa, hatiye rehmet li xelqa.
He made the world light and radiance, mercy has come to the
people.
Bela kirye keyf û eşqa, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
He spread joy and love, Muhammad has come to the world.
Slav û rêz cimetê şîrîn, inşalla hûn kêf xweş û rihet bin.
Greetings and respect sweet community, God willing you are
happy and comfortable.
Em liron li gundê Badîna ne, li mezerê Şêx Reşîd.
We are here in Badina village, at Sheikh Rashid's shrine.
Teben me mirîşk îna...
Of course, we brought chickens...
Bîmarê tewasol bîn bo jorê Tirkiyê, go wunê du mirîşka jarjî
kin.
A sick person contacted [us] from upper Turkey, they said
"You will sacrifice two chickens."
Li ber mezerê Şêx Reşîd, Xudê qebîl ke.
At Sheikh Rashid's shrine, may God accept it.
Xudê mirazê dil bike.
May God fulfill the heart's wish.
Dê dinê pirr germ e cimet, wekî hûn zanin, qayîl ayî noka
jî.
So the world [weather] is very hot community, as you know,
[it's boiling] right now too.
Xudê qebîl ke û ya Bismillah rəhman rəhim.
May God accept it and oh In the name of God, the Most
Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Ya Rabbî ke rehmê carek, ji mer bike nesîb carek.
Oh Lord, have mercy once, grant us a portion once.
Dîtina rewda mubarek, li cem te ya Resûlullah.
Seeing the blessed Garden (Rawda), beside you oh Messenger
of God.
Dîtina rewda mubarek, li cem te ya Resûlullah.
Seeing the blessed Garden (Rawda), beside you oh Messenger
of God.
Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan... [Fade out]
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts... [Fade out]
Eset, awa vîn e ka.
Asad, film this here.
Destê nede, nengê nekê xûn bî ha.
Don't touch it, don't get blood on yourself.
Eset?
Asad?
Ew vîn e ka.
Film that right there.
Na germ e.
No, it is hot.
Hûn nînin ber kef, wextim paşê pê de, ser çavê şû.
You aren't [seeing] the foam, I stepped on it later,
splashed on my face.
Ez zormiyam berê çavê xwe nabînim.
I am straining, I can't see in front of my eyes.
Eke bira çêkim, wele nawêrim çêkim.
[If I fix it brother], by God I don't dare to fix it.
Germ e cimet, pirr germ e, bu şeref hereret 40 de dî ye. Eke
pirro çêkim...
It is hot community, very hot, upon my honor the temperature
has hit 40. If I fix the feathers...
Wele naverim çêkim.
By God, I don't dare to fix it.
Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Bismillah rəhman rəhim.
In the name of God, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful.
Ev jî mezerê Şêx Reşîd e.
This is Sheikh Rashid's shrine.
Ya Bismillah.
Oh Bismillah.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Bismillah, Maşallah.
Bismillah, Mashallah.
Şêx Reşîdê Badîna.
Sheikh Rashid of Badina.
Gundê Badîna wekî we dî ye.
Badina village, as you have seen.
Sar e, gelek sar e.
It is cool, very cool [inside the cave].
Kaniya avê jê tê, ava kaniyê ye.
A spring of water comes from it, it is spring water.
Bismillah rəhman rəhim, Bismillah.
In the name of God, the Most Gracious, the Most Merciful,
Bismillah.
Bismillah, Maşallah.
Bismillah, Mashallah.
Xudê rehmê xwe lêke, û lmiriyê me giya ke ya Reb.
May God have mercy on him, and on all our dead, Oh Lord.
Ya Bismillah.
Oh Bismillah.
Teben evir jî sing û ko dike tin.
Of course, here too it makes the chest and cough [better] /
[Or: people make vows here].
Ev jî mezerê Şêx Reşîd e.
This is Sheikh Rashid's shrine.
Şêx Reşîdê Badîna.
Sheikh Rashid of Badina.
Xudê rehmê xwe lmiriyê wî cîhê xwe cenet bî, inşalla.
May God have mercy on his dead, may his place be paradise,
God willing.
Û lmiriyê me giya ke, inşalla.
And on all our dead, God willing.
Her kesê vê vîdyoyê dibîne.
Everyone who sees this video.
Xudê rehmê xwo lmiriyê giya ke inşalla.
May God have mercy on everyone's dead, God willing.
Mezer qobî vekirî ye, xelk tê...
The shrine dome is open, people come...
Tê ji gundat tê.
They come from the villages.
Şams edaletê danî.
He established the sun of justice.
Maşallah ji navê Subhanî, Muhammed gula dunyayê.
Mashallah to the name of the Subhan (God), Muhammad is the
rose of the world.
Maşallah ji navê Subhanî, Muhammed gula dunyayê.
Mashallah to the name of the Subhan (God), Muhammad is the
rose of the world.
Şewqa dilan, baxçê gulan, bêhna xweş daye her deran.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, has spread sweet scent
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Rabin tebda, şakin dilan, Muhammed hatiye dunyayê.
Rise up in devotion, joy of hearts, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Erê cimet wekî we dî ye, mezerê Şêx Reşîdê Badîna eve hewe.
Yes community as you have seen, this is the shrine of Sheikh
Rashid of Badina right here.
Lê navê wî yê esil Reşîd Hebeş e, ji gundê Badîna ye.
But his original name is Rashid Habash, he is from Badina
village.
Bi leqeb vira dibên Şêx Reşîdê Badîna.
By nickname, they call him Sheikh Rashid of Badina here.
Rehmetî hezar û heş sed û nod û du (1892) hatîye dunyayê.
The deceased came to the world in 1892.
Hezar û neh sed û sî (1930)...
1930...
Pisîk hebû, pisîka reş.
There was a cat, a black cat.
Wana şîd û... du'a û... zikir dikirin.
They were reciting poems and... prayers and... doing dhikr.
Dibê roke hinda bî, pişî çêrî fîtilî.
It is said one day it was around there, the cat spun around
him.
Ewa taba'an hewal didin, ji xelkê dî ye yanê.
Of course, friends narrate this, from other people, you
know.
Dibê pişî çêrî fîtilî, gotî: "Tilkê be Şêx Reşîd".
It is said after it spun around him, he said: "Be a fox,
Sheikh Rashid".
Gotî: "El bin erd bî, ma zikir dikir, ma Qur'an dixwend û
nivîsandin dikir".
He said: "The one under the ground [the Sheikh], used to do
dhikr, read the Quran and write".
Û ma'na xwendina wî tune bî, ne çûbû mektebê.
And there was no meaning of his education [he was
illiterate], he hadn't gone to school.
Yanê hewa mo'jîzek ji Cindî ye, wekî me zanin.
Meaning this is a miracle of the Noble One, as we know.
Û ne çûbû mektebê lê, dibê me nivîsandin dikir.
And he hadn't gone to school but, it is said he was writing.
Çêrî... xeybî... tek ra fîtilî.
Around... the unseen... suddenly turned.
Mulk wa bin erd bî, ma zikir dikir, ma bang Xwedê dikir,
derd dikir.
His realm was under the ground, he used to do dhikr, call
upon God, and express pain.
Milet dibê, ji roçkê Cindê nûr derdiket.
People say, light used to come out of the window of the
Noble One.
Û kani Cindê tim hazir bî vêra.
And the spring of the Noble One was always ready there.
Dibê mesefe dûr qut dikirin.
It is said they used to cut long distances short.
Yanê mesefe dirêj, bi zeman besîd cîdden, sewanî.
Meaning long distance, in a very simple time, seconds.
Misir û l'vir... noka, deqaqekî din li Efrînê, xelkê didî
yanê.
Egypt and here... now, a minute later in Afrin, people saw
him, you know.
Basît salan bibin... pir diketin îla Efrîn, da hatine îsbat.
Though years were simple... they often went to Afrin, so it
was proven.
Dibê roke çû cem jinkekê, runiştî.
It is said one day he went to a woman, sat down.
Jinkê jî şîvê dikê. Çi dikê? Şorbê nîskê dikê.
The woman is making dinner. What is she making? She is
making lentil soup.
Dibê mêrê jinkê jî li Hecê ye.
It is said the woman's husband is at Hajj.
Gotî mêrkê me heba, vê şorbê hez dikir.
She said if my husband were here, he loved this soup.
Şêx Reşîd gotî: "Têk zerke kê".
Sheikh Rashid said: "Pour it into a bowl".
Tamam. Gotî têk zerke jî, kire zerke wela, dibê çû ye.
Okay. She said pour into a bowl too, she put it in a bowl
indeed, it is said it went.
Mêr ji hecê fitiliye, jinkê xora gotî, çî kelfetiya xora
gotî.
The husband returned from Hajj, told his wife, told his
family.
Saet ew û wext, şorbe pir xweş derketî.
At that hour and time, the soup arrived very delicious.
Yanê seke, mo'jîzê Cindê pir ne.
So look, the miracles of the Noble One are many.
Xwedê rehmê xwo lêkê, cîyê xwo cenet bê.
May God have mercy on him, may his place be paradise.
Ev jî mezerê... milet ji gundo tê viderkê.
This is the shrine... people from villages come here.
Îhay nêt kirî, mirîşka jerj dikê, singek xwo dikutê.
Whoever made a vow, slaughters chickens, beats his chest [in
devotion].
Yanê mezereke, mo'jîzetî Şêx Reşîd taba'an pir ne.
Meaning it's a shrine, Sheikh Rashid's miracles are of
course many.
Metel wesser we hewal da.
Stories about him were told to you.
Lê, hezar nehsed nod pêncî wefat kir.
But, he passed away in 1950.
Xwedê rehmê xwo lêkê, meqamê Cindê heye, li gundê Ba'dîno,
nav Turba.
May God have mercy on him, the Noble One has a maqam, in
Baadina village, named Turba.
Kî divê herê, ew nobe.
Whoever wants to go, that is the opportunity.
Ew jî xwestekiye, cim'at ne terkê bî.
That is also a wish, that the congregation is not abandoned.
Silav û rêzê me ji we ra, em dibên gom a nav mekin, me go
ehlen we sehlen.
Our greetings and respect to you, we say don't make a fuss
among us, we said welcome.
Gune... mirîşka jerj kin, nêt kiribî, Xwedê qebûl kê.
Whoever... wants to slaughter chickens, if they made a vow,
may God accept it.
Ev me wa jî, hesefer e wekî me gotî.
This of ours too, is a journey as we said.
Saeta we xweş, bimînin bi dinyayê hejar, bi dinyayê xweş, bi
xatirê we.
Have a good time, remain in a humble world, in a happy
world, goodbye.
Şewqa dilan, o can, hilan, te'bû û êş û eziyet kişand.
The light of hearts, oh soul, rose up, he suffered fatigue
and pain and torment.
Ashabê xwa li heb civand, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
He gathered his companions around him, Muhammad has come to
the world.
Ashabê xwa li heb civand, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
He gathered his companions around him, Muhammad has come to
the world.
Şewqa dila, baxçê gula, bi hinek xweş da yê her dera.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, with some joy he gave to
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şa kin dila, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
Stand up all together, make hearts happy, Muhammad has come
to the world.
Rabin tebda, şa kin dila, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
Stand up all together, make hearts happy, Muhammad has come
to the world.
Îlahê alem ji hez kir, nebî û dilber, dila xweş kir.
The God of the universe loved him, the prophet and beloved,
made hearts happy.
Bi dîn û wî wer bilhez kin, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
With his religion, come love him, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Bi dîn û wî wer bilhez kin, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
With his religion, come love him, Muhammad has come to the
world.
Şewqa dila, baxçê gula, bi hinek xweş da yê her dera.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, with some joy he gave to
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şa kin dila, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
Stand up all together, make hearts happy, Muhammad has come
to the world.
Rabin tebda, şa kin dila, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
Stand up all together, make hearts happy, Muhammad has come
to the world.
Dinya kirye nûr û şewqe, hatî ye rehmê l'xelqê.
He made the world light and radiance, mercy has come to the
people.
Bela kirye kêf û eşqê, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
He spread joy and love, Muhammad has come to the world.
Şewqa dila, baxçê gula, bi hinek xweş da yê her dera.
Light of hearts, garden of roses, with some joy he gave to
everywhere.
Rabin tebda, şa kin dila, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
Stand up all together, make hearts happy, Muhammad has come
to the world.
Rabin tebda, şa kin dila, Muhammed hatî dinyayê.
Stand up all together, make hearts happy, Muhammad has come
to the world.
Ya Reb bike rehmê carek, ji mer bike nesîb carek.
Oh Lord, have mercy once, make it our destiny once.
Dîtina rewda mubarek, l'er da Resûlallah'î.
Seeing the blessed Rawdah, on the earth is the Messenger of
Allah.
Dîtina rewda mubarek, l'er da Resûlallah'î.
Seeing the blessed Rawdah, on the earth is the Messenger of
Allah.
Şewqa dila, baxçê gula, bi hinek xweş...
Light of hearts, garden of roses, with some joy...