Rûyê me... xweş biskirin meke vê.
Make our faces... pleasant, do not do this [badly].
Em... em kêfxweş bûn.
We... we were happy.
Xweş bin, xweş bin û xweş bin.
Be happy, be happy and be happy.
Eyn Hacere jî... ji zineyr dihat.
And Eyn Hacere... came from the cliff.
Ereb jêl re bûn teb'en.
Arabs were from there of course.
Go her avê kaniyê wara.
He said just the water of the spring there.
Rast e.
It is true.
Lo kes li dora me namayî.
Oh, no one is left around us.
Xwedê heye.
God exists.
Şeş qîçik heban, yek tenê bê, qîz tenê bin...
If there were six children, let there be only one, let them
be only daughters...
Yeke hana çûbû be...
One like that had gone...
Kuro xalî min maşallah emrê heştê sal e.
Boy, my uncle, mashallah, his age is eighty years.
Emrê xwe heştê sal e, traktorê doj û derec û to.
His age is eighty years, [like] a Deutz tractor and gears
and...
Ser te taxweş xalî, serxweş.
Health to you uncle, health.
Dibên cefaf.
They say drought.
Cefaf e, he sal cefaf e.
It is drought, this year is drought.
Bîdar derneket?
Did the crops not come up?
Ne hişk bî, baran jî neketin ne?
Was it not dry, rain didn't fall right?
No no no no. Çêleh hişk bûn çû.
No no no no. The pastures dried up and went.
Walla maşalla hewşê van hene ke.
Wow mashallah look at their courtyard.
Bilindiyê durçirme vakirye.
He opened the height of the wrinkle [unclear].
Nexweş, zindave...
Sick, alive...
Kanî ka kuro... kîkê vira têda.
Where is the spring boy... who is in here.
Jibona... vê ardê.
Because of... this ground.
Xweliya...
Soil of...
Rûçikê genda.
The face of the village.
Ez xwesteka neyî me... em ji giyan razî ne.
I am not demanding... we are pleased with everyone.
Serê te giya xweş be.
May all your heads be well.
Û inşallah welat rind bibe û gî bi fitilin warên malên xwe.
And God willing the country will be good and all will return
to their homes.
Na...
No...
Merheba hevalno.
Hello friends.
Dîsa em bi we ra ne û vîdyokî xweş kîbar.
We are with you again with a nice beautiful video.
Em kê hatin? Eyn Hacere, teswîr kin.
Where did we come? Eyn Hacere, to film.
Tabaan ev jî ser telebê muşahîdîna ye.
Of course this is upon the request of the viewers.
Biraykî me Ebû Cemal, û kesê din li me seyr dikin, ez çavê
we maç dikim.
Our brother Abu Jamal, and others who are watching us, I
kiss your eyes.
Bîr nekin, me ra... layk û iştîrak rûpelê me kin.
Don't forget, for us... like and subscribe to our page.
Û hûn jî hemen werin Eyn Hacere.
And you all come to Eyn Hacere immediately.
Bimera bin hetan em bigihîjin nava Eyn Hacere.
Stay with us until we reach inside Eyn Hacere.
Em Xezal, te dibê çi?
Em Ghazal, what do you say?
Subê we bixêr be hevalê me, renc û nîşîva çûye.
Good morning our friend, toil and hardship is gone.
Sihet çûye, şolê me germ û rehet nin.
Health is gone, our work is hot and not comfortable.
Erê îro em kê werin herin gundê ki hejar.
Yes today we will go to a poor village.
Gundê me îro jî Eyn Hacere ye.
Our village today is Eyn Hacere.
Em kê îro herin wara Eyn Hacere bisewirînin.
We will go there today to film Eyn Hacere.
Û bimera bin, em herin derbaz bin gundê Eyn Hacere.
And stay with us, let's go enter the village of Eyn Hacere.
Arê tabaan hevalno, Eyn Hacere mezin jî em kê bisewrînin û
Eyn Hacere cûcik jî.
Yes of course friends, we will film Eyn Hacere the big and
Eyn Hacere the small too.
Yanî her du Eyn Hacera em kê biser hev daxin.
Meaning both Eyn Hacera we will cover together.
Bimera bin hetan em digihîjin Eyn Hacere.
Stay with us until we reach Eyn Hacere.
Emê paşê hev bibînin.
We will see each other later.
Arê hevalno, tabaan ev o em ketin duxûliya gund.
Yes friends, of course here we entered the entrance of the
village.
Maşalla ji vê gundî re, çi hewşê berdane ber deriyên xwe.
Mashallah to this village, what courtyards they have left in
front of their doors.
Arê hevalno, tabaan vê derê da jî... li gundê Eyn Hacere ew
heye... Delûb.
Yes friends, of course in this place too... in the village
of Eyn Hacere there is this... Delûb [stone roller].
Ev Delûbê jî emrê xwe pir kevnar e.
This Delûb is also very old in age.
Milletê vê gundî, gundî dûr e.
The people of this village, it is a far village.
Genimê xwe tînin li vê derkê, boş dikirin.
They bring their wheat to this place, empty it.
Tabaan vê derê jî dewar pê ve girê didan, dewarê qaba.
Of course here they tied cattle to it, large cattle.
Bi vir de xistin, wê dewarê jî tim di dora ra digerî.
They pushed it around, that cattle would constantly rotate
around.
Û genimê xwe jî tim têva didan binê.
And they would constantly stir their wheat underneath.
Binî kevir... kevir di ser da diçûye, hûr dikir.
Underneath is stone... the stone went over it, crushed it.
Paşê wê genimê jî tim bi legan an na ba dikirin.
Then that wheat they would winnow with basins or wind.
Manî wê... pirçikê wê genimê qalq ser ra biqeşre, ev
dikirin.
Meaning that... the husk of the wheat peel off, they did
this.
Hava jî emrê xwe kevnar e.
This is also old in age.
Divê ortê vê gundî da heye.
It says it is present in the middle of this village.
Maşalla tebîeta vir pir xweş e.
Mashallah the nature here is very nice.
Tabaan hevalî min vir da were, zake ev Eyn Hacere cûcik jî
li hember me ye tabaan ho.
Of course my friend come here, look this Eyn Hacere Small is
also opposite us of course look.
Emê noka herin Eyn Hacere cûcik.
We will go now to Eyn Hacere Small.
Maşalla oo binêre.
Mashallah oh look.
Gelek mentîqe ho ho ho, heta çav dibîne ferq dikin.
A very [great] region look look look, as far as the eye sees
they differ.
Coyê gundê şêx ho ho ho.
The stream of the Sheikh's village look look look.
Arê hevalno, emê noka gund gi teswîr kin û paşê ra jî emê
herin mala biraykî me, mala Ebû Cemal. Arê.
Yes friends, we will now film the whole village and
afterwards we will go to the house of our brother, the house
of Abu Jamal. Yes.
Arê hevalno, tabaan emî noka... li Eyn Hacere ne.
Yes friends, of course we are now... in Eyn Hacere.
Em kê xalî min Ebû Îmad...
We will [ask] my uncle Abu Imad...
Ebû Mihemed.
Abu Muhammad.
Ebû Mihemed, em kê du sê gotina ji wî bipirsin.
Abu Muhammad, we will ask him two or three words.
Paşê ra emê herin mala... meyrê xwe, emê mêvan darê herin.
Afterwards we will go to the house of... our host, we will
go as guests.
Xalô Eyn Hacere, ez kêm sual kêm te bipirsim.
Uncle Eyn Hacere, I will ask you a small question.
Bûyîn... Eyn Hacere xê nav lê kirin? Eyn Hacere mena xwe
çiye?
Being... Eyn Hacere why was it named so? What does Eyn
Hacere mean?
Eyn Hacere bixwe... kanîk... li ber avê bû.
Eyn Hacere itself... a spring... was by the water.
Û gund bixwe li jêr bû, ne li vir bû.
And the village itself was below, not here.
Kanî bixwe jî... çi zineyr dihat.
The spring itself... came from a rock.
Ewa?
Yes?
Ereb jêl dibêjin teben...
The Arabs call it, of course...
Go here ovê kaniyê wer e. Ovê... çi kaniyê... Kêvir.
He said go to this spring and come back. This... what
spring... The Rock [Spring].
Nav lê kirin Eyn el-Hacer.
They named it Eyn el-Hacer [Spring of the Stone].
Eyn el-Hacer. Êwa.
Eyn el-Hacer. Yes.
Berê kaniyê diçî kêvir dabû bî?
In the past, did the spring flow forcefully [hit the rock]?
Av xelk jê tîn, no? Wê manê... nav lê kirin Eyn el-Hacer.
People took water from it, right? That is the meaning...
they named it Eyn el-Hacer.
U bi xweş dibên kaniya tew...
And happily they call it the spring of...
Êwa.
Yes.
Tê gotin mîna... li vî derî... Gund li wir be.
It is said like... in this place... The village would be
over there.
Paşê... hatin vir?
Later... they came here?
Hatin virê.
They came here.
Jivir va dûr e ev kaniya?
Is this spring far from here?
Na, teqrîben... kîlometrek du kîlometre hene.
No, approximately... it's a kilometer or two kilometers.
Wele mecal me ro çêbî em kanîn xwe pê bigînin nê? Av hey
têda no?
By God, if we have the opportunity, we could reach it,
right? There is water in it, no?
No heye hindike.
No, there is a little.
U ê pir jî mîl hatis ser xitimandiye.
And mostly, silt has come over it and blocked it.
Êwa.
I see.
Teyb Xalo, sualek din. Gundî we... çiqas malbat e? Hewş?
Okay Uncle, another question. Your village... how many
families is it? Households?
Bi Xwedê sê çar ta yî fene.
By God, there are only three or four left.
Tabî îst...
Of course...
U bil eded jî gi meriya heftine.
And by number, everyone is about seventy [years old].
Êwa.
Yes.
Ji jinan da, ji mêran da gi bîna meriya hefta.
Among the women, among the men, everyone is like seventy
years old.
Yanî teqrîben, em heftê mal, şêst mal, heftê mal heye.
Meaning approximately, we have seventy households, sixty
households, seventy households.
Êwa. Xalo sekanê xwe hege heye yan xolî ye?
Yes. Uncle, does its terrain consist of rocks or soil?
Xolî ye, hen... tinene.
It is soil, there are... there are none [rocks].
Tinene. Ne henk li dervanin, henk li Heleb'nin, mişklek
nine.
None. No, some are outside [abroad], some are in Aleppo,
it's no problem.
Xalo, bi gundî Eyn Hacer'ê bi giştan malbatê tenoskirin,
malbatê têda me'rûf yane?
Uncle, regarding the Eyn Hacer village, everyone knows the
families, are there famous families in it?
Malbatê... Elxelyo.
The family of... Elxelyo.
Elxelyo?
E.
Yes.
Yan boyî malbatê... ewino berî giya hatin vî derî ne?
Meaning regarding the family... were they the ones who came
here before everyone else?
Berî giya... malê ewê hatin... Seydê Zêbo hatin.
Before everyone... the house of... Seydê Zêbo came.
Êwa.
Yes.
Tê gul mino? Paş... yanî teben hemgî pismamê hevdune.
Do you understand me? Then... meaning, of course, they are
all cousins to each other.
Xo.
Okay.
Ew nobed... berî giya hatin wir, paşê jî... kolet me hatin.
They... came there before everyone, and then... our side
came.
Te bi xweş vî gundî xalo?
Are you happy with this village, uncle?
E.
Yes.
Saeta te xweş. Bereket, emr çend e lê?
Bless you. A blessing, how old are you?
Pêncî ye.
Fifty.
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te. Maşallah.
May God give you a long life. Mashallah.
Xolîmê me'lûmatê rind zane ser vî gundî. Maşallah gundekî
bar e, mewqihê xweş rind e. Teben Efrîn jî li hember me ye.
Ew Efrîn gundê Hemzeyê Mado ye?
My uncle knows good information about this village.
Mashallah, it's a prominent village, its location is very
nice. Of course, Afrin is also opposite us. Is that Afrin,
the village of Hemzeyê Mado?
Bakî hênek li vî derê tê.
A breeze comes a little to this spot.
Saeta te xweş. Xalo, Xwedê Pêxember ji te razî be. Gotina te
hene? Te milet ra, te silava dişîne?
Bless you. Uncle, may God and the Prophet be pleased with
you. Do you have any words? To the nation, are you sending
greetings?
Silavê min ji miletê me Kurd ra teva heye.
My greetings are to our entire Kurdish nation.
Saeta te xweş. Silavê tey bigihîjin inşallah.
Bless you. Your greetings will reach them, God willing.
Mîd selamê, ehlen wesehlen.
A hundred greetings, welcome.
Sax be, ehlen wesehlen.
Be healthy, welcome.
Arê, arê. Wale bare. Xwenu... tabaan em noka cem xaltîkê ne.
Yes, yes. By God, wonderful. We are now... of course, we are
now with Auntie.
Arê.
Yes.
Xaltîk, maşallah bereke emr te go çend in?
Auntie, Mashallah, a blessing, how old did you say you are?
Heftê û yek, heftê û dodo.
Seventy-one, seventy-two-ish.
Maşallah, maşallah. Xwedê sihetek xweş bide te.
Mashallah, mashallah. May God give you good health.
Xwedê rehetîyê bide we jî.
May God give you comfort as well.
Xaltîk... me dîtî Xalo rûnişt vî sarsikê rûniştî.
Auntie... we saw Uncle sitting, sitting on this corner.
Ee.
Yeah.
Maşallah, migo ez herim cem xaltîkê silavke pê dim.
Mashallah, I said I would go to Auntie and give her a
greeting.
Ê, ehlen we sehlen.
Yes, welcome.
Xaltîk... berê rind bî, noka rind bî?
Auntie... was the past better, or is now better?
Wele berê rind bî.
By God, the past was better.
Berê pirr rind bî ne?
The past was much better, right?
Berê pirr rind bî. Em bi kêf bûn.
The past was much better. We were happy.
Noka ne rind e?
Now is not good?
Lo ne rind e lê. Gib hewa ye. Ew kes li dora me namayî. Şeş
qîçik hebin, yek tune be. Qîz tune bin. Ekê hino çûbû be.
It's not good, dear. It's all empty air. No one is left
around us. To have six children, and not one is here. No
daughters. As if they were just gone.
Xaltîk te tane?
Auntie, are you alone?
Ez û kulfetî min jî kalo.
Me and my spouse, the old man.
Êwa. Kalo hîn ji mi xerîbtir e.
Yes. The old man is even stranger [more wretched] than me.
Qîçik dûr te neman, gi çûne?
The kids didn't stay far from you, they all left?
Dûr mi şû, yekî li jêr e, yek jî, ê din jî li Tirkî ne.
They went far from me, one is down there [Germany?], and
one, the others are in Turkey.
De wekî dibê, inşallah, inşallah Xwedê wekî dibê destî we bi
hev bigîne inşallah.
Well as they say, God willing, God willing, as they say, may
God join your hands together, God willing.
Inşallah bi hev bigîne yûrum. Xwedê heye. Xwedê heye. Xwedê
heye.
God willing, he will join us, my child. God exists. God
exists. God exists.
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te.
May God give you a long life.
Xwedê destê giya bi hev bigîne.
May God join everyone's hands together.
Te silavê dişîne ji millet ra, Xaltîk? Tu dibê çi?
Are you sending greetings to the nation, Auntie? What do you
say?
Ez dibêjim çi? Bila bi silav bibin, bi qentara ji milet ra
hebin.
What do I say? Let there be greetings, let there be tons [of
greetings] for the nation.
Silavê tey bigihîne. Qurtx nikan, bibin silavê te da rabin.
Mashallah.
Your greetings will reach them. The youth, look, they are
standing up for your greeting.
Arê, arê, arê, arê.
Yes, yes, yes, yes.
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te. Xwedê sihetek xweş bide te.
May God give you a long life. May God give you good health.
Wele yûrum, Xwedê sihetek xweş ji we re bide.
By God, my child, may God give you good health too.
Lav silav ji miletê me gî ra hene.
Son, there are greetings to all of our nation.
Aman.
Please [Ensure it].
Çor parçe Kurdistanê.
The four parts of Kurdistan.
Arê.
Yes.
Arê, arê, arê.
No?
Yes, yes, yes.
Çor parçe Kurdistanê, silavê me ji wa ra.
The four parts of Kurdistan, our greetings to them.
Me ji me ji wa ra hene yûrum.
We... we have [greetings] for them, my child.
Xaltîk, ev xolîmê te ye, kulfetê te ye?
Auntie, is this your uncle [husband], your spouse?
Eva?
Yes, yes.
Is this him?
Lê me noko leqtekê te kinê.
Yes.
But we will take a shot of you now.
Ê te kinê.
Yes, take it.
Temam.
Okay.
Tê kinê, tê kinê yûrum, belkî em bimrin, li dewletê
derkevin.
Take it, take it my child, perhaps we will die, and appear
in the country/state [records/TV].
Xwedê neke, Xwedê neke. Xaltîk Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te.
God forbid, God forbid. Auntie, may God give you a long
life.
Reka me gî waha ye de, bes hîn zû ye inşallah.
But?
Our path is all like that [we all die], but it is still too
soon, God willing.
Wele halê me namayî, namayî.
By God, our condition is gone, gone.
Lê de merikê be çi?
But what about the man?
Hal nama, hal nama, em mirin.
No condition left, no condition left, we are dead.
Xwedê heye şukir.
It is God, it is God.
God exists, thanks.
Na, siheta te xweş e.
No, your health is good.
Lo wela kuştim, tima toqtarona.
Oh by God, it killed me, going to the doctors.
De Xwedê rehetîyê bide. Xaltîk gelek spas, Xwedê heyatê we.
Well may God give comfort. Auntie, thank you very much, God
[bless] your life.
Teşke derbas be, tehl tirş ke derbas be.
Let it pass pleasantly, let it pass bitterly or sourly.
[Life goes on].
Eke derbas be. Arê, arê, arê, arê, waye.
It will pass. Yes, yes, yes, yes, that's it.
Waye yûrum, waye, waye, waye.
That's it my child, that's it, that's it, that's it.
Xalo?
Uncle?
Tê bêjî qey dersa xwe rind nexwendiye ha.
Yes.
You'd say he hasn't studied his lesson well, huh.
Xolîmê jî, kulfeta xaltîka ya, ser serî me, ser çavê me st.
My uncle too, Auntie's spouse, upon our head, upon our eyes
[you are welcome].
Deste xwe nade ser rono bime eyb e.
Don't put your hand on your thigh/knee, it is shameful.
Ere lawo, maro ca fihaskê adî.
Oh man, snake... just relax, it's normal.
Arê, arê, arê, dêko qiciko ye, berka...
Yes, yes, yes, the mother of the kids, because...
şeş heft sal e... ewro bileyî banê rebbê buçukirî.
For six or seven years... today she is complaining to the
Lord Almighty.
Adî ye.
It is normal.
Çi? Arê Tirkiyê jî lê sêr kin e?
What? Yes, will Turkey also watch this?
Arê, hemû dinya dibîne.
Yes, the whole world sees it.
Tirkiyê jî?
Turkey too?
Xalo, te çi silavê dişîne ji milletê me Kurd ra?
Uncle, what greetings are you sending to our Kurdish nation?
Ez pirr... kêfxweş im... ji miletê me... Kurd ra.
I am very... happy... for our... Kurdish nation.
Efu ne... Kurd ra.
Excuse me... for the Kurds.
Êzîdî...
Yazidis...
Ewna ser serî me, ser çavê me... Xwedê û Pêxember jê razî
bin.
They are upon our heads, upon our eyes
[welcome/respected]... May God and the Prophet be pleased
with them.
Em gihîştin vê merheleyê, elhemdulelah.
We reached this stage, praise be to God.
Xwedê nefişa gindî yox, kêskîn bike.
May God make the breath of the village green/fertile.
[Unclear idiom, likely wishing prosperity].
Xwedê reka gindî yox, dogre bike inşallah.
May God straighten the path of the village, God willing.
Rûk... xaş bi serî me keve.
May a good day/face fall upon us.
Em... em kêfxweş bin.
Let us... let us be happy.
Inşallah.
God willing.
Xweş bin, xweş bin û xweş bin.
Be happy, be happy, and be happy.
Xwedê rehetîyê bigihîne we.
May God bring you comfort.
Xwedê rehetîyê bide we, giştika de.
May God give you comfort, to everyone.
Amîn, amîn.
Amen, amen.
Hebe.
Let it be.
Saeta we jî xweş.
Bless you too.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Milletê me cebar e xalo, milletê me Kurd bi dilbirrehmin jî.
Our nation is mighty, uncle, our Kurdish nation is also
compassionate.
Ê, bila bi ti tişt jî danke.
Yes, let them acknowledge [give voice] to everything.
Bi dengê we, dengê we.
With your voice, your voice.
Dengê we ji her derî re heye.
Your voice is everywhere.
Te kê me tirkî?
Okay.
Will you put us on Turkish [TV]?
Avolî min ko, me rabe? Hare.
My friend, where, shall we get up? Go on.
Maşallah ji xolû ra, maşallah.
Mashallah to the uncle, Mashallah.
Migo xolîmê maşallah, beraka emrê wî heştê sal e.
I said my uncle, Mashallah, the blessing of his age is
eighty years.
Emrê wî heştê sal e, direkto... da joy, darê joy to.
His age is eighty years, the tractor... he is driving, he
drives the tractor.
Saeta te xweş, xalo saet xweş.
Bless you, uncle, bless you.
Her bijî, her bijî.
Long live, long live.
Arê, maşallah xolû, meroq e, go leke direkto rûniştî, min
kêm me bisawirînin.
Yes, Mashallah uncle, it's interesting, seeing him sitting
on the tractor, I said let's film him.
Saeta te xweş, xalo, saet xweş.
Bless you, uncle, bless you.
Xolîmê meroq e.
My uncle is interesting.
Arê hevalno, îro jî xolû derê ber pês.
Yes friends, today the uncle is at the steering wheel.
Xalo, ne germ e dinya te darê?
Uncle, isn't the world hot while you are inside [driving]?
Dinya germ e, pas germbûnê nizane.
The world is hot, [but] rust [work/machine] doesn't know
heat.
Weleh.
No?
By God.
Berçî dibe de mordan?
Won't a man get hungry?
Birçî dibe. E de sibe, ovî nîro qalibî.
He gets hungry. Well in the morning, that noon turned over
[passed].
Êwa.
Yes.
Lê?
But?
Pas ke do keve here ber ova zirov ke.
If the rust [machine] falls, go to that smooth water.
Em kê harê nîşta, bar ova ra bihewitî, sal jî mehal e.
Yes.
We will plow that place, protect it from that water, the
year is impossible [bad].
Sal mehal e?
The year is impossible?
Îsal mehal e. Yanî tikê bibê, xeyo ti sal ona nebûye.
This year is impossible. Meaning whatever you say, God, no
year has been like this.
Emrî min biyo pêncî... yanî wek salê îsal, zerîet jî, u gi
jî, dinya wek dibên cefaf.
My age has become fifty... meaning like this year, the
agriculture too, and everything, the world is as they say,
drought.
Cefaf e, îsal cefaf e. Bidar dernakeve, bi hişk bî, baran jî
nakeve ne?
It's drought, this year is drought. The seed doesn't come
out, it was dry, rain didn't fall, right?
No, no, no, no, no. Çêla hişk bûn çû.
No, no, no, no, no. The cows went dry.
Are wela, Allah seadê we be, de Xwedê rizqê we bişîne.
Yes by God, may God help you, may God send your sustenance.
Sax be. Elhemdulelah, rizqê Rebbî aleme ye.
Be healthy. Praise be to God, sustenance belongs to the Lord
of the Worlds.
Serkeftin be ştar.
Success to you.
Adî, ta çavê daro jî heye?
By the way, do you have an eye on the thresher [harvest]
too?
Lê?
What?
Talma barî gîne.
You the machine...
The machine takes the load.
Oho, maşallah, kêf kêfê xolû. Wela ehla bita xolû re biçûme
çolê.
Oho, mashallah, the uncle is in high spirits. By God, the
sweetest thing is going to the fields with the uncle.
E wera, talma kê çêkî.
Yes come, we will fix the machine.
Saet xweş, Xwedê ştar azî be xolû.
Bless you, may God be pleased with you uncle.
Wela. Ehlen we sehlen. Mîd selame.
By God. Welcome. A hundred greetings.
Ko bikşîne.
Pull it [film it].
Maşallah pas cîçke barketî, barketî, havolno. Em çêret kin
hey, dar hişk in.
Mashallah the rust [machine] started moving, started moving,
friends. We are grazing [working], the trees are dry.
Ka havolî min wera men mole xolatî me din jî?
Where is my friend, come, I have the house of my aunt as
well?
Arê, Ebû Cemal, taban, avo mala meîrê ta ye. Birakî me
Fîroz. Emkê darbas hewşê gindî bin. U taban sar xênî vo ji,
emê çend laxto ş saro çêkin.
Yes, Abu Jamal, of course, this is your ?? house. Our blood-
brother Firoz. We will enter the village courtyard. And of
course from the roof as well, we will make a few shots from
the top.
Poş emê herin malbatê meîrê ta. Ko bi maro bin darbas bin.
Then we will go to your ?? family. Come with us, let's
enter.
Yalla, yalla.
Let's go, let's go.
Merheba ştaren.
Hello to you.
Ekî tanos kir? Av jî Birakê me Fîroz e.
Did you recognize him? This is our blood-brother Firoz.
Yalla, yalla.
Let's go, let's go.
Wela maşallah hewşê vano hênik e.
By God, Mashallah, their courtyard is cool.
Lê bilind e, durçer me vekirî ye.
But it is high, our binoculars [view] is open.
Ne xazî ne, da darim hêşîn...
It's not gas, the trees are green...
Werin, werin, werin, min dêm derkevin, werin.
Come, come, come, I said let's go out, come.
Arê havolno, taban emkê sar xênî vo laxtana bikşînin.
Yes friends, of course we will shoot some shots from their
roof.
Maşallah tebîeta vê gundî pirr xweş e.
Mashallah, the nature of this village is very nice.
Arê havolî min ona, du sê laxta xolî mira derxe, ona mla...
mla meraq vêra nemîne.
Yes my friend, like that, take two or three shots of the
soil for me, so that... so that curiosity doesn't remain
about it.
Gundê Ehmed e...
Ahmed's village...
Ev hevşo opîta Ehmed e, birê Cemal?
Is this courtyard Opita Ahmed's, brother Jamal?
Hevşo opîta Ehmed e, erê.
Yes, the courtyard is Opita Ahmed's.
Ev hevşo ê kêle?
Who does this courtyard belong to?
O... o nêrî ye.
Oh... that is a male [pistachio tree].
Ev jî hevşo nêrî ye?
Is this courtyard [tree] also a male one?
Erê, ibrê min.
Yes, my brother.
Ev o hevşo nêrî ye. O zortir kêlakê vî jî ê nêrî ye.
This courtyard one is male. And mostly the side shoots of
this one are also male.
Em ê noka derkevin.
We will head out now.
Vê tebîetê, vê gundî gi darxun.
[Look at] this nature, this village is all trees.
Havûlo maşallah... bokî... bokî heye ne tê? Te got dûr e,
gundê... Me...
Over there, Mashallah... it has a view... a view, doesn't
it? You said it's far, the village of... Me...
Maşallah, ho ho, roava di nava gund de mauxûnte, aferîn.
Mashallah, yes yes, the west is visible inside the village,
bravo.
Pismam, me'na wê... ev nan gund e, çi kirine, çû kirine
wuro?
Cousin, the meaning of that... those over there, is it a
village, what have they done, what is going on there?
O Kafarûm e, li wê derê muxeyem çêkirine.
That is Kafarûm, they have built a camp over there.
Kafarûmê, muxeyem çêkirine, erê?
Kafarûm, they built a camp, yes?
Bînayet ne, ne?
They are buildings, right?
Bînayet ne?
Huh?
Are they buildings?
Erê bînayet in, li wê derê muxeyem e.
Yes, they are buildings, there is a camp over there.
Erê, havûl nû bînayet ne li wî derê.
Yes, those over there are new buildings.
Vî derî poşman... vî derî poşwa hedmî ye... xêr e?
This place is regretful... this place is completely
destroyed... is everything okay?
Ev derê... ev derê hav bî.
This place... this place was like this.
Bela kirte bî yekî gundî me.
It was belonging to a certain person from our village.
Pismam, vê... avo... me'na avê bîne berê?
Cousin, this... water... meaning, did you bring the water?
Erê, avo... henefî ye, avê berdidin, gotin henefî. Vê zemanê
da...
Yes, the water... it's a tap, they release the water, they
call it tap water. In these times...
Henefî li Raco dîtin, gundî gi da av cê av tê ber.
They found the tap [source] in Raco, water comes to the
whole village from it.
Ji vê av tê ber?
Does water come from this?
Erê. Zêde... xet hat û niqtek li nav gunda ye.
Yes. More... the line came and there is a point inside the
village.
Du niqte hene.
There are two points.
Eywa. Welle deryûbek jî cama heye gundo, deryûbî nahê?
I see. By God, there is a doorway to the mosque in the
village, isn't the doorway coming [visible]?
Erê... kavnar e, xirabe ye.
Yes... it is ancient, it is ruined.
Temam, ka wer, marê me yê geçe dîn çi.
Okay, come, let's see what our snake [man] is doing.
Allahu Akbar]
God is the Greatest]
Erê Ebû Cemal, wer, wer... wer dolma bixwe, te re dolma
hazir dînine serê êr.
Yes Abu Jamal, come, come... come eat dolma (stuffed
vegetables), they have put ready-made dolma on the fire for
you.
Dê bêmlo were dolma bixwe. Çolî rezo, hey hecer e, hey sol
e...
I'm saying come eat dolma. In the open orchard, oh it's
stone, oh it's bare earth...
Dilî te tê re ye, were em ê sifrekî te re dînin.
If your heart desires, come, we will set a table for you.
Xwedê ji te razî be Ebû Cemal.
May God be pleased with you, Abu Jamal.
Erê birê min, teb'en ev hevşo wa esasî ê hev e.
Yes my brother, naturally this courtyard is basically this
one.
Bes kavnar e, xirabe ye.
But it is ancient, it is ruined.
Merekî bêiş ta.
It's a desolate/idle place.
Ev jî şta... hevşê opê tan e, meyrê tan e.
And this is also... it's your father's courtyard, your
mother's.
Zikriyatê te li vir pir hene?
Do you have many memories here?
Xwedê û Pêxember ji te razî be, Xwedê emrê ki dirêj bi te
de. Înşallah tu gulek gulek biftile, wara welatê xwe jî.
May God and the Prophet be pleased with you, may God give
you a long life. God willing, you will walk around flower by
flower, back in your own country.
Nav malbata xwe.
Among your family.
Maşallah gundekî pir xweş e, mi ecibandî.
Mashallah, it is a very nice village, I liked it.
Erê havûl nû, welle maşallah, ev gundî ember meke... birûkî
min?
Yes, those over there, by God Mashallah, do not consider
this village a storehouse... my brow [dear]?
Gundê Stêr e.
It is the village of Ster.
Teb'en Gundê Stêr jî li hemberî min e. Voyê em pozarî xwînte
jî gi Efrîn e.
Naturally, the village of Ster is also opposite me. The
views we are seeing are all Afrin.
Meydankê, der... gi li ber vî xwînte. Maşallah pir tebîetê
rind e.
Meydanke, around... everything is visible before this.
Mashallah, nature is very beautiful.
Wê ev gundî hane li hember me kî der e?
And those villages opposite us, where are they?
Xilaqê mezin...
Big Xilaqê...
Xilaqê mezin e?
Is it Big Xilaqê?
Çîçik e... Qestelê ye.
It's small... it is Qestel.
Qestelê.
Qestel.
Qerebaba ye.
It is Qerebaba.
Kafarûm e.
Oh.
It is Kafarûm.
Kafarûm e.
E... we wano Sînka ye, Metîna ye.
Uh... and those are Sinka, Metina.
Maşallah, mentîqê me mezin e, havûl nû mentîqe pir mezin e.
Mashallah, our region is big, those over there, the region
is very big.
Vî şorbe gundê Helkê...
This soup [mix] of the village of Helkê...
Gê teynxun.
Is visible.
Erê.
Yes.
Girê Zîkê ye avine.
That over there is Zîkê Hill.
[Call to Prayer continues]
Her gundekî de maşallah xêr û bêr... xêr û bêra wî gundî
heye. Her gundekî da.
In every village, Mashallah, there is goodness and bounty...
the goodness and bounty of that village exists. In every
village.
Yanî çiqas gundî çûçik hebe, xêr û bêra wî gundî pir e.
Meaning, however small a village is, the goodness and bounty
of that village is plentiful.
Di her tiştî de.
In everything.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Navê gundo Cebar e, Cebar.
The name of the village is Jabar, Jabar.
Ne Cebar ba, dê mîş ne dibî li ser vê ardê.
If it wasn't for the "Compeller" (God), there wouldn't be
people/life on this land.
Maşallah, serkeftin be, serkeftin be gelî Kurd.
Mashallah, victory, victory to the Kurdish people.
Erê Ebû Cemal... me ha... me xwest... dilî te kir, saeta te
xweş. Em ê teb'en mala opîta ne.
Yes Abu Jamal... we... we wanted... your heart desired it,
bless you. Naturally, we are at Opita's house.
Pismamî te.
Your cousin.
Mala pismamî te ye îşta.
It's your cousin's house now.
Cem bavê Ehmed.
With Ahmed's father.
Cem bavê Ehmed, em qehwêkî end vexwin.
With Ahmed's father, let's drink a coffee together.
Te teb'en em rast dolma solma jî hatin, te kê bixwe were, em
te re çêkin sifre, dawî sor...
Naturally, we also came right for the dolma and such, you
said you'd eat, come, we prepared a table for you, the final
red [tea/feast]...
Te tane ji me ke mita, evî ne xweş şîrîn biba.
You are mocking us, may this be pleasant and sweet.
Xalo, te çend sal li vê duniqê ji miletro, ji birûkî me,
cêmêrî rûwên ro...
Uncle, how many years have you been in this world, from the
people, from our brow [dear ones], from the sitting men...
Silo, kergiya...
Silo [name], the...
Saeta wa xweş.
Bless you all.
O ta jî xweş.
And you as well.
Xalo, s(w)al... vê derê... xalê xwdê... yekî emrê xwe pêncî
salî bî...
Uncle, a question... this place... uncle... one whose age
was fifty years...
Elî Heso...
Ali Heso...
Şivan e?
Is he a shepherd?
Go... vê derê... Eyn Hecer e.
He said... this place... is Eyn Hecer (Stone Spring).
Bikanîkê tenos kirin, go we kaniyê jî di çi zinar kî da bî.
He recognized it by a spring, he said that spring was also
in a rocky cliff.
Ber o vê.
In front of it.
Heye?
Is it there?
Erê.
Yes.
Şêre vê?
Is it visible?
Şêre.
It is visible.
Gundim ro hewal da...
My village friend gave...
Eyn Hecer...
Kanîka... an o jî çîkevire tê de.
The spring... or that one also has a rock in it.
Şbone? Di zinardê?
The shepherd? In the cliff?
Ho je.
Like that.
Ruçikî gund e.
It's the face/outskirts of the village.
Welle mekanî baxwe pêk anî do rind bî, dûr e ne?
By God, the place itself brought it about well, is it far?
Yo, ne dûr e.
No, it's not far.
Noka hişk bî ye?
Has it dried up now?
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Hişk bî ye.
It has dried up.
Cafaf e, cafaf, fisl cafaf î şta ye.
It's drought, drought, it's the drought season now.
Înşallah... ha vol nû işta, em î li mala xalû ne, Ebû Cemal.
Te qusûrî me ji ef bike, şaşbîn maşbînê me hene, her kesî...
me serdike.
God willing... folks right now, we are at uncle's house, Abu
Jamal. Forgive our faults, we have mistakes and confusion,
everyone... visits us.
U em ê noka jî li çend leqta din nav gund çêkin û em ê Eyn
Hecerê çûçik jî sarba we ra teswîr kin.
And we will now make a few more shots inside the village and
we will film the little Eyn Hecer for you.
Ehlen wa sehlen ji we ra.
Welcome to you all.
Bimînin, em ê noka we bibînin.
Stay tuned, we will see you now.
[Sound of car driving and dishes clattering]
Erê havol nû, teb'en am noka jî li Eyn Hecerê çûçik ne,
urte...
Yes folks, naturally we are now at the little Eyn Hecer, in
the middle...
Ma Eyn Hecerê mezin we ra teswîr kir, hav jî ê çûçik e.
We filmed the big Eyn Hecer for you, this is the small one.
Em ê noka êre mala Ebû Fadî...
We are now here at Abu Fadi's house...
Mala vêre dibên bi leqeb, mala Arifê Pîrê.
The house they call by nickname, the house of Arif Pîrê.
Em hatin vî derê.
We came to this place.
Em ê nav gund teswîr kin, û malbata jî em ê rûnên silav ke
bo we din. Teb'en seltelebeyê muşahîdî ya, êl me dixwazin.
We will film inside the village, and we will sit with the
family and send greetings to you. Naturally, based on the
request of the viewers, the people want us.
Û vîdyoyê du vêra jî, înşallah gundê Qorşo, em ê bi
sewirînin.
And the video after this one, God willing, we will film the
village of Qorşo.
Havol nek ma ji ma xwestî, pir neqla me ro yazmîş dike.
A friend requested it from us, he writes to us very often.
Gundê Qorşo, em ê du vêra daxin înşallah. Bimînin hetan
dîginîn nav gund, lextanê xweş kîbar.
The village of Qorşo, we will drop [upload] it after this
one, God willing. Stay with us until we reach the village,
[for] beautiful elegant shots.
[Instrumental Folk Music Starts]
Erê, me dest pê kir havol nû. Bimînin, lextanê xweş kîbar.
Yes, we have started folks. Stay tuned, beautiful elegant
shots.
Teb'en her gundekî ya d'kavime, xwe îspat kin ser gundê xwe.
Naturally, whatever village I fall into [visit], prove
yourselves regarding your village.
Belav kin, vîdyûyê gundê xwe belav kin, mil millet lê sêr
ke.
Share it, share the video of your village, so the people can
watch it.
[Instrumental Folk Music Continues]
Teb'en ko em hod hatin, paşê em ê biftilin.
Naturally, since we came up to here, afterwards we will turn
back.
[Instrumental Folk Music Continues]
[End of Audio Segment]
Erê welle hevalno, teb'an em li mala Ebû Fadî ne.
Yes, by God friends, of course we are at Abu Fadi's house.
Bi leqebê wî dibêjin Arifê Pîrê ne?
By his nickname, they call him Arif Pîrê, right?
Em ê li malbatê gerin, ka were merd derbasî hewşê be.
We will look around the family home, come let's enter the
courtyard bravely.
Merheba apê min.
Hello my uncle.
Tu çawa yî?
How are you?
Welle hemdulillah.
By God, praise be to God.
Maşalla te bîstan çandiye.
Mashallah, you have planted a garden.
Belê, me çandiye.
Yes, we planted it.
Te bi tahcer çêkiriye hewş?
Have you paved the courtyard with stone?
Belê, min çêkiriye, hemûs.
Yes, I made it, all of it.
Erê welle, xalê Arif xwe ra berberûk çandine.
Yes by God, Uncle Arif has planted purslane for himself.
Û bacanê sor çandine.
And he has planted tomatoes.
Se'etê gundê xweş.
The time in the village is pleasant.
Av heye? Şolê avê heye?
Is there water? Is there a water issue?
Belê, aveke paqij e, derekî heye.
Yes, it is clean water, there is a well.
Ya rind e, bereket be.
That is good, may it be blessed.
Ava paqij e, derekî heye.
Clean water, there is a well.
Welle rind e, rind e. Maşalla rind e.
By God it is good, good. Mashallah it is good.
Se'eta te xweş.
Good health to you.
Hisên, werin bixwin, werin bixwin.
Hussein, come eat, come eat.
Erê Em Henan tahr dibê Em Henan were, dibê were bixwe.
Yes, Em Henan is calling, saying come Em Henan, saying come
eat.
Xeyara bixwe, bacana bixwe...
Eat cucumbers, eat tomatoes...
Erê kî wê dest bavê feqîrê?
Yes, who would touch the poor thing?
Merheba xaltîk.
Hello auntie.
Merheba, ser çava.
Hello, you are welcome.
Çu halê te?
How are you?
Welle hemdulillah.
By God, praise be to God.
Kerem ke Ebû Henan, werin.
Please, Abu Hanan, come.
Erê hevalno, tebîeta vî gundî ha ye.
Yes friends, the nature of this village is like this.
Bayê hênik ber me jî tê teb'an.
A cool breeze is coming towards us, of course.
Gundê me heye, nêzîk e teb'an.
Our village is here, it is near of course.
Ka wer, vira, wer vira.
Come here, come here.
Erê hevalno, rêka Efrînê, hewayê pêşiya me ye.
Yes friends, the road to Afrin, the view is in front of us.
Ma'melê Bêrînê li hember me ye.
The Bêrîn factory is opposite us.
Gundê hember me Kûkan e.
The village opposite us is Kûkan.
Inşalla Kûkanê jî emê derxin, bes rê tine emê derxin
inşalla.
God willing, we will show Kûkan too, but there is no road,
we will show it God willing.
Ew Kûkan e.
That is Kûkan.
Xalo ev xezana avê ye?
Uncle, is this a water tank?
Erê, ev a kevin e, a mezin e.
Yes, this is the old one, the big one.
Xalo, her malekî da xezanek çêkirine û av...
Uncle, in every house they made a tank and water...
Bi tankerê dihat, her malekî xezanek danî.
It used to come by tanker, every house placed a tank.
Maşalla, hevalî min... li vê tebîetê jî mirov dikare seyr
bike.
Mashallah, my friends... one can also look at this nature.
Gundê dûr jî Eyn Hecer e.
The distant village is Ayn Hajar.
Efrîn gundê hember me ye, pir xweş e.
Afrin villages are opposite us, very beautiful.
Hevalno, mala wekî derket, her yek çar pênc deqîqe heye
meşkin...
Friends, the houses as they appeared, each is four or five
minutes walking...
Erê hevalno, teb'an saeta xaltîka me xweş.
Yes friends, of course our auntie's health is good.
Me qehweke gundî jî vexwar.
We also drank a village coffee.
Wekî tê bê çi, saet xweş.
As one says, good health.
Emê noka ji xalû jî bipirsin.
We will ask the uncle now.
Xalû tu çi dibêjî? Tu bîra kesî li wir nekirî?
Uncle what do you say? Haven't you missed anyone there?
Welle, Ebû Henan me pir bêrî kiriye.
By God, we have missed Abu Hanan a lot.
Em Henan tu çi dibêjî?
Em Henan, what do you say?
Ez jî jê razî me, saeta giyan xweş be.
I am also satisfied with them, may everyone's health be
good.
Inşalla welat rind bibe, em jî bizivirin warê xwe.
God willing the country becomes good, and we return to our
homeland.
Nav ehbabê xwe, xudanê xwe.
Among our loved ones, our family.
Her çi dûr ketin, nêzîkî hev dibin inşalla.
Whoever fell far apart, will get close to each other God
willing.
Xwedê rizqê jê bişîne.
May God send sustenance to them.
Xwedê qewetê bide we jî.
May God give you strength too.
Spas, xaltîk.
Thanks, auntie.
Erê hevalno, wekî me we ra gotî, saeta xaltîkê û xalû xweş.
Yes friends, as we told you, the aunt and uncle are well.
Em li Eyn Hecerê bûn.
We were in Ayn Hajar.
Me xîtama xwe bidin.
Let us give our ending.
Bi teswîr kin, saeta we xweş, bimînin xweşiyê de.
Film it, good health to you, stay in goodness.
Xwedê qewetê bide we.
May God give you strength.
Bay bay Em Henan, Ebû Henan.
Bye bye Em Henan, Abu Henan.
Oxir be, oxir be.
Farewell, farewell.