Gundê Elî Bago... xêr nav lêkirin gundê Elî Bago, tu nizanî
o tenê?
Ali Bago Village... why was it named Ali Bago village, do
you know or is it just that?
Solik na... inşallah milet gi va karî, inşallah...
Shoes, no... God willing all the people can do this work,
God willing...
...tiştek ma, ew dikirin. Yekî me ra bikirî ma pir kêf
dikir.
...something remained, they were buying it. If someone
bought it for us, we would be very happy.
Teba ne eyb e û ne heram e.
Of course, it is neither a shame nor a sin.
Te nedîtî hêna?
Have you not seen it yet?
Weleh pir nake anca dîsa we ra bikirim... Hene!
By God, it's not much, otherwise I would buy for you
again... Here!
Wele xar! Gû xwarinda!
Oh wow! He ate it!
Are weleh.
Yes, by God.
Merheba ji were hevalno, dîsa em hatin.
Hello to you friends, we have come again.
Erê hevalno, me gundê Xelolkê me sawirand.
Yes friends, we filmed the village of Xelol.
Me got emkê derbas gundê Elî Bago bin.
We said we would proceed to the village of Ali Bago.
Tebe gundê Elî Bago jî, tabi'ê nahiya Bilbilê ye.
Of course, Ali Bago village also belongs to the Bilbil sub-
district.
Gundekî çûçik e, ne mezin e.
It is a small village, not big.
Dûr çêl malî, heta çêl û pênc mala ye.
Around forty households, up to forty-five households.
Emkê noka derbas bin, gundê... ewê wera bisawirînin, Elî
Bago.
We will cross over now, to the village... we will film it
for you, Ali Bago.
Tebe mabeyna Xelolkê û Elî Bago kîlometrek heye.
Of course, there is one kilometer between Xelol and Ali
Bago.
Kîlometrek, kîlo nîvek.
One kilometer, one and a half kilometers.
Ê me got, milet virdê vê gunda ney mîne.
So we said, the people shouldn't just stay on this side of
the village.
Na, bi me ra bin, emê derbas gund bin, emê tebîeta vê gundî
jî pişwa kin.
No, stay with us, we will enter the village, we will show
the nature of this village.
Miletê vê gundî, çû derbas dike. Bi me ra bin heta tora
vîdyoyê.
[To see] how the people of this village spend [their lives].
Stay with us until the end of the video.
Saeta we xweş. Ka em derbas bin.
Have a good time. Let us proceed.
Gundekî pir xweş e.
It is a very nice village.
Maşallah çiyayê gund e pir dexem ne.
Mashallah, the mountain of the village is very huge.
Wa dî çiyayê gund e çiqasî dexem ne?
Did you see how huge the mountain of the village is?
Ohooo! Heta ewr ta ferq dike.
Ohooo! It almost touches the clouds.
Gundekî pir xweş e.
It is a very nice village.
Are weleh.
Yes, by God.
Me'zed jî, mirov dar nakeat weleh... me'zed cew ne kerbay e.
The slope/path too, one wouldn't dare/fall... the weather
isn't bad/dusty.
Are rû derketî, bes bokî qerimî tê.
Yes the sun is out, but a bit of dust is coming.
Ew jî duman kîne dayê.
That makes it a bit misty/foggy.
Are weleh.
Yes, by God.
Are hevalno, vî derê me dase pî kir.
Yes friends, we waved [to someone] here.
Selam Aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Are hevalno, li vê derkê jî em gihiştin duxulî Elî Bago.
Yes friends, at this point we have reached the entrance of
Ali Bago.
Elî Bago jî, maşallah cemaet li vir e.
As for Ali Bago, Mashallah the community is here.
Ebû Xelîl jî vê derê di şixul e.
Abu Khalil is also working here.
Kar dike, Ebû Xelîl... te gav ro derdixê? Çû dike? Mehre
dike? Dûz dike?
He is working, Abu Khalil... are you taking out the
[cattle]? What are you doing? Cleaning it? Fixing it?
Na, mehre dikim, dûz dikim.
No, I am cleaning/shoveling, I am fixing it.
Me got em ji Ebû Xelîl pirsken, tebîeta vî gundî çawa ye.
We said let's ask Abu Khalil, how is the nature of this
village.
Bi çi rengî tenaskirin. Emê bi hev ra noka pirsken.
In what way is it known. We will ask together now.
Me got merheba dîsa ji te ra.
We said hello to you again.
Ser seran, ser çavan.
You are welcome, upon my head and eyes.
Ebû Xelîl, gundê Elî Bago... xêr nav lêkirin gundê Elî Bago?
Tu we yekê zanî?
Abu Khalil, Ali Bago village... why was it named Ali Bago
village? Do you know that?
Ee wele, dabeşîya me... Beg bîn... ew çû bîn... ne Axa bîn.
Uh well, our division... they were Beys... what were they...
they were not Aghas.
Beg bîn.
They were Beys.
Beg bîn?
They were Beys?
Ne Axa bîn, Beg bîn.
They were not Aghas, they were Beys.
Beg başqe ne, Axa başqe ne?
Are Beys different, are Aghas different?
Axa başqe ye, Beg başqe ye.
Agha is distinct, Bey is distinct.
Beg ji Axa mezin tir e?
Is a Bey bigger than an Agha?
Ee, Beg... de bêje axa Beg li Axa mezin tir bîn. Belê.
Yes, Bey... let's say the Agha... the Bey was bigger than
the Agha. Yes.
Ê, le Beg... Bêg başqe ye ser axa ra ye. Belê.
So, the Bey... Bey is distinct, he is above the Agha. Yes.
Cîma digotinê Elî Bago?
Is that why they called it Ali Bago?
Belê, Elî Beg. Beg başqe ye.
Yes, Ali Beg. The Bey is different.
Xol û çiqas hewş tê da heye vê gundê?
How many households and courtyards are there in this
village?
Wele, çêl, pênc û pênc cîmal e.
By God, forty, fifty-five households.
Çêl, pênc heta pêncî ne?
Forty-five up to fifty?
Şûma.
Roughly.
Aaa. Tabi'ê kê?
Ah. Belonging to whom [which administration]?
Em tabi'ê Bilbilê ne.
We belong to Bilbil [sub-district].
Tabi'ê Bilbilê ne.
Belonging to Bilbil.
Firna gundî wa da heye?
Do you have a village bakery?
No, firne tîne.
No, there is no bakery.
Mokinî tîne ne?
There is no machine/mill?
Mokin tîne.
No machine.
Dikan, samon, der heye?
Shop, groceries, are there any?
Hene, samon hene.
There are, there are groceries.
Aywa. Ê rind e, samon hebîn rind e.
Okay. That's good, if there are groceries, it's good.
În mekteb cem we heye tîne ne?
And do you have a school with you or not?
Mekteb, em tabi'ê Xelolkê ne, heta şeşan.
School, we belong to Xelol, up to sixth grade.
Lên nav gundê Xelolkê ye?
Is it inside the village of Xelol?
Ee, nav gundê Xelolkê.
Yes, inside the village of Xelol.
Eta na dûr e qiçik ji vir darin Xelolkê?
But isn't it far for the kids to go from here to Xelol?
Çû na dûr e? Wele zehmet e, zehmet.
How is it not far? By God, it is difficult, difficult.
No, gerek e meselen mokînî gundî we hebe, telebe bibin û
bînin.
No, it is necessary, for example, for your village to have a
vehicle/bus, to take the students and bring them.
Ê mokîn hatin e...
Well, vehicles have come...
Tine ne? Zehmet e?
There aren't any? Is it difficult?
Zehmet e. Wele bi giv meşê... û zivistanê serma ye, der
nakevin.
It is difficult. By God, walking in snow... and in winter it
is cold, they can't go out.
Noka jî cew û berf... zivistanê darê zor e.
Even now the weather and snow... in winter the trees/road
are difficult.
Are da û pênc...
Yes ten and five...
Pênc qaçik darin, da û pênc narin.
Five steps go, ten and five don't go. [Meaning access is
very limited].
Yanî pênc darin, da û pênc narin?
You mean five go, ten and five don't go?
Da û pênc jî morin.
Ten and five also get stuck/die.
Bes muwaselat hebu? Ê bîçûna? Gê bîçûna?
But was there transportation? Did they go? Or did they just
go?
Ee bîçûna? Ekîda we.
Did they go? Certainly.
E maşallah. Xudê emrê gi dirêj bike.
Oh Mashallah. May God prolong all their lives.
Xolû kesek te heye tu silava jê ra bişînî, bişîne?
Uncle, do you have anyone you want to send greetings to?
Send them.
De silav... zimrêtî, kirmêşî, giş ê ra dişînim.
I send greetings... to the Zimrêtî, the Kirmêşî
[tribes/families], I send to all of them.
Çar parçan?
[To] the four parts [of Kurdistan]?
Çar parçan.
The four parts.
Silavê min û yê Ebû Xelîl, silavê me ji we giya ra hene, li
her derekê.
My greetings and Abu Khalil's, our greetings are to all of
you, everywhere.
Her kesî kurd, meser be.
Every Kurd, may they be happy/head held high.
Her yekî li me seyr dike, çavê yekî maç dikim.
Everyone who is watching us, I kiss everyone's eyes.
Gundê Elî Bago, silavê min cûcik mezin ra hene. Çi dûr dibe,
çi nîzîk dibe, kî ser serî me ser çavê me ne.
Ali Bago village, my greetings to the small and the great.
Whether far or near, you are upon our head and upon our
eyes.
De yek hewş derneketin, nûne qusûrî efû ken. Tu zanî tebîeta
gunda çawa ye.
So, [if] not a single household came out, forgive our
shortcomings. You know how the nature of the villages is.
De hewşin hene, dibê heft dabe, tabi'î.
There are courtyards, maybe seven, naturally.
Mîneynî, mîneynî teswîr kin.
We won't stay, we won't stay to film.
Lê xelolkê maşallah mezin bî. Ço... ço mala me d'filtin.
But Xelol, Mashallah, was big. Many... many homes escaped us
[we missed them].
Emê noha bi hevra derbaz bin, emê vê gundî peşwa kin.
We will now proceed together, we will show this village.
Saeta wa xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Have a good time, may God be pleased with you.
Em derbaz bin?
Shall we pass?
Welehî serî serî min ser çavê min, Xwedê ji te razî be.
By God, upon my head, upon my eyes, may God be pleased with
you.
Bergê me ratin e. Heta em teswîrê xelas kin. Heta em hem bi
gund kinî, îvorkê bibe.
Our time has come. Until we finish the filming. Until we
tour the village, make a U-turn.
O em vê sibê do derketine, saet bîst û sê came.
Oh, we went out this morning, it's twenty-three [minutes]
past the hour.
Saet o waye.
That is the time.
Onca pênc o îkîndam, mal gînin.
Then at five in the afternoon, they bring the cattle home.
Cew jî tu zanî zivistan e, sor dibe.
The weather too, you know it is winter, it gets red
[cold/dark].
Xwedê ji we razî be, saeta wa xweş.
May God be pleased with you, have a good time.
Bibînin di xweşî da. Maşallah gundî wa bixêr û bêr e.
See you in happiness. Mashallah your village is bountiful
and blessed.
Avîl simsibî avîlî tîne ye. Ka... dikan heye nîzîk biron?
[Unclear] is not there. Where... is there a shop nearby?
Wele dikan di şû da hene.
By God, there are shops down there.
Mîke mir han dikanê?
Shall we go to the shop?
Ha?
Huh?
Lênin, lênin, lênin, mir han dikanê. Lênin, lênin.
Where are they, where, where, let's go to the shop. Where,
where.
Lênin, qapaxê veke, lênin.
Where, open the cap, where.
Maşallah hevalno...
Mashallah friends...
Gind na hana di kevime, maşallah bixêr û bêr ne.
The village... I am falling into it [entering], Mashallah
they are bountiful.
Welehî nizanin maro çû ken.
By God, I don't know what we should do.
Zehr xweş.
Very nice/pleasant.
Hay miletê me cebbar e. Xwedê ji giyo razî be.
Hey, our people are resilient. May God be pleased with
everyone.
Merheba Xalo!
Hello Uncle!
Tavê xudê ro ye ho?
God's sun is [bright] today, huh?
Yaa...
Yeah...
No, da maro kê çû key gundo?
No, what should we do in the village?
Çêl nuxwe bi heyîn, çêl...
Are you well/healthy, are you...
No, pî li min...
No, my feet [hurt]...
Bas tinî, bas?
Just that, only?
Wele, pêjî tinî, em çû... çû dabînin... em hatin...
By God, just the legs, we... what we saw... we came...
Un ye naw hetinî?
You came from inside [the fields]?
Kul bîn, kul bîn.
They were lame/flowers, they were flowers.
Solik ne?
No shoes?
İnşallah milet gi va karî, inşallah Xwedê şîfa bide.
God willing, all the people can do this, God willing may God
give healing.
Rind e, saeta wa xweş.
Good, have a good time.
Wey gund şên kirî maşallah.
Wow, they have enlivened the village, Mashallah.
Avîl dikan dûr e?
Kid, is the shop far?
Hê?
Huh?
Dikan dûr e?
Is the shop far?
Vê derê.
This way.
E.
Yes.
Maşallah ooo, weleh gundekî bilind e.
Mashallah ooo, by God it is a high village.
Jêr vellê binêr, tê bê...
Look down there, you would say...
Ewa kûr ta daye, war cûr jî gundekî bilind e.
That deep part down there, and up here too is a high
village.
Erê welle, vî derî jî dikanek vekirine heya.
Yes, by God, they have opened a shop in this place too.
Bro cemedan heye.
Bro, there is a freezer (icebox).
Vê hewîlê jî... ezê kê vêra... ekeletê bikirim. Were dikanê
were.
For this family too... I will... buy chocolates/treats from
here. Come to the shop, come.
Gundo welle dengê we pir kêfxweş bûn.
Villagers, by God, your voices were very happy.
Ka hûnê çi bixwin? Ka berî giya em vana pêdinê.
What will you eat? Here, before anything else, let's give
these.
Ka vêra tew tûrik e, tûrik e vêra nuka.
Look here, it is a whole bag, a bag is here now.
Te çi divê? Te çi divê? Tûrik.
What do you want? What do you want? A bag.
Nika çi bixwî? Dilê wa çi dixwaze, de la?
Now what will you eat? What do your hearts desire, come on?
Te çi bixwî ewîl? Te çi bixwî?
What will you eat, child? What will you eat?
Ez çu nînim.
I [want] nothing.
Te çi bixwî de?
What will you eat, come on?
Ka vê bixwe vê?
Here, will you eat this?
Ev na çin e?
These aren't going [being sold]?
Çikolata zêde naçin. Ev jî didime birin.
Chocolates don't go [sell] much. I give these to take away.
Ka emkê çi bidin wan... eee...
Let's see what we shall give them... uh...
Ne te hesab kirine?
Have you calculated it?
Aaa.
Yes.
Hayê ji didu. Ka Asîr hane kûptel?
Here is two. Where is Asir [the boy]?
Hane wir.
He is over there.
Konî?
Where?
Aaa ka em vanan jî didiyê, vêra bibîne.
Aaa, let's give him these too, take them over here.
Rind e, dikan... çend dikan dibin gundî da hene?
Good, shops... how many shops are there in the village?
Sisê.
Three.
Sisê dikan? Maşallah rinde.
Three shops? Mashallah, that's good.
Haa... vana jî me didi birin?
Haa... you gave us these to take too?
Eta biskwîta na...
Those biscuits, no...
Awa jî ya Şelîmanî gindin e. Hay didu.
That one is for Selim, sending it. Here is two.
Were... Tu xudanê dikanê yî?
Come... Are you the owner of the shop?
Her mal bome me.
Every house is ours.
Ew xudanê dikanê ye. Hatorş barê xwe dike? Were, were.
He is the owner of the shop. Does he carry his own
load/goods? Come, come.
Were tu jî bibî, were.
Come, you take some too, come.
Em la em o na.
We... us... no.
A ne, din bibî me'nî qaçik rast me hatin, ez pê dimê.
Oh no, take another, because the girl came right to us, I'm
giving it to her.
Da bahs zêna ye, qaçik rast me tênê.
It's a matter of mindset, the girl comes right to us.
Ka ewê gundê tinn e? Şelîman?
Are there no others from the village? Selim?
Hane.
There they are.
Ka mulo dafî me ke.
Here, push it [the box] toward us.
Weşka tûrikî din ez bibim, ka.
I should take another bag, here.
Me'nî sa qaçik rast me hatin.
Because the girl came right to us.
Ve gundo da hatin, işta çaxsu bibê.
They came into this village, hoping things would be good.
Awa ne, da qaçkê çûçik jî nizanin.
Not that, the little girls don't know either.
Da çaxsu bibê, işta... em çûçik bîn.
Hoping things would be good, look... when we were small.
Wexta em çûçik bîn, coghê yona tiştek me... ew dikirin, yekî
me ra bikirîya me pir kêf dikir.
When we were small, in places like that... if they did
something, if someone bought for us, we would be very happy.
Tabe ne eyb e û ne heram e jî.
Of course, it is neither shameful nor forbidden (haram).
Me ra dilê qaçkêkî şa bikê. Pir rind e. Ne te hasibandin?
For us to make a girl's heart happy. It is very good. Did
you calculate it?
Ka ezê nuka... çendek din bibim.
Here, I will now... take a few more.
Hay yek.
Here is one.
Hay dudu.
Here is two.
Hay sese.
Here is three.
Sisyê jî ji bona hemkê bibin.
Three also for everyone to take.
Kêmasî çêbû bêje ha.
If there is a shortage [of money], say so, okay.
Hay sese mi ji bon jî birin.
Here is three I took for myself/them too.
Ji bo wî jî çûçik e.
For him too, he is small.
Van jî dibir ke.
Pack/take these too.
Sê biskêwît û evna jî sê.
Three biscuits and these three too.
Erê welle gele... henderê dênê sor e, av herikî ye, xwozîk
çêbî ye.
Yes, by God, folks... the cheeks are red, the water is
flowing, it is an enviable scene.
Xwozîk çêbî ye.
It is an enviable scene.
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Şanikê gerîna nijan, comî ezêm bi wan dim jî.
The joy of wandering... I will give to them too.
Were, were... hevalî min were, hevalê min.
Come, come... my friend come, my friend.
Hevalê min ji giya pirtir raderdikeve misawirê min.
My friend who gets tired more than anyone is my cameraman.
Xwe demoq nêre derdixîne...
Showing himself in that fashion...
Ez ne?
Not me?
Ez dibêm misawirê min radibe, xolîk dibê pir dan dike
radibe.
I say my cameraman gets tired, the kid says he gets very
tired doing it.
E we jî çet... xolîk hewa bo lê dixe, dimoq nêre temam sora.
And that too... the wind hits the kid, look his face is
completely red.
Are welle.
Yes, by God.
Were ewîlno, were, ewîlno were.
Come children, come, children come.
Were, were ke tişta hatin were.
Come, come, things have arrived, come.
Jêlî bo min!
Jelly for me!
Were.
Come.
Maşallah çi comerd virdo çêkirine.
Mashallah, what generosity they have created here.
Yoş maro.
Look at that snake [joking about the shape of jelly or a
toy].
Were ewîl were.
Come child, come.
Yoş, yoş, yoş yek... ew jî tadem. Te bona hez dikî? Hane.
Good, good, good one... I gave you that one. Do you like
this? Here.
Were.
Come.
Were, were, were.
Come, come, come.
Wa peymak e, were were.
That is a contract/deal, come come.
Were.
Come.
Mamoooo!
Uncle!
Mamê kanî ye kîme?
Uncle, where is mine?
Aa... a.
Aa... here.
Were tu jî ya xo bibe were.
Come, you take yours too, come.
Biskêwît kêtadem.
I gave you a biscuit.
Hene.
Here.
Êta jî biskêwît kêtadem, êta yoş yek mo, qutiyek mo.
I gave you a biscuit too, here is one good one, one box
remained.
Êta abû nadime. Da abû nadime.
He is not giving me this one. He is not giving me this one.
Yoş.
Good.
Ê Kerîm da abû nadime.
Hey Karim, he isn't giving me this one.
Hey bino.
Here, look at this.
Ooo, maşallah qaçik hatin. Ha. Were, were, were, were.
Ooo, mashallah, the girls came. Here. Come, come, come,
come.
Were.
Come.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Hene, bigir.
Here, take it.
Yoş.
Good.
Êta jî patata.
This one is potato [chips].
Aaa, êta jî ew maşallah wele qaçikî vê gindî pirne, hûndarin
mektebê?
Aaa, and this one mashallah, by God, there are many girls in
this village, are you inside school?
Handa.
Yes.
Êta Şelîmanî xoyabo? Yoş.
Is this Selim's own? Good.
Kiye nî? Aa, te nebirî hene. Ooo wele pirna ko, anja dîsa
werim.
Who is it? Aa, you didn't take, here. Ooo by God there are
many, I should come back again.
O toz be ta, toz be bibe ta re bişîne.
Oh, let it be dust [powder juice], take the dust to send.
Ta re bişîne? Namo, a te re dikan e, ha, tiji. Ko çend man?
Send to you? No, here is the shop for you, here, you too.
Look, how many left?
Çend man? Maşallah.
How many left? Mashallah.
Xalo tûyî sa wû çî?
Uncle, you... what is that?
Mişo were dikanê ta re bikirim.
Go, come to the shop, I will buy for you.
Biskêwîtê were. No, no, were heke ta re bikirim, were were
were.
Come for biscuits. No, no, come so I can buy for you, come
come come.
Dilê xo...
Your heart...
Konî?
Where?
Aa, vê de mol no. Were lo... Ham pşî dikanê noka ezê wa re
bikirim, ham pşî dikanê?
Aa, don't leave this home. Come on... All behind the shop,
now I will buy for you, all behind the shop?
Çû Xoltîk? Xoltîk pencere te çiye?
What happened, Khaltik (Auntie/Girl)? Khaltik, what is your
window [referring to camera lens or something she is
holding]?
Maşallah çi pincor kirî, yê?
Mashallah, what a pinch/squeeze she did, eh?
Welle gundî me tinn e, camo, ha maşallah hay. Em çûn vê ruyê
m' sûrke me kir.
By God, we don't have this in the village, look, mashallah,
here. We went and my face became red [from cold/sun].
Jamê xwaşko yî.
The glass [lens] is beautiful.
Na cema.
No, glass.
Aa pşî dikanê noka ezê wa re... wa re bibim.
Aa, behind the shop now I will... take for you.
Pşî weşko ye miş em arîne.
Behind the dry place... we bring it.
Xwedê emirê te dirêj bike de, seet xwaş, welle gindekî wa
xwaş e.
May God prolong your life, bless you, by God, it is such a
nice village.
Wejû efrîn da hatine?
Have they come from Afrin too?
No ne, em badînan in xoltîk.
No, no, we are from Badinan, Khaltik.
Me hat vira... xelolkê teswîr kir.
We came here... filmed the people.
Ya me hatin, ma go em vê gindî jî bisawirînin.
Since we came, we said let's film this village too.
Wa em qaçka jî kêfxweş kirin bidin.
And let's make the children happy too.
Maşallah qaçik pirn e.
Mashallah, there are many children.
Lê... mekteb çiçke... mekteb jêva... dûr e.
But... the school is small... the school is... far from
here.
Bi meşê deherin.
They go by walking.
Qaçik dehan gona.
The kid is saying ten.
Ha bi tebîetê vê gindî, hav, noka emê parçe din jî wa re
bisawirînin.
Here, with the nature of this village, summer/air, now we
will film another part for you too.
Kaş nabe, nabe, kes vira meşîno.
No one, no one, let no one walk here.
Kaş nabe, kes vira meşîno.
No one, let no one walk here.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Gind şên e, maşallah, maşallah.
The village is lively, mashallah, mashallah.
Paş to sîwî tinne tew hîlo pîde.
Behind you there is no apple, look fully behind.
Boyî? Aa. Ew belkîm vê... te dixê vê?
Really? Aa. He probably... do you want this?
Lê ke biskêwîtê bibe.
But take the biscuit.
Ke biskêwîtê bibe, ta re bikirim.
Take the biscuit, I will buy for you.
Wey bro kî min e.
Oh brother, who is mine.
Were hekê noka ta re biskêwît bikirim were. Were.
Come, I will buy a biscuit for you now, come. Come.
Were tar biskêwît bikirim were.
Come, I will buy a biscuit for you, come.
Were, were, were.
Come, come, come.
Were xorê wî ne were, xorê wî ne were. Anka em cam qaçko.
Come eat it, come, come eat it come. Now we are with the
kids.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Gindê xêr û bêr e, maşallah.
A village of blessings and abundance, mashallah.
Qaçik çaxsi kêf tikin, kêf tiken.
The children are having such fun, having fun.
Aa... min...
Aa... I...
Were ez.
Come, me.
Were, were.
Come, come.
Were te bihasibîne, heke bi qaçko dim.
Come, calculate it, look I am giving to the girl.
Ew le pşî qê pe ben, le pşî qê pe ben.
Stay behind each other, stay behind each other [in line].
Pşî qê pe ben.
Stay behind each other.
Aa.
Ax bo na no bim...
Ah, don't be for this...
Jêlî!
Jelly!
Jêlî.
Jelly.
E oş cora ba.
And that one is spicy.
Be tûrik be.
With a bag.
Hoş ta re yek. Hoş ta re di. Hene.
Here is one for you. Here is two for you. Here.
O ji min çora ba.
Give me the spicy one.
Aye xalip nobet ê tişt.
Yes, uncle, it's the turn for the thing.
Xalê min nobet ê tişt.
My nephew, it's the turn for the thing.
Hene ewil hene.
Here child, here.
Ezî bo min?
Me, for me?
Na mulo bibe, mulo bibe.
No, take it easy/quietly, take it quietly.
Ezî bo min no bî, Ezî.
There wasn't any for me, for me.
Na tagû jêlî.
No, you said jelly.
Ooo çûd bî warr o.
Here/Come on.
Ooo it went that way.
Bibe ka'ke bibe.
Take it, take the cake.
Pencî ye.
It is fifty [dinars].
Lowik dibê hekê ka'ke bibim, dilê xo ka'ke dixwaze. Hene. De
her, her mol, mas ke no.
The boy says "look I will take cake," his heart wants cake.
Here. Go, go home, don't wait.
Emî jî ta'ta. Emî jî ta'ta.
For us too, chips. For us too, chips.
Ne ta wî xwar, xolê, wî xo bir?
Didn't you eat that, man, did he take his?
Emî jî ta'ta. Emî jî ta'ta.
For us too, chips. For us too, chips.
Dar keve, dar keve.
Get out, get out [of the bag/box].
Ez na...
I didn't...
Erê welle na bir, na bir. Ko... Kê na birî ji wa? Kê na
birî?
Yes, by God, he didn't take, didn't take. Look... Who among
you didn't take? Who didn't take?
Min na bir!
I didn't take!
Kê na birî?
Who didn't take?
Emî na birî!
We didn't take!
Hane ewîl hane, bûyîna, ha, har.
Here child here, take it, here, go.
Av har tixto bibe.
Take this hard/crunchy one.
Kê, kê na birî ji wa?
Who, who among you didn't take?
Min jî na birî.
I also didn't take.
Yoş be.
Be good.
Bi hasibîne.
Calculate it.
Haştî.
[Unintelligible/Name].
Çimo... Giyorê dar dekave.
Why... It falls on the grass.
Hane ewîl.
Here child.
Ooo, ê min ta'ta.
Ooo, mine is chips.
Emî jî ta'ta. Emî jî ta'ta.
For us too chips. For us too chips.
Ta dar bixwe.
You eat outside.
Na wey xwa...
No, oh God...
Kemî na ta berî be.
Who didn't take before.
Xolê vî ber be, vî dine xalê de be.
Man, let this one take, let this other uncle give.
Hene, bibe.
Here, take it.
Mlo bibe, zîyada txer, xêr e. Ta na birî were.
Take it easy, plenty of good, it is charity. You didn't
take, come.
Yoş.
Good.
Bo min jî ta'ta.
For me too chips.
Were, boyî na birî.
Come, really you didn't take.
O xolê o yî nîskan çî na bir.
Oh man, that one with lentils [small stuff] didn't take
anything.
Yoş, yoş.
Good, good.
Em a... em agiya nakin dikanê, me'nî lowik şoş neke.
We uh... we won't empty/finish the whole shop, meaning don't
confuse the boy [shopkeeper].
Se... se di pênc.
Three... three and five.
Êta jî a vana.
This one is for these.
A ta...
And you...
Oş ta'ta.
Here is chips.
Xo kakê wa giyo dim, akê wa giyo dim. Hasib meke.
I am giving cake to all of you, giving to all of you. Don't
calculate [worry].
O bî na birî were.
Oh, the one who didn't take, come.
Har, har.
Go, go.
Yoş birbe.
Good, take it.
De qîçkê ra boy boy bikin, qîçkê ra boy boy bikin.
Come on, say bye bye to the girl, say bye bye to the girl
[camera].
Boy boy bikin.
Say bye bye.
Maşallah qîçkê vî gundî çiqas pirr in, gundî kî çûçik e
qeçax têt de pirr in.
Mashallah, how many children are in this village, it's a
small village but there are many kids in it.
Maşallah maşallah.
Mashallah mashallah.
Hûn diçine mektebê lê ne?
Do you go to school or not?
Hûn bixwînin, şatir bin, nexlê tîjîkî wêra bimra (bînim).
You should study, be clever, and I will bring you a small
palm tree.
Heke biderê hediyê mezin we re tînim.
If it grows, I will bring you a big gift.
Ê wekî şatir be heke nexlê de lî'b ke... ew na mezin î ne.
Uh, act clever, if you play in the palm tree... no, that one
is big.
Tu dixwînî?
Do you study?
Maşallah. Na rê?
Mashallah. No way?
Re wada, de nê re wada, re wada. Ka ez nê ko, wes seknê
nebirin jêr o bibim.
Go that way, come on go that way, go that way. Where am I...
stop, don't take the stand down so I can take it.
Are saeta giya xweş. Xwedê wekî dibê berqeda...
Yes, a good time to you all. As God says, blessing...
...malê me li bal we ke. Pirr tiştekî besîte, yanê ne...
...make our home with you. It is a very simple thing,
meaning not...
...milo qeçax xor û kefxweş bibin. Yanê bûş e, îş kî bûş e.
...people and kids be happy and joyful. Meaning it is
plenty, a plentiful job.
Em jî çûçik bûn, em jî holê bûn. Yekî tiştek me ra bikira em
pirr kefxweş dibûn.
We were small too, we were like that too. If someone did
something for us, we would be very happy.
Yanê qîmetê xo tine, tiştekî wekî... saeta we giya xweş.
Meaning it has no value, something like... good time to you
all.
Xwedê iştekir (işte) bile'kis xolti ma tiştek nekir, hîn me
ye pirr bikira...
God willing, on the contrary, auntie, we didn't do anything,
we should have done more...
...ê ko ê xayo... me hesavê xo jî nekiribû, saeta giya xweş
û...
...oh well... we hadn't calculated for it either, good time
to you all and...
Her kes e'n malê xo sor e. Sor e sor e, here.
Everyone to their own homes, go ahead. Go ahead, go ahead,
go.
Maşallah. Me gundî xelol kir jî, me qîçkarokirî, erê welle.
Mashallah. We disturbed the village too, we gathered the
kids, yes by God.
Me hesav jî nekiribû, me ye hîn tiştê mezin wê re bikira ne,
me ye kefxweş kiribû da, ê ko... helqe hewnabî.
We hadn't calculated, we would have done bigger things for
them, we would have made them happy, oh well... the episode
wasn't like that.
Erê welle. Jorê ta werim, heke werim la'b... la'bik o înim
ha.
Yes by God. I will come up to you, if I come play... I'll
bring a toy, okay.
Heke gel la'biko hem mektebê xo, xwendina xo saken, gel
la'bê werim.
If with the toy, also fix your school and your studying,
I'll come with the toy.
Harin, gûle gûle, gûle gûle, harin.
Go, bye bye, bye bye, go.
Qîmetê dek bafkê xo zanibin ha, qîmetê...
Know the value of your parents okay, the value of...
...dara o ye. Tayar e.
...that tree. It's ready.
Yaro serê... suretê me reş neynin (neînin). Na na...
Friend, head of... don't make my face black (on camera). No
no...
Xoltîk dibê suretê me reş neke, bogo xoltîk te...
The auntie says don't make my face black, I say auntie
you...
...erê welle.
...yes by God.
Gundî kî zor xweş e dar e.
It is a very nice village with trees.
Bê dar e jêrî me jî, terba ne (triba ne).
It's treeless, below us is the cemetery.
Bê dar e, Ehme... xol gîyake zor e te biro.
It's treeless, Ahme... a lot of grass that takes you away.
Te bi mal ne, wane poşiya hene.
(Unclear) homes not, they have turbans.
Maşallah qîçkê vî gundî çiqas pirr in he?
Mashallah, how many children are in this village, huh?
Maşallah Xwedê giyo bêle.
Mashallah, may God keep them.
Vê gundo qîçik pirr kirine, işta ewana qîçka pirr bikin,
rind e.
This village has made many children, look, they make many
children, it's good.
Vê her yek deh'a panzika bîne.
Each one should bring ten or fifteen.
Bet (bese) min go... germe peke...
Enough, I said... make it hot...
...ca ew na germ ke, kî xor derketin ber ro ye.
...wow, don't let the weather get hot, when the sun came
out.
Me eklek jî qîçikan ra kirîn, ê maşallah kûm bûn.
We bought some food/treats for the kids, and mashallah they
gathered.
Esas sê çar qîçik tenê bûn, paşê bûn kûm bûn serê me, ma
biner.
Basically there were only three or four kids, then they
gathered on top of us, just look.
Maşallah. Xwedê emrê giya dirêj bike, giya dê...
Mashallah. May God lengthen all their lives, all of them...
Bê bimin zîk ra.
Come with me quickly.
Saet xweş.
Cheers / Good time.
(Muzîk)
(Music)
Erê hevalno, îro em hatin ba gogê dileyizin.
Yes friends, today we came to where they are playing
football.
Ê, ê, ê!
Hey, hey, hey!
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Dinya germik e?
Is the weather warm?
Dinya germik e, qeçik kêf dikin.
The weather is warm, the kids are having fun.
Lo molo gola neke, gola heyma... lêxe!
Hey man don't score a goal, goal... kick it!
Lêxe!
Kick it!
Bave, bave, bave, bave!
Throw it, throw it, throw it, throw it!
Maşallah... îîî!
Mashallah... eee!
Kî xwarziyê min e?
Who is my nephew here?
De bave!
Come on, throw it!
Were!
Come!
Ê, ê!
Hey, hey!
Ya qeçikê me gerok in... yo yo yo.
Our kids are wandering... oh oh oh.
Ê, ê, gol! Gol!
Hey, hey, goal! Goal!
Gol, gol, gol!
Goal, goal, goal!
Yek sifr e!
One nil!
Bar mada, bar mada!
Don't put it out, don't put it out!
Ax xwarziyê xwe fisa kir.
Oh, my nephew missed/messed it up.
Cero, lîstikvanên gogê dileyizin û cografiya...
Jaro, the players are playing football and the geography...
Alîkî dorekî ecnebî bome hewa pîs xweş bikim.
Like a foreign environment, let me make the weather very
nice.
Dabar gogê ro... gog bi xwedê riyad e.
About the football... football is truly exercise.
De bave!
Come on, throw it!
Ê, ê!
Hey, hey!
Lêxe!
Kick it!
Maşallah!
Mashallah!
Ez ê teqînim, wî bifirînim.
I will blast it, I will make it fly.
Ê, lêxe seriyê xwe lêxe!
Hey, hit it, hit it with your head!
Seriyê xwe lêxe!
Hit it with your head!
Kat xwar, kat xwar.
He fell down, he fell down.
Bave de bave!
Throw it, come on throw it!
Bes hewa germ e kin.
But the weather is getting hot.
Lêxe!
Kick it!
Wala gart, wala gart!
By God hard, by God hard!
Lêxe!
Kick it!
Lo lêxe!
Hey, kick it!
Lêxe!
Kick it!
Gog pir xweş e rinda.
The ball is very nice, good.
Ê nuko golekê dikin.
Now they are scoring a goal.
Wala bibînin lîbe, rind dileyize.
By God look at the player, he plays well.
Babo ooo!
Oh father, ooh!
Gola min lidare... nabe... gola tekin.
My goal is happening... no... they are scoring.
Çûbî ya?
Did it go out?
La jîte mir de, lêxe!
No, it died from you [you lost it], kick it!
Eş te me... eger golekê têke mi yê...
From you... if he scores a goal against me...
Wala rinde ha.
By God it's good, huh.
Ûne!
Look there!
Lêxe, lêxe, lêxe.
Kick it, kick it, kick it.
Maşallah qeçik sivik in.
Mashallah the kids are light [fast].
Maşallah!
Mashallah!
Ez nikanim gogê jê bistînim.
I can't take the ball from him.
Ez ê em kûlik hatê kim ê.
I will make a move coming here.
Gol!
Goal!
Ah rehet bîm.
Ah, I'm exhausted.
Qeçik sivik in, ez jî rehet bîm.
The kids are fast, I got exhausted.
Erê hevalno.
Yes friends.
Taban li vî darê.
Basically at this place.
Em gihîştin dawiya vîdyo xwe.
We reached the end of our video.
Saet wekî ya xweş.
A good time.
Taqsîr meqsîrê hene li me qusûrê ef bikin.
If there are shortcomings, forgive our faults.
Ez ji mêj de nalîstime.
I haven't played in a long time.
Û hereket in ê, hereket.
And it's movements, movements.
Hebe rinde.
It is good.
Gog jê bi xwedê riyad e.
Football is truly exercise by God.
Em çûçik bûn, em jî wina dileyîstin gundî me.
When we were small, we also played like this in our village.
Derke nefes li min qut bû.
Look, my breath is cut off.
Sobe min kûkûl kirin.
Because... [unintelligible, possibly regarding running].
Erê hevalno vî darê, em gihîştin dawiya vîdyo xwe, boy boy
bikin, boy boy bikin.
Yes friends, at this place, we reached the end of our video,
say bye bye, say bye bye.
Goga me jî ev e.
And this is our ball.
Misawirê min jî panê lêxe.
My cameraman is also kicking [filming] it.
De yalla boy boy. Bi marê min vîdyo kê de min xweş, kîbar em
inşallah we radoxin.
Come on, bye bye. With my wish, a good video, polite,
hopefully we will see you.
Kes golek da tenê, ez golek xwa jî têkime.
Nobody scored a goal, I will score a goal myself.
De yalla bi xatire we, boy boy. Saeta we xweş.
Come on, goodbye, bye bye. Have a good time.
Evana riyadî bûn ha.
These were athletic guys, huh.
Boy boy.
Bye bye.
(Muzîk)
(Music)