Walo kûrî ve belxur bî?
Uncle, was this bulgur?
Erê belxur da.
Yes, it was bulgur.
Milet êdî genim diçîne.
The people are planting wheat now.
Genim diçînin wa...
They are planting wheat...
Na va genim kî...
No, this wheat...
Erê em rayan jêdkin... saet sê dused û pêncî misqal e.
Yes, we are removing the weeds... at three o'clock, it is
two hundred and fifty misqals.
Ev Muxter, feqîr ti nema baki re deyne.
This Mukhtar, the poor guy, has nothing left to put in the
storage.
Emi nanê cehirin... nanê genim tînin...
We eat barley bread... they bring wheat bread...
Kanê qestel heye?
Where is the spring?
Li wir duma qestel e.
Behind there is the spring.
Gunda ki... di hode veder ke... babê xwedê berê mal ke ha...
The village... separate it there... by God, facing the
house...
Wê meqter fokte me betir erdê...
That place [unintelligible] more ground...
Milet pê setirî bî.
People were sustained by it.
Lê nuke teqrîben hişk buye maalesef.
But now, unfortunately, it has approximately dried up.
Erê dileyî ava...
Yes, the water flow...
Îstîmal dikir ebu?
Did they use to use it?
Ebu... teqrîben di sala heştî û pêncî da me îstîmal dikir.
Yes... approximately in the year eighty-five we used to use
it.
Heştî û pêncî?
Eighty-five?
Hezar nehsed heştî û pêncî da wilo.
Nineteen eighty-five, like that.
Paşê motor derketin, motor danîn...
Then engines came out, they installed engines...
Erê dînya hadîs bû.
Yes, the world became modern.
Xerab bî. Sê çar xerab bûn...
It got ruined. Three or four got ruined...
Di gelî da...
In the valley...
Bê mentiq e.
It is illogical.
Li Balkana sê çar xerab bûn.
In Balkana [area name] three or four were ruined.
Mago emê herin gundê Olkano, ez û kekê Mesûd va, emê gundê
Olkano teswîr kin.
Friends, as we said we will go to the village of Olkano, me
and brother Masoud, we will film the village of Olkano.
Maşallah gundekî pir xweş e.
Mashallah, it is a very nice village.
Hewayekî pir xweş e, hewayekî gundekî delal e.
It is very nice weather, the atmosphere of a beautiful
village.
Emê nuke herin nav gundê Olkano, ale emê gundê Olkano wer
teswîr kin.
We will now go inside the village of Olkano, come let's film
the village of Olkano.
Ala gundekî çawa ye, çi karî dikin, çi îşî dikin, hela
derbaz bin maro.
Let's see how the village is, what work they do, what jobs
they do, let's proceed friends.
Erê cemaatê şirîn, vîdyoya me her wekî gundê Olkano ye.
Yes sweet community, our video is just like the village of
Olkano.
Lê berî em derbasî gund bibin, like û îştîrak û te'lîqek
xweş ji me ra yazê kin.
But before we enter the village, write a like, a
subscription, and a nice comment for us.
Bo gundî dîdevan hun kedara dixwazin.
For the villagers [viewers], wherever you want [us to go].
Emê nuke derbasî gund bibin, emêş gund rengekî xweş pêşwa
kin.
We will now enter the village, we will also present the
village in a nice way.
Ka bi me ra bin heta dawî vîdeo bibînin.
Stay with us until you see the end of the video.
[Music Playing - Instrumental]
Erê cemaat silav û rêz, em di şînin ji we ra, ji ortê gundê
Olkano.
Yes community, greetings and respect, we send to you, from
the middle of the village of Olkano.
Lê em derbasî gund bûn, em mîvan darê Muxter bîn.
We have entered the village, we are the guests of the
Mukhtar.
Emê nuke wanoskê rên bidin Muxter.
We will now give the microphone to the Mukhtar.
Hela kî ye û navê xwa çi ye.
Let's see who he is and what his name is.
Ê ji me ra xeber de ser gund û ser turasê gund.
And he will talk to us about the village and the heritage of
the village.
Lê silav em dişînin ji miletê Olkano ra, miletekî pir delal
e.
But we send greetings to the people of Olkano, they are very
lovely people.
Miletekî pir kîbar e.
They are very noble people.
Ê li xurbetê em didin silavî me ji we ra hene.
And to those in exile/diaspora, we give our greetings to
you.
Lê ka nuke em wanoskê rên bidin Muxter.
But come now, let's give the microphone to the Mukhtar.
Muxter merheba ji te re.
Mukhtar, hello to you.
Ahlen wa sehlen, elo bi we ra.
Welcome, hello to you.
Tu bi xêr hatî, ser çava.
You are welcome, upon my eyes.
Elhemdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Keyfa te xweş e, siheta te xweş e?
Is your mood good, is your health good?
Elhemdulillah, şukir ji Xwedê re.
Praise be to God, thanks to God.
De rehet be inşallah.
May you be comfortable, God willing.
Lê Muxter xêra te be, navê te bi xêr çi ye?
Praise be to God.
So Mukhtar, all the best to you, what is your good name?
Erê cemîla el xêr, û Feysel Muxterê gund im.
Yes, beautiful goodness [phrase], and I am Feysel, the
Mukhtar of the village.
Ahla wa sehla ji we ra, em bi hatina we kêfxweş bîn, bawer
bin weletê me.
Welcome to you, we were happy with your arrival, believe in
our country.
Gundî me yane bişerînin û alem zane bêhna Olkano li ku ye.
Our village, that is, they are sweet and the world knows
where the scent of Olkano is.
Erê saeta te xweş.
Yes, bless you (nice hour).
Xweş halê te zêde be.
May your well-being increase.
Lê Muxter navê te bi xêr te hewal neda.
But Mukhtar, you didn't say your good name.
Min hewal da.
I gave the news (said it).
Lê Cemîla el xêr...
But [you said] "Cemîla el xêr"...
Û Feysel.
And Feysel.
Feysel, erê ser çava mamoste.
Feysel, yes, upon my eyes master (sir).
Emrê te bi xêr?
Your age?
Emrê min şêst e.
My age is sixty.
Xwedê emrekî dirêj inşallah xalê min.
God grant a long life, God willing, my uncle.
Saxbî.
Be healthy.
Xalê min em derbasî gundê Olkano bîn.
My uncle, we have entered the village of Olkano.
Lê berî vîyê kû destpêkê ji me ra hewal de û xeber de, milet
jî zane be Olkano navê gund ji ku hatiye.
But before this, first give us the news and speak, so the
people know where the name of Olkano village comes from.
Olkano ji berê paşê da... navekî gundekî qedîm e, gundekî
pir qedîm e.
Olkano, from way back... is a name of an ancient village, a
very ancient village.
Û menase navê Olkano yane pir nizanim Olkano dibên çiye,
menase xwa yane... kûr e.
And the meaning of the name Olkano, that is, I don't know
much what they say Olkano is, its meaning is... deep.
Olkan.
Dibê Olkanî yane.
Yes.
It says Olkani, that is.
Erê.
Yes.
Yane walo kurmancî ye ev.
That is, it is Kurdish like that.
Yane menase xwa ye... û şebîbê gundî... îşte zîraetê daxil
in.
Yes.
Yane menase xwa ye... û şebîbê gundî... îşte zîraetê daxil
in.
That is, it has its meaning... and the youth of the
village... well, they are into agriculture.
Xalê min gundî çi diçînin?
My uncle, what do the villagers plant?
Gundî çi diçînin, berê dexil mexil hebû wey şo nema, ma
xwestîbî.
What the villagers plant... before there were grain crops
and such, now no more, it wasn't desired [anymore].
Erê.
Yes.
Yane baran barî nakê teş nobe, bes zeytûn e.
That is, it doesn't rain, nothing happens, it's just olives.
Haliya nîsba zeytûna alemê giş şewitîn.
Currently, regarding the olives, everyone's [trees] all
burned/froze.
Erê.
Yes.
Şewt... îşte ev bî ye.
Burned... that's what happened.
Yane xalê min tenê bi zîraetê de dijîn?
That is, my uncle, they live only by agriculture?
Zîraeta xwa îşte bes zeytûn e, xêrî zeytûnê teş livir nobe,
berê gûz dibûn, mişmiş hebûn...
Their agriculture is just olives, other than olives nothing
happens here, before there were walnuts, there were
apricots...
Lo sêv hebûn, xêr bêr berê pir bûn, bes haliya nema ne.
And there were apples, the bounty was plenty before, but
currently they are gone.
Deh sal hişkayî bî, baran tayê qurban Xwedê bin... ev wa bî
ye.
For ten years it was dry, rain is up to the sacrifice for
God [God's will]... this is how it happened.
Xwedê el me warê rehmê.
May God bring us mercy.
Amîn.
Amen.
Lê xalê min çiqas mal li vî gundî heye?
So my uncle, how many households are in this village?
Gundê me teqrîben şêst heftê mal e.
Our village is approximately sixty, seventy households.
Şêst heftê mal e.
Sixty, seventy households.
Silav û rêz em dişînin ji gundî yara, gişî rêz û hurmeta ne
xalê min.
I see.
Silav û rêz em dişînin ji gundî yara, gişî rêz û hurmeta ne
xalê min.
Greetings and respect we send to the villagers, all respect
and honor to them my uncle.
Teşê xweş.
Good thing.
Xalê min mago milet bi zîraetê, ta kîjan topî em bibên...
sînaet tune.
My uncle, as you said the people [live] by agriculture, up
to what point should we say... there is no industry.
Sînaet tune li gunda tune begê min.
Industry does not exist in the villages, my sir.
Gund neyî mezin e, tune.
The village is not big, there isn't any.
Bes zîraet e.
Just agriculture.
Ziro çî ye, Xwedê rizqê ciyan bişîne inşallah.
Yes, just agriculture.
Whatever crops there are, may God send provision to
everyone, God willing.
Xalê min gundê Olkano me got kareba, av, ev tiştan mutefer
e?
My uncle, the village of Olkano, as we said, electricity,
water, are these things available?
Welle kareba berê gelek hebû... da çend sal in derge xera
bûn.
Well, electricity used to be plentiful... for a few years
the stations have been ruined.
Heye beharbe yane îş ev kir, ne kebil man û ne teş man.
There is, due to war, meaning this work did it, no cables
remained and nothing remained.
Û bê hal kareba giş ser taqa ma ko deşxilînin.
Yes.
And the situation of electricity, everything operates on
solar energy now.
Nuke milet karebayê dikanê, mal ser taqa dişxilînin.
Now the people operate electricity for shops and homes on
solar energy.
Ser taqa ma ko ne, kareba ne maye.
It's on solar energy, electricity is gone.
Na maye.
Whatever the crops/situation is.
It is gone.
Ziro çî ye, lê xalê min av?
Whatever the situation is, but my uncle, water?
Av e çê dikin, hekire halê çê dikin.
Water, they are fixing it, if they fix the situation.
Ê ware inşallah ê ware.
Yeah.
It will come, God willing, it will come.
Ê ziro çî ye inşallah ê ware.
Whatever the situation is, God willing it will come.
Lê xalê min Olkano, gundê Olkano, tiştê tûrasî, bi çima
meşhûr e?
But my uncle, Olkano, the village of Olkano, historical
things, what is it famous for?
Çi têda heye?
What is in it?
Xwedê tiştê tûrasî, berê Olkano bi xwo, yelî reqsê da derece
ûla bî.
By God, historical things, in the past Olkano itself, in
terms of dancing [folk dance], it was first class.
Ma'rûf bî li mentiqa Efrîn gişî da ma'rûf bî.
It was famous in the entire Afrin region, it was famous.
Kurmanc bi şekl am walo...
Yes.
Kurds in general like that...
Ê walo, Olkano bi zor.
Yes like that, Olkano strongly.
Yane dawetê gundî me dibûn gumitirê... nas kena ewnan nas
kena, şefeq berê da firqê gunda bî, dera bî.
Yeah.
Yane dawetê gundî me dibûn gumitirê... nas kena ewnan nas
kena, şefeq berê da firqê gunda bî, dera bî.
That is, the weddings of our village were booming...
[people] know them, [people] know them, at dawn usually
there was a village troupe, there was a circle.
Erê.
Yes.
Yane meşhûr e bî ev gundo wekî.
That is, this village was famous like that.
Erê.
Whatever the situation is.
Yes.
Xwedê saeta xweş ke.
God grant a good time.
Soolkî ji xalê xwo pirs kem.
Let me ask a question to my uncle.
Gundî we taba kîjan nahiyê ye?
Which district does your village belong to?
Gundî me taba Şiyê ye.
Our village belongs to Shiye [Shaykh al-Hadid].
Taba Şiyê ye.
It belongs to Shiye.
Şiyê pir ji vir va dûr e?
Is Shiye very far from here?
Teqrîben deh donzdeh kîlometre ne.
Approximately ten, twelve kilometers.
Deh donzdeh kîlometre.
Ten, twelve kilometers.
Yane îdarî yênun taba Şiyê ne.
That is, administratively you belong to Shiye.
Taba Şiyê ne.
We belong to Shiye.
Ê ziro çî ye.
Whatever the situation is.
Xalê min terbî gundê we li kune?
My uncle, where is the education/upbringing of your village
[located/how is it]?
Bê gundî me qedîm e ne pir, li sê ciya ne.
Look, our village is ancient, not very, they are in three
places.
Xerbî gunda ne, û şerqî gunda ne.
West of the village, and east of the village.
Û kaniyê gundî me jî hemîne, hene sekin li wa mîn heker
hal...
And the spring of our village is also there, there are
residents staying there if the situation...
Qestel heye?
Is there a spring?
Erê tûrasî pir ji mêj e.
There is a spring.
Yes, historical, very old.
Qestelî zemanê Îngilîz derxist.
The spring that was brought out in the time of the English.
Qestel li kîderê ye xalo?
Where is the spring, uncle?
Yano xerbî gunda, me ne nado kamerê.
It is west of the village, we haven't given it to the camera
[shown it yet].
De nuke emê ba herin inşallah.
So now we will go to it, God willing.
Saet xweş xwedê iş te razî be.
Bless you, may God be pleased with you.
Lê nuke bi me ra bin, xalî me ye nuke em nav gund bigerînin.
But now stay with us, our uncle is here, now we will tour
inside the village.
Ci... cîran, ev me begîne.
Pl... place, he will take us to this place.
Û emê peşwe kin, sûryetekî xweş.
And we will present, a nice image.
Lê li vir jî xalê min jî heye.
But here implies my uncle is also here.
Em wanoskê rên bidin, hela xalê min kî ye. Xalê min merheba
ji te re.
We will give him the microphone, let's see who my uncle is.
My uncle, hello to you.
Ahlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Tu bi xêr hatî şale?
Are you well/welcome?
Bi xêr hatî ser çava, dê rehetî, hemdulillah şukir ji Xwedê
re.
Welcome, upon my eyes, are you comfortable, praise be to
God, thanks to God.
Saet xweş.
Bless you.
Xalê min em qenatê Efrîn Vlo, em li gunda digerin.
My uncle, we are Afrin Vlo channel, we are touring the
villages.
Bi rengekî xweş.
In a nice way.
Em peş milet dikin.
We present to the people.
Miletê heye li Ewrupa em bibên, li xurbetê ye.
There are people in Europe let's say, in exile.
Qçkê gunda, gundê xwo nedîne.
The children of the village, they haven't seen their
village.
Bixwo jî bîra gundê xwo kirî, lê em vê karî dikin bi rengekî
xweş tevî çibê hekî ro.
They themselves also miss their village, so we do this work
in a nice way, whatever happens today.
Te divê çi bêjî hekî ro?
What do you want to say today?
Saetê wa xweş pir in dewa le, însanî li der va.
Your hours are very good indeed [bless you], the people
outside.
Yane...
That is...
Gundet xwo bibînin di televîzyon da.
Seeing their villages on television.
Bibînin bêrê xwo.
Seeing their homes/places.
Inşallah yane giştê ware biftirin ser kesb gundê xwo.
Yes.
God willing, that is, everything comes so that everyone
returns to their village.
Inşallah.
God willing.
Mentiqê me pir, mentiqê xweş û rind û zeviyê xwo, yane pir
rind e.
Our region is very, a nice and beautiful region and its
fields, that is, it is very beautiful.
Xwedê selmetêkê bide.
May God give safety.
Bi ardê giştekî yane ne bes em tenê.
To the whole land, that is, not just us alone.
Amîn ya reb.
Amen, oh Lord.
Silmetê ji gişî re xalê min.
Safety to everyone, my uncle.
Erê wella, alem hemûyê dixwazin, teb'en alem hemûyê
dixwazin.
Yes by God, the whole world wants it, naturally the whole
world wants it.
Amîn ya reb.
Bless you.
Amen, oh Lord.
Lê xalê min dewr da me pirs nekir navê te bi xêr çi ye?
But my uncle, back then we didn't ask, what is your good
name?
Navê min... Yûsif e.
My name... is Yûsif.
Aslê min ji gundê Xelîl e, bra gundê me, gundê Xelîl û
Olkano teqrîben gişt yek in.
My origin is from the village of Xelîl, brother, our
village, the village of Xelîl and Olkano are approximately
all one.
Erê zaten zêran û binerd yek in.
Yes, actually the land and the subsoil are one.
Lê xocê, gundê Xelîl im û, vê gundî me, yane xocê hez dikim
gundê xwo.
But the Hodja [teacher/elder], I am from Xelîl village and,
this village of ours, that is, the Hodja loves his village.
Wiy saetê te xweş.
Oh, bless you.
Ê men, el Şamê bîm berê yane, vê ezmê da hatim xwedê dizanî,
pî şeş heft sal walla.
And me, I was in Damascus before that is, I came during this
crisis God knows, for six, seven years by God.
Ê ziro çî ye.
Whatever the situation is.
Û hekê biftirim Şamê warim, em li wir bîn û li wir mezin bîn
û, zarokê me li wir in, neqişkê me li wir in.
And if I return to Damascus to come back, we were there and
grew up there and, our children are there, our little ones
are there.
Erê.
Yes.
E însan pîr risqê xwo digere yane, risqê maro li ku be, maro
li wir e xalê min.
Well, a human seeks their provision that is, wherever one's
provision is, one is there, my uncle.
Sehiye.
Correct.
Tengiya min heye... qelebê min kirine... şebek.
So what is your ailment?
I have tightness [shortness of breath]... they operated on
my heart... stent/mesh.
Selametiya xwo, şîfayê bixwazî Xwedê yê mezin.
Your safety, may you ask for healing from the Great God.
Saxbî mamoste, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Be healthy master, may God be pleased with you.
Saxbî.
Be healthy.
Ez me'nî xudê, zi'îf im welle, ku çê gund tune bî, terefî
min kirin a hatim.
I mean by God, I am weak by God, if there hadn't been anyone
in the village, they directed me and I came.
Ê ziro çî ye, saeta te xweş.
Whatever the situation is, bless you.
Şeş heft sal, heşt sal li xurbetê bîm.
Six, seven years, eight years I was in exile.
Saet xweş, Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide xalê min, û saeta te xweş
kekê min.
Bless you, may God give a long life my uncle, and bless you
my brother.
Saet xweş.
Bless you.
[Music Starts - Song "Sewda Sewda"]
Erê wekî me gotî, em hatin orta gund, lê li vir jî Delîb
heye.
Yes as we said, we came to the middle of the village, but
here implies Delîb is also here.
Delîb jî kevindor e.
Delîb is also an old-timer.
Emê nuke ji Muxter pirs kin, hela emrê gund çiye?
We will now ask the Mukhtar, let's see what is the age of
the village?
Û pê çi karî dikirin ko me ra bêjin.
And what work they used to do so he can tell us.
Emrê vê derê bê teqrîben hema bi çi qas sal da ye?
My uncle...
Approximately how many years old is this place?
Sed, sed û bîst û pênc salan.
One hundred, one hundred and twenty-five years.
Ev dera... bo ard û koton.
This place... for flour and cotton.
Zaman da?
Back in the day?
Zaman da, berê ard û koton... na zaman da, deh sal e ne
xirabî ye.
Back in the day, before flour and cotton... no back in the
day, it's not been ruined for ten years.
Yekî Ermenî tanî xirab kirine. Pê ev dikutan, dînî kutan, ya
dara geba heye...
An Armenian came and ruined them. They used to pound with
this, pound grains, there is a large wooden tool...
Bitûmê tê dixistin dikutan.
They put seeds in it and pounded them.
Belê, noq...
Yes, chickpeas...
Hemû korî vê... bulxur bû.
All of this... became bulgur.
Miletê gund gişt dihatin vira?
Did all the village people come here?
Belê gund gi bûn.
Yes, the whole village.
Emrê yê nêzîkî sed, sed û bîst û pênc salan e.
Its age is nearly one hundred, one hundred and twenty-five
years.
Gund gi bûn.
The whole village was here.
Ê Muxtar, noka em têne ber ku derê lê?
So Mukhtar, where are we coming to now?
Kanî gotî me ye.
It's the spring I told you about.
Qestel e ye.
A spring?
It is a cistern.
Li ber dêmê qestel.
At the face of the cistern.
Erê.
Yes.
Ê meşê, kevn e ew jî?
Walking... is it old too?
Kevn dar e.
It is ancient.
Erê, lê ka em herin bin, emê kaniyê jî seh kin Muxtar, ka em
herin bin.
Yes, let's go down, we will look at the spring too Mukhtar,
let's go down.
Ka? Na tirs tiron nîne.
Where? No, there is no fear or danger.
Baş e, xalê min, ko vederkê ev çiye vir?
Okay, my uncle, what is this place here?
Ev mal e, berê ev tijî jimej, evê Ermeniya dar û veder û
hewş bûn.
This is a house, before it was full of livestock, the
Armenians had trees and places and courtyards here.
Kesê nizanîbigirta lê?
No one could take it?
Ev hewşê Ermeniya girtin.
They occupied these Armenian courtyards.
Evê berê wana digirtin, malqab û...
They used to occupy these before, properties and...
Çiqab o çêkirin.
How they built them.
Belê noka Îstemo nabe ne?
But now Istanbul doesn't work, right?
Wele Xwedê... Îstembol dad bar û îro...
By God... Istanbul gave up and today...
Segen nîzamê xantermê wa... Şeb aba bere ştekil bûn rûniştin
xwarin.
Look at the system of their construction... At night they
sat and ate in this manner.
Vir cihê rûniştinê bû?
Was this a sitting place?
Xwarin û rûniştin...
Eating and sitting...
Pir kevnar e ev hewşa wekî wa dîye cimeet.
This courtyard is very ancient, as you have seen folks.
Binê heta ke î girtî, evê çoqçikê...
Look until it is closed, these small marks...
Ev nîşanek e ji xora çêkiriye ne?
This is a mark they made for themselves, right?
Ev nîşanê genda no...
These marks of the villages...
Nîşanê ê vê hewşê girtine?
Marks of those who occupied this courtyard?
Erê.
Yes.
[Music]
Erê xalê min, ev çal vederkê, ev kîjan me ra xeber de?
Yes my uncle, this hole here, tell us about this one?
Ev jî tiştek kanyek bun, bîr e, ge diten vederê av dibirin.
This was also something like a spring, a well, they came
here and took water.
Şînî, gunî, seherî, mahrî, şitil mitil diçandin berê.
Greenery, sacks, mornings, hoes, they planted seedlings
before.
Tev xûl...
All soil...
Dîrektor tune bûn. Pê dihatin ji ber betan e ko...
There were no tractors. They came on foot because of the
animals...
...û dewêr dibirin mal, betan e kê.
...and took the animals home, by foot.
Yanî gund gi ser vê bîrê bûn?
So the whole village was dependent on this well?
Gund gi ser vê bîrê bûn.
The whole village was dependent on this well.
Bîra Olkana ku der e?
Where is the well of Olkana?
Bîra Olkana va ye.
Here is the well of Olkana.
Berê qedîm e.
It is ancient from the past.
Xalê vederkê, heta niha...
Uncle, this place, until now...
Em dibêjin mesela yek mir de.
We say for example one died in it.
Na, em gavinê lê hacer ne?
No, we are stepping on stone?
E hecer ne, tebîetê wan... şiye salan e ev cî.
Yes stone, their nature... this place is six hundred years
old.
Erê, yanî hecer mirîye w'a...
Yes, so the stone has died like that...
Zivir bûye dişike.
It has become rotten, it breaks.
Tînekî berde.
Give it a kick.
Lê xalê vederkê, heq bûye vala bibe?
But uncle, this place, has it rightfully become empty?
Ewa herimî, berê işta av dereqitîre...
It is ruined, before water used to drip...
...dereqitî dero di bîrê ketiye, dereqitî...
...dripped into the well, dripped...
Yê avê sol bi sol gi da ron hişk bûye?
The water year by year all dried up?
Sol bi sol gi da ron hişk bûye.
Year by year it all dried up.
Erê welle, wekî wa dîye cimeet, ev vira kevnar e.
Yes by God, as you have seen folks, this place is ancient.
Emrê wê çiqas hebe teqrîben?
How much is its age approximately?
Walla sed, du sed sal heye.
By God, there is one hundred, two hundred years.
Yanî bine va cî cî lê dikê, ku kişandina tê ra, ku bi
zincîra û dêla dikişandin.
I mean look at the spots on it, where the pulling marks are,
where they pulled with chains and buckets.
Kevn dar miletê gund...
Ancient, the village people...
Lê ne berê li mala da bîr, birkê der tune bûn.
But before in the houses there were no wells, no wells out
there.
Tune bûn, sarinc tune bûn.
There weren't, there were no cisterns.
Erê, hino tune bûn, hino nebû ev o mala.
Yes, those didn't exist, those weren't in the houses.
Milet dihat vederkê?
The people came here?
Miletê gund, tevayî, dihat ser vê bîrê.
The village people, entirely, came to this well.
Avê xwa dibir, milkê xwa...
Took their water, their animals...
Ê heywanê xwa, ê kinc şûştin...
Their animals, washing clothes...
...kanî şûştin, lê kinc şûştin.
...washing at the spring, yes washing clothes.
Hino li ber gelîyê diçû, vederê, berber û me diçû bîrê mal.
Some went to the valley, here, and we went to the house
well.
Yanî sibê êvarê av pê dihat, avê xwarin bî.
Meaning morning and evening water came via it, it was
drinking water.
Sehet û xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Health and happiness, may God be pleased with you.
Wekî me gotî, gund berê, zamandekî...
As we said, the village before, in a time...
...dawet vederkê...
...weddings here...
Avê xwa dibir, milkê xwa, û weadê xwarin...
Took their water, their livestock, and eating time...
Yanî milet pê sitirî bî.
Meaning the people were sustained by it.
Lê noka teqrîben hişk bûye me'lesef?
But now approximately it has dried up unfortunately?
Noka... e tî de av heye.
Now... eh there is water in it.
Heye hindik e?
There is a little?
Gemar ketiye.
Dirt has fallen in.
Kanî jî ver hebiye me got?
The spring was also here we said?
Ew jî hişk bûye sol... çike baro kêm e.
That also dried up year... because rain is scarce.
Lê xalê min, ka noka têne ber ku derê lê?
But my uncle, where are we coming to now?
Ka emrê binerin.
Let's look at the age.
Qestel e gundî ye.
It is the village cistern.
Ew jî qedîm e.
That is also ancient.
Ka em hinekî seh kin, qestel çiye, manê çiye, ka em herin
bin.
Let's look a bit, what is a cistern, what is the meaning,
let's go down.
[Music]
De erê cimeeta şîrîn, vîdyûya me ro gundê Olkana bî.
Yes sweet folks, our video today was Olkana village.
Maşallah Muxtar, zilamekî xweş, meriv hûrdike...
Mashallah Mukhtar, a nice man, explains to people...
...di kefê pişî me, tiştnê xweş dîtine.
...behind us, we saw nice things.
De ya noka em hatin cîkî, vederkê av nîhay e.
So now we came to a place, here there is water finally.
Ka Muxtarê ji me ra hewal de...
Let the Mukhtar tell us...
...ela ev çiye, û navê vî çiye.
...what is this, and what is its name.
Muxtar, ela ev çiye ji me ra mehs bike?
Mukhtar, explain what this is to us?
Ka ev bîra hawal de?
Tell about this well?
Ewa qestel e, di mabênê du gunda, gundê me û gundê Hecî
Belî...
This is a cistern, between two villages, our village and
Hecî Belî village...
Hecî Belî Sêgundo yî.
Hecî Belî of Segundo.
Yanî ev a pird zeman dar in?
So these are very old?
Zemanî Rûm, mûm li veder nebûn.
Time of the Romans, candles were not here.
Ewa di kevirî... gindir... o belê...
This in the stone... rolling... yes...
Ewa qedîm e.
It is ancient.
Ne hecer e.
It is not stone.
Işta, berê gund bîstan veder na hebûn?
So, before did the village have gardens here?
De re bûn, ev sal jî av heye, te hî dînê qet tine av.
They were there, this year there is water too, you saw there
is no water at all elsewhere.
Ere, yanî xalê min, ev ava vexwarinê bû?
Yes, so my uncle, was this drinking water?
Bo xwarinê?
For drinking?
Pak û, berê ge pak bû.
Clean and, before it was very clean.
Paqij bû?
It was clean?
Paqij bû, tişt têda nedişûştin.
It was clean, they didn't wash things in it.
Bîstan dişûştin... na ka heye bî, sêv mîv tê de nanibûn.
They watered gardens... no there was... they didn't put
apples etc in it.
Lê gelek kesê min got...
But many people told me...
...şevê da av digirtin?
...they took water at night?
Paşê şevê de mehmel o... û em hatin av veder na av tê nebû.
After night... loaded... and we came water here, there was
no water in it.
Yekî li gundê Hecî Belî hebû, navê xwa Eyneto bû, vê bîrê,
ew da cêra kûla.
There was one in Hecî Belî village, his name was Eyneto,
this well, he dug it.
Ew bîr bi destê xwa kûla.
He dug that well with his own hands.
Ruwan jê bibin.
May soul take from it.
Yanî xêra xwa kûla ku...
Meaning he dug it for his charity...
Av barê mexlûq bî, şev...
Water for the creatures, at night...
Û gundê me jî, hefse yê li gundê Olkana, av e yanî.
And our village too, the basin at Olkana village, it is
water.
Xerbî gund, û... me go şimalê gund, û vederê ge av e.
West of the village, and... we said north of the village,
and here is much water.
We mane gund ketî ber.
That's why the village was built here.
Belê, av heyat e.
Yes, water is life.
Belê, heyat e.
Yes, is life.
Xalê min, noka ev bîra çiqas metro hebe?
My uncle, now how many meters is this well?
Pênc, şeş metro ye.
Five, six meters.
Destê kûla ne bawo?
Dug by hand, father?
Dest e.
Hand.
Av jî tê de?
And water in it?
Tê de ze, bin erd e, bin erd e.
In it plenty, underground, underground.
Rehma tîkî.
Mercy on him.
Eyneto, gundê Hecî Belî.
Eyneto, Hecî Belî village.
Wî kûla, wî manê şe'bî vederê warê avê jê ver bibe.
He dug it, for that meaning people here come take water from
it.
De nî şev bîstan dişûştin, bi şev em dihatin li ber...
So at night they watered gardens, at night we came to...
Bîra dibîn, waz bû manê avê nebin.
Seeing the well, it was open so they wouldn't take water.
Avê bibin bîstanê xwa.
Take water to their garden.
Lê de ne bîstanê xwa av didan?
But didn't they water their gardens?
Me rîk u xar bîkî, bîstanê xwa...
We prepared and ate, our garden...
Zerzewatî, firingî, xiyar, şebeş...
Vegetables, tomatoes, cucumbers, watermelons...
Rehma Xwedê li dê û bavê te be.
God's mercy on your parents.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Wekî we dî, Olkana maşallah tiştnê xweş tê da heye.
As you saw, Olkana mashallah has nice things in it.
Ê Muxtar ciwanê, dinê man.
The Mukhtar is young, remained in the world.
Na na, xerefok e elî dar bû.
No no, senile on the wood.
Eme wî jî seh kir.
We saw that too.
Ka em herin sêkin, hela qesta çiye, manê çiye. Ka em herin
bin.
Let's go look, what is the purpose, what is the meaning.
Let's go down.
Xalê min, vederkê çi bû, bi xêr vederkê, aliyê dîwar ne
tebîetî, çi bû vederkê?
My uncle, what was here, please here, the wall side is not
natural, what was here?
Ev berê, aş bû yê nê bîrê me.
This before, was a mill in our memory.
Teqrîben emrê mi şêst e, ne bîrê me.
Approximately my age is sixty, not in our memory.
Aş bû, ji dera dihatin li vederê, ew digerandin.
It was a mill, they came from there to here, turning it.
Ard, genim, dikutan, ew la...
Flour, wheat, they pounded, that...
...ew dêrdin dikirin ard.
...they ground it into flour.
Ev pir tura jimej e.
This is full of history.
Kevn dar e?
Ancient?
Yanî ji dera da dihatin, bê aş a pirî qedîm e.
Meaning they came from there, this mill is very ancient.
Işta, ev çi bî?
So, what was this?
Ewa biner, cîyê avê, wekî avê bî digerandin, çû dikirin, vê
kevirê han gêj dikirin.
Look at this, the water place, as water turned it, made it
go, made this stone spin.
Wey...
Wow...
Aşê avê bî, ne yê motorê bî, yê ceyranê bî.
It was a water mill, not a motor one, not an electric one.
Yanî bi avê dizivîrî?
So it spun with water?
Bi avê dizivîrî.
It spun with water.
Genimê xwa, cehê xwa...
Their wheat, their barley...
Ê genimê xwa, cehê xwa tanîn vederê dikirin ard.
Their wheat, their barley, they brought here and made into
flour.
Dikiran nan û dixwarin.
Made bread and ate.
Apo ev çi ye? Ez di xoleka evrê çi ye?
Uncle, what is this? I wonder what is this in this hole
here?
Ev qebr e, hel ke, hel ke.
This is a grave, leave it alone, leave it alone.
Qebra kê ye? Ez pê ne hatimê?
Whose grave is it? Did I not step on it?
Na, tu pê ne hatî.
No, you didn't step on it.
Ere, baş e xalê min, li ser vê kevirê çi ye ev?
Yes, okay my uncle, what is this on this stone?
Kevirê hindê ne hedimandin.
Stones of... they didn't destroy.
Erê, zraça.
Yes, agriculture.
[Stran] Lê xwedê qurban a te da... Ma ji qe neşgûlê te da...
Li vadiyê mexel nadî... Ma çi heyî axret a te da... Ma çi
heyî cennet a te da... Sevda sevda sevda zor e... Bûrsê pê
bû ez kal kirim... Derdê eşqê... Rê namal...
[Song] Oh God, I am your sacrifice... Don't let me be
distracted from you... In the valley... What is in your
afterlife... What is in your paradise... Love, love, love is
hard... The stock market was involved, it aged me... The
pain of love... No way home...
Lê gelî cemaet, xalê min ê mamê nîncî kî? Î lê noka jî me ra
xeber de hela, ev çi ye? Bo vanê çi ye?
So dear group, my uncle... tell us now, what is this? What
is this for?
Bê teb'en hejî kevindor e, pirê me hejî nezanin, noka emê
wara naskirin bidin, hejî li jêrî gundê Holkono ye.
Of course, this is also ancient, many of us don't know, now
we will introduce it, it is also below the village of
Holkono.
Xalê min ka hela fêm kim hela ev çi ye?
My uncle, let me understand, what is this?
Ev berê bistan diçandin, ji vê ra dibêjin xerafe.
Before they planted gardens, they called this a 'xerafe'
[water wheel].
Navê wî gundî Xerafe ye?
Is the name of that village Xerafe?
Na vî xoy xerafe ye. Kwanter dikirin wekî cer-cer e. Dû re
destî li qadîşê da bûn, tase mana digerî, buş dibû wekî
newaîrê Hemê memê.
No, this itself is a 'xerafe'. They harnessed it like a
threshing sled. Then hands were on the strap, the cups would
turn, empty like the Norias of Hama.
Tase qadîş tije diçûn û buş dibûn şwîn da diçûn tase wa
diftiling. Av pê bistan da berdan. Berê motor derketin hebûn
zemanê.
The cups on the strap would go full and empty going back,
the cups would turn. Water was released to the garden.
Before engines came out, in that time.
Yanî em bibên wekî dînamo, xetase?
So can we say like a dynamo, a pump?
Sed sale heye yanû teqrîben ez zanim me he... ev ne hene.
It's been a hundred years, meaning approximately I know...
these aren't around.
Emrê gundî sed sal e?
The age of the village is 100 years?
Sed sale heye na. Û pirr nana lêm ye nezanin çi ye eslen ev.
It's been 100 years, no. And many don't know what this is
actually.
Lê em dixwazin xelk naskî.
But we want people to know.
Lê heta tev taliyê kî çawa sekinandin mal dî bî ev?
But until the very end, how did this stop working?
Ev? Teqrîben di sala heşt û pêncî me nîvçe mal dikir.
This? Approximately in the year fifty-eight we stopped
working [it].
We şûnda se...
After you...
Paşê motor derketin, motor kirrîn. Dinya hedîs... xera bî.
Sê çar xerafe bûn di van geliya da.
Then engines came out, we bought engines. The world became
modern... it got ruined. There were 3-4 'xerafes' in these
valleys.
Bê mentiq e.
That makes sense.
Lê Holkono sê çar xerafe bûn.
But in Holkono there were 3-4 xerafes.
Xalo wekî te jûr gotî, Holkono bi avê pirr e welle.
Uncle, as you said upstairs, Holkono is full of water
really.
Lê bi avê xwarin bî. Avê, avê yanî pirr dibê kêm dibê...
But it was eaten by water. The water, the water, meaning it
gets high and low...
Wextê dikurt e dabe, bes bi mehne avê hindik dereke.
When it was short [drought], but regarding water, a little
comes out.
Nav genc e, av têder.
The name is young, water comes out.
Welle. Maşalla. Xwedê xêr û bêr pir bike înşalla.
What?
Really. Mashallah. May God increase the blessing God
willing.
Lê wekî wag diyet, teb'en vîrjî xolo kevn e bî ne?
But as it appears, naturally this place is also old, right?
Kevn e, hêşta xêrî me kevnî din heye. Gundê jêrî gund heye,
li jor heye.
It's old, yet there is older than us. The lower village
exists, up there exists.
Are.
Yes.
Dûr gundî me gelek av e.
Far from our village there is a lot of water.
Hinar ne, mêwî sê...
Pomegranates, vines/apples...
Zeytûn, hinar ne, sêv ne, gûz ne... Tu çi dixwazî hebû.
Olives, pomegranates, apples, walnuts... Whatever you wanted
was there.
Are.
Yes.
Tiştê nebû tunne. Heta bîra min, findiq darê findiqê hebûn
li vir.
There was nothing that wasn't there. As far as I remember,
there were hazelnut trees here.
Tiçk?
What?
Hebûn, findiq jî hebûn.
There were, there were even hazelnuts.
Westa.
Wow.
Findiq bûn.
They were hazelnuts.
Lê noka çikî kêm bûye lê?
But now why has it decreased?
Wele, çavî dinê ye, salboran nebûye, titnê şewitî, tiştek
nema.
Well, it's the eye of the world, years didn't pass [well],
tobacco burned, nothing remained.
Are. Lê xalê min, meşhûrî me divê ra, me gundê Hecbiliwa
mînan?
Yes. But my uncle, our famous [spot] here, we [call] the
village Hecbiliwa?
Em gundê Hecbiliwa dibêjin.
We call it Hecbiliwa village.
Hecbiliwa?
Ew gundê Hecbiliwa ye, ewjî tabyê şêx e.
That is Hecbiliwa village, it is also attached to the
Sheikh.
Tabyê şêx e?
Attached to the Sheikh?
Kêla gundî waye.
The village's tombstone is there.
Mezin e, çûçik e?
Big, small?
Welle gundî xo teqrîben sî mal têt bûn.
Well, the village itself had about 30 houses.
Bûn xirab e hede.
They are ruined now.
Ka mehraba.
Where are the ruins.
Ema ew gund e Hecbiliwa mînan.
But that is the village Hecbiliwa.
Mixtar, Allah kî me beke de.
Mukhtar, may God keep you.
Are are, emê...
Yes yes, we...
Lê em dibên silav û rêz, jimalbatê Mixtêr ra, tek tek.
But we say hello and respect to the Mukhtar's family, one by
one.
Bicûk dibên, mezin dibên, gijî rêz û hurmet e ne.
The young say, the old say, all are respect and honor.
Û sato gundê xweş, mêrik welle meqara. Rehet kir jî, xwedê
emrê dirêj bide. Te jî xweş xalê min, ka mehraba.
And a happy village hour, the man really [in the] cave. He
made us comfortable too, may God give long life. You too
[be] happy my uncle, where is the ruins.
[Stran] Eger bimrim, eger biftim... Sevda te se...
[Song] If I die, if I fall... Your love...
Erê cemaet, vîdyoya me herû anha bî. Me rengekî xweş wêneyê
teswîr kir, lê bi fedlê Mixtêr.
Yes group, our video was like this until now. We filmed a
nice image, but thanks to the Mukhtar.
Em dibên Mixtar, saeta te xweş be, xwedê emrê dirêj bide te,
xwedê we qeçik û neviyên te ra bîhêle. Mala te ava.
We say Mukhtar, may your hour be happy, may God give you
long life, may God keep you for your children and
grandchildren. May your house be prosperous.
Saeta we jî xweş. Û heke hal we me teqsîrek baro we nekiribe
me ra.
Your hour be happy too. And if... we didn't make a
shortcoming towards you.
Hûn hatin nav gund, geriyan, saeta we xweş.
You came into the village, walked around, may your hour be
happy.
Ma'nê alem gi zanibin... gundekî Holkono gi zanibin.
Meaning the whole world should know... know the village of
Holkono.
Her çi derver lê binerin... zîkratê berê were bîra. Saeta we
xweş.
Wherever they look from... memories of the past come to
mind. May your hour be happy.
Te jî xweş, lê bimînin qesran.
You too, but stay in the palaces.
Elhemdulîlla. Mixtarekî pir rind û delal e.
Praise be to God. A very good and dear Mukhtar.
Înşalla em dibên gi wekî wî bin. Û em gi jê hez bikin.
God willing we say all should be like him. And we all love
him.
Û saeta we xweş, bimînin vîdyoyên nû û hêja, xatirê we.
And may your hour be happy, stay for new and worthy videos,
goodbye.