Merheba hevalno, hevalê me, hûn çitan in? İnşallah hûn baş
in, rehet in.
Hello friends, our friends, how are you? God willing you are
well and comfortable.
Îro vîdyokî Hecer, bi me ra bin, vîdyokî Hecer.
Today, a video of Hecer, stay with us, a video of Hecer.
Avalê mecma Bostin e, em kî vîdyokî Hecer daxin inşallah.
For the Bostin group, we will upload a video of Hecer, God
willing.
Îro...
Today...
Ez û xortikê me ne, xalê Reşo jî çêmayî îro.
It's just me and our young guy, Uncle Reşo stayed behind
today.
Bi me ra bin, namê noko vîdyokî xweş wera çêkim, namê
inşallah hewya... bi nezim.
Stay with us, I will make a nice video for you now,
hopefully you will... like it.
Hadi şimbar.
Come on, move it.
Wanê manê xweş bibê.
So that our pictures turn out nice.
Erê mûtabiînê me, hewa em li orta gund in.
Yes our followers, right now we are in the middle of the
village.
Hewa orta gund e.
This is the middle of the village.
Hevser hewşê mala xaltîkê min e, vêrê dibên mala Hacî Hemke.
This courtyard is my aunt's house, they call this Hacî
Hemke's house.
Mala Nezmî Mîrêt.
Nezmî Mîrêt's house.
Amê li mala Nezmî Mîrêt bin... orta gund e.
We are at Nezmî Mîrêt's house... it's the middle of the
village.
Vêber me re tirba jî çîçikî nîzîk bike, huna derxîne.
Bring the cemetery closer to us over there, film there.
Haf... yo no jî tirbê gundî me ne.
This... this too is our village cemetery.
Emê noko dokeve jêr jî wera teswîr kin.
We will go down now and film for you.
Bi me ra bin çîçikê... bira sewanê lextana jî vir bikşînin.
Stay with us a bit... let the people's laundry be filmed
from here too.
Yelha.
Let's go.
Wê ber tiwî dimînî...
Over there on the mulberry tree, it stops...
Wê ber li tiwî dimînî vîdyo.
Over there on the mulberry tree, the video stops.
Xalk îşta cû doşû...
People are busy with plowing and milking now...
O xalkî qor to her kes karî xwe dike.
And the people... everyone does their work.
Îyay cûtixû doşû...
This one with his plow and milking...
Ûrû dinê germ e, kinc-mincê xwe dişûn, xalkî heye.
Today the weather is hot, they wash their clothes, there are
people.
Her ya karî xwe dike, ûrû rû germik e.
Everyone does their work, today is a warm day.
Îşta... wextê kora ye, wextê cûta ye, wextê her tiştkî ye,
kesax e.
Now... it's time for work, time for plowing, time for
everything, it's pruning time.
Xelkî îşta kesaxê jî dikin noko, kesaxê ew mêwa.
People are doing pruning now too, pruning those vines.
Bi me ra bin, bi me ra bin nosan heta kevin jêr.
Stay with us, stay with us let's go down.
Vîdyokî xweş amê wera daxînin îro.
We will upload a nice video for you today.
Wê ber çîkî çikî jî bigre.
Film that small chick too.
Awa çîkî çik e.
That is a small chick.
Merheba...
Hello...
Tu çitanî xaletê?
How are you auntie?
Ez xulama te bim, tu çitanî?
I am your servant (polite reply), how are you?
Em baş in, tu çitanî? Keyfa te xweş e?
We are well, how are you? Is your mood good?
Weleh ez nexweş im.
By God, I am sick.
Çiyê te ye? Xêr e?
What's wrong? Is it okay?
Wele piyanê min diêşin.
By God, my legs hurt.
Piyê te diêşin?
Your legs hurt?
Here.
Yes.
Xwedê şîfê bide.
May God give healing.
Emrê Xwedê, Xwedê...
It's God's will, God...
Mala Ehmed li vir e?
Is Ahmed's house here?
Na, Ehmed bar kir çû.
No, Ahmed moved and left.
Ehmed bar kir çû?
Ahmed moved and left?
Here. Ehmed naha çû...
Yes. Ahmed now went...
Haa, mala kê li vir e?
I see, whose house is here?
Mala... Hecî...
The house of... Haji...
Mala Hecî...
Haji's house...
Hecî [Nav].
Haji [Name].
Temam, xatirê te.
Okay, goodbye.
Oxir be.
Farewell.
Erê mûtabiînê me, wekî we dîye...
Yes our followers, as you have seen...
Evna tirbê gundî me ne, tirbê Be'dîna ne.
These are our village graves, the graves of the Be'dîna.
Evna hewna.
All of these.
Maşallah pirr in.
Mashallah there are many.
Xwedê rehma xwe li miriya giyan ke.
May God have mercy on all the dead.
Xwatxwe qebûl ke, nûbarê hekî em dikin.
May God accept this visit we are doing.
Vêber bikişîne.
Film over there.
Hev tarafê Opî me ne.
This side belongs to our Opî family.
Opî me ne.
Our Opî family.
Kesî xerîb tê nîne.
There are no strangers in it.
Gi nas in.
All are acquaintances.
Tirba pirr in.
The graves are many.
No nav hebe... navê gundî kamil be.
If there were names... if the village names were complete.
Û mewqê gundî me de... ow yali jêr... ow yali jûr...
And in our village location... that lower side... that upper
side...
Ow binî serê cêway e.
That is the bottom of the stream head.
Merov di xure herin ser... ê pirr in.
If one goes straight up... they are many.
Du saet tu bigerî... tû li nîv bigerî... hetan tu bibînî.
If you walk for two hours... walk in the middle... until you
see.
Yani nîzîkî... pirr in... sê çar hezar tirbe heye, pirr in.
Meaning close to... many... there are three or four thousand
graves, they are many.
Dame lê digerin.
We are walking around.
Af tarafa gêmeylê me ne, afciyê Opî me ne.
This side belongs to our Gemeyl family, this place belongs
to our Opî family.
Afciyê Opî me ne.
This place belongs to our Opî family.
Yani kesî xerîb tê nîne, gi nas in, îşta pirr in.
Meaning there are no strangers in it, all are acquaintances,
they are many now.
Tirba pirr in.
The graves are many.
Noko nav hebe, navê gundî kamil be.
If there were names now, if the village names were complete.
Û mewqê gundî me de... ew yali jêr, ew yali jûr...
And in our village location... that lower side, that upper
side...
Ew binî serê cêway e.
That is the bottom of the stream head.
Merov dixwe re here ser... pirr in.
If one goes straight up... they are many.
Du saet... di gerek ne... tel nîv bigere heta tu bibîne.
Two hours... is not enough to walk... walk in the middle
until you see.
Yanî nîzîko... pirr in, sê çar hezar tirbe hene.
Meaning nearly... many, there are three or four thousand
graves.
De emê lê digerin.
So we are walking around.
Erê mûtabiînê me, wekî we dîye.
Yes our followers, as you have seen.
Em îro hatin kû? Tirbê Be'dîna ne.
Where did we come today? The graves of Be'dîna.
Noho emê herin Mezora Şêx Reşîd jî aw bikin... derxînin.
Now we will go to the shrine of Sheikh Rashid to... film it.
Kil hal Xwedê rehma xwe li miriya giyan ke, ciyê giya cennet
be.
Anyway may God have mercy on all the dead, may everyone's
place be paradise.
Binerin ew tirbê Şêx Reşîd em wera derxin.
Look, we will film Sheikh Rashid's tomb for you.
Erê cemaet wekî we dî, ev o mezarê Şêx Reşît e.
Yes folks, as you saw, this is the shrine of Sheikh Rashid.
Ê Şêx Reşît e biro.
It is Sheikh Rashid, brother.
Xelk têyê... şta du'a dikin.
People come here... well, they pray.
Em hew jê melawkê dikin. Ê Şêx Reşît, bi Xwedê melawkê ye
keko.
We are just rubbing our faces for a blessing. Oh Sheikh
Rashid, by God, it is a blessing, brother.
Erê cemaet wekî we dî, ev o mezarê Şêx Reşît e.
Yes folks, as you saw, this is the shrine of Sheikh Rashid.
Insanekî pak e, insanekî wekî dibê...
He is a pure human, a human that as they say...
Dibê bi destnivêj bî, wekî melawkê koyê...
You must have ablution, like washing your face...
Hew jî... teb'en em na dikin şirîkê Xwedê Rebê 'Alemîn. Ê
mezin Xwedê Rebê 'Alemîn e.
Also... of course we are not making partners with God, the
Lord of the Worlds. The Great One is God, the Lord of the
Worlds.
Wextê Şêx Reşît xelk tê cem, gindor... biro.
At Sheikh Rashid, people come to the [wishing stones]...
brother.
Ev o cihê mezarê... singo ye.
This is the place of the shrine... the chest.
Mesela nêtê kê hene... mesela ên tên... tê bi berê singê xwe
diketin.
For example, whoever has intentions... for example those who
come... they place the stone against their chest.
Xwedê miradê dilê gundiya diket, lê bi derê ve dizeliqe.
God grants the wishes of the villagers' hearts, if it sticks
to the wall.
Yanî xelkê pir tecrube kirine û meşî ye yanî.
I mean, people have tested it a lot and it has worked, I
mean.
Yanî ê mezin jî Xwedê ye.
I mean, the Great One is God.
Xwedê rehma xwe li miriyê we ke, û cihê we jî cenet be.
May God have mercy on your dead, and may your place be
paradise.
Û înşalla hemî ew ên ber mezarê Şêx Reşît...
And God willing, all those at the shrine of Sheikh Rashid...
Her kesê miraz di dil da, Xwedê bike.
Everyone who has a wish in their heart, may God grant it.
Û her yekî, hûnno, bi ewê difikire, mesela...
And everyone, you know, with what they are thinking about,
for example...
Ê qîçika xwe tîne... ê mesela... ê dest teng... ê deyndar...
toxozê bextê malê xwe em du'a ji wan ra dikin.
The one who brings his daughter [for marriage luck]... the
one for example... the one who is broke... the debtor...
regarding the luck/dowry of their home, we pray for them.
Xwedê miradê dilê we giyan bike, destê xwe ser we giyan ra
bigire.
May God grant the wishes of all your hearts, may He hold His
hand over all of you.
Û înşalla, înşalla bi îznê Xwedê...
And God willing, God willing, with God's permission...
Wekî dibê, yê bixwazin malê xwe, ser erdê xwe, derê xwe...
dîsa rehma li miriyê we giyan bin.
As they say, those who want their home, on their land, their
place... again mercy be upon all your dead.
Û Xwedê miradê dilê we giyan bike. Çi di dilê we da hene,
Xwedê miradê dilê we giyan bike.
And may God grant the wishes of all your hearts. Whatever is
in your hearts, may God grant the wishes of all your hearts.
Êşta ev o mezarê Şêx Reşît e.
Now, this is the shrine of Sheikh Rashid.
Axul de gogê ke Bilîs!
Dude, give the ball here, Bilis!
Axul de gogê ke Bilîs.
Dude, give the ball here, Bilis.
Erê mutabî'înê me wekî we dî, me got em hinekê gogê bikin.
Yes, our followers, as you saw, we said let's play some
ball.
Heke em westiyayî ne... nizanm Hemûde, nizanm çi...
Even though we are tired... I don't know Hamude, I don't
know what...
Me go emê pîçekê gogê bikin, cew germ e ke, şebap, xwo ro
gogê dileyîzin.
We said we will play a little ball, the weather is hot man,
the youth, they are playing ball nicely.
Erê wele. Me go cew germ e ke, şebap xwo ro gogê dileyîzin
sehke.
Yes, by God. We said the weather is hot man, look the youth
are playing ball nicely.
Axul de, xul de, xul de!
Dude give it, give it, give it!
'Arûfe!
Arufe!
Erê mutabî'înê me wekî we dî...
Yes our followers, as you saw...
Me rehet nebir, me rehet nebir.
We didn't catch a break, we didn't catch a break.
Bi mera bin, înşalla vîdyo kete di dilê we da, kêfa we jê ra
hatibe.
Stay with us, God willing this video entered your hearts,
[and] you enjoyed it.
Wellahî... em çûn ser tirba, hinek tazî...
By God... we went to the graveyard, there was a funeral...
Em tirsiyan teswîr kin.
We were afraid to film.
Me nêwêra, gundî bûn, eciz nebin.
We didn't dare, they were villagers, don't be upset.
Mewqi' nedan me, mewqi' nedan me, me ye ji bir kiro.
They didn't give us the opportunity, they didn't give us the
opportunity, otherwise we would have done it.
Eke hal mişkîla tune, emê werrin hefteya emê dîsa çêkin.
If there is no problem, we will come next week, we will do
it again.
Sax û silametê we xweş, ji bîr nekin like û subscribe ji me
re sehke û mezin kin.
Health and wellness to you, don't forget to like and
subscribe, watch us and grow [the channel].