Ya xwedê, min di 'Elke... Gundê 'Elke he?
Oh God, I'm in Elke... Is it the village of Elke?
Li ewil car ez têm gundê 'Elke.
For the first time, I am coming to the village of Elke.
Oh, darê ma mostê xwe çêkiriye?
Oh, did I fix the microphone stand?
Ya min jî mixtêl merê gû nal mûl ne...
Or is the microphone looking skewed on me...
Ya binê... maşallah.
Or look... Mashallah.
Ee darê no mostê xwe çêkiriye.
Yeah, look, the stand is fixed.
Ooh, vî derê binê... Em can birakî me Luqman ne...
Ooh, look here... We are with a dear brother, Luqman...
Ez yê beramberî qehwê vediweşem, yan çi şekil e?
I am shaking in anticipation of the coffee, or what is going
on?
Te sanako ku du-sê kîlo zêde jê tê.
You'd think I've gained two or three extra kilos.
Tevî zêde wure heso liviya, tiçkê hereket hema tra...
With all that extra [weight] moving around like that, a bit
of movement...
Ezî ber wî qehwê vediweşem.
I am shaking for that coffee.
Li hewşê berê sîya me hat.
In the courtyard, our shade has appeared [it's getting
late/sunny].
Şûna qehwe... De bota ye qehwek bime dat.
Where is the coffee... Just bring me a coffee.
Tu ne mewcûd e? Em çûkan?
Is it not available? What are we to do?
Silavê me îştera hene birayê Henan... Bikin.
We have greetings for you, brother Hanan... Do it.
Maşallah xalû Silk çandîye haa, ê girs bûye.
Mashallah, Uncle Silk has planted [something], look, it has
grown big.
Aa, Ooo heval Mihemed!
Ah, Ooo friend Mohammed!
Erê milel canî te eyî ne be, aa.
Hey, may your dear soul not be harmed, ah.
Maşallah hînik e.
Mashallah, it is cool.
Merheba hevalno, dîsa em hatin.
Hello friends, we have come again.
Em gihîştin vîdyoya xwe li gundê 'Elke.
We have arrived for our video at the village of Elke.
Teb'en, em li vî derê sekinîne, kesî nas nake tenê ye, vî
derê me'rûf e.
Naturally, we have stopped here, nobody recognizes [the
place] alone, this place is well-known.
Li vî derkê, emkê darbazi noka gundê 'Elke bin.
At this spot, we are about to cross into the village of
Elke.
Teb'en me gundê Sînka sawirandin, û me Xirabê Şehra jî
sawirandin.
Naturally, we filmed the village of Sinka, and we filmed
Xirabê Şehra as well.
Me go em di vira, em li vî derê beskinin, em darbazi gundê
'Elke bin ji megwastina.
We said since we are here, let's stop at this spot, and pass
into the village of Elke per the requests.
Bi me ra bin, vîdyoyekî xweş kîbar. Navê gundê 'Elke.
Stay with us for a nice, elegant video. The name is Elke
village.
Me'zet gotina ten?
Does Me'zet have anything to say?
Erê hevalê me, noka jî emkê darbazî gundê 'Elke bin, wek
babê 'Ezet we gotî.
Yes our friends, now we will cross into the village of Elke,
as Mr. Azet just said.
Bi me ra bin, em darbazî gund bin.
Be with us, as we enter the village.
Em seke ew jî gundekî rengê xwe çawa ye.
Let us see what kind of style this village has.
Gundekî xweş e, le kîbar e.
It is a nice village, elegant.
Em sekinin, hela gundekî çawa ye.
We shall see what kind of village it is.
Me we gund hîn nedîye, emê we gundî jî bi hawarê bibînin.
We haven't seen this village yet, we will see this village
together with the help [of the camera].
Bi me ra bin, em darbazî gundê 'Elke bin.
Stay with us, we are crossing into the village of Elke.
Erê hevalno, saet xweş Me'zet.
Yes friends, thank you Me'zet.
Erê hevalno, kesê vê meqamî nas deke, me ra di te'lîqê da
binivîşkin.
Yes friends, anyone who recognizes this location, please
write to us in the comments.
Em navê vê zozanê nizanin kîder e ye.
We don't know the name of this plateau/area, where it is.
Cama zozan hene ez nas dikim, bes cora min bivir nebistiye.
There are plateaus I know, but I haven't been this way
before.
Ser mefreqa gundê 'Elke ye.
It is at the intersection of Elke village.
Û rê ji derin Şehra. Teb'en meydankê, derin kîderê...
And the road goes to Şehra. Naturally to the square, where
it goes...
Ya ez navî gende nizanim.
Oh, I don't know the names of the villages.
Kesê zane nav çî ye, me ra di te'lîqê da binivîşkin.
Anyone who knows what the name is, write to us in the
comments.
Mîzoriya bo min re wara xeber da, ez nizanim nivî xwe çî ye.
The Mizori [tribe member] spoke to me about it, but I don't
know what its name is.
Tebîetek xweş li vira heye.
There is beautiful nature here.
Avî ne war vî derê, pir xweş kîbar e.
The water coming this way is very nice and elegant.
Xelk tê bin vê darê rûdinê, seke, ew çêkirine.
People come and sit under this tree, look, they have built
this [seating area].
Berkok xweş li vî derê heye, maşallah maşallah.
There is a nice small pool/basin here, mashallah mashallah.
Maşallah çi tebîetek xweş li vî derê heye.
Mashallah, what beautiful nature is here.
Mirov avîna xwe ra were vir rûdinê.
One would come here with their beloved to sit.
Milet tê, teb'en milet tê avîna rûdinê vî derê.
The people come, naturally people come to sit by the water
here.
Bes noka ne çilê darê dar weşîne.
But now it isn't the peak season where the trees are
full/shedding.
Hîşnayî ji hê derkeve, hê pir xweş bibe.
Once the greenery comes out, it will be very beautiful.
Erê.
Yes.
Erê hevalno, li vî derê emkê darbazî gundê 'Elke bin.
Yes friends, at this point, we are about to enter the
village of Elke.
Me go em vîdyoya dekabîn kin, em we ra teswîr kin.
We said let's adjust the video, and film for you.
Erê dibêm law law law law law law law...
Yes, I say oh boy, oh boy, oh boy...
Law law delalo were malo law law law...
Oh dear boy, come home, oh boy...
Delal delalo were malo, law law delal delalo were malo...
Dear, dear one, come home, oh boy, dear, dear one, come
home...
Were malo...
Come home...
Erê dibêm law law law law law law law...
Yes, I say oh boy, oh boy, oh boy...
Law law law law law law delalo were malo...
Oh boy, oh boy, dear one, come home...
Serê min bi qurban o, were malo.
May my head be a sacrifice, come home.
Ê lo delal dinya j'bistan e...
Oh dear one, the world is a garden...
Serê min bi qurban o, here hutan e, were malo.
May my head be a sacrifice, go to the whales [far away],
come home.
Ê lo delal dinya j'bistan e, here hutan e, were malo.
Oh dear one, the world is a garden, go to the whales, come
home.
Delal o malo bavê min sipî û bilind e ji du qat e...
Dear one, my father's house is white and tall, with two
floors...
Law law law law delal te xibal e.
Oh boy, oh boy, dear one, you are distracted/troubled.
Ê lo delal dibinî ava teşta dûze, serê min bi qurban o...
Oh dear one, under the water of the flat basin, may my head
be a sacrifice...
Tav da binêr go kaniyê.
The sun struck the bottom of the spring.
Ê la bigelî û newal e, bicanî ye, biçawîr û çîman e delal...
Oh, with valleys and streams, with young horses, with
pastures and meadows, dear one...
Delal o biçawîr û çîman e.
Dear one, with pastures and meadows.
Ê lo delal di sera ciyayê bilind e, tav da bi dar û ber e...
Oh dear one, on top of the high mountain, the sun struck the
trees and stones...
Bimeşe niqeb hîm û zinar e.
Walk through the pass of rocks and cliffs.
Serê min qurban o, tav da bi yaylew û zozan e...
May my head be a sacrifice, the sun struck the summer
pastures and plateaus...
Law law delal bi yaylew û zozan e.
Oh boy, dear one, with summer pastures and plateaus.
Erê hevalno, teb'en li vira malbatek ji megwastina gundê
'Elke...
Yes friends, naturally here a family [was] requested from
Elke village...
Emkê herin mala weledê... El-Canû?
We will go to the house of the son of... Al-Janu?
Mala Ebu Cem'a. Emkan mala Ebu Cem'a.
The house of Abu Juma. We will go to Abu Juma's house.
Emkê darbazî wê malbatê bin.
We will visit that family.
Bi me ra bin vîdyoyekî xweş kîbar, emê noka we ra teswîr
kin.
Stay with us for a nice, elegant video, we will film for you
now.
Teb'en Kefarûmê jî ji megwastina.
Naturally, Kefarume [historical ruins] was also requested.
Kefarûmê jî ji megwastina, ye em wûru gihîştin vira.
Kefarume was also requested, since we arrived here.
Em vê sibê da derketin e.
We set out this morning.
Dergeh ha va, me ye noka Kefarûmê jî bi sawiranda.
The opportunity is here, we would have filmed Kefarume now.
Ê welakîn, hatan her noka...
But, up until just now...
Kefarûmê jî îvarê bibe.
Kefarume will [have to be] in the evening.
İnşallah emê hilqekî werin Kefarûmê çêkin, milet ji me
xwestiye.
God willing, we will come and make an episode about
Kefarume, the people asked us for it.
Min nizanî Kefarûmê li vî derê ye, mêrek mi ra we got.
I didn't know Kefarume was here, a man told me.
Go Kefarûmê vê gundî jêr, gul Kefarûmê ye.
He said Kefarume is below this village, the flower is
Kefarume.
Wanê hember me jî, gimo xeyam bîn...
Those opposite us too, I think they were tents...
Milet tê dabîn, noka milet tê tine ye, gijê derketî ye.
People used to settle [there], now there are no people, they
have all left.
Erê dîsa dibêm law law law law law law law...
Yes, again I say oh boy, oh boy, oh boy...
Law law law law law law law delalo were malo...
Oh boy, oh boy, oh boy, dear one, come home...
Delal o were malo.
Dear one, come home.
Serê min bi qurban o, ne dûr were, hatin ji mi ra gotin û
hewal dan e.
May my head be a sacrifice, don't come from afar, they came
and told me and gave news.
Bi mi ra gotin wa delalê te jê hez dikî, derê pîşê
şewitandin.
They told me that dear one you love, they burned the front
door.
Ê lo delal, mara pîşo, jin e, bîyan, bî halet û derd û merez
û wêran e.
Oh dear one, don't go forward, it is women, strangers,
without tools, pain, disease and ruin.
Ez na bêjim li ser hemû jin e, bîyan, ez dibêjim li ser
hindkan e.
I am not saying this about all women, strangers, I am saying
it about some.
Ê lo delal, belkî eşqa me stir bibe bi salekî û du dyana.
Oh dear one, maybe our love will be sung/remembered for a
year or two religions [eternities].
Femo ji berê paşê da dibê, nesîhetê mezinî mera j'berarê...
Understanding comes from the past to the future, the advice
of the elders for us...
Xwedê rehma xwe li giyanê te bike, vira mirin hene...
May God have mercy on your soul, there are deaths [graves]
here...
Xwedê rehma xwe li giyanê te bike, cîhê giya cennet be.
May God have mercy on your soul, may their place be
paradise.
Erê hevalno, hewa tebîeta gundê 'Elke... Gundê 'Elke hev ha
wa.
Yes friends, this is the nature of Elke village... This is
Elke village.
Li ewil car ez têm gundê 'Elke.
For the first time, I am coming to Elke village.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Hewa darê zeytûna da dişîne çikan?
Does that one look like an olive tree, or what?
Ew xewx si darê da hezînin.
Those peaches sway in the tree.
Tu pê dimeşî?
Can you walk on it?
Rizqê min heye. Hevalno wara, rizqê min heye.
I have sustenance [luck]. Friends come, I have sustenance.
Migo rizqê min pir e.
I said my sustenance is plentiful.
Ez rast evê hatim, vê heywanî.
I came right upon this water, [and] these animals.
Teb'en...
Naturally...
Abo, awê sar û av bî ye.
Oh, the water is cold and it is spring water.
Abo, ez destê xwe pir av nakim.
Oh, I won't put my hand in the water too much.
Çiqanê çawîr mawîr derkeve, heywan heye bixwe.
Once the pasture and grass comes out, there are animals to
eat.
Her, her, rêka xwe temam bike, her.
Go, go, complete your path, go.
Me tê dî.
We saw you.
Çawîr derket, oxa ne heywanê çawîr bixwara.
The pasture came out, oh, would that the animals eat the
pasture.
Cilik darê... bixwara.
The buds of the tree... eat.
Erê vallah, li ewil car ez têm gundê 'Elke, vê gundo...
Yes, by God, for the first time I am coming to Elke village,
this village...
Gundekî xweş e vallah.
It is a nice village, by God.
Erê hevalno, gundê 'Elke pir ne mezin e.
Yes friends, Elke village is not very big.
Pir ne mezin e, heta sed û bîst û pênc mala ye.
It is not very big, it is up to one hundred and twenty-five
households.
Sed û bîst û pênc hewş in, tê da gundê 'Elke...
One hundred and twenty-five courtyards [houses], inside Elke
village...
Tebîetek nohiyê Şehra ye.
It is the nature of the Şehra sub-district.
Erê.
Yes.
Ne mezin e.
It is not big.
Teb'en li vî derê, em ji 'ewê tên...
Naturally at this spot, we are coming from that
[direction]...
Ji gundê Sînka û Xirabê Şehra me sawirandî, em ji wûr tên.
From Sinka village and Xirabê Şehra which we filmed, we are
coming from there.
Û me go em gundê 'Elke bisawirînin.
And we said let's film Elke village.
Kefarûmê ji megwastina, min nizanî li vî derê ye vallah,
mêrek mi ra wa gû.
Kefarume was requested, I didn't know it was here by God, a
man told me so.
Go hewa ha wa.
He said it is right here.
Inşallah emê hilqekî di wûr da jî çêkin.
God willing, we will make an episode in there too.
Ko bi me ra bin, em darbaz bin... nav gund.
So stay with us, let's enter... inside the village.
Emkan mala Ebû Cem'a jî.
We will go to Abu Juma's house too.
...hadîsê xwe can e delal.
...his sayings are lovely, dear one.
Law law delal û hadîsê xwe can e.
Oh boy, dear one, and his sayings are lovely.
Kafirê bê îman e, bê dîn e, şerîe, nizanî hatî dîn e.
The infidel is faithless, religionless, evil, not knowing he
came to religion.
Ê lo delal law law law law law law...
Oh dear one, oh boy, oh boy...
Incîl e, Tewrat e, Zabûr e, Qur'an e.
It is the Bible, the Torah, the Psalms, the Quran.
Ê lo delal, law law law law... hatin ji mi ra gotin û hewal
dan e.
Oh dear one, oh boy, oh boy... they came and told me and
gave news.
Bi mi ra gotin wa delalê te jê hez dikî, mera pîşo şêx û
sofî...
They told me that dear one you love, don't go forward,
sheikhs and sufis...
Ê lo delal, mera pîşo şêx û sofî, heciyan, qelenî şer'ê xwe
çatin e...
Oh dear one, don't go forward, sheikhs and sufis, pilgrims,
they have fixed their heavy sharia law...
Em nikarin têk evîne, xurati.
We cannot fall into love, superstition.
Go ji hemberê vanî cûke.
Said from opposite these young ones.
Teb'en zift bi ra, toliya ziftê ye.
Naturally asphalt is on the road, it is the remnant of
asphalt.
Binî gund.
Below the village.
Seke zift û toliya xwe ve ra ye, emkê noka di qerçaxa ra
biçin.
Look, the asphalt and its remnants are here, we will now go
through the curves/rough path.
Ê lo delal, sîng û beregê qeçika lolo serêm qurban o.
Oh dear one, the chest and neck of the girl, oh my, may my
head be a sacrifice.
Memikê va dibê hinar û sêv û tevtahî mîşxan e.
Her breasts are like pomegranates and apples and all kinds
of apricot orchards.
Ê lo delal di sîng û berê keçika da, serî rakirî mahrê çayê
qeftaxê ser mixmarî du vikaşane.
Oh dear one, in the chest and front of the girl, the snake
of the tea cup raised its head... [metaphor for
shape/adornment].
Ê lo delal, mera pîşo keç û kevan e.
Oh dear one, don't go forward [towards] girls and
housewives.
Faqa mirinê li pîşo tev vedan e.
The trap of death is set all out in front.
Heger ti tê werbê tora, nabê bêyî yekêv dudyan e, delal...
If you come get caught in the net, it won't be without one
or two [consequences], dear one...
Delal û bê yekêv dudyan e.
Dear one, without one or two.
Ê lo delal were malo, delal û were malo...
Oh dear one, come home, dear one and come home...
Îro dîsa çû rojek ji emrê min.
Today, another day has gone from my life.
Efrîna rengîn naçe ji bîra min.
Colorful Afrin does not leave my mind.
Derdê min giran e, ax welatê min.
My grief is heavy, oh my homeland.
Derdê min giran e, lo bira, ax Efrîna min.
My grief is heavy, oh brother, oh my Afrin.
Îro dîsa çû rojek ji emrê min.
Today, another day has gone from my life.
Efrîna rengîn naçe ji bîra min.
Colorful Afrin does not leave my mind.
Derdê min giran e, ax welatê min.
My grief is heavy, oh my homeland.
Derdê min giran e, lo bira, ax Efrîna min.
My grief is heavy, oh brother, oh my Afrin.
De vê darê jê... vî makîna tê... vî gundî kuncê darê de...
Turn from this tree... the car is coming... in the corner of
this village's tree...
Em hatin gundê Elkê... em ê tola xwe têkin...
We arrived at Alke village... we will take our revenge
[metaphor for filming/visiting]...
Em ê vegerin cî û warê xwe.
We will return to our place and home.
Bixemilînin gund û bajarê xwe.
We will adorn our villages and cities.
Em ji bîr nakin koç û koçberiyên xwe.
We will not forget our migration and displacements.
Em şêrîn bikin, lo bira, ax jîna xwe.
Let us sweeten, oh brother, oh our life.
Em ê vegerin cî û warê xwe.
We will return to our place and home.
Bixemilînin gund û bajarê xwe.
We will adorn our villages and cities.
Em ji bîr nakin koç û koçberiyên xwe.
We will not forget our migration and displacements.
Gundê Elkê, Elkê... Gundê Elkê ser bi Mêbata... Gundê Elkê
ser bi Raco ve ye.
Alke village, Alke... Alke village belongs to Mabata...
[No], Alke village belongs to Rajo.
Em va îro li gundê Elkê ne. Pîroz dikin, gundekî xweşik û
kîbar e.
Here we are today in Alke village. We congratulate it, it is
a beautiful and elegant village.
Tabîetê gund, cografya gund pir xweş e... Gundê Elkê.
The nature of the village, the geography of the village is
very nice... Village of Alke.
Hember me Meydankê ye, Halebî ye... gobelek a li hember me
ye.
Opposite us is Meydanki, Halebi... there is a mound opposite
us.
Tebîetek pir xweş e, em li vê dere jî mala mixtar... Em li
ser Hewşa gund in.
The nature is very nice, and here we are at the Mukhtar's
house... We are at the village square.
Megû manê gund, gima vî xwînwarê... ha va li min kû bi
sewirîne dûrçîr me.
I said the meaning of the village, the noise of this
place... look here, let my cameraman film this.
Me pirs kir jî, mala Cuma, dibê noka ji mal derketiye...
dibe ne li mal e, em ê noka derbas bin.
We asked about Cuma's house, they say he just left the
house... maybe he is not home, we will pass by now.
Ha va tebîeta gundê Elkê, ha va. Tebîetek pir xweş û kîbar
e.
Look, this is the nature of Alke village, look here. A very
nice and elegant nature.
Hewşek kevnar jî tê de heye... ha va nû... hewşek kevnar tê
hene.
There is also an ancient courtyard inside... here is new...
there are ancient courtyards.
Megû gund ne mezin e... 120 mal e.
I said the village is not big... it is 120 households.
Maşallah, maşallah. Wana dûrçîr me bigire ha va li min...
jor jî bigire.
Mashallah, mashallah. Let my cameraman capture those, look
at me... capture up there too.
Aaa ha va li min, melûmatê ser vî gundî... megû 120 mal ne.
Ummm look here at me, information about this village... I
said there are 120 houses.
Me teqreqot mixtar pirs kir, mixtar dibê 110 mal tê de
rûniştî ne.
We knocked and asked the Mukhtar, the Mukhtar says 110
houses are inhabited.
Şaşbîn 10 hewş ne... ê wala mişkilêt hene.
There are about 10 [empty] courtyards... well, there are
problems.
Teb'en mixtar î luku hat... mala Eba Cuma li me...
Of course, where did the Mukhtar come from... Abu Cuma's
house...
Erê ha va li min, ev malbata jî me xwestine, mala Eba
Cuma... mala Elcane.
Yes look here at me, this family we also wanted [to visit],
Abu Cuma's house... the Aljane family.
Ê bes mixtar miro go... go çûye Efrîn. Ne li mal e. Go
derketiye çûye Efrîn.
But the Mukhtar, the man said... said he went to Afrin. He
is not home. Said he left and went to Afrin.
Ev jî şansa me ye.
This is also our luck.
Ha re, ha va hewşa xwe ye.
Here, look, this is his courtyard.
Ev na cîranê gund in e. Ev na jî cîranê xwe ne.
These are the neighbors of the village. These are also his
neighbors.
Li mal bûn, me silavek lê da.
If they were home, we would have given a greeting.
Erê birakî min Idrîs... teb'en Idrîs jî me xwest. Malbata
xwe.
Yes my brother Idris... of course we wanted Idris too. His
family.
Idrîs birakî min, silavên me jê re hene, ser serî me ye, ser
çavî me ye.
Idris my brother, we have greetings for him, he is on our
head, on our eyes (highly respected).
Şansa me tune bî, em ji gundê Sînka hatin... me gû em ê
werin malbata, we jî derbas bin, istirahetkê xwe bibin.
We had no luck, we came from Sinka village... we said we
would come to the family, pass by you too, take a rest.
Em ê hewşê teswîr kin tero... bi kun ta bîra hewşa xwe jî
kirî.
We will film the courtyard anyway... so that you remember
your courtyard.
Yam hatin jî mixtar me re go, ne li mal in.
When we came, the Mukhtar told us, they are not home.
Erê, teqsîrê me jî efû ke. Ha va gundê we ye. Ha va xûreta
we ne.
Yes, forgive our shortcoming. This is your village. This is
your scenery.
Efrîm lê bigre dûrçîr me, hewşa wan a... dûrçîr me bigre.
Afrim (cameraman), capture it my cameraman, their
courtyard... capture it my cameraman.
Erê... Miletiyê vî gundî jî pir ne hatî mal... nîvî heye,
nîvî tune ye.
Yes... The people of this village have mostly not come
home... half are here, half are not.
Rebek ji çûyî zeytûna... rebek li mal mane. Erê.
A quarter have gone to the olives... a quarter remained at
home. Yes.
Erê birakî min Idrîs... malbata te ne li mal bî. Ha va mala
mixtar e.
Yes my brother Idris... your family was not home. Here is
the Mukhtar's house.
Teb'en mixtar hat mala we, mira ew hewal da, go ha va mala
gundî ye.
Of course the Mukhtar came to your house, he gave me that
news, said here is the villager's house.
Qusûrê me jî pir efû ke. Yanî em mubaşer na hatine...
Forgive our shortcoming very much. Meaning we didn't come
directly...
Em çûne gundê Sînka û xirabê şara me sewirand... Em di vira
werin...
We went to Sinka village and filmed the ruins of Shara...
[We said] we would come through here...
...em derbas gundê Elkê bin. Yam hatin jî... îşte na li mal
bî malbata te.
...we would pass through Alke village. When we came... well,
your family was not home.
De îşta wexta kar e... her kes derê karê xwe.
Well now it is work time... everyone is at their work place.
Reqemê telefona der heba, mekanî vira tewasul kira, me
bigota em ê tên.
If we had a phone number, [if] the place here communicated,
we would have said we are coming.
Ê ko reqemê telefonê tune ye. Noka jî wexta hereket e, yanî
kes di mal de rûnanê.
But well, there is no phone number. Now is also the time of
movement, meaning no one sits at home.
De... Em ê gundê ji... em nizanin kijan deqe, kijan lehze em
ê derbas gund bin.
So... We [go to] the village too... we don't know which
minute, which moment we will pass the village.
Yanî bes gunda jime dixwazin di te'lîqê de... yazî dikin,
enû ha war gundê filanî... û em tên.
Meaning, the villages just want from us in the comments...
they write, "come to such and such village"... and we come.
Pirik hene ser xwast mera daxwaz dikin, navê malbata xwe
didin min...
There are many, upon request they ask us, they give me the
name of their family...
Em vêra tewasul dikin, em tên... hazirîya xwe dikin, em tên
vêra teswîrkê çê dikin. Teswîrê kîbar.
We communicate with them, we come... they make their
preparations, we come there and make a video. A nice video.
Miletiyê jime dixwaze xudanê xwe bibînin, xudanê gundê
derketin, dundikin... yanî pir kîbar xweş derdikeve.
The people want from us to see their owners [relatives], the
owners of the village who left... meaning it turns out very
elegant and nice.
De xayo mişkîla te'lîqa de, bes dibê mala meselen filanî
der... î em...
So brother, the problem in the comments, [they] just say "go
to so-and-so's house"... but we...
Em jî muface'eten, em muface'e îş tên... bi kun na li mal
ne... çûne ser kar.
We also [come] by surprise, we come as a surprise job... so
they are not home... they went to work.
De dîsa em ê bêjin... qusûrê me wînê pir pir efû kin.
So again we will say... forgive our shortcoming very very
much.
Çavê we giya maç dikim. Xwedê ji we giya razî be.
I kiss the eyes of you all. May God be pleased with you all.
Wile tebîeteke gelekî pir xweş e, ecêba gundî.
By God, the nature is very beautiful, the wonder of the
village.
Ciyê bilbila xwendin e, ciyê bilbila me şewq didê.
It is a place where nightingales sing, a place where
nightingales give us delight.
Gelî.. Gemrûkê xwin tê, Semolkê, gundê Şurbe, Meydankê...
The valley... Gemrûk flows into it, Semolk, the village of
Shurbe, Meydanki...
Gobelekê, Şera, gi dar xwin tê, di ber va.
Gobelek, Shera, trees flow into it (are abundant), around
here.
Gundekî pir xweş e.
It is a very beautiful village.
Maşallah, maşallah. Xwedê milettê me yê muhafaze ke.
Mashallah, Mashallah. May God protect our people.
Ew zeytûna da di şixulin, wextê zeytûna ye jî.
Those working in the olives, as it is the olive season too.
Erê hevalno, li vê derê jî em hatin gihiştin cem Helûbiyê.
Yes friends, here we have arrived near Helubiye.
Hevalî ma we vê tebîetê bikşîne lê, çi tebîetek xweş e.
My friend, film this nature here, what beautiful nature it
is.
Tebîetek pir xweş e.
It is very beautiful nature.
Maşallah, tiştê wekî behrê ye gelî lê?
Mashallah, isn't it like a sea, folks?
Tiştê wekî behrê ye.
It is just like a sea.
Av cem mere be, çokso dilê merov bi eşq dibe. Hişînî,
hebine.
When water is near us, one's heart becomes filled with
passion. Greenery, look at it.
Maşallah... Êê darên wî mûsa xo çêkiroo.
Mashallah... Hey, he fixed his banana trees.
Li wê derê binê, çû dibe.
Look over there, how it is.
Hevalno av pir daketiye. Cezîre, Cezîre gelî, av heta nîvî
bû.
Friends, the water has gone down a lot. The Island, folks,
the water used to be halfway up the Island.
Berê makîna nikanî biçûna wi geçê.
Before, machines/cars couldn't go to that side.
Noka makîna di wiyo li ro... gelî di we ortê ra, av zev de
qetiye.
Now machines go there... folks, from the middle, the water
has been cut off (receded).
Duwir o darê ser wê cezîrê.
Far away on top of that island.
Berê rêk tune bû. Gi av bû.
Before there was no road. It was all water.
Av pir daketiye, binêrin. Elset bigre hevalê min, çokso
daketiye.
The water has dropped a lot, look. Film the landscape my
friend, it has dropped so much.
Av berê heta berê ber kevir bû.
The water used to be up to the rocks before.
Av heta berê ber kevir bû. Noka pir daketiye.
The water was up to the rocks. Now it has dropped a lot.
Lê... sê çêl pêncî metreyî av daketiye.
Like... the water has dropped thirty, forty, fifty meters.
Tebîetek pir xweş e.
It is very beautiful nature.
Ew no gi masi ne, çi ne?
Are all those fish, or what?
Wela masî qeçik tê de hene.
By God, there are small fish in it.
Wela, dibê gelek masi ne.
By God, she says there are many fish.
Ma... dik ma.
Just... look at that.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Şebaka o kirine wo, şebaka masiyan.
They have set a net there, a fish net.
Erê hevalno, dîsa em hatin.
Yes friends, we have come again.
Teb'en li vê derê jî em li mala... em cem birayê Luqman in.
Of course, here we are at the house of... we are with
brother Luqman.
Mala Mihemed Beytoz.
The house of Mihemed Beytoz.
Em li wê malbatê ne.
We are with that family.
Slavê me ji birayê Mihemed ra hene, Mihemed Beytoz.
Our greetings go to brother Mihemed, Mihemed Beytoz.
Û em hatin cem mala birayê me Luqman e.
And we came to visit our brother Luqman's house.
Me go em îstîrahe xwe çûçik vir bibin. Me go merheba ji te
ra birayê Luqman.
We said let's have a little rest here. We said hello to you,
brother Luqman.
Merheba, xêr hatî, kekê tu bi xêr hatî.
Hello, welcome, brother you are welcome.
Sax bî.
You are honored (Upon my eyes).
Be healthy (Thank you).
Birayê Luqman, te çi slavê dişînî ji Mihemed wana ra?
Brother Luqman, what greetings do you send to Mihemed and
the others?
Em slav dikin, bi dil û rûh û can, ji Mihemed ra û Siyabend
Mistefa ra, li xurbetiyê ne.
We greet them, with heart and soul and life, to Mihemed and
Siyabend Mistefa, who are in exile/abroad.
Slavê me ji birayê me Siyabend Mistefa ra jî hene.
Our greetings go to our brother Siyabend Mistefa as well.
Em wî jî slav dikin.
We greet him too.
Ew jî dengbêj e.
He is also a Dengbej (folk singer).
Erê rast e.
Yes, that's true.
Me go merheba ji te ra xalo.
We said hello to you, uncle.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Xalo... gundî we, xê nav lê kirin gundê Alke?
Uncle... your village, why did they name it the village of
Alke?
Gundê Alke, ji berê... yek li vir bû, esasê gund e.
The village of Alke, from the past... there was one here,
the foundation of the village.
Wekî gund, pê gund rûniştin. Navê xwe... navê xwe Alke bû.
As a village, the village settled after it. Its name... its
name was Alke.
Eeee, dar ji tê de heye. Çand dar e ku tû ye.
Ummm, there is a tree in it. Like a mulberry tree.
Vêra, li berê honan, hewşê xwe da çandikirin. Darê gundê
Alke.
Here, in front of those places, they planted in their
courtyards. The trees of Alke village.
Darê gundê Alke.
The trees of Alke village.
Û gund bi xwe du ayla ne.
And the village itself consists of two families.
Ayla Ce'bûlan e, ayla jî Hemkelekwan e.
It is the family of Ja'bul, and the family of Hemkelekwan.
Hemkelekwan.
Eywa, Hemkelekwan e.
Yes, Hemkelekwan.
Û vî din jî, gew cîranê me gi hotin cem me, gew bûn.
And the others too, the neighbors all came to us, they
became [part of us?].
Gund mezin bû, hereket çû.
The village grew big, movement happened.
Û hewîkî wekî nefs çû, be'dê nû rûniştin.
And that one [original site?] was abandoned, afterwards they
settled anew.
Wele.
Indeed.
Xudanê gund.
The owners of the village.
Îja gund kirin, binavê gundê, nav kirine gundê Alke, hewa çû
lê ew rûniştin.
So they made the village, in the name of the village, they
named it the village of Alke, that [old one] went, but they
settled [here].
Milletê vî gundî gi heye, gel mal e?
Are all the people of this village here, at home?
Welle, ê pir li vir in.
Well, the majority are here.
Ê pir li vir in.
The majority are here.
Millet çawa îdare dike, çi karî dikin?
How do the people manage (survive), what work do they do?
We her kes milkê gund de heye, darê gund de heye.
Well everyone has property in the village, trees in the
village.
Bi mewdûhê xwe, bi milkê xwe, darê xwe radikin, ditekînin.
Xizmet dikin yanî.
With their situation, with their property, they harvest
their trees, shake them down. They serve/work them, that is.
Û pê îdare dibin el-hemdu lillah. Û ya heye derê vaye ro tê.
And they manage/survive with it, praise be to God. And
whatever comes from outside [income] comes daily.
Ya nê îdare dibe.
That means it's manageable.
Xalo... şababê te kes li derva heye?
Uncle... do you have any young men (children) abroad?
Walayî, şababê min sê li Tirkiyê ne.
By God, three of my young men are in Turkey.
Û yek li Heleb e.
Yes.
And one is in Aleppo.
Û keçik jî zate li derva ne.
And the daughters are essentially abroad too.
Xwedê ji te ra bihêle. Slavê me ji qîçkê xalo ra hene, çavê
giya maç dikim.
May God keep them for you. Our greetings go to the uncle's
children, I kiss all their eyes.
Xalo tu yê slav ke bişînî ji qîçka ra, bişîne, ewa li te
seyr kin, mubaşer e li te seyr kin.
Uncle, if you want to send greetings to the children, send
them, they will watch you, they will watch you directly.
E hikumet e, lawê min, li hemberê min Mihemed Ebdilhenan e.
Navê gund de, Mihemed Ebdilhenan bes.
The government [representative], my son, opposite me is
Mihemed Ebdilhenan. In the village name, just Mihemed
Ebdilhenan.
Navê lêuk bi xwe hikumet e.
The name itself [of the position/person] is the government.
Slavên ji giya ra bişîne, ey pîgî nîn e.
Send greetings to all of them, it doesn't matter.
Erê wa, û Farûq heye.
Yes like that, and there is Faruq.
Slavê me ji wî re hene.
Our greetings to him.
Û Menan jî heye.
And there is Menan too.
Ew jî nefs, lawê Mihemedî Menî Ce'bûlî ne.
He is also the same, they are the sons of Mihemed Meni
Ja'bul.
Li Stenbolê ne.
They are in Istanbul.
Slavê te gihiştinê, mubaşer.
Your greetings reached them, directly.
İnşallah, sihetxweş be, Xwedê ji we razî be, ehlen we sehlen
bi hatina we.
God willing, good health, may God be pleased with you,
welcome to your arrival.
Sihetxweş xalo.
Good health, Uncle.
Erê slavê me ji miletê gundê Alke ra tevayî ra hene. Çûçik û
mezinan, çavê giya maç dikim.
Yes, our greetings go to all the people of Alke village.
Small and big, I kiss everyone's eyes.
Qîçkê xalo jî slavê me ji wê ra hene.
Our greetings also go to the uncle's children.
Ji Heleb ra, ji Rêzê wan ra, ji giya ra hene el-hemdu
lillah.
To Aleppo, to the Rêzê [family/place?] and them, to
everyone, praise be to God.
Erê.
Yes.
Ê serçavan.
Upon my eyes (You're welcome).
Teb'en birayê min Luqman li vê derê çûbî zeytûna. Ji zeytûna
hat.
Of course, my brother Luqman here went to the olives. He
came back from the olives.
Erê welle.
Yes, by God.
Çuwalê xwe anîne, da be meqbese.
He brought his sacks, to give to the press.
Ê... zêt diprê, da ku zêt diprê birayê Luqman?
Uh... does it yield oil, does it yield oil, brother Luqman?
Te ne, çuwal deh û heşt kîlo, deh û heşt kîlo nîv, duwê
durna tê.
Only, a sack of eighteen kilos, eighteen and a half kilos,
comes in that turn/cycle.
Yanî her çuwalek, ser tenekekê kêm tê?
That means for every sack, it comes less than a tin?
Tenekek û du-sê kîlo zeyt jê tê.
A tin and two or three kilos of oil comes from it.
Tibe zeyta wir a hisa li evî ye. Çiçikê hereket...
It seems the oil there right now is on the rise. A little
bit of movement...
Bazarê zeytê me noka li meqbesê pirskir teqrîben heştê û çar
dolaran û jor da.
Our oil market right now at the press, I asked, is
approximately eighty-four dollars and up.
Heştê û çaran û jor da.
Eighty-four and up.
Du mişbaba bera wek go heştê û pênc û bar jor.
Or as the guys told me, eighty-five and up.
Heştê û sî û...
Eighty-three and...
No' ewwel teb'en, evî hema no' ewwel.
First type of course, this is just the first type.
Heştê pênc, şeş, şêst û hewt.
Without a reason...
Eighty-five, six, sixty-seven [likely meant eighty-seven].
Erê ev no' ewwel e.
Yes, this is the first type.
Ko wara em hilkişin, derbasî ser hewşê bin.
Come, let's go up, pass onto the courtyard.
Emê hinekî tebîetê ser xweynin, li wa mînim.
We will breathe in some nature, I'll stay here [looking at
it].
Cewkî pir xweş e, gundê Alke.
A very beautiful atmosphere, the village of Alke.
Tebîetek pir xweş e, emê noka gunda jî pêşwa kin.
Very beautiful nature, we will show you the village now too.
Erê hevo, bo ye hemberî me, me go gundê Keferrûmê ye.
Yes friends, the one opposite us, we said it is the village
of Keferrum.
Keferrûmê.
Keferrum.
Ê...
Uh...
Evna jî me'rûf in, mabeynî wek tî, Gemrûkê û Meydankê...
These are also famous, between, like, Gemrûk and Meydankê...
Pir gund xuyn tên, Semolkê...
Many villages appear, Semolk...
Gund pir in.
There are many villages.
Qertqulaqê piçikêkê ji vir, Qertqulaq ji yê mezin.
Qertqulaq is a little bit from here, the big Qertqulaq.
Xeleqê milê wir heye, Qertqulaqê yakê herêmê, xeleqê milê
wir heye.
There is a circle/ring on that side, Qertqulaq of one
region, there is a circle on that side.
Maşallah, tebîetek pir xweş e.
Mashallah, very beautiful nature.
Maşallah, çi hewş dor digirtine.
Mashallah, what a courtyard they have surrounded.
Êêê...
Yeah...
Okay ev hewşa wye noka kîbar çêkirine.
Okay, they have made this courtyard of theirs very elegant
now.
Hewş...
Courtyard...
Ji me'lem cebûlî trompêçî ye.
It's from Master Cabul, the trumpet player.
Trompêçî?
The trumpet player?
Êêê, mala cîran mîranê wa ye.
Yeah, it's the neighbors' house.
Xeber isqê gund bixînim, wela hewşek kîbar çêkiriye.
Let me tell the news of the village, by God he built an
elegant courtyard.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Camo hîn karê dewletê negihîştiyê ne?
Man, has the government work [infrastructure/plastering] not
reached it yet?
Na, na wextê...
No, no the time of...
Ê inşallah, ewê, ewê bigihî derê gundê.
Uh God willing, it will, it will reach the village entrance.
Ma hezî marî me?
Are we [ready/going]?
Maşallah çi hewş difirandin, qe vî hewşê na dîbîn.
Mashallah, what a courtyard they opened up, we haven't seen
this courtyard.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Mewqi'ê gundê Alke pir xweş e.
The location of Alke village is very beautiful.
Mewqi'ê xwe bilind e.
Its location is high.
Birayê Mihemed, evna şta... hewşê wa ne, horata wa ye.
Brother Mihemed, this is... your courtyard, your open space.
Mala cîran mîranê wa ne.
It's your neighbors' house.
Evê ebdil şêx mûmed e.
This belongs to Abdul Sheikh Mumed.
Evê mamet e?
Is this Mamet's?
Êê sewax nekiriye.
Yeah, he hasn't plastered it.
Slavê me ji wî ra hene. Hewşê xwe xirab bî feqîre.
Our greetings to him. His courtyard is ruined, poor guy.
Abû Qazifalî kete.
Abu Qazifali entered.
Behele.
Never mind.
De mlo bişxule çawa ra xû bef gîne, ew wara teslîh ke, çêke.
So tell him to work, [so he can] bring himself together,
come and repair it, fix it.
Birayê Mihemed, evwa şta... hewşa te ye, li hewşê xwe sêr
ke, zîkrayatê te tê da pirr in.
Brother Mihemed, this is... your house/courtyard, look at
your courtyard, your memories in it are many.
Ekîd te ji mêjî nê çûye, heyşt sal ne te çûye. İnşallah tê
were mala xwe jî.
Surely you haven't gone long ago, it's been eight years
since you left. God willing you will come to your home too.
Are, ave şta halê gunda hona ye, daren zeytûna, noka wextê
zeytûna.
Yes, this is the state of the village here, olive trees, now
is the time of olives.
Em jî birayê me Luqman em ewra nakin, manî ew jî her ser
karê xwe, zeytûna diçinin, mlo ew jî here ser karê xwe.
And we, our brother Luqman, we won't delay him, as he is
also busy with his work, harvesting olives, so let him go to
his work.
Emê noka lextanê xweş kîbar emê nav gund wara çêkin, tiştê
xweş kîbar emê wara darxin.
We will now make nice elegant clips for you in the village,
we will produce nice elegant things for you.
Erê...
Yes...
Me go slavê me ji birayê me Siyabend ra hene, û birayê me
Mihemed ra.
We said our greetings go to our brother Siyabend, and to our
brother Mihemed.
Ez ji ber wava qehwe va dixwim, li... li hewşê birayê
Siyabend.
I will drink coffee on their behalf, in... in brother
Siyabend's courtyard.
Şûna qehwekê, du qehwa ez ji ber va dixwim, tedî, yek ji ber
wava, tedî?
Instead of one coffee, I will drink two coffees for them,
you know, one for them, you know?
Sê çarek dînîne pişê min.
Bring three or four others after me.
Ez ji ber wava va dixwim, wern.
I will drink for them, come.
Erê hevalno, noka emke darkevin, teb'en lextanê jêr çêkin, û
lextanê jî emkê li paş çêkin, tiştê xweş emê wer darxin.
Yes friends, now we will head out, of course make clips down
below, and we will make clips at the back too, we will
produce nice things for you.
Bi me ra bin, heta em darbazî gçê din bin.
Be with us, until we pass to the other side.
Bay bay ke xalo, vêra bay bay ke.
Bye bye uncle, say bye bye to here.
Erê birayê Mihemed, ev o hewşa te ye.
Yes brother Mihemed, this is your courtyard.
Erê ewê jûr hewşê birayê me Siyabend bî, ev jî hewşê Mihemed
e.
Yes that upper one was our brother Siyabend's courtyard,
this is Mihemed's courtyard.
Dibê qopî girtî ye, heta noka ew dike.
It seems the door/gate is closed, he is doing that until
now.
Erê birayê Mihemed, ev o hewşa te ye.
Yes brother Mihemed, this is your courtyard.
E qope klîd e.
The door is locked.
Ereb têda ne, çûye... qopî girtî ne.
There are Arabs in it, they went... the doors are closed.
Ev o horata wa ye.
This is your open space.
Mala kê li gundî ye? Kî li gund maye?
Whose house is in the village? Who has stayed in the
village?
Mala Hecî Gundî ye... Mala Bapîr Xweşê, Bapîr Kîbar e.
It is Hecî Gundî's house... Bapîr Xweşê's house, Bapîr
Kîbar.
Hecî Gundî, Bapîr Xweşê, Bapîr Kîbar e?
Hecî Gundî, Bapîr Xweşê, Bapîr Kîbar?
Ewa, ev mala li quncî ne, ev li quncî ne.
That one, these houses in the corner, these are in the
corner.
Erê.
Yes.
Ez ê hinekî ji vî alî ve jî hinekî bişînim, teswîr ke, min
hewş nafilite.
I will also film a bit from this side, film it, I didn't let
the courtyard go unfilmed.
Ev cîhê kê ye?
Whose place is this?
Maşallah xwelî û ciyê gundî ye, ciyekî xweş e xweş.
Mashallah, it is the soil and place of the villager, it is a
very nice place.
Maşallah tu dibêjî qey dar ji mer re axivîne.
Mashallah you would say the trees are talking to us.
Meytîno?
Meytîno na, yê na Çûnê...
Not Meytîno, these are Çûnê's...
Me şole, me berê sewirandîye.
We did the work, we filmed it before.
Meytîno?
Meytîno na, hîn em neçûne.
Not Meytîno, we haven't gone there yet.
Maşallah gund pirr in û daxwazan em nalahîqînin. Em nahên
ketin nahîyekê, ew nahîye pirr ji me daxwaz in.
Mashallah the villages are many and we cannot catch up with
the requests. We enter a district, that district has many
requests for us.
Erê rast e.
Yes, that's true.
Ji nahîyekê her yacîkî din jî pirr çetin e. Teselsul ez
teswîr dikim, berber ez teswîrê xilas dikim ez derim.
Going from one district to another place is very hard. I am
filming in sequence, one by one I finish filming and I go.
Maşallah çi hewşeke kîbar e. Pismamî te ye?
Mashallah what an elegant courtyard. Is it your cousin's?
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê rizqê gundî bişîne.
May God send the villager's provision.
Spas dikim.
Thank you.
De bikemile, wa hewşa kê ye?
Well complete it, whose courtyard is that?
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Evî enber me gubelek waye na?
On this side we saw a dome, right?
Gubelek e.
It's a dome.
Ew gubelaka min sewirandî.
That dome I filmed.
Çiyê, hewa bêtir ew gubelaka te sewirandî.
What is it... more that dome you filmed.
Erê gubela ko heftokê min teqwast.
Yes, the dome which I asked about.
Maşallah ew çi hewşeke min veda.
Mashallah what a courtyard I captured.
Ev ê...
This is...
Ev ê Halebî.
This is Halebî's.
Ew ê gundî piçûk e?
Is that the small villager [Gundî Piçûk]?
Erê erê.
Yes yes.
Avahî miletê me lê mal nava bigir wane... Wane, wane,
enberê...
The building of our people, but film inside the house...
That one, that one, that side...
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Ya Xwedê tu xêrê bikî.
Oh God may you do good.
Ev hewşa kê ye, piş mamo?
Whose courtyard is this, cousin?
Mala Birukê Mihemed.
House of Birukê Mihemed.
Mala Beytîs?
House of Beytîs?
Mala Beytîs.
House of Beytîs.
Erê.
Yes.
Maşallah, ciyê gundî xweş e, ciyêkî xweş e xweş.
Mashallah, the villager's place is nice, it's a very nice
place.
Erê.
Yes.
Maşallah ji vî gundî ra. Gundekî pirr xweş e, kîbar e.
Mashallah for this village. A very nice, elegant village.
Gedar mer re axivîne.
The walls speak to us.
Heya gundê Qeda, gundê Dewrêş...
Even the village of Qeda, village of Dewrêş...
Tiştê gundê we na bilind e jê hez dikim.
The thing about your village is it's high, I like it.
Qeregul e.
It is a watchtower [Qeregul].
Qeregul e?
It is a watchtower?
Erê.
Yes.
Tabîatê gundê we, mewqîyê xwe bilind e cografî...
The nature of your village, its location is high
geographically...
Min ji vî rekinî bigira.
I should take it from this angle.
De şole feqîro... Şole kes mera, ew neke, nebê mala me
derneketî.
Well, poor people's work... Someone's work, don't do that,
don't say our house didn't appear.
De em hewla dikin em hewşokê derxin.
Well we are trying to bring out the courtyards.
De şole şaşbîn çê nebin, hinek qusûrê me efû bikin.
So that misunderstandings don't happen, forgive some of our
faults.
De şole de xulû bes hewş hene, xweş hewş dane, dernakeve.
Mirov izmîş deke dibê hey hewşa me derneketîye...
The issue is, there are courtyards, nice courtyards, they
don't appear. One gets upset saying hey our courtyard didn't
appear...
Ciyê tê gundekî yek dibê hewşa me derneketî, yanî mala me ra
giya derketiye, ê mere dernekeve jî, mere çetin dibe.
In a village someone says our courtyard didn't appear,
meaning grass has grown on our house [it's abandoned], even
if it doesn't appear for us, it becomes hard for us.
Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, ciyê wî cenet be.
May God have mercy on him, may his place be heaven.
Erê Birê Mihemed, ev no rehmetiyê we ne, Xwedê rehma xwe lê
ke, ciyê wî cenet be. Li vê derê ne?
Yes Brother Mihemed, these are your deceased, may God have
mercy on him, may his place be heaven. Are they here?
Ê Bovkî Siyabend e.
It is Bovkî Siyabend.
Bovkî Siyabend? Kîjan e kîjan?
Bovkî Siyabend? Which one, which one?
Av no e... ew ê Spî...
This one... the white one...
Av no yê kê ye? Bovkî Mihemed, Ebû Beydoz e na?
Whose is this one? Bovkî Mihemed, Ebû Beydoz right?
Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, ciyê wî cenet be Mihemed.
May God have mercy on him, may his place be heaven Mihemed.
Ê Bovkî Siyabend e.
That is Bovkî Siyabend.
Erê av no jî ê rehmetî ne, ê Bovkî Siyabend.
Yes this one is also the deceased, Bovkî Siyabend.
Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, ciyê wî cenet be. Birê Siyabend av no
jî miriyê we ne, Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, ciyê wî cenet be. Av
no li min vê jî derxîne.
May God have mercy on him, may his place be heaven. Brother
Siyabend this is also your dead, may God have mercy on him,
may his place be heaven. Bring this one out for me too.
Bes boya ser çûye, boya ser çûye... 25-9-1981.
But the paint on it has gone, paint on it has gone...
25-9-1981.
Birê Hanan, ê miriyê we me nadîn. O xolû ew birê Meleqmon bi
mer ra ne, em çiqas digerin em nabînin.
Brother Hanan, we didn't see your dead. Oh uncle, that
brother Meleqmon is with us, however much we search we don't
see them.
Yumkin e tirba qebe nakirî be. Yanî qebe kirî be yozil ser
e, em ê zanibin qebe kirî ne.
Maybe the grave hasn't been built up. Meaning if it was
built there would be writing on it, we would know they are
built.
De em sehet dikin lê digerin, em nav nabînin. Bicûz qebe
nekirî be, bicûz av no ew bin. Ser hebin.
So we are searching looking for it, we don't see names.
Maybe it hasn't been built, maybe these are them. Let them
be on it.
Erê birêkî me Hanan, bicûz heve hew be, bicûz hev ew be.
Yanî kevrê xoy o şikî ye, rind yazi nate xuyankirin.
Yes our brother Hanan, maybe this is it, maybe this is it.
Meaning its stone is broken, the writing doesn't show well.
Yeko 1992. Vê derê jî yezmîş e 2012.
First one 1992. Here is written 2012.
Gerek hevo be. Yanî kevrê xwe şikî ye tenê perçê gindî
digerin.
Must be this one. Meaning its stone is broken, only looking
for pieces [around].
De Xwedê rehma xwe l miriyê giyo ke, û qusûrî me jî efû kin.
May God have mercy on all the dead, and forgive our faults.
Erê birê Hanan, mi li vê derê miriyê we bicîh kirin. Ovo
liyo pîta camêr e, mero hewal da.
Yes Brother Hanan, I located your dead here. Here is the
picture/plate of the gentleman, the friend gave.
Havo yek ev e, û havo, vana her sêk ewle ne.
Here is one, and this, these three are the ones.
Xwedê rehma xwe l gîyo ke ciyê gîyo cenet be. Saken nav li
ser tinen e, em nizanin, nav hebin, em ê zanibin. Avulî min
her sêko bigir nîzik.
May God have mercy on all, may everyone's place be heaven.
Look, there are no names on them, we don't know, if there
were names, we would know. Anyway take these three close up
for me.
Havo her sêk rehmetî ne, Xwedê rehma xwe l gîyo ke ciyê gîyo
cenet be. Av no her sêk ewle ne.
These three are deceased, may God have mercy on all, may
everyone's place be heaven. These three are the ones.
Taban liyo pîta mero hot hewal da.
Of course the picture/plate of the man came, friend gave.
Şole wekî dibê tijma razî be, ma av no ta ra sewirand in,
Nêçîrvan mero agû liyo pîta.
So that you may be satisfied, I filmed these for you,
Nechirvan told us regarding the plate.
Saeta genda xweş. Saetekine em lê digerin.
The village hour is nice. We've been searching for an hour.
Xwedê rehma xwe l gîyo ke ciyê gîyo cenet be.
May God have mercy on all, may everyone's place be heaven.
Wê bigire, vê ro.
Film that, from here.
Birê Hanan. Birê Hanan av no jî malbata te ye. Havo malbata
te ye. Taban av no jî mala Kolkî te ye, berê me tê da ew
kirîye. Hav hewşa we ye.
Brother Hanan. Brother Hanan this is also your family. This
is your family. Of course this is also your Kolkî's
[relative's] house, previously we did that inside. This is
your courtyard.
Silav, silav, êzîbar teva li vê derê me o.
Greetings, greetings, respect to all here with us.
Te ha bo tey qewaq bi me da te na mewcûd e am çûkan. Silavê
me ji te ra hene Birê Hanan.
You had a promise with us, you are not present, we left. Our
greetings to you Brother Hanan.
Erê birêkî min em vê derê jî me go em hatin gihiştine
Helebîyê. Em kê mala teter o teswîr kin. Havo hewşa we ye,
were.
Yes my brother, here too we said we arrived at Helebîye. We
will film Teter's house. Here is your courtyard, come.
Maşallah çi tebîatek xweş e.
Mashallah what a nice nature.
Erê birêkî min, havo hewşa we ye.
Yes my brother, here is your courtyard.
Were vro bes meke bê çi bê.
Come here, don't say "enough", whatever it is.
Hunur tê da namîne.
Art doesn't stay inside.
Avulî min wer wan o nîzik bike.
Anyway bring those close for me.
Abû hewalê te dikave Helebîyê, maşallah. Anobê gund çûbîn av
ne? Wadî ye Anob çûbîne wekî Helîko maşallah, maşallah. Av
no anob e dorê anobê ye.
Abu your friend falls to Helebîye, mashallah. Did the
village Jujube go [grow] these? It looks like Jujube went
like Helîko mashallah, mashallah. This is jujube, jujube
tree.
Qal nîzik bo min ê bixwara. Lê bigir şêx avulî min hewşê
bigir. Ono dûr çer me bigire.
Come close I would eat. Film it sheikh anyway film the
courtyard. Take the distant view for me.
Erê birêkî me av no hewşa we ye.
Yes our brother this is your courtyard.
Na têda peyabe, hewş xrad e be?
No get out inside, is the yard bad?
Erê bira kîmin hewşa xwe sererast ke, ava hewşa te ye.
Yes brother whoever fixes their yard, this is your yard.
Were Kuxul boy boy ke.
Come Kuxul say bye bye.
Maşallah xolû silk çandî ha, î girs biye.
Mashallah the uncle has planted chard huh, it has grown big.
A, hewş a way ji hoke ye, tê dît, ava hewşa way.
Ah, their yard is also like that, you saw, this is their
yard.
Sehet xweş, sehet xweş xalo. Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike de.
Health to you, health to you uncle. May God prolong your
life.
Erê birê Siyabend, li vî derê jî, em nav milkê wî ne. Havo
milkê te ye, ê birê me Siyabend.
Yes brother Siyamend, here too, we are in his property. This
is your property, of our brother Siyamend.
Hav zeytûnana û wê mehdera kêlekê ê birê me Siyabend in.
These olives and that plot on the side belong to our brother
Siyamend.
Xwedê rizqê gundiyan bişîne, wekî dibê, sehetê wî xweş,
milkê xwe rind e, ciyê xwe, mewqihê xwe pir xweş û kîbar e.
May God send sustenance to the villagers, as they say,
health to him, his property is good, his place, his location
is very nice and elegant.
Erê, havna zeytûnê te ne, birê Siyabend.
Yes, these are your olives, brother Siyamend.
Tabe'en av jî heye, av jî têdaye, û kêlekê jî ê birê me
Mihemed e.
Of course there is water too, water is in it, and the side
belongs to our brother Mihemed.
Erê, were lê bigre, ha vî alî me. Ev jî ê birê me Mihemed
in.
Yes, come film it, oh this side of us. These also belong to
our brother Mihemed.
Birê Mihemed silav ji te ra, û ji birê Siyabend ra.
Brother Mihemed greetings to you, and to brother Siyamend.
Erê, emkê noke Henarê jî buxun, werim. Wer bin, maşallah,
xêr bêr li vir pir e.
Yes, we will now eat Henar too, let me come. Come look,
mashallah, bounty is plentiful here.
Xalê Mihemed, migo xêr bêr cem te pir e. Maşallah gayê jî
derketin, ka em gayê bikin.
Uncle Mihemed, I said bounty is plentiful with you.
Mashallah oxen came out too, let's do the oxen.
Pêncêr e, pêncêr. Henara cûcik e, çi tana...
It is clover, clover. Henar is small, what...
Gelek cûcik e, bes biye.
Very small, but she is there.
Tarraciyê jê neke, bes çi tana pa...
Don't take off the earrings, but what...
Maşallah, were ha vî alî, were lê bigre. Birê Mihemed. Erê
min li canî te ayna be ha.
Mashallah, come this side, come film it. Brother Mihemed.
Yes, may I reflect on your soul.
Maşallah hênik e. Oh.
Mashallah it is cool. Oh.
Maşallah. Tabe'en hav ava jî, vê xêr bêra jî, ser lewah
şemsiye ye.
Mashallah. Of course this water too, this bounty too, is on
solar panels.
Mesref tune ye, mazot tune ye.
No expense, no diesel.
Seke, birkê xwe tije av kirine, û diser ra dirjê. Darê nav
zeytûna.
Look, they filled their pond with water, and it spills over.
Trees among the olives.
Heywan veduxwe, pê milkê xwe av didin. Dey wadîye, xêr bêrê
Efrîn, hav e ha.
Animals drink, they water their property with it. It is like
this, the bounty of Afrin, is this right here.
Î kê sebîl lêxey, bîra lêxey, hona lê dixin, te dît? Hona av
çêdikê, ha.
Whoever builds a sebil, digs a well, they do it here, you
saw? Here it makes water, look.
Were ha vî alî me darê din jî. Maşallah, a werin.
Come this side of us, the other tree too. Mashallah, ah
come.
Werin ez ji ber gişgiş me, gişgişa meydonkê, were were.
Come I am before the sprinkler, the sprinkler of the square,
come come.
Seke, birk tije biye, ku diser ra dirjê, ha. Hav jî henefî
ye.
Look, the pond is full, that it spills over, look. This is
also a tap.
Binêrin ha. Yo maşallah, maşallah.
Look here. Yo mashallah, mashallah.
Selaat 'en nebî. Oh.
Prayers upon the Prophet. Oh.
Wadîye? Xêr bêr pir e, li vî derê. Lewah şemsî ye honane,
havno binêrin ha.
You see? Bounty is plentiful, in this place. Solar panels
are over there, look at these here.
Onoy. Kesê ji me xwestî, as kê sebîl vira çêkim, pir ko ji
me xwest, ake sebîl vira çêkim.
There they are. Someone wanted from us, I will build a sebil
here, many wanted from us, if I will build a sebil here.
Go mara bîrê lêxe. Tabe'en dikulin, dikulin xetas berdidinê
û lewah şemsî ye hono drak bînin, wadîye?
[He] said dig a well for us. Of course they dig, they dig
and lower a submersible pump and bring solar panels here,
you see?
Havo cîhazê xwa ye. Cihazê lewha, di nava ardê, cîhazê
qa'îda vira çêke hobo.
This is its device. The device of panels, in the ground,
make the device base here like this.
Tabe'en ta qa'îda çêkir, mesref lê dikelfe. Havno ser qa'îda
ne.
Of course until you build the base, expense costs it. These
are on the base.
Û cîhazê lewha di nava ardê. Kerpîç naxwe bin ke. Almuhim
hono vê tesmîmê dişixule.
And the device of panels in the ground. Adobe... anyway here
this design works.
Çend lewh ne? Deh û heyşt lewh ne. Deh û heyşt lewh ne,
cîhaz rakib dikin, we kemiya avê derdixê.
How many panels? Eighteen panels. Eighteen panels, they
install the device, and it brings out this amount of water.
Çend înç ne? Awa înçek e? Du înç. Bi du înç av ne, bi deh û
heyşt lewha derdikeve.
How many inches? Is that one inch? Two inches. It's two
inches of water, coming out with eighteen panels.
Hav xêr bêr e. Birê Mihemed, havo ciyê te ye. Hewşê gindî jî
bigre.
This is bounty. Brother Mihemed, this is your place. Film
the village yard too.
Maşallah xêr bêr vir pir e, av pir e, hemkû do darin herre.
Mashallah bounty is plentiful here, water is plentiful, as
if we are going to [somewhere muddy].
Ge av bi civlaq. Maşallah, eke wadîye, nava vîstîn tije av
biye.
Look water is everywhere. Mashallah, look like this, inside
the dress is full of water.
Ê noka wîn vê avê, wê bikişin tije bî dar, hûn kê çûkin?
Berdayî zeytûna?
So now you, this water, you will pull it full be trees,
[where] will you go? Released to the olives?
Berdayî zeytûna, 'eşwayî ta berdayî na? No, xeta... berî
'eyar kirî...
Released to olives, random until released no? No, lines...
before adjusted...
Henefiyan va dikim, xo da. Welle? Bê mesref? Mesref tune ye.
I open the taps, it gives itself. Really? Without expense?
No expense.
Ma kî bişixule heqê lûh... ew lûh... avê derxe? Destê jor
kî?
But who works the price of panels... that panel... brings
out water? Whose upper hand?
Maşallah. Erê birê Mihemed, ev jî hewşa te ye, ho. Hava
hewşa te ye, te dî?
Mashallah. Yes brother Mihemed, this is your yard too, look.
This is your yard, you saw?
Nav milk da, ho çîçek jî çandine. Ya selam.
Inside the property, look flowers are planted too. Oh peace.
Mele dilê te bi me naşewite ho. Mele dilê te bi me nayê.
Man, doesn't your heart burn for us look. Man, doesn't your
heart feel for us.
Te xwest, te ixtiyar kir û tu çû Orûpa. Mitarê goher e ne
wey? Îşê wiye.
You wanted, you chose and you went to Europe. Is it the
airport of jewels, isn't it? It's his job.
Na wey, ox, çiboy hênik e weh. Sebah el xêr, sebah el nûr.
No way, oh, how cool it is wow. Good morning, light of
morning.
Ka cevizok? Hîn çênebine. Ewe? Hîn kulîlk in? Kengî çêdibin?
Heta mehek din.
Where is the walnut? They haven't formed yet. Is that so?
Are they still blossoms? When do they form? Until another
month.
Eke cevizok çavî min, eke li bin vir ceviza çoyê çêkim
bexem.
Look walnut my eye, if under here I make walnut tea
carefree.
Heye? Dibe ceviz heye, hemkê noko çawkê jî vexwin. Û dê
herro dê herr.
Is there? Say there are walnuts, we will now drink a tea
too. And go and go.
Erê welle. Cewkî pir xweş û kîbar e.
Yes really. A very nice and elegant atmosphere.
Birê Mihemed, em jî... Birê Mihemed, û Mihemed, û emîlca
Mihemed ne. Sê Mihemed.
Brother Mihemed, and we too... Brother Mihemed, and Mihemed,
and cousin Mihemed. Three Mihemeds.
Erê hav jî, birê me Mihemed, vî derê, ew jî xizmet dike,
xizmet milk dike û vê avê vî derê, hav jî li vî derê, li vê
hewşê dironiştiye.
Yes this too, our brother Mihemed, here, he also serves,
serves the property and this water here, he also here, sits
in this yard.
Sehetê gundî jî xweş. Wekî dibê, Efrîn cenet e, cenet. Bêhna
mirov dernakeve vî derê.
Health to the villager too. As they say, Afrin is paradise,
paradise. Man's breath does not run out here.
Mirov li vî derê be, her roj mirov bixwe, vexwe, mirov têr
nabe. Bi taybet ava şirîn e, ava hênik e.
If man is here, every day man eats, drinks, man does not get
full. Especially sweet water, cool water.
Seke, seke, seke, seke. Eze, eze xwe bavêjim nava ho. Xwe
bavêjim nava, melevaniya bikim.
Look, look, look, look. I will, I will throw myself inside
look. Throw myself inside, do swimming.
Çawa ye? Birê Mihemed, tu naxwazî xwe bavêjî nava? Hewa
hênik e.
How is it? Brother Mihemed, don't you want to throw yourself
inside? The weather is cool.
Hewa hênik e, ne? Tabe'en hewa hênik e. Hewa hênik e, av
hênik e, mirov dicemide.
Weather is cool, no? Of course weather is cool. Weather is
cool, water is cool, man freezes.
Bes zivistanê av germ e? E, zivistanê av germ e. Haho, hewa
sar e, av germ e.
But in winter the water is warm? Yes, in winter water is
warm. Aha, weather is cold, water is warm.
Havînê av sar e, hewa germ e. Berovajî ye. Welle, welle,
seke.
In summer water is cold, weather is hot. It's the opposite.
Really, really, look.
Eze dakevim, te hîvî dikim, eze dakevim nava. Welle bi
kincan ve dakevim.
I will go down, I beg you, I will go down inside. Really I
will go down with clothes.
Kuro de were, kuro de were, şerm ke. Şerm ke, eyb e. Mirov
mezin e, melevaniya dike nava hewşê.
Boy come on, boy come on, have shame. Have shame, it's
shameful. Man is big, doing swimming inside the pool.
Eyb e, şerm ke, welle eyb e. De here, xatirê te. Kê bi
Mihemed ra boy boy ke.
It's shameful, have shame, really it's shameful. Go on,
goodbye. Who will do bye bye with Mihemed.
Êwa. Erê... Baran e, ortê erdî tade. Tebî'etek pir xweş e vî
derê.
Yeah. Yes... It's rain, middle of ground is wet. A very nice
nature here.
Birê Mihemed, helal ke, eke henorkê jêkim. Bes henor hîn
havna rind mezin nebine.
Brother Mihemed, forgive me, if I pick a pomegranate. But
pomegranates here haven't grown well big yet.
Migo hîn mezin nebine. Wexta mîsuma zeytûna xelkê... xelkê
dest pê kiriye.
I said they haven't grown big yet. Time of olive season
people... people have started.
Welê? Maşallah. Henarê Efrîn, henarê Efrîn.
Really? Mashallah. Pomegranates of Afrin, pomegranates of
Afrin.
Henarê gundê 'Elkê, wa bixwin. Fermo. Havo xêr bêr ho.
Pomegranates of village 'Elkê, eat them. Here you go. This
is bounty look.
Kesê dixwaze sebîl çêke, es kê hono vêra çêkim, wadîye?
Whoever wants to build a sebil, I will build it here for
them, you see?
Havo du înç av ne. Erê. Tabe'en hesebî xemaqê ginde, kûrbîna
ginde.
This is two inches of water. Yes. Of course according to
depth of the ground, depth of the ground.
Hone sî metro? Sî û pênc. Sî û pênc metro av derketiye.
Here is thirty meters? Thirty five. Thirty five meters water
came out.
Eke kûrbîn sed metro be, sed û pêncî metro be, lewh pir
divê.
If depth is 100 meters, 150 meters, more panels are needed.
Tabe'en dikelfe, bes na wane, heseb, havo rizq e, marov
nizane.
Of course it costs, but not like that, depend, this is
sustenance, man doesn't know.
Erê birê Mihemed, em tabe'en me vîdyê xwe xilas kir. Em î jî
li ser... awê ta rûniştine... hewzi avê, li paş me ye.
Yes brother Mihemed, we of course finished our video. We are
also on... sitting on that... water pool, is behind us.
Xêr bêr heye, Xwedê rizqî wa bişîne. Rind e, kîbar e, hono
marov xizmet milk ke û av jî hebe, pir rind e.
There is bounty, May God send their sustenance. It's good,
elegant, look if man serves the property and there is water,
it's very good.
Erê le 'eynî cefof e, sol cefof hebî. Pir bîrê xelkê hişk
bîn. Û silavê me ji te ra hene.
Yes in the eye of drought, year was drought. Many people's
wells dried up. And our greetings to you.
Û her yekî li vî vîdyoyî seyr ke, silavê me ji wer hene.
Gotinê tan e? No, bes silavê me şewa wa ra hene, û bes.
And everyone who watches this video, our greetings to you
all. Do you have words? No, just our greetings to them
tonight, and that's it.
Xwedê canî kî sax gîndî wo de. Sehet xweş. Qolû gotina tan
e? Na, seheta te xweş.
May God give health to the soul of your villagers. Health to
you. Uncle, do you have words? No, health to you.
Seheta şewa wa jî xweş, û em silav dikin. Sehet xweş. De ho
de, bi xatire we. Boy boy.
Health to you all too, and we greet. Health to you. Come on
then, goodbye. Bye bye.
Erê havolno, li vî derê jî tabe'en magû am li ber Sêdê
Meydonkê ne, serî sêd ne. Hamber min gundê 'Elkê ye.
Yes friends, here too of course I said we are before the
Meydanko Dam, at the top of the dam. Opposite me is the
village of 'Elkê.
Hamber min verê Helebî ye. Magû gemrîkê gundê şurba
Meydankê.
Opposite me is the Aleppo road. I said a tour of the
village... Meydanko.
Bi mara bin dîsa vîdyokî xweş kîbar. Bîr nekin laykê
îştîrakê pê din. Saet xweş.
Stay with us for another nice elegant video. Don't forget to
give like and subscribe. Health to you.