Maşalla li vê derê... Av hebe, li sorkê av hebe, maşalla
hêşîn e.
Mashallah, here... If there is water, if there is water in
the market, mashallah it is green.
Hevalno bi me ra bin emê hinekî... sorkê, malê mêrek. Yanî
îro bazar sist e hûru. Bazora vê derê sendewîşê çêdike, î
kezab e û î kift e.
Friends, stay with us, we will a little... market, a man's
goods. Meaning today the market is weak. The market here
makes sandwiches, this is liver and this is kofta.
Erê hevalno Xwedê hem xelas kirin, îşta qeza heval du mera
çêbî, Xwedê hem xelas kirin. Û qeçik jî gel bine, dûr bin vê
derê.
Yes friends, God saved us, an accident happened to two
friends of ours, God saved us. And may the girls also be
well, stay away from here.
Erê hevalno siba we bi xêr. Çûnin şolan? Rewşa we, rehet ne?
Hevalno hûru vîdyokî xweş kîbar emê were çêkin. Hûru ro
şêşem e, cema, şêşem. Cema bazora Raco, bazora dewer. Xokek
me jî ji me xwestî em vêra dewarekî bikirin û vêra bibin ber
tirba Şêx Reşîd, em vêra darjikin.
Yes friends, good morning to you. How are things? Your
situation, are you comfortable? Friends, today we will make
a nice, neat video for you. Today is Tuesday, folks,
Tuesday. Folks, Rajo market, the livestock market. A sister
of ours asked us to buy a livestock animal for her here and
take it to Sheikh Rashid's tomb for her, we will slaughter
it for her.
Lawkê gundê tim qezê dikeve. Go hema dê mera berxekî bikire
û bibin ber Şêx Reşîd emê kê vêra darjikin û emê li feqîra
vêra bela kin. Wînên bi me ra bin, em hatine bazora Raco û
emê asara jî bipirsin qurban biçin e, ne, meselê xwo çûye,
emê bipirsin asara, î mê biçine û î nêr biçine. Emê ji milet
bipirsin, bi me ra bin.
The village boy always gets into accidents. She said just
buy a lamb for us and take it to Sheikh Rashid, we will
slaughter it for her and distribute it to the poor for her.
You stay with us, we have come to Rajo market and we will
ask the prices, how much the sacrifices are, no, how the
issue went, we will ask prices, how much the females go for
and how much the males go for. We will ask the people, stay
with us.
Erê hevalno li vê derê jî em hatin gihiştin bazora Raco.
Bazora şêşem e. Teben yek şemiyê, şemiyê bazar pir zehmet
dibe, bes şêşemê bazar sist e. Em hatin jî bazar sist e.
Yanî hîn zû ye, sebe saet nehe. Ê mêrek me ra dibê li cem
min hene li sorkê. Akê noka mêrek raherim ro sorkê, akê
berxê bimade.
Yes friends, here too we have arrived at Rajo market. It is
the Tuesday market. Of course, one is Saturday, on Saturday
the market gets very crowded, but on Tuesday the market is
weak. We arrived and the market is weak. Meaning it's still
early, morning nine o'clock. And a man tells us "I have them
with me at the market". Here now I will get up and go to the
man, face the market, he is going to give us the lamb.
Xonê malê Sîno sork e.
Owner of Sino's house is red.
Xonê malê Sîno? Ez jî ji malê Sîno me.
Owner of Sino's house? I am also from Sino's house.
Ahlan wa sahlan bi ser çava. O me îlemê derket hadi.
Welcome, upon my eyes. Oh, our relative turned out to be,
come on.
Ezbenî, ez man xonê berxikî pêde, wezin çi de? Ez benî.
Sir, I gave the owner a lamb, what weight did he give? Sir.
Ser serê min.
Upon my head.
Bi ser çava, hela serim.
Upon eyes, welcome.
Li vê derê bazar sist e?
Is the market weak here?
Bazar hûru şêşem hûru tine ye bixwedê.
The market today Tuesday today is non-existent by God.
Roja şemiyê zehm e?
Is Saturday crowded?
Xêr e, zehm e.
It's good, it's crowded.
Ê bazar namo? Bazar wate xelas be?
And the market isn't staying? When will the market finish?
Asar biçine? Bixwedê asar rindin. Î mê dûr çor nîv e, î nêr
pênc.
How much are the prices? By God prices are good. The female
is two four and a half, the male is five.
Weleh.
Really.
Kerem kin herin cem wan.
Please go to them.
Emê kerem kin herin. Yalla hevalno bi me ra bin emê noka do
kevin sorkê, malê mêrek. Lan îbro bazar sist e hûru.
We will please go. Come on friends, stay with us, we will
now go down to the market, a man's goods. Man, brother, the
market is weak today.
Bazar sist û xelas bûyî.
Market is weak and finished.
Û zû ye, saet neh e. Ka bi me ra bin.
And it's early, nine o'clock. Come stay with us.
Erê hevalno li vê derê jî xolê Ehmed ji gundê Ba'dîna ye.
Bazora vê derê sendewîşê çêdike. Î kezab e û î kift e. Yanî
sendewîşê gundê me'rûf ne, milet git tê cem gundê dikire.
Pir xweş çêdike. Hamo kifta çêdike vir û ewê zeytê... bero
durim dike.
Yes friends, here too is Uncle Ahmed from the village of
Ba'dina. The market here makes sandwiches. This is liver and
this is kofta. Meaning the village sandwiches are famous,
all the people come to the villager and buy. He makes it
very well. Hamo makes kofta here and that oil... he wraps
it.
Tu bi çend difroşî sendewîş?
How much do you sell the sandwich for?
Sendewîş bîst pênc wereqe.
Sandwich is twenty-five bills.
Sendewîş bîst pênc tirk. Erê. De ko bi me ra bin am han
sorkê.
Sandwich twenty-five Turkish [Lira]. Yes. So come stay with
us let's go to the market.
Mî birçî me tîr bik. Ka sorkê? Ka berxikî xoyin û were.
I am hungry, make it big. Where is the market? Come let's
eat a lamb and come.
De bi me ra bin.
So stay with us.
Erê hevalno li vê derê jî em hatin gihiştin sorkê. Vê derê
jî ew e qoban e, qoban. Cî dewer e. Ê malê Sîno ye. Me îlemê
derket. Erê. Ko hevalî min lê bigir emhen dewer sekin. Erê
dewarê liko ye? Welle mêrek me ra hot em rohatin sorkê.
Yes friends, here too we have arrived at the market. Here
too that is the scale, scale. The place for livestock. It
belongs to the Sino family. Turned out to be our relative.
Yes. Come my friend film it, let's look at these livestock.
Yes, where are the livestock? By God the man told us, we got
up and came to the market.
Wara abozat wara. Em go hatin mêrek ma'nî kûçik natin me?
Xalo here here hinek ta başqa kir ne, xêr e?
Come Ebo Zad, come. We came, did the man bring us puppies?
Uncle go go you separated some, is it good?
Nê?
What?
Viro ewe pezî reş e?
Here are those black sheep?
Na na belê... pezî reş e, pezî... bas ne helo noka germ e...
çikê...
No no yes... black sheep, sheep... but not like that, now
it's hot... small...
Hevalno qurbanên çû doxizen henen. Î nêr, î mê. Xonê malê
Sîno.
Friends, there are the sacrifices you want. Male, female.
Owner of Sino family.
Erê xonê malê Sîno li sorkê, awolî te ket sorkê. Xone li vê
derê haya. Te dewerê çû doxizî hene. Ko hevalî min lê bigir.
We vê derê hevalî ma vano lê bigir. Maşalla maşalla. Te
hazir qesandîne jî.
Yes, owner of Sino family in the market, around you fell the
market. The owner is here. You have the livestock you
wanted. Come my friend film it. Here my friend film these.
Mashallah mashallah. You have even selected them ready.
Paqij ne welle, rind e.
They are clean by God, good.
Erê maşalla. Rind e.
Yes mashallah. Good.
Abozat veke.
Ebo Zad open it.
Hevalno sekin maşalla li vê derê. Av hebe, li sorkê av hebe,
maşalla hêşîn e. Weren. Hevalno binêrin bîberê. Maşalla ha.
Teze ne. Î bîstên. Gê tenqîta çondî ye.
Friends look mashallah at this place. If there is water, if
there is water in the market, mashallah it is green. Come.
Friends look at the peppers. Mashallah ha. Fresh. Of the
garden. It is all drip irrigation planted.
Xwedê rizqê gundê bişîne. Mere şaxil, Xwedê rizqê gundê
bişîne. Û av jî dewran ke dilyzîne. Maşalla binêrin.
Bacansorkê bîstên teze ye, ha.
May God send sustenance to the villager. Man works, God
sends sustenance to the villager. And the water also
circulates, plays. Mashallah look. Tomatoes from the garden
are fresh, ha.
Hevalno maşalla. Avno manî dolme.
Friends mashallah. These are meant for dolma.
Ê batmanê ye.
They are from Batman.
Lê ê Batmanê sorkê. Lê maşalla xêr bér li vir pir e.
Yes, the Batman ones of the market. Yes mashallah, goodness
and produce is plentiful here.
Erê hevalno, gelê maşalla xeyarê... gih teze ne têda. Av jî
gih xiti û xeyar ne, vê derê çandine. Wîn hotin, ji jorî
Raco gelî Sîrisînê têne. Awolî sorkê, wir malbateke heye,
qopîkî mezin e. Li vê derê berxo dirvşê. Hevalî min vana jî
lê bigir.
Yes friends, many mashallah cucumbers... all fresh in there.
These are also all snake cucumbers and cucumbers, planted
here. You came, from upper Rajo, Sorsine valley they come.
First at the market, there is a family there, it's a big
place. Here he sells lambs. My friend film these too.
Erê gereke wek hene wînê wan vê jî... çim nişakal hene. Kar
hene, bizin hene, mî, berx. Qemir ya tivîn çû doxizen li vê
derê.
Yes, there needs to be like these, you will see their
place... because there are types. There are kids, goats,
ewes, lambs. Brown ones, whatever you see or want is here.
Abozat bigir Abozat. Abozat maşalla pişta te jî ye. Xêr bér
vir pir e, xêr bér vir pir e.
Ebo Zad hold it Ebo Zad. Ebo Zad mashallah your back is also
strong. Goodness and produce is plentiful here, goodness and
produce is plentiful here.
Erê hevalno avo qoban e, li virdê dipîvin. Sekin manî na
roxên. Ko bigir heta mêrek tê.
Yes friends this is the scale, they weigh here. Look,
meaning not bad. Come film until the man comes.
Hevalno maşalla çi cî mêrek haya. Of ofa behr e. Ofa behr e.
Erê hevalno me avo kirî. Avo me kirî. Yekî serzer e. Me
girêda û me kir bogajê. Serî xwo bifilitîne belû merû rêgi
bişkîne welle.
Friends mashallah what a place the man has. Water, water of
the sea. It's a sea of water. Yes friends we bought this
one. This one we bought. It's a yellow-headed one. We tied
it and put it in the trunk. It saves its head but the
snake/man might break the way by God.
De ko bi me ra bin emê herin noka gundê Ba'dîna, emê ben Şêx
Reşîd jî emê darjikin ji xokê me ra. Ko bigire.
So come stay with us we will go now to the village of
Ba'dina, we will take it to Sheikh Rashid and we will
slaughter it for our sister. Come film.
Erê hevalno am li vê derê jî... amj awe tên, vê gundiyana
jêr sorkê. Av gindeno jî gih gundê ê tirk ne. Gelê diwori
liko. Erê. Or bi çoyî wono keti. Wî wilî. Maşalla sorkê
xweş.
Yes friends, here we also... we also come to those, this
village below the market. These villages are all Turk
villages. Many walls where. Yes. The place has fallen to
their tea. Like that. Mashallah nice market.
Erê viro bêr dibin Geliyê Sorsînê hevalno. Geliyê Sorsînê.
Vir jî Xarobê Simaq. Av gindo Xarobê Simaq e. Kûk çend mal
ne. Heyşt mal ne, heyşt mal. Erê û dê toli jî bigir hevalî
min. Gih çûçik e hema di vê derê de be gelî do. O mêrikî
dorê şemsê diçîne.
Yes here they call it Sorsine Valley friends. Sorsine
Valley. Here is also Kharabe Simaq. This village is Kharabe
Simaq. Just a few houses. Eight houses, eight houses. Yes
and you take the surroundings too my friend. It's all bushes
just here in the valley. Oh the man is planting sunflowers.
Erê hevalno em li vê derê li gundê Ba'dîna bertirbê Şêx
Reşîd ne. Xokek me, teben nêt kirî, berxekê jî qaçka xwo re
darjike. Navê qaçkê gindî jî... yekî Birahîm, Salar, û
Bilind. Inşalla Salar bidobiti ki mezin be û Bilind jî
bilaybi gûke tav mezin be. Û Bilind jî, çavî wî jî maç dikim
û Xwedê ji giyo razî be, Xwedê barqado balo ke û ber destê
miriyê gindyo gine, Xwedê wekî dibê ji xişm û bêtorê gindyo
bixafilîne, Xwedê bedenê we jî şê bike û inşalla bi tewfîq
we necah wekî dibê ji Salar ra û Bilind ra û Birahîm ra.
Inşalla pêşketin be ji wa ra, serkeftin be. Û barxo me jî
ovoye emê noka darjekin. Lani em nikanin kêrê bisidin û
darxînin. Lani bicuz xwin ser ji ave me... ew be. Yanî
zirarê pê bike. No emê darjikin. Ebû Ehmed... ko hevalî min
bigir heta darjêke.
Yes friends here we are in Ba'dina village at the tomb of
Sheikh Rashid. A sister of ours, naturally made a vow, to
slaughter a lamb for her daughter. The name of the village
girl too... one Ibrahim, Salar, and Bilind. Inshallah Salar
will grow up with a wedding and Bilind also be high... grow
up big. And Bilind too, I kiss his eyes and may God be
pleased with her, may God remove troubles and may it reach
the hands of the dead of the villagers, may God as they say
protect the villagers from wrath and calamity, may God keep
your bodies healthy and inshallah with success and victory
as they say for Salar and for Bilind and for Ibrahim.
Inshallah progress for them, success. And our lamb is this
one, we will now slaughter it. Meaning we cannot hold the
knife and take it out. Meaning maybe blood on that... it
might be. Meaning it might cause harm. No, we will slaughter
it. Abu Ahmed... come my friend film until he slaughters.
Xwedê xêra wî qebûl bike, Xwedê qurbanê wî qebûl be. Inşalla
qaçka wî... ê jin ke, inşalla qebûl be, Xwedê siheta xweş
bidê, Xwedê rizqê gundê bişîne. Sibo şêşem e, baş e reş e,
emê vêra sng dikin, Xwedê qaçkê me mihafize ke. Xwedê qaçko
jêra bêle.
May God accept her charity, may God accept her sacrifice.
Inshallah her daughter... make from her, inshallah it be
accepted, God give her good health, God send sustenance to
the villager. Morning is Tuesday, it is good black, we are
slaughtering for her, God protect our daughter. God keep the
daughter for her.
Erê, avo jî bo Salar e.
Yes, this is also for Salar.
Bo Salar e avo.
This is for Salar.
Salar û Bilind û Birahîm vo. Erê.
Salar and Bilind and Ibrahim here. Yes.
Ma vêra bikim, emê vêra dia jî bikin, inşalla bela qada bela
ke, Xwedê rizqê wan pir bike, inşalla canî sag bidê. Am
hatine ber Şêx Reşîd, sibo şêşem e. Emê ro xirban jar ji ke,
inşalla Xwedê qebûl ke û canî sag pê dê. Xwedê rizqê gundê
bişîne.
We will do for her, we will pray for her too, inshallah may
He remove trouble and calamity, God increase their
sustenance, inshallah give healthy bodies. We have come to
Sheikh Rashid, morning is Tuesday. We will make a sacrifice
for her, inshallah God accept and give healthy body. God
send sustenance to the villager.
De ji xweş.
Thanks auntie.
You too be good.
Hevalno, qaçkno jî... cîçkno... cîçkno, ne mazin e. Cîçkno,
sake, bi... yanî bi tiştê pênc deqe, ne pênc dafqa, pênc ro
da bin, pir tişkî mazin e.
Yes friends...
Hevalno, qaçkno jî... cîçkno... cîçkno, ne mazin e. Cîçkno,
sake, bi... yanî bi tiştê pênc deqe, ne pênc dafqa, pênc ro
da bin, pir tişkî mazin e.
Friends, little ones too... little ones... little ones, not
the big ones. Little ones, look, with... I mean, with things
that take five minutes, not five minutes, five days, it's a
very big thing.
Arê, nivîsî go Salar û Îbrahîm û Bilind. Înşallah yek bibê
şifêrê, yek bilayîbî guke bê û inşallah yek jî bi da bê, yek
jî tixtor bê, û bi bilind, hîn bilind bin.
Yes, it was written Salar, Ibrahim, and Bilind. God willing,
one becomes a driver, one becomes a ball [soccer] player,
and God willing one becomes a [unclear], one becomes a
doctor, and rise high, rise very high.
Qaçkno, yanî hîn cewîl ne? Saetê gendîyê xweş û inşallah
xwedê bereketê belav ke, ko maro bin.
Little ones, meaning are they still twins [young]? Have a
good time, and God willing, God spreads blessings, may you
remain alive.
Arê hevalno ma vederê... darje kir, nuke mêrke mar here mal
çêke, em ê têkevin tûra û em ê inşallah belav kin.
Yes friends, we here... [unclear] here, now the man went to
fix the house, we will start the tour and God willing we
will broadcast it.
Arê hevalno, hewa, hewa teb'an gundê me ye, gundê Badîna.
Gundê me jî mazin e ha.
Yes friends, this, this is naturally our village, the
village of Badina. Our village is big too, huh.
Erê maşallah. Em î naha çûn şexraşîtê ne, em ketin jor mal.
Mêrikî cîranê mal. De dî gundê me çiqas mazin û rind e.
Yes, Mashallah. We have now gone to Shexrashit [location],
we entered the upper house. The neighbor of the house. Look
how big and beautiful our village is.
Xelkê Hikmet jî lê mê ke, dinya xelkê Hikmet. Saetê xostka
Hikmet xweş.
Look at Hikmet's people too, the world of Hikmet's people.
Have a good time, Aunt/Uncle Hikmet.
Hevalno senkê xelkê Hikmet jî pir qedîm in ho. Yanî
melevanî... de eh gund pir qedîm in. Meyra Şexreşîtê jî.
Friends, looks like Hikmet's people are very ancient too. I
mean swimmers... the village is very ancient. The Meyra of
Shexreshit too.
Wadî ye xelk çûn meşrûa ta radike, ho ho ho. Meşrûat pir ne.
It seems the people went to start the project, ho ho ho.
There are many projects.
Ho ho evro... Maşallah şixul behr e ho. Ev çi meşrûa ki hewa
jî. Maşallah.
Ho ho today... Mashallah the work is [like] a sea. What kind
of project is this too. Mashallah.
Mago şixul bî behr. Wa xebitiyo kio.
I said the work has become a sea. Who has worked.
Tabea malê min xol binî banî ye ha.
Naturally my house is under the roof, huh.
Hewa jî Warşo berî ve, muwereda derxistîye. Wadîye digota
bildozer û de kola.
This is Warsho from before, he has brought out the
generator/supplies. It seems he was saying bulldozer and
digging.
Mago heke do destpêkrin, caiz kirin, magû. Mago heke do
destpêkrin, caiz kirin.
He said if they started, they made it ready, he said. He
said if they started, they made it ready.
Malê me jî hewşekî ye, rekê darê xezanê. Selam eleykum.
Our house is also a courtyard, the way of the Gazane tree.
Peace be upon you.
Hevalno hewa hewşa min e, seke dû vederê qeza bî. Hevalno
hewa hewşa min e, malê min hewşekî gundkî ye.
Friends, this is my courtyard, look, an accident happened
here yesterday. Friends, this is my courtyard, my house is a
village courtyard.
Dû jî hevalkî min sîtelka av mirov îna. E sîtelka vê wîna,
li vederê jor sekinand. Kevir daber, sîtel jî giran bî. E
xweser kevirê çe kir, filitî mêrik ro.
Yesterday a friend of mine brought a bucket of water. He
brought this bucket, he stopped up here. The stone
underneath, the bucket was heavy too. It spontaneously moved
the stone, it slipped from the man.
Wîna, kîna kî sireat bî hezar, xo berda. Xwedê hem xelas
kirin. Draktor jî li wrta vir ket, hevalî min lê bigir.
Bine.
It came, came, the speed was a thousand, it let itself go.
God saved us too. The tractor fell in the middle here, my
friend, hold it. Look.
Mêrik car da şifêr bî, rabî wê sireatê hatî, qelebû li
vederê. Yanî jêr da here, ekî dinyayê xera bike. Draktor û
tişt û av.
The man was a driver for a while, he got up and came with
that speed, he flipped over here. Meaning if it went down,
it would destroy the world. Tractor and things and water.
Tekerek li vir ma û yek li jor ma. Xudê neke, eger bîstek
mabî, teker têwerbiba, dîsa e qeza e biba no. Makîna xwe jî
li paş wê sekinandî bî.
One wheel stayed here and one stayed up there. God forbid,
if a short time passed, if the wheel had turned, the
accident would have happened again. He had parked his car
behind it too.
Diyor gi ser makînê da çû, xwedê hem xelas kirin. Yanî ineke
diyor ketiba ser makînê, makîneke hûr hûrî biba.
It went right over the car, God saved us too. I mean, look,
if it had fallen on the car, the car would have been smashed
to pieces.
E mago wa bî, wa bî. Nihat wîna yî, ez keviro amîda têk me û
baa binim, ez ê makîna xwe têkim vederê. Derabîk xwe jî
mekanî em ê pêxin. Yeweş yeweş.
Uh, he said it was like this, like this. Nihat brought it, I
will put the stone pillars and bring the level, I will put
my car here. We will light up the gate mechanism too. Slowly
slowly.
Arê hevalno, xwedê hem xelas kirin işta qeza hewa dû maro
çêbî. Xwedê hem xelas kirin. Û qiçik jî gil binê dîwar bîn
vederê. Qiçkê min li hewşê dilîstin, makîna min bine wir bî.
Yes friends, God saved us too, look, this accident happened
to us yesterday. God saved us too. And the children were all
under the wall here. My children were playing in the
courtyard, my car was under there.
Yanî xwedê neke îşek biba, hen qiçik jî, hen makîne jî gi
çûbî. Arê, xwedê hem xelas kirin. Dilî me pak e.
Meaning, God forbid if something happened, both the children
and the car would have been all gone. Yes, God saved us too.
Our hearts are pure.
Arê, draktor ro jor da filitî. Û li vederê jî mêrikî noko
qurbanê maro ew dike. Silar e o, hewa qurbanê te yo. Sake.
Îbrahîm. Bilind.
Yes, the tractor slipped from up there today. And here the
man is now sacrificing [an animal] for us. It is Silar, here
is your sacrifice. Look. Ibrahim. Bilind.
Noka mêrikê caiz bike, em ê paşê ra daxin cem gundê mehele,
ê giyi li makînê xînê. Û em ê inşallah belav kin li feqîra.
Arê. Xwedê bereketê belav ke, saetê giya xweş.
Now the man will make it ready, we will then take it down to
the village neighborhood, the one who hits the grass with
the machine. And God willing we will distribute it to the
poor. Yes. May God spread blessings, have a good time
everyone.
Arê hevalno, ev jî dêka min e. Um Semîr, tîkê çi silavê didî
şînê millet ra?
Yes friends, this is my mother too. Um Samir, what greetings
do you give to the viewers?
Merheba Zuwara. Xwedê saetê xweş bide, xwedê bereketê belav
ke. İnşallah hûn serkevin. Xwedê qiçkê we zewara bêle.
Hello Zuwara. May God give happy hours, may God spread
blessings. God willing you succeed. May God leave your
children for you, Zuwara.
İnşallah xwedê we mehfeze ke, destê xwe bavînê xê, dest we
da zer be, inşallah.
God willing, may God protect you, may you put your hand in
goodness, may gold be in your hands, God willing.
Qurbanê jî zaf e, hê heval, şîvê pê zêr jî dikin, e harin li
feqîra da ro belav kin. Saetê we giya xweş.
The sacrifice is plenty, hey friends, they are making dinner
with gold [value] too, let them go and distribute it to the
poor. Have a good time, everyone.
Um Semîr, serî vana jî me xîn lê xist. Ne, ma te li bîr ne?
Semîr serî xirab wana? Arê.
Um Samir, regarding these guys, we spilled blood
[sacrificed] on them. No, don't you remember? Samir is a
headache for them? Yes.
Wa hevalno, dinê germ e.
Oh friends, the world is hot.
Arê hevalno, hewe vîdyoyê ma dimal da bî teban. Ez nikanim
derkevim, ser wê qeza dû maro çêbî ye.
Yes friends, this video of ours was at home, naturally. I
cannot go out, because of that accident that happened to us
yesterday.
Arê hevalno, ê min, ez a pirça vîdyoyetê xwe çêdikim, ez
nokim minîyê ser kesî, işim bi kesî tune.
Yes friends, mine, I am making parts of my videos, I don't
put obligation on anyone, I have no business with anyone.
Însan kî, wekî dibê, ma ten medenî me, însan kî, yanî wekî
dibê ez perisqê xwe ketime.
A person, as they say, I am a civilized person, a person, I
mean as they say, I am chasing my sustenance.
Û em ê jî wekî dibê agî divero dikime, ez divero dardixim.
Joxê mi qenaat çêkir, ez zanim mesele qenaat û tuktoko dero
ez gi zanim.
And we also, as they say, I do this here, I put it out here.
When I made the channel, I know the issue of the channel and
the TikTok around, I know it all.