Rojbaş xuşk û birano, dîsa em hûr hatin, vîdyoyekî xweş,
kîbar.
Good day sisters and brothers, again we came to you, with a
nice, neat video.
Erê, hevalno vîdyoya me jî hûr em hatine... vêderê...
nahiyeya Mabeta, em hatine gundê Hebo.
Yes, friends, our video, we have come... here... to the
Mabeta district, we have come to the village of Hebo.
Teb'an cew nexweş e, cew... vistan e, mij û dûman e. Em
nikarin gundê dûr, ji me xwestina xelkê, em nikarin
bişkênin.
Of course the weather is bad, the weather... is winter, it
is foggy and misty. We cannot [go to] distant villages,
[but] the request of the people from us, we cannot refuse
it.
Xuşk û birayekî ji me xwestî.
A sister and a brother asked us.
Em herin jî, cew ne mesele ye, me got mla rûxweş derkeve,
emê herin me'nî cefê me bike.
Even if we go, the weather is not an issue, we said let it
result in happiness, we will go so our effort is worth it.
Emkî jî hûr derbasî gundê Hebo bin.
We will pass through to the village of Hebo for you.
Gundê Hebo jî pir ne mezin e, çûçik e, tabî'î nahiyeya
Mabeta ye.
The village of Hebo is not very big, it is small, belonging
to the Mabeta district.
Erê, heft heşt kîlometre ne heta Mabeta.
Yes, it is seven or eight kilometers to Mabeta.
Bîr nekin te'lîqê na me ra binivîsînin, mla vîdya me
pêşkeve, le'nî vîdya me şûnda de are.
Don't forget to write comments for us, so that our video
progresses, because our video is coming from behind
[lagging].
Û... em nikarin... di mal de vîdyoya xwe çêkin, le'nî ye me
muhtewê me gunda ye.
And... we cannot... make our video at home, because ours,
our content is villages.
Û vîdyê dû vêra jî înşallah emê vîdyokî çêkin, emê vîdyê
te'lîqa wera çêkin.
And the video after this one, God willing, we will make a
video, we will make a video for your comments.
Emê te'lîqê we giya bixwînin, emê vîdyokî wana çêkin. Le'nî
ez di mal de nikarim çêkim.
We will read all your comments, we will make a video like
that. Because I cannot make it at home.
Sebehxêr, hevalno hûn çawane? Îşê we çawane, sihet çawane?
Işallah hûn gir rind bin, rehet bin.
Good morning, friends how are you? How is your work, how is
the health? God willing you are all good, comfortable.
Erê, hîro dîsa em ba wer hatin, vîdkî xweş kîbar çêkin, li
gundê Hebo.
Yes, today again we came to you, to make a nice neat video,
in the village of Hebo.
Bi me ra bin heta dawîlî vîdyo, û bîr nekin te'lîqa me ra
binivîsînin.
Be with us until the end of the video, and don't forget to
write comments for us.
Û yê îştîrak nekirî jî, xêra xwe me ra îştîrak ke. Dest û
sihetê we giya xweş.
And the one who hasn't subscribed, for their own sake
[please] subscribe to us. Health to all your hands.
Erê, hevalno bîr nekin, me got vîdyê dû vêra, emkê te'lîqê
we giya bixwînin.
Yes, friends don't forget, we said the video after this, we
will read all your comments.
Ez te'lîqa dixwînim, ez li giya jî red dikim.
I read the comments, I reply to all of them too.
Û di vê vîdyê da jî te'lîqê xwe binivîsînin, xwestekê we kê
çine, emê bixwînin, emê vîdyokî xwe wana çêkin.
And in this video too write your comments, whatever your
requests are, we will read, we will make our video like
that.
Kê çi ji me ra binivîsîne, telebê kê çine, emê te'lîqa
bixwînin, emê vîdyokî xwe wana çêkin.
Whoever writes what to us, whatever anyone's demands are, we
will read the comments, we will make our video like that.
Pirs, siwalê we kê hene, di waze pirs kin, derbekin, te'lîqa
de binivîsînin, ma'nî em wera bixwînin, wera cewab kin.
Questions, whatever questions you have, [if you] want to
ask, shoot [ask], write in the comments, so that we read for
you, answer you.
Erê, siwalê we kê hene, wekê M'azet gotî, di te'lîqê vê
vîdyê da binivîsînin, emê wera bixwînin û emê vîdyo jî
daxînin.
Yes, whatever questions you have, as M'azet said, write in
the comments of this video, we will read for you and we will
upload the video too.
Sihetê we giya xweş, û bi me ra bin, emê nika derbas bin
vîdyokî xweş, nîv gund emê çêkin.
Health to you all, and be with us, we will now proceed to
make a nice video inside the village.
Ko em bi hevra derbasî nîv gund bin.
So that we proceed together into the village.
Maşallah, bî sê çar ne, baranê evha nekirî.
Mashallah, it's been three or four [cm?], it hasn't rained
like this.
Me got... cefaf e, cefaf e. Maşallah jî berf, baran.
We said... it's drought, it's drought. [But] Mashallah snow,
rain.
Welle pir ke'nî hene jî derbînin, ke'nî pir derbînin.
By God, there are many springs too coming out, many springs
are coming out.
Maşallah, xudanê xweş lêkir, temam kir.
Mashallah, the Lord made it well, completed it.
Em têmîşkî bibîn. Ewwel merre berka min ave tiji dibe.
Let's see a spectacle. It's the first time my pond fills
with water.
Ewwel merre.
The first time.
Elhemdule, dîsa bereket birsin.
Praise be to God, may He rain blessings again.
Kuro, halê şewqê min binêre.
Bro, look at the state of my hat.
Keça min, eva ha lê anîye.
My daughter has brought it to this state.
Tu binêre tewlê wê kîderê ye.
Look where its tassel is.
Ewa kişandibû, rakiribû, tesera qetandibû.
She had pulled it, lifted it, tore the tassel.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Erê a min veda, ji pir xerabiyê... bes seke ava gundî ya
heye ha.
Yes, mine is turned on, because of how bad it is... but
look, the village water is there, huh.
Vê gundî ava xwe heye. Bes kareba xwe hîn nehatine, kareba
nekêşane he?
This village has its own water. But their electricity hasn't
come yet, they haven't pulled the electricity lines yet,
right?
Wele, bibîne. Wele.
By God, look. By God.
Hêj bariyan û herî ye, ji pir xerabiyê we ne. La hawle
wela... ji pir xerabiyê.
It is still raining and muddy, it is like this because of
how bad [the road] is. There is no power but God... from
being so bad.
[Music]
Maşalla... Çi ciheke rind e, ciheke rind e. E?
Mashallah... What a beautiful place, it is a beautiful
place. Huh?
Min go çi ciheke rind e.
I said what a beautiful place.
Ma cewze xwe çiyo, xwe nîn e? Me vir çiqas xweş nekir.
What about its walnuts, aren't they good? We didn't clean
this place up much.
Gerek em hatiban, me tembîl bikira vê.
We should have come, we should have cleaned this.
Na? Ê cew... vesta ne... û ew bî... seke maşalla roj
veçêkir, gelê.
No? Well the atmosphere... is tired... and let that be...
look, Mashallah the sun came out, dear.
Destpêkê, ceme duman bî. Hela... hela sa samdar nakevin.
At the beginning, it was foggy. Still... the ruins still
aren't visible.
Welle me digot hemdar nakevin, vê sibê me seke çiçqas baran
sekinî ye?
By God, we said the ruins wouldn't be visible, look at how
much the rain stopped this morning?
Me go ku hemdar kevin. Maşalla em gihîştin vir jî, roj
veçêkir.
We said so the ruins would be visible. Mashallah, as soon as
we arrived here, the sun came out.
Bes di geçîdê teng e, di man e... ne? Cawe... ana wekî
awe... ewre, xwînate.
But the pass is narrow, it is foggy... no? The weather...
now it's like water... cloudy, you know.
Maşalla, çi rûniştin li vir heye.
Mashallah, what a seating area is here.
Min go, kelmê gundî mara, kevirê gundî mara şîrîn e.
I said, the brush of our village, the stones of our village
are sweet.
Çiqas gundî mara xerabe be, mentiqa mara şîrîn e.
No matter how ruined our village is, our region is sweet.
Her kes dibê gundî min. Noka, ê min ez dibêjim gundî min.
No, ê gundê jî dibê gundî min.
Everyone says "my village." Now, mine, I say "my village."
No, the villager also says "my village."
Ere. Tu zanî her kes gundî lê tê de mezin bûye, pê şîrîn e.
Yes. You know, everyone finds the village they grew up in
sweet.
Na efrîn serçavî min ser nede ka, eneqo milê rûnim. E têt
neyê bijim, xêra, ez elimîme gundê...
No, don't put Afrin above my eyes, let me sit on the side.
Whether it happens or not, it's okay, I am used to the
village...
Hisê çûka, kelema... ana vê tebîetê, ez dêmişî nabim.
The sound of birds, the brush... now this nature, I can't
give it up.
Axê wele pir şîrîn e. Seke wan e... vê kevir no...
The soil, by God, is very sweet. Look at those... at these
stones...
Erê... bi hezara salan tatiyû, bi hezara jî çûye.
Yes... thousands of years have come, and thousands have
gone.
Mentiqek pir xweş e. Min go mentiqek pir xweş e. Nêrgiz têne
bûn wextê nêrgiza ye o.
It is a very nice region. I said it is a very nice region.
Narcissus flowers used to be here, it is the season of
narcissus.
Maşalla, roj germik çêkir. Ê...
Mashallah, the sun made it a bit warm. Yeah...
Bes cawî vedikişe va kişe. Şole sibê jî dinê xweş be, emê
herin...
But the weather is clearing up slowly. If the world is nice
tomorrow too, we will go...
Xanê, vîdyoyekî din ji ware çêkin. Are wele.
To the inn, make another video for you all. Yes, by God.
Noka vane... 'Alim el asar'... 'Alim el asar' tiştê ha
nizanin.
Now these... 'Archeologists'... 'Archeologists' don't know
these things.
Tu dizanî hevna... bicûz ku îşaret bin. Tu dizanî meriv
nizane.
You know these... maybe they are signs. You know, people
don't know.
Di viro berqefek heye... av dikeviyê, di viro tê der.
There is a cistern here... water goes in, it comes out here.
O qil di viro jî heye, wina?
Oh, there is a hole here too, see?
Qelpi kirine.
They have chipped/carved it.
Emê bêjin îşaret û nîşanê neqşên hene.
Let's say there are signs and engraved marks.
Alemê asar pê zanin, remzê gund hene.
The world of antiquities knows about it, there are symbols
of the village.
Sehke, divê derê ra qul e.
Look, there is a hole through this place.
Nefsî qul e?
Is it the same hole?
Erê, divê ro berqafek heye.
Yes, there is a cliff face along here.
Wê tahtê ro dipişire dertikeve.
It crumbles from the rock and comes out.
Noko dibe cûz te nizanî, bi cûz eve remzek be.
Now, perhaps you don't know, maybe this is a symbol.
Ewe îşaret dertikeve, a binî jî heye.
That sign appears, there is one at the bottom too.
Êş di wir de jî yek heye.
Look, there is one in there too.
Awa, welî li vir.
Yes, right here.
Sehke hevalno, li vir jî heye.
Look friends, there is one here too.
Li ser pişta vê qul e, di alî din de dertikeve.
On the back of this is a hole, it comes out the other side.
Û di vir de jî, hana qul e û hana der e, binêre.
And right here too, here is the hole and here is the exit,
look.
Eve ecêbiyek gende, wan e, di hundir de heye.
This is a wonder of the village, of those ones, it exists
inside.
De noko, baasê tiştê wane sêr dikim, ê wanê li asar û deran
digerin.
So now, I am looking into their things, those who search for
ruins and places.
Ez sêr dikim ka kevirekî am tom e.
I am looking at a rock that is generally whole.
Wek vê qulê na, vê îşaretê na.
Like this hole, like this sign.
E pê dikevin, doğru diherin rast tênê, rast tişta dibînin.
They follow it, they go straight and come right to it, they
find the exact things.
Lê em nizanin.
But we don't know.
Te zanî?
You know?
Îşaretê ho ne cam a, pirr ne.
There are many signs like this here.
Bes em pê fehm nakin.
But we don't understand them.
Wa, sehke.
Here, look.
E pê fehm dike, e zane be.
The one who understands it, would know.
Sehke, vê derê jî heye, bes viro şikî ye, te dî?
Look, this place exists too, but it is broken here, did you
see?
Awa berê vir jî wekî awa bî.
This front part here was also like that one.
Bes şikî ye, hana daketiye.
But it is broken, it has fallen down here.
Pirr ne, îşaret pirr ne.
There are many, there are many signs.
Em pê nizanin.
We don't know about them.
E xwendaye, e xwendaye pê zane vê tiştî.
The educated one, the educated one knows about this thing.
Mi go qurban te xudê bim, te dî ew darê ser kevire darketî?
I said, I sacrifice myself for your God, did you see that
tree coming out of the rock?
Meziyê bide ser tahtê hişk didê.
Hit the spine, it strikes on the dry rock.
Lê dibê xudê bim, maro de ser tahtê hişk didê maro.
But they say my God, the snake strikes on the dry rock, the
snake.
Hevşî vê darê jî ser tahtê hişk derketî, qurban te xudê bim.
Just like this tree that has come out on top of the dry
rock, I sacrifice myself for your God.
E, gelo?
Yeah, right?
Ser tahtê.
On top of the rock.
Meazet qene kêr wî nabe, e pênc car bike, pênc car.
Ma'am, since his knife isn't working, make it five times,
five times.
Ê wele xweda min ti gûz ne xwarin.
Oh well, by God I haven't eaten any walnuts.
Wele kêr mir heye, bes a no deme.
Well, there is a knife here, but it's not sharp (lit:
doesn't give).
Heye, mokne dimir heye.
It exists, don't worry, there is one.
Here wele.
Go on, really.
Bide min, gûza bide min ez naxwim.
Give it to me, give me the walnuts, I won't eat.
Ha?
Huh?
E hisol, ma ma mezbûd naxwar?
Oh, like that, didn't you eat well?
Bela me kordû me naxwar.
Since we didn't eat Kordu (a type of edible plant).
Min go herim, çûne canke.
I said I'd go, go to the young woman.
Mm.
Bi mera ben, ha, mer nekin, noko vîdyo xweş hîmay.
Stay with us, ha, don't go, now the video remains beautiful.
A makenê xweş mane.
Our location remains beautiful.
Xêr nê, qa cîyûzki destê xwe nakim, ez norim, awê nagarim.
No, no good, I won't touch the walnuts, I won't eat, I'm not
looking for that.
Zêra?
Gold?
Mire ya zmiş ke.
Look for the man.
No, na gelê digerim.
No, no I am looking for the leaves.
Digerî?
You are searching?
Gelê digerim.
I am looking for the leaves.
Manzor, gibrav kirin.
Manzor (mushroom type), they have turned to dust/rotted.
Mi go gibrav kirin, neman.
I said they turned to dust, they are gone.
Mire di tealîqa da yozmîş kin, bêjin tealîqê we pirr bin.
Look, write in the comments, let your comments be many.
Ma'nî ez harem lê bigerim, tiştê wanû hîn zanin.
Meaning I should go search for it, things that you guys
know.
Bila xibratê we ser heye.
Let your expertise be upon it.
Emê nizanin.
We don't know.
Erê wele, vê diriyo mero qut kiro, ma'nî rêk teng nebe,
gelî?
Yes indeed, they cut this thorn bush, meaning so the road
wouldn't be narrow, you see?
Rêk teng kirî.
It narrowed the road.
Bi çiqê mir hebo?
Was it with branch here?
Ma ne amone baro qut kiro, ser rêkê de hatî.
Didn't they cut the front of it, it came over the road.
Wele hisol ne me gayo pir xwar û ne me kordû xwar.
Well, this year we didn't eat much Gayo and we didn't eat
Kordu (wild edible plants).
Erê wele.
Yes indeed.
Hata waxtê baran tenê bî, takro jî baranê lê kir bî berf
û...
Until the time the rain came, and then the rain turned into
snow and...
Erê wele, na, em nekun, tişt ne şuxulî.
Yes indeed, no, we didn't do it, things didn't work out.
Par, me çiqas kordû dikir, me gayo dikir, kivarko.
Last year, how much Kordu we picked, Gayo we picked,
mushrooms.
Salê ke me pir kivark kirin, hisol me nekirin kêm.
One year we picked a lot of mushrooms, this year we didn't,
very little.
Avo mufraqê darê gundê Xelîl.
This is the intersection of the tree of Khalil village.
Gundê Xelîl heqûk li cem min heye, akey herim gundê Xelîl.
The village of Khalil has a right upon me (I respect them),
I will surely go to Khalil village.
Bes mulo cew one bekşe, xweş bibê.
But let the weather clear up a bit, let it get nice.
Ezê werme, ma vo nîzîkê gundê Xelîl.
I will come, aren't we close to Khalil village?
Maleke jima xwestî, birakî kî ma.
A family requested it from us, a brother of ours.
Emê Kawa jî jima xwestî, birakî me Kawa jî jima xwestî.
Kawa also requested it from us, our brother Kawa also
requested it from us.
Û birakî medin jî jima xwestî.
And another brother of ours requested it from us.
Erê, emê hewa, hemê warem.
Yes, we will, all of us, we will come.
Ya'nî ew na, kimsûr le hofê gund ne, em nekun noko têkevine.
Meaning not that, the combines (harvesters) are around the
village, we can't enter now.
Bes emê saorinê.
But we will film it.
Wele mexê taq korî û tişî cûki hebne.
Well, my brain is tired and things... there were
chicks/birds.
Ma yikor o bikiro, ma...
He did that work, he...
Xudê rehma xwe li dê û bavê te bike.
May God have mercy on your mother and father.
Biçukê.
The little one.
Maşalla, erdê, erdê av rind vexwar.
Mashallah, the ground, the ground drank the water well.
Erdê têr av bî.
The ground became full of water.
Heta tirbanoyê kê ne, hevalî min divê tirbano bigre.
Even whose harvesters/machines are these, my friend wants to
take the harvesters.
Xudê rehma xwe li êkê ciwan ke.
May God have mercy on the young one.
Cîyê wi cenet be.
May his place be paradise.
Çî gino?
What, boy?
Qismat, dît û hesin.
Destiny, seen and felt.
Eh, zanim ci dagi dagi da.
Eh, I know it burns, burns, burns.
Dil tiraşî.
Heartbreak.
Xudê rehma xwe li êkê ciwan ke.
May God have mercy on the young one.
Rêpo me giya me hemûjî yane.
Our path, all of us are going there (to death).
Son son tê em divro derkeban.
In the very end, we will leave from here.
Dil tiraşî, ebî tiraşî di.
Heartbreak, it becomes heartbreak.
Tê defat abne?
You will pass away?
Sekinandin nîne.
There is no stopping.
Xudê rehma xwe li êkê ciwan ke.
May God have mercy on the young one.
Rêpo me giya me hemûjî yane.
Our path, all of us are going there.
Ko gorkê me, ko bofkê me, di çûn.
Where are our grandfathers, where are our fathers, they
left.
Em jî di dû de.
We are following them.
Sa heyat wane.
Just, life is like that.
Erê hevalno, li vê derkê jî am gihîştin tolya vîdyo xwe.
Yes friends, at this spot we have reached the end of our
video.
Vîdyo me kinik bî, wîna qusura me afkin.
Our video was short, please forgive our shortcomings.
Gundê Habû çûçik bî, erê.
The village of Habu was small, yes.
Kîstî ne bi ma go em herin, le'nî em dîso bibin, ew bî, caw
ne mezbûd bî.
There weren't any bags (mushrooms/plants) for us to say
"let's go," meaning we would take them again, that was it,
the weather wasn't good.
Gundê Habû li hafê ma mo.
The village of Habu remained in our memory.
Avo ji Soryo ye, û Şeytano.
This is from Soryo, and Sheytano (names of specific sites or
spirits).
Rehmanî ye vêra dibên.
It is Rahmanî (merciful/divine) they call it around here.
B'erebî dibên Rehmanî ye.
In Arabic they say it is Rahmanî.
Erê, berê me helqek divir da çêkiriye.
Yes, we had made an episode here before.
Erê.
Yes.
Û tealîqê xwe pir yozmîş kin.
And write many comments.
Tealîqê we milo pir bin, ma'nî em tealîqê we jî vîdyokî
tealîqê jî we ro çêkin.
Let your comments be many, meaning we will make a video for
you from your comments.
Xwestakê we kiyane, gotinê we kiyane, milo di yozmîş ke di
tealîqê da.
What your requests are, what your sayings are, write them in
the comments.
Ma'nî em we ro ew bikin.
Meaning we will do that for you.
Kesê gundê xwe dixwaze, kesê fikran di cem gundê hene.
Anyone who wants their village (filmed), anyone who has
thoughts about the village.
De bimîne dîsa vîdyokî xweş û kîbar, emê we ro daxin nîzîk
da înşallah.
So stay tuned for another nice and decent video, we will
upload it for you soon, God willing.
No, no min nîşanê gundê Bêgova jî çêkirin, emê înşallah wê
jî daxin.
Now, I have also made the signs of the village Begova, we
will upload that too, God willing.
Erê.
Yes.
Mekanî emê sar av daxin, sek vîdyo me jêr dirêj bî.
We might upload this one first, look our video down there
was long.
Emê başqa daxin wê vîdyo.
We will upload that video separately.
Bimîne bin dîsa vîdyokî xweş û kîbar, emê nîzîk da we ro
daxin, saetê we xweş.
Stay tuned for another nice and decent video, we will upload
it for you soon, have a good time.
Teqsîr meqsîr jî hene, qusura me afkin.
If there are shortcomings or faults, forgive our
shortcomings.
Silaçûm.
Greetings.
Çarne Aşta (Unknown Name), em bêrîya we dikin.
Charne Ashta (Unknown Name), we miss you.
Qenata min şûl nedikir.
My channel wasn't working.
Çar pênc rojan ez teaxirim, ecbîrî we dikim.
I am four or five days late, I am doing this out of longing
for you.
Em aalim bîne we, em vîdyo jî danexin, em bêrîya we dikin.
We have become accustomed to you, even if we don't upload
videos, we miss you.
Erê wele.
Yes indeed.
Abxo, arde canî midaye.
By myself, I have given my soul to the earth (idiom: I am
deeply committed/exhausted).
Erê wele, ma'no vê meselê heleb e, ma dav pênc ro teqrîben
me vîdyo çê nekirin, qenata mi şûl neket.
Yes indeed, meaning this issue is... for about four or five
days we didn't make videos, my channel didn't work.
Erê wele.
Yes indeed.
De bimîne bin, elhemdulila ji xwedê ro.
So stay tuned, praise be to God.
Erê wele.
Yes indeed.