Mala Şêxoyê Eylikê.
The house of Şêxoyê Eylikê.
Û manene mala Hemî Senemê.
And then there's the house of Hemî Senemê.
Û mala Seydî Ûso.
And the house of Seydî Ûso.
Ber destan, ser serê me, ser çavê me.
At your service, upon our heads, upon our eyes.
Hûn mezin in, me nexwest...
You are the elders, we didn't want...
Gundî me bi çi me'rûf e? Bi meqsefo me'rûf e?
What is our village known for? Is it known for the cafe?
Bi meqsefo, erê.
For the cafe, yes.
Lê nema go... ma go ketiye destê...
But it's no longer there... they say it fell into the hands
of...
Maşallah, wekî riya me di vî gundî re çû, camêrek waha me
sekinandin, silavê xwe...
Mashallah, as our path went through this village, a
gentleman like this stopped us, his greetings...
Çi saff e we ye, kîderê ye bira?
What grade are you in, where is it brother?
Ay saff, entê?
Which grade, you?
Sadis.
Sixth.
Sadis, maşallah. Û entê?
Sixth, mashallah. And you?
Samin.
Eighth.
Samin, maşallah, maşallah.
Eighth, mashallah, mashallah.
Roj baş xwişk û biron û em hatin vîdyoyekî xweş, kibar.
Good day sisters and brothers, and we came with a nice,
beautiful video.
Erê hevalno, ev der e, vîdyoyê me, hur e em hatine... em kê
Qere Depe wê ra teswîr kin.
Yes friends, here it is, our video, here we have come... we
will film Qara Tepe for you.
Qere Depe jî navê xwe bi tirkî ye.
Qara Tepe's name is in Turkish.
Qere yanî reş e, tepe jî yanî til e.
Qara means black, Tepe means mound.
Em hatine em kê we ra vîdyoyekî xweş kibar, nav çêkin. Teba
xwişk û birakên me ji me xwestine,
We have come to make a nice beautiful video for you. Of
course, our sisters and brothers asked of us,
gundî gundî em kê vêrê bi seyrînin û em kê herin du malbata
jî ji me xwestine.
we will tour this village, village by village, and we will
go to two families that also requested us.
Silavê min ji miletî vî gundî ra hene, çavê giya maç dikim.
I have greetings for the people of this village, I kiss
everyone's eyes.
Û bîr mekin bi me re bin heta dawîya vîdyo, vîdyoyekî xweş
e, em ê nav gund wê ra çêkin.
And don't forget, stay with us until the end of the video,
it's a nice video, we will film inside the village for you.
Min hez e gotinê te hene?
Do you have words you'd like to say?
Silav û xêr, hevalên me re, çawanin, hûn çawanin, sihhet û
silametî hûn giyan in, rehetin e.
Greetings and blessings to our friends, how are you, how are
you doing, health and peace to you all, are you well.
Erê hevalno wekî em hatin gundî Qere Depe, em kê wê ra vîdyo
çêkin.
Yes friends, as we have come to the village of Qara Tepe, we
will make a video for you.
Bîr mekin me re like û iştîrake pêdnin û ta'lîqne xweş kibar
yazmîş kin.
Don't forget to give us a like and subscribe, and write nice
beautiful comments.
Û bi me re bin noke em derbasî gund bin.
And stay with us now as we enter the village.
Saet xweş abê me. Lê te ti kê şore kî bikî?
Bless you my brother. Will you say a word to us?
Like û iştîrake me re têxin.
Put a like and subscribe for us.
Ewe... Erê hevalno, ev der kê, tab'en ev riya Helebê ye, ev
riya Helebê ye.
That's it... Yes friends, here, of course, this is the
Aleppo road, this is the Aleppo road.
Vê derê jî salin e, gih salan e, em ê noka derbasî hindir
bin, derbasî nav gund bin, em ê bi hev ra li vî gundî seyr
kin,
It has been years here, all these years, we will now enter
inside, enter the village, we will tour this village
together,
coğrafyê vî gundî, tebî'etê vî gundî, sikonê vî gundî, em ê
bi hev ra lê seyr kin.
the geography of this village, the nature of this village,
the residents of this village, we will tour them together.
Û min li ta'lîqê we jî pirr bin, û vîdyoyekî xweş e, em ê
noka wê ra çêkin.
And I want your comments to be many, and it's a nice video,
we will now make it for you.
Ev gundo, pirr gundekî xweş e, hewşê kibar tê da hene,
cografyê xwe pirr xweş e.
This village, it is a very nice village, there are beautiful
yards in it, its geography is very nice.
Axê xwe reş e, wekî Qere Depe ye. Qere Depe jî axê xwe reş e
vê derê. Lê.. Qere yanî reş.
Its soil is black, just like Qara Tepe. Qara Tepe too, its
soil is black here. So... Qara means black.
Depe jî.. şor bi tirkî tê, yanî til.
Tepe also... the word comes in Turkish, meaning mound.
Erê... Erê hevalno li vî derkê, em kê herin mala Ehmed Hec
Mihemed û mala Malbata Sebrî.
Yes... Yes friends here, we will go to the house of Ehmed
Hec Mihemed and the Sebrî family's house.
Em kê derbasî wê malbatê bin, mala Sebrî Şemsî, em kê
derbasî wê malbatê bin, du malbat in, ji me xwestine,
We will visit that family, the house of Sebrî Şemsî, we will
visit that family, there are two families, they asked of us,
hurû jî wekî di bê, em kê derbasî vî gundî bin, vîdyokî xweş
wê ra çêkin. Ka bi me re bin em derbas bin.
and today as it is said, we will enter this village, we will
make a nice video for you. Come stay with us as we enter.
Ev duxolî gund e, tab'en riya Helebê ra em ketine.
This is the entrance of the village, of course we entered
from the Aleppo road.
Ev meqsef e... Meqsef diyare ev e.
This is a cafe... The cafe is clearly this.
Dawetê xweza lê çêdikrin.
They used to hold outdoor weddings here.
Erê... Kê dawetê xwe li vî meqsefî wextî na kiribû... min e
ta'lîqê we da binvîsin. Pirr dawet di vir da bûn.
Yes... Whoever held their wedding at this cafe in those
times... I want you to write it in the comments. Many
weddings took place here.
Dawetê pirr lê çêbûn.
Many weddings took place here.
Erê.
Yes.
Kevnar e...
It's ancient...
Erê birakî min li vî derkê em gihiştin pêşiyê hewşê... mala
Ehmed Hec Mihemed.
Yes my brother, here we have reached the front of the
yard... the house of Ehmed Hec Mihemed.
Tab'en ev der e, mehetê şîmendo fêr kevnar e. Erê... wekî av
e, xarabûye.
Of course here is the ancient train station. Yes... like
this, it is ruined.
Em ê noka li pêşiyê qapîyê wana... Ev hewşa wa ye. Ka bi hev
re em derbas bin.
We are now in front of their gate... This is their yard.
Come let's enter together.
Maşallah hewşek xwe mazin û kibar heye.
Mashallah, they have a large and beautiful yard.
We hes kirî... Hesi dîko, mirîşko... Dîk çiqas rind e, cewê
gundan pir xweş e, kibar e.
You liked it... Look at the rooster, the chickens... The
rooster is so nice, the village atmosphere is very nice,
beautiful.
Tab'en ev gund jî nîvî vî gundî Ereb in, nîvê Kurmanc in.
Yanî tev li hev in.
Of course, half of this village are Arabs, half are
Kurmanjis. So they are mixed together.
Dar û we çandine. O kulyekî paqij in, çav te lê ne.
They have planted trees. And those clean flowers, you are
looking at them.
Emê vira rind hewşê gundê bigerin. Ewqas dîro mala xwe kirin
e. Dîwarê hewşa xwe kirin e.
We will tour the yard of the village well here. They have
built so many walls around their house. They have built
walls for their yard.
Xwedî derec hene, em lê hildikşin jor.
There are stairs, we climb up them.
Waliyê axê, axê vî derê gund, axê xwe hinekî reş e.
Towards the soil, the soil of this side of the village...
its soil is a bit black.
Bas ev axa qewetley e ha, axê reş qewetley e.
But this soil is strong you know, black soil is strong.
Maşallah hewşek xwe mezin, fereh heye.
Mashallah it has a large, spacious yard.
Diyar e şaş e çêbe, çêbe... ew e riya seravê.
It seems something wrong will happen, will happen... that is
the way to the water.
Gundekî xweş e ha. Bi gundekî xweş e.
It's a nice village huh. It really is a nice village.
Xwedêkî ev bera meheta bîn e. Xirabe ye. Şîmendifer bi vir
re diçû ne?
By God this used to be the station before. It's a ruin. The
train used to go through here, right?
Erê hevalno, li vî derkê jî em cem xalo ne, vêr de bini, ev
o Mihemed, Xwedê emrê te dirêj peyda, Xwedê neke ber destan,
çîrokê vî gundî ye.
Yes friends, here we are with the uncle, look here, this is
Mihemed, may God grant you a long life, may God not make you
dependent, he is the story of this village.
Erê, çîrokê gund.
Yes, the story of the village.
Xalo vî gundî... bi kîjan an malbatê nas kirin e?
Uncle, this village... by which families is it known?
Bi malbata, mala Şêxoyê Eylikê.
By the family, the house of Şêxoyê Eylikê.
Şêxoyê Eylikê.
Şêxoyê... Şêxoyê Eylikê.
Ewe.
That's it.
Û manene mala Hemî Senemê.
And then there's the house of Hemî Senemê.
Hemî Senemê.
Û mala Seydî Ûso.
And the house of Seydî Ûso.
Ewe.
That's it.
Mala... Elî Şêxo. Ev in esasê gund in.
The house of... Elî Şêxo. These are the foundation of the
village.
Esasê vî gundî ne.
They are the foundation of this village.
Erê, esasê vî gundî ne.
Yes, they are the foundation of this village.
Silavê min ji van malbatna re hene, çavê giya maç dikim.
I have greetings for these families, I kiss everyone's eyes.
Ev ne esasin... Xalo, emrê vî gundî, teqrîben, çiqas sal e,
hey emr, kevnar e?
These are the foundation... Uncle, the age of this village,
approximately, how many years is it, its age, is it ancient?
Çi bibe... yanî... emil çarsed, sêsed i ra ye.
What will it be... I mean... its age is going on four
hundred, three hundred years.
Kevnar e?
Is it ancient?
Eh dîna wî, em rûniştine.
Ah since then, we are settled here.
Sê bav min kalê min li vir mirine.
Three fathers of mine, my ancestors died here.
Sê bav?
Three fathers?
Çar.
Four.
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê rehma xwe li giya ke.
May God have mercy on them all.
Heta çaro, pênco, digihêje min e.
Up to four, five, it reaches me.
Ewa.
That's it.
Û bavkî min jî vî.
And my father too here.
Qîblê gundê me, randa destê rastê we da dîtî, ew qederê
xwe...
In the south of our village, right on your right side when
you see it, that much...
Xwedê rehma xwe li giyokê jî, giyo cinet lê bê.
May God have mercy on all of them, may paradise be for all
of them.
Em navên wan biderê, navê wan ez zanim hene.
Let's give their names, I know their names.
Xalo, ev qere di vira da bi çi meşhûr e?
Uncle, what is this area famous for here?
Bi ziraetê meşhûr e, ev tûtin heye, tirî heye.
It is famous for agriculture, there is tobacco, there are
grapes.
Tiştên wisa meşhûr ev in welleh.
Things like that are famous here by God.
Hani xelk, emelê berê bi çi dikir?
Well the people, what did they do for work in the past?
Bi emelê berê?
With the work of the past?
E.
Yes.
Welleh wan tiştan... fadilê umir.
By God, those things... the grace of life.
Eywa.
I see.
Û em hatin, me bazên mecîrê firotin bûn wê.
And we came, we had sold the immigrant bracelets there.
E, rind e welleh.
Yes, that's good by God.
Em pê debara xwe dikirin.
We made our living with it.
Xalo, firne di vî gundî de heye? Firne?
Uncle, is there a bakery in this village? A bakery?
Firne tinne.
There is no bakery.
Tinne.
There isn't?
There isn't.
Ava wî, av heye? av tî şebekeyê?
Its water, is there water? Is the water from the network?
Şebekeya avê tî qut dibe, ê dewletê heye.
The water network comes and cuts off, the state's one
exists.
E, heye?
Yes, it exists?
E, giştî ye.
Yes, it is general.
E, rind e.
Yes, that's good.
Bes bo giştî camiyan na.
But it's not for all the mosques.
Bo camiyan çi? Têra vî gundî nake giştî na?
What about the mosques? It doesn't suffice for the whole
village, right?
Nake. Belkî kê bîne nav... ê qut dibe.
It doesn't. Perhaps whoever brings it in... it cuts off.
Hinek pera didin... qesd dikin, go bîran bi xwe dikolin.
Yes.
Some pay money... they intend to, they dig wells themselves.
Ava bin erdê ser hesabê xwe dikişînin.
They draw underground water at their own expense.
Ser hesabê xwe dikişînin? Mane perê didin, ser hesabê xwe
tînin?
They draw it at their own expense? Meaning they pay money,
and bring it at their own expense?
E, me bi xwe heyame nekola ne.
Yes, we ourselves haven't dug for a while.
E, rind e. Xalo... mekteb di vî gundî de hene, mekteb?
Yes, that's good. Uncle... are there schools in this
village, schools?
Mekteb heye, serê kê qest bike, wî gundî gundê xerbî.
There is a school, whoever decides to, goes to that village,
the western village.
Heta çendê dixwînin?
Up to what grade do they study?
Heta nehê naka.
Up to ninth grade now.
E.
Up to ninth?
Yes.
Û nehê şûn de diherin ku?
And after ninth where do they go?
Nehê şûn de diherin Efrînê.
After ninth they go to Afrin.
E.
Yes.
E, diherin Helebê.
Yes, they go to Aleppo.
Xalo te bi te, cefê pir dî ye na? Da dema çûçikniya xwe
de...
Uncle, you yourself have seen a lot of suffering, right?
Since your childhood...
Heftê û pênc sal e bes min traktor ajotiye...
For seventy-five years I have only driven a tractor...
Heftê û pênc sal e te traktor ajotiye?
You have driven a tractor for seventy-five years?
Maşellah. Xalo çi mibarek e umrê te çend e?
Yes.
Mashallah. Uncle, how blessed, how old are you?
Heştê û pênc.
Eighty-five.
Heştê û pênc?
Eighty-five?
Maşellah ev xalo wekî çûçikan e maşellah...
Yes.
Mashallah, this uncle is like a young boy, mashallah...
Xalo... te heştê û pênc sal e umr derbas kirine.
Uncle... you have passed eighty-five years of life.
Te çawa dît? Te pê hesî, ev heştê û pênc sal wek nuh te pê
hesî?
How did you find it? Did you feel it, these eighty-five
years, like you just felt it?
Me pê nehesîn, van çend salan ez bi xwe pê hesîm... em pê
hesîn.
We didn't feel it, these past few years I myself felt it...
we felt it.
De heştê û pênc sala de te pê nehesî, vê heft-heşt salî te
pê hesî?
In eighty-five years you didn't feel it, in these seven-
eight years you felt it?
Van çend salan nuh ez pê hesîm, mirin min bi welleh.
These past few years I just felt it, death is upon me by
God.
Xalo berê xweş bû na? nika xweş bû?
Uncle, the past was better, right? Is it better now?
Welleh berê xweş bû, berê lo me tişt nexwar... berê çay...
By God the past was better, back then we didn't eat
things... back then tea...
Lo me rûn dixwar, lo me dims dixwar, lo me kincî dixwarin...
We ate butter, we ate molasses, we ate sesame...
Lo me dehn... tenekek dims dîti ne wan.
We had fat... we saw a whole tin of molasses.
Lo me tişt... gûzan me dîtin e we.
Mashallah.
We saw things... walnuts, we saw them.
Welleh.
By God.
Lo me tiştê... rûnê sar bû, rûnê batî bû.
Our things... it was cold butter, it was solid butter.
Dims, şîrînî ele tûl me dixwarin.
Molasses, sweets, we ate them all the time.
Maşellah. Xalo te traktor ew cût ajot e na?
Mashallah. Uncle, you drove the tractor and plowed, right?
E.
Yes.
Berê erê, marlqe pir bûn na, xweş bûn?
Back then yes, there were a lot of pastures, right, they
were good?
Marlqe nînin, nika rûniştin.
There are no pastures, now we are settled.
Eywa.
I see.
Nika gişt mitawefir e bes te'm name na?
Now everything is available but there is no taste left,
right?
Te'm name... welleh te'm nîne welleh.
There is no taste left... by God there is no taste, by God.
Heta dunya rind bû umr nema ha!
By the time the world got good, life was gone, huh!
Umr nema, mirin e.
Life is gone, it is death.
Xwedê hey, Xwedê Xwedê... Xwedê destê xwe li ser we ra
bigre.
Oh God, God God... May God keep His hand over you.
Û Xwedê we bixefirîne, miletê me Kurmanc bi şeklê am...
And may God forgive you, our Kurmanji people in general...
E, bi şeklê am, Xwedê giya bixefirîne, Xwedê destê xwe di
ser giya ra bigre, li her derê kî na?
Yes, in general, may God forgive everyone, may God keep His
hand over everyone, everywhere, right?
Welleh xewn in ma ne wekî, me şabûn welleh me pê de fkirin.
By God they are like dreams, we were happy, by God we were
proud of it.
Xwedê ha, ma de Xwedê heye mera qey dibêje da dewran bibe
çi.
God is there, since God is there, whatever the era brings.
Maşallah gundê we... gundekî wekî xweş e.
Mashallah your village... it is a nice village.
Gundê me rind e. Maşallah e...
Our village is good. Mashallah it is...
Xalo te min pirs kir de bê nivê Ereb in nivê Kurmanc in?
Uncle, I asked you, is it half Arab and half Kurmanji?
Qismek Ereb e, qismek Kurmanc.
A part is Arab, a part is Kurmanji.
Ji berê de tev hevdin e na?
Have they been together since the past?
Nav wî sed salî de ev in ev sed salek î de tev hevdin.
For this hundred years they are, for a hundred years they've
been together.
Sed sal î tev hevdin ne.
They have been together for a hundred years.
Ereb hatine vira Ereb di konan bûn... di konan bûn.
Arabs came here, Arabs were in tents... they were in tents.
Çadir bûn?
They were in tents?
E. Û erd jî bor bû.
Yes. And the land was also barren.
Qîmetê erdî... erd tinne bû.
The value of the land... the land was worthless.
Ne erd tişt bû pera nedikirin. Wekî ev yek eşqar dikirin...
I see.
The land was not a thing, they didn't pay for it. When they
started working on it...
Min ev eşqarê we... ev kom bûn.
I saw this work of yours... they gathered.
E, rind e, rind e welleh rind e.
Yes, that's good, that's good by God, it's good.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Ehlen bîkum. Xwedê we...
Welcome to you. May God...
Welleh, ji bextê me xalo em hatin gundekî wisa em taswîr
kin. Cuxrafî gundekî wisa em hatin...
By God, to our luck uncle, we came to film such a village.
Geographically, we came to such a village...
Em hatin malbata, we malbata, mala... Ehmed.
We came to the family, your family, the house of... Ahmed.
E, mala Ehmed.
Ahmed's house.
Yes, Ahmed's house.
Em hatin we malbatê, we malbata cîran ji me xwestin e, go
gundekî wisa bikişînin gundiya... wekî di bînin.
We came to your family, your neighbor family asked us, to
film such a village, the villagers... as they see it.
Maşellah.
Mashallah.
Xalo oxê wek reş reş, ev qeredaş e na?
Uncle, those black spots, that's Qeredash, right?
E. Li wir kevirên reş in.
Yes. The stones there are black.
Heta de rind e nedih in?
Are they quite plentiful there?
Hedîdî we... pir in na?
There are iron ones... they are many, right?
Hedîdî xwe pirr in.
Its iron ones are many.
E. Bes ev sê çar sal... ev sê çar sal baran nîn bû, yekcar
hişk bûn.
Yes. But these three or four years... there was no rain
these three or four years, they completely dried out.
Nuh bes ev sal, sal qenc bû?
Only this year, was the year good?
Bes îsal qenc bûye welleh em dernebûn.
Only this year was good, by God we hadn't come out.
Em wisa bi deyn bi derbûn e. Wexta me deyn kirin.
We had survived like that with debt. At the time we took
debt.
Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê umrê we dirêj bike ta te dît. Tu
tiştekî din, tu tişt dixwazî daxwazên te hene xalo?
May God be pleased with you, may God prolong your life since
you saw it. Do you want anything else, do you have any
requests, uncle?
Xwedê we biewqîne, Xwedê we neke ber destê xerîban ser serê
me ser çavê me.
May God protect you, may God not leave you at the mercy of
strangers, upon our heads, upon our eyes.
Tu mezinê me yî, ser xêr û bereketa we me, em xwe bi we
digrin e.
You are our elder, we are upon your goodness and blessing,
we hold onto you.
E mezin, em tên we gunda we mezinan di bînin em pir kêfxweş
dibin.
Yes elders, we come to your villages and see you elders, we
become very happy.
Millet gişt bi xêr û bêr e, saeta te xweş... Xwedê we neke
ber destê kesî, ser serê min, ser çavê min.
The entire nation is good and blessed, have a good time...
May God not leave you at anyone's mercy, upon my head, upon
my eyes.
Ser seran... sax bî saeta te xweş, xalo.
Upon the heads... be healthy, have a good time, uncle.
Malên hewşên kevnar di vir de hene. Niha kuçeyên hewşên
kevnar di vir da ne.
There are old courtyard houses here. Now, there are old
courtyard streets here.
Wa nahnu al-yawma fi...
And we are today in...
...al-ayyam
...the days
Min al-ashr al-awakhir
Of the last ten days
Min shahr Ramadan
Of the month of Ramadan.
Natadhakkaru fil-ashril-awakhir
We remember in the last ten days
Min hadha ash-shahr ash-sharif
Of this honorable month.
Wa natadhakkaru fil-ashril-awakhir
And we remember in the last ten days
Min hadha ash-shahr ash-sharif
Of this honorable month.
Hadha ash-shahr
This month,
Al-fadhil
The virtuous.
Hadha ash-shahr al-mubarak
This blessed month.
Annaha...
That it...
Al-ayyamu...
The days...
Tanqadi...
Are passing...
Tahta farhatin wa surur
Under joy and happiness
Wa innama
And indeed
Tamdi kalamhil-basar
It passes like the blink of an eye
Madaat ayyam
Days have passed
Wa hiya al-ashrul-awakhir
And it is the last ten days
Kalamhil-basar
Like the blink of an eye
Wa sa tamdi in sha'allah ta'ala
And it will pass, God Almighty willing
Ayyaman ma'dudat
A few days
Na'am, ayyaman ma'dudat
Yes, a few days
Min shahr Ramadan al-mubarak
Of the blessed month of Ramadan
Wa ayyamun tamurru sira'an kalamhil-basar
And days that pass quickly like the blink of an eye
Inna shahra Ramadan
Indeed, the month of Ramadan
Ayyuhal-ikhwah madrasatun azima
O brothers, is a great school
Al-ghayatu minha kama akhbarana Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala
The goal of it, as God Almighty has informed us
Hiya at-taqwa
Is piety
Ya ayyuha al-ladhina amanu kutiba alaykum as-siyam kama
kutiba ala al-ladhina min qablikum la'allakum tattaqun
O you who have believed, decreed upon you is fasting as it
was decreed upon those before you that you may become
righteous
Fa at-taqwa ayyuha al-kiram
So piety, O honorable ones
Hiya thimratul-mukhlisin min hadha as-siyam
Is the fruit of the sincere from this fasting
Wa hiya an yaj'ala al-abdu baynahu wa bayna ma yaghdhabullah
And it is that the servant places between him and what
angers God
Wiqayatan bi-fi'li awamirihi wa ijtinabi nawahihi
A protection by doing His commands and avoiding His
prohibitions
An taj'ala baynaka wa bayna adhabillah, wiqaya
That you place between yourself and God's punishment, a
protection
Hadhihi hiya at-taqwa lillahi subhanahu wa ta'ala
This is piety towards God Almighty
Wa lakin ma'a al-asafi ash-shadid
But with deep regret
Hunak min as-sa'imin
There are some among the fasting people
Man siyamuhu huwa mujarradul-imtina'i an-it-ta'ami wash-
sharabi wash-shahwa
Whose fasting is merely refraining from food, drink, and
desires
Fa-yufawwitu alayhi al-maqsad al-a'dham
Thus he misses out on the greatest purpose
Wa tadi'u alayhi al-hikmatu al-kubra
And the supreme wisdom is lost on him
Wa ilaykum ayyuha al-ikhwah al-kiram
And to you, O honorable brothers
Waqfatan ma'a badihi al-asnaf
A pause with some of these categories
Allati lam tatannabaha
Who have not paid attention
Li hadhihi al-ayyam al-mubaraka
To these blessed days
Hunak sinfun min an-nas
There is a category of people
Yaqdhi shahra Ramadan
Who spend the month of Ramadan
Wa huwa fi laghwin wa lahw
While they are in idle talk and amusement
Yamdi alayhi an-nahar
The day passes for him
Wa huwa na'imun ghafil
While he is asleep, heedless
Wa yamdi alayhil layl
And the night passes for him
Wa huwa sahira
While he stays awake
Ala laghwin wa lahw
On idle talk and amusement
Aw ala maharimi Allah subhanahu wa ta'ala
Or on the prohibitions of God Almighty
Hadha as-sinf
This category
Al-ladhi...
That...
Erê em lê vegeriyan. Em gihiştine mala... Xalê Sebrî. Erê
Ebu Şemsî. Em gihiştin malbateke gund e.
Yes, we have returned. We have arrived at the house of...
Uncle Sabri. Yes, Abu Shamsi. We reached a village family.
Ka em bi hev re derbas bin, em hem hewşê gund jî pêş we
bikin.
Let's go in together, so we can show you the village
courtyard.
Ka wer Ebu Lîman, hewşê ji vira pêş gund bike.
Come on Abu Liman, show the village courtyard from here.
Wer de şitê mero bîriya gundê xwe dikî, bîriya hewşê xwe
dikî...
So that people can see how much they miss their village,
their courtyard...
Erê eva... eva hewşek weha ye. Naho te pir bîr kiriye,
zikreyatê me ra teb'en lê hene.
Yes, this... this is what the courtyard is like. Now you
must have missed it a lot; of course, we have memories here.
Maşallah gundekî xweş û kîbar e.
Mashallah, it's a beautiful and lovely village.
Maşallah çîçekê behîv û qertex nîzamî giş peqîne, ne?
Mashallah, the almond and plum blossoms have all bloomed
beautifully, haven't they?
Erê.
Yes.
Erê em îne dîsa li hundir hewşê wane. Teba'en îroj jî ro înê
ye, xoce xutbê dide.
Yes, we are inside their courtyard again. Of course, today
is Friday, the imam is giving the sermon.
Vî gundî... gundê we pir maşallah şên e, bi xêr û bêr e.
This village... your village is, mashallah, very lively and
prosperous.
Ê îroj jî înê ye, millet giş çûye camiyê da. Hîn milletê vî
gundî giş hene, xalo?
And today is Friday, the people have all gone to the mosque.
Are the people of this village still all here, uncle?
Giş mal in.
They are all at home.
Giş mal in heh?
They are all at home, huh?
Maşallah, maşallah. Yanî ji gund gişî teqrîben hîn du mal,
bes sê mal, sê mal bes nayêtine bes.
Mashallah, mashallah. Almost all of the village is still
here, only two or three families, three families haven't
returned, that's all.
Ê baş e, ew jî werin, ha ew jî werin.
Well, that's good, they will come too, yeah, they will come
too.
Maşallah gundekî kevnar e, gundekî kevnar e, û milletê xwe
giş hazir in.
Mashallah, it's an ancient village, an ancient village, and
its people are all present.
Û pir... cuxrafiya gund, mentîqa gund jî pir xweş e. Ne wilo
ye xalo?
And it's very... the geography of the village, the location
of the village is also very beautiful. Isn't that right,
uncle?
Erê, rind e elhemdulîllah ji Xwedê re.
Yes, it is good, thank God.
Ê lê wek bigir... lê wek bigir pisîkê... ha...
Oh, take this... take this cat... yeah...
Tu ji pisîka hez dikî ne? Ha?
You like cats, don't you? Huh?
Çima tu napeyivî? Ha? Tu mezin bibî tu yê bibî çi? Dîxtor?
Muhendis? Tu dixwînî?
Why aren't you speaking? Huh? What do you want to be when
you grow up? A doctor? An engineer? Do you go to school?
Ez naxwînim.
I don't go to school.
Ê na pirçeko malxirap. Çima?
Well no, you little rascal. Why?
Bavê min ez derxistim.
My father took me out of school.
Ah wane ne.
Oh, I see.
Maşallah maşallah, gundê we... çaxê ku min dît, gundekî xweş
û kîbar e.
Mashallah, mashallah, your village... when I saw it, it's a
beautiful and lovely village.
Gundê me... pir muttefiq in bi hev re.
Our village... they are very united.
Bi hev re muttefiq in... îttîfaqek hebe rind e.
They are united... it's good to have unity.
Gundê me ewil gund e, eger tu herî mentîqa Efrînê da ziftê,
da hettî Sûriyê di ziftê de ye.
Our village is the first village, if you go to the Afrin
region on the asphalt road, up to Syria it's on that asphalt
road.
A... Kezalîk her weha jî ... xeta Şiyê de jî ewil gund
teqriben ev e.
Really?
A... Kezalîk her weha jî ... xeta Şiyê de jî ewil gund
teqriben ev e.
Yes... Also, it's almost the first village on the Shiye line
as well.
Gundekî pir muttefiq e, rind e, rind e. Xalo milletê vî
gundî bi şiklekî 'am çi karî dikin?
It's a very united village, that's good, that's good. Uncle,
what kind of work do the people of this village generally
do?
Wellehî î heye muwezef in, î heye zîra'at in, î heye mesela
li Efrînê in. Şixulê xwe li Efrînê in. Mînak li Efrînê da
şuxil in.
Well, some are civil servants, some work in agriculture,
some are in Afrin, for example. Their work is in Afrin. For
instance, they work in Afrin.
Werşe ... werşeyên derziyê li gundê we da tinne ne?
Workshops... aren't there sewing workshops in your village?
Hene, teqrîben sê-çar werşê me hene tê de.
There are, we have about three or four workshops here.
Werşeyên çine?
What kind of workshops?
Xiyata ne.
Tailoring workshops.
E rind e millet pê sebeb dibe. Xwezîka her gundek de...
werşeyek wilo tê de hebe.
Well, that's good, people make a living from it. I wish
every village had a workshop like that.
Ma'ada yê xelkê gund meselen ... eger qeçkên me ... wekî li
Efrînê bin... bes ... bes nav gund vala kirine, xelk di
gundên ha de ne.
Besides the village people, for example... if our girls...
if they were in Afrin... but... but they have emptied the
village, people are in this village.
Yanî gundê me hem sîna'î ye, hem tîcarî ye, û giş e...
So our village is both industrial and commercial, it has
everything...
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Gundê me bi ... mexsefê xwe me'rûf e...
Our village is famous for... its cafe...
Mexsef hah, arê...
A cafe, yes...
Lê wekî min got, min gund... kesên de'weta xwe tê de kirin,
mere te'lîqan de dinivîsin, ka nêvînî me dera xwe.
But like I said, I meant the village... the people who held
their weddings there, people write in the comments, asking
us to show them that place.
Ew bajara me'ruf e... meselen ... me'melê sabûnê ye, me'melê
bîrînê ye.
That town is famous... for example... there is a soap
factory, an olive press factory.
Na ev gundê me hem sîna'î ye, û hem zîra'î ye, û hem tîcarî
ye. Teb'en î heye xwe da xudanê dewar jî hene tê de.
No, this village of ours is industrial, agricultural, and
commercial. Of course, there are also people who own
livestock here.
Xalo dewar... heywanxwedîkirin ... pez û çêlek li der hene?
Uncle, livestock... animal husbandry... are there sheep and
cows around?
Çêl tinne ne. Bes ... dewarên mî, bizin pir in.
There are no cows. But... there are a lot of sheep and
goats.
Pir in ha. Rind e, şîrîn e...
There are a lot, huh. That's good, it's sweet...
Rast e heywan xwedî kirin...
It's true that animal husbandry...
No her gundekî de... sê-çar meşarî' hebin... ev şebabên wî
gundî meselen ... î ha meselen ... kaniyek xwe tê de îdare
bike... wê çêtir be, her gundekî da hebe rind e.
There aren't any.
No her gundekî de... sê-çar meşarî' hebin... ev şebabên wî
gundî meselen ... î ha meselen ... kaniyek xwe tê de îdare
bike... wê çêtir be, her gundekî da hebe rind e.
Well, if every village had... three or four projects... for
example, the youth of that village... like... could manage a
shop there... it would be better, it's good to have it in
every village.
Naho Efrîn giş ... meselen jê gundan pir e ku naha sikem...
şêst, sê-sed û şêst gund e... giş ... darên Efrînê werşetê,
der û dor xelkên Efrînê da vala dikin. Di gundan da jî vekin
wê teb'en ew fêr be... hinek milletê gund tê de îdare
bike...
Now all of Afrin... for example, there are many villages
that I am going to now... sixty, three hundred and sixty
villages... all... are in Afrin's workshops, they are
emptying their surroundings into Afrin. If they opened them
in the villages too, of course, they would learn... some of
the village people could manage it.
Naho gundê me tu çi tiştê bi xwazî heye. Mesela em bêjin ...
ustad tê de hene. Anse tê de hene.
Now our village has whatever you want. For example, let's
say... there are male teachers. There are female teachers.
Yanî hetta hîn ... berê wextê di Sûriyê de yanî... rêberî
... mudîrê muhemî (muhcemme') yê mentîqê Efrînê sêsed û şêst
gundê... ew ji gundê me bi xwe bû. Yanî...
Even then... during the time in Syria... the director... the
complex manager of the Afrin region with its 360 villages...
he was from our village itself. I mean...
Yanî camêr... xwendewan jî hene, giş hene...
You mean... there are also educated people, there's
everything...
Cema'etê zanîngehê hene. Û giş ji cema'etê zanîngehê ne
elhemdulîlah, giş hene.
There are university graduates. And they are all from the
university community, thank God, they have everything.
Yanî seqafet ji nav gundiyan ... gundê ha pir e?
So the culture among the villagers... in this village is
rich?
Maşallah gundekî seqafet... hettî weha diyare jî... gundekî
hedarî ye, saqafeta wan heye...
Yes, it is a lot.
Maşallah gundekî seqafet... hettî weha diyare jî... gundekî
hedarî ye, saqafeta wan heye...
Mashallah, it's a cultured village... it looks like it
too... it's a civilized village, they have culture...
Bi ansa ve, anse herî pir in... ser da heta pir car zêde
wekî...
With the female teachers, the female teachers are the
most... to the point that there are even more sometimes...
Yanî heseb îlmê min ev di vî gundî zêde jî hebîn...
Mashallah.
So to my knowledge, there might even be more in this
village...
Maşallah maşallah... na gundekî kîbar e. Maşallah hedarî ye,
saqafet a xwe pir e. Yanî gundekî pêşketi ye.
Mashallah, mashallah... no, it's a lovely village.
Mashallah, it's civilized, it has a lot of culture. I mean,
it's an advanced village.
Silavê min ji milletê vê gundî re hene, çûçik û mezin ez
çavê gişka maçî dikim.
I send my greetings to the people of this village, I kiss
the eyes of everyone, young and old.
Û ma tiştê din... we rabe ez... ev êlê, vê malbatê, weha
esas di vî gundê de rûniştine xalê min re we go...
And another thing... let me get up... this tribe, this
family, originally settling in this village, my uncle told
you...
Erê ji evê malbatê re jî teybet silavên min... ji evê
malbatê re jî hene...
Yes, my special greetings to this family as well... to this
family too...
Maşallah gundekî xweş e, kîbar e. Hûr û jî rûyê garmik...
çak kirî... şite qert sahet xuya dikir... na?
Mashallah, it's a beautiful, lovely village. Today also, the
warm weather... it's nice... it seemed a bit cold earlier...
right?
Xwe de... we qe... xilas... êdî em dikevine biharê... qêtên
biharê ye.
God... we just... finished... now we are entering spring...
it's the beginning of spring.
Lê... ji vira û pê de, mentîqa xweş be... hîşînayî derdikeve
dar û ber giş dipelqin... pir xweş dibe mentîqê me.
Yes... from here on out, the area will be beautiful...
greenery will come out, the trees will all blossom... our
area will become very beautiful.
Înşallah înşallah...
God willing, God willing...
Xweş be naho wele... Xweş be naho, erê.
It should be beautiful now... It should be beautiful now,
yes.
Amîn, amîn... pir milletê me ro... dan dikî... ekser di
kevin... Sûriyê di kevin...
Amen, amen... many of our people nowadays... give... mostly
go down to... go to Syria...
Mator şuxul na ku... cî nîbe.. ku ne kevin... î cinsîyeta
wan heye kî we ne di kevin..
They work on motorcycles... there is no place to... if they
don't go down... those who have citizenship, those don't go
down...
Î qaça xwe heye jî.. kevin ê Lubnanê da re werin.. ma'nî...
dewleta xwe gunda da xew nake..
Even those who have their smugglers... they go down to
Lebanon and come back... I mean... they don't sleep in their
state's villages..
Tên... pir şebab tên na welle...
They come... a lot of young men come, yeah really...
Wele me'lûm e ew têt... te ... kîş derba gî ... de ketin
werin... hesbê ku... eke cewazê sefera wan gişî... sariyê
mef'ul be yanî...
Well, it's obvious they come... to... wherever they go...
they can come down... depending on... if their passports are
all... still valid, I mean...
Tên, tên... pir tên.
They come, they come... a lot of them come.
Û hetta ewê din jî... bi cewazê orupî hatin... erê... zanî,
ma... erî cinsiyetên Erebî lîba wan hene... û qaîmê daîmî jî
hene...
And even the others... came with European passports...
yes... you know, well... yes, they have Arab citizenships...
and permanent residencies too...
Cihû dîtin da evgerandin gundê... bes we cewazê sûrî eke
sariyê mef'ul be.
They saw Jews, they returned them to the village... only if
the Syrian passport is valid.
Erê. Erê.
Yes. Yes.
Yanî her tiştê ku ma'lûmat we bi lo ... ê... hema ez dikim
... Cewazê sefera we girtiye ...
So, whatever information you have, to... well... I just
do... You got your passport...
Lê ... pir kê hene... bi dera Lubnanê ra tên... mesela tên
Lubnanê ... derbaz dibin ... ma'nî dewleta gund e nizanibe.
But... there are many who... come through Lebanon... for
example, they come to Lebanon... they cross over... I mean,
the state of the village wouldn't know.
Lê naho yê îqame we daniye. Îqame jî daniye ... bes wek
dewleta xwe ... tu herî tebê te diçûyî ... dewleta xwe ...
esbah... dewlet çêbûye... ro bi her e..
But now they have put residency for you. They put residency
too... but like your state... you go, you say you were
going... your state... it became... a state has been
formed... now go..
Ew na wema xweş e. Rind e tiştên wetî girt ... u pir zêde...
tik tok o... da ra... mutaheridîn û ... we tiştên ... diko
pir... êv we ne diçin gundên we.
That is really nice. It's good you brought up these
things... and a lot of... TikTok and... outside...
instigators and... those things... they do a lot... these
don't go to your villages.
Lê teb'en evên mutaheridîn ... teke pir gundî yê mentîqa we
xweş e wele ... her derê xweş de be ...
But of course these instigators... make a lot of villages in
your region beautiful, really... every place is going to be
beautiful...
Yanî ku tu te... gundekî weha ... pir zêde... cewê wê xirab
be. Ne weke mêr we bibî ... erê... erê... Çîçekê... îlam jî
ew e dikeve... îlam jî pir evî dike. Naho em giş li hev
dikin ha...
So if you come... to a village like this... a lot of... its
atmosphere will be bad. It won't be like a man... yes...
yes... A little bit... the media also does that... the media
does a lot of that. Now we all get along, huh...
Millet giş mala xwe ye... her kesekî kari xwe, şixlê xwe ye.
The people are all in their homes... everyone is at their
job, their work.
Belê, erê. Belê. Belê... e ha bi, belê... ê ... eşkîlat
hebîn... bes naho we her derê xweş de be... her kesekî karê
xwe, malê xwe ye. No ji erdê xwe, milkê xwe ye...
Yes, yeah. Yes. Yes... yeah, yes... there were problems...
but now everywhere is going to be nice... everyone is at
their job, in their home. Now it's their land, their
property...
Kêsî jî nav gundî pir xweş e.
Everyone is also very happy in the village.
Lê... u pir jî ji gund der ketin. Yanî pir ji gundê der
ketin ... çûn malên xwe.
Yes... and many also left the village. I mean, many left the
village... went to their homes.
Naho ke mesela wek min bibe... mela wekî ev dîto ... Gundê
min weha xweş bê... sebra min vir re têt? Ew we di pey re
canê min keve. Ez herim gundê xwe. Ne wisa ye?
Now, for example, if someone is like me... if a mullah sees
this... If my village is this beautiful... would I be
patient here? It would follow my soul. I would go to my
village. Isn't that so?
Wele qerar e derkevin ... tu bî ... bi te re bernameye ...
Well, it's decided they will leave... you will... the
program is with you...
Raste her kes çû walatê xwe çû malatiya xwe ... şêrîn e ...
ew je ... dîsa dîsa ... aştî û gundê xwe ...
It's true everyone went to their country, went to their
homeland... it's sweet... they too... again and again...
peace and their village...
Xwedê ji we razî be... maşallah. Maşallah.
May God be pleased with you... mashallah. Mashallah.
Hebsekî were ber bi vir.
Wait a little bit, come over here.
Lê... Maşallah maşallah.
Look... Mashallah mashallah.
Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide wan de xwedê destê wa ser we bigre.
May God give them a long life, may God keep His hands over
you.
Maşallah wek rehmekî bi gundî camêra me sewirand e.
Mashallah, they recorded the village of these good people
like a blessing.
Çaxmaq o yekî derê biron.
Give me a lighter bro.
Çaxmaqo nebê lo...
Don't say lighter...
Çiço kir qet xuliqî ev çûçika mezin...
What did he do, this big bird got created...
Me milete qerebol ma dî ev qere depa ma dî...
We saw the people of Qerebol, we saw Qere Depa...
Wer we dît we hat lo... Ha niha ev...
You came, you saw... Now this...
Erê ev lew pî min e. Lêçûna derbasbûyî tenê xwe diqede lo.
Yes, this is enough for me. The past costs just finish
themselves.
Ema ez tebîet e cûgrafya ye harat e ez...
But I, the nature, the geography, the harat, I...
Têbikoşe mûtabeqet ke.
Struggle and make an agreement.
Pir jî pê nakavim yanî ez dervayî muhteweyî nakavim.
I don't fall for it much, I mean I don't fall outside the
content.
Welahî... Erê erê maşallah maşallah saetê gîya xweş.
By God... Yes yes, mashallah mashallah, good hours to you
all.
Yanî êdî em îhtîmam kin em tiştê xweş pêşkêşî milet kin. Da
çiqas be bêje tiştên zikriyatê me ra gundî me ra me ra
bibînin. Xweş e.
I mean from now on we will pay attention to presenting nice
things to the people. So they can say, show us our memories,
our village. It is nice.
Xwezî xwa... Da gî di sala da çawa...
I wish... How they were in the years...
Meriv xerîbîyê dî ye pir jî dî ye... weleh çî ye ne gundekî
ye hema her xerîbî bi vî rengî te paşî zanîbî hema weleh
şîrîn e.
A person has seen exile, seen a lot of it... by God, what is
it, it's not a village, just every exile in this way, you'll
know later, by God it's sweet.
Welahî şareşare tê bîra me ne we ye?
By God, it comes to our minds city by city, doesn't it?
Harat harat.
Wele di guta guta têkin hîç qasirat... tebî însanî ye
heger... Na însan sinif sinif e. Însan heye meselî bes pê
pera ketiye bes bibe pera xelas di derheqê eslê xwe da
tiştekî nabîne.
By God, if they say they make mistakes... of course it's
human if... No, humans are class by class. There are humans,
for example, only after money, just get money and that's it,
they don't see anything regarding their origin.
Na.
No.
Însan jî heye welahî gî te bibê ardê axê te ardê te zeminî
te malê dinyê giyan nadê ne bi qasro na bi malê dinyê tev da
te nayê.
There are also humans, by God, even if you give them the
earth, the land, your earth, your ground, all the worldly
goods, they wouldn't trade their home, not for palaces, not
for all the worldly goods.
Welah welah ax şêrîn e welah ax şêrîn e.
By God, by God, the land is sweet, by God, the land is
sweet.
Şîrîn e lê... Berê kuro me loma da digotin welleh çiqa şîrîn
e me digot lo derê ha da di nav da şixulê ber gundan da
qasirîn me digot çî ye?
It's sweet but... Boy, in the past they used to say, by God,
how sweet it is, we used to say, oh man, over there, dancing
among the villages' work, we used to say, what is it?
He heta gava dî me zanî.
Yes, until we saw it, we knew.
Na. Bi hesse. Nam...
No. With sense. Yes...
Qertax e...
It is Qertax...
Maşelleh mentîqeya gî da ava xwe hûn tê.
Mashallah, all the region has its own water coming.
E he he maşallah. Heta çayî Bilbilê ye vava xwen tê.
Yeah yeah mashallah. Even the tea of Bilbil has its own
coming.
Erê erê hêbêr ve kerema xwe bike tiştek nebêje çî ye vî da.
Yes yes, please, if there is anything, don't say anything,
what is this here.
Nogo te mira xeber daye ev gundo kî der e? Ev o Kefer Romê
ye. Ha Kefer Romê ye.
Wait, you told me, where is this village? This is Kefer
Romê. Oh, it is Kefer Romê.
Am hatin mesawirin... Jêvê da Gevrîk e, jêvê da gundî Şorba
ye, jêvê da Sêmala Şêxwîtka ye.
We came and recorded... Over there is Gevrîk, over there is
the village of Şorbe, over there is Sêmala Şêxwîtka.
Ev o kî der e?
Where is this?
Ev o Qurtqilaqa mezin e.
This is Qurtqilaqa mezin.
Ev o Qurtqilaq e te xîyana awot im ev e awot im ev e...
This is Qurtqilaq, you betrayed, I said it's this, I said
it's this...
Jêvê da gundî E'lkê ye.
Over there is the village of E'lkê.
E'lkê jî çûmê. Ev o Kefer Canî ye ne?
I went to E'lkê too. This is Kefer Canî, right?
Na. Ev o Meşalê ye. Paş gund da Kefer Canî ye.
No. This is Meşalê. Behind the village is Kefer Canî.
Am hatine wir jî. Xwe lo ew gundê hanê poş war da xweyî tê
kî der e?
We came there too. Oh man, that village behind where they
stay, where is it?
O Metîna ye. Metîna wele ji me xwestin e.
That's Metîna. They asked us for Metîna, by God.
Milet ... Ev jî her waha ne jî Kefer Miz e vê ra dibên?
Kefer Miz e?
People... Is this also Kefer Miz they call it? Is it Kefer
Miz?
Metîna rêkê xwe dikir o dar in?
Did Metîna make its way, are those trees?
Bi canibê ziyareta Xanan ro tê heta ku te peyî kefa... gava
digihê ziyareta Xanê du mefreq têne.
By the shrine of Xanan you come, every time at the palm...
when you reach the shrine of Xanan, two junctions come.
Yek dere Şera. Yek jî diçe Qurtqilaq...
One goes to Şera. One goes to Qurtqilaq...
Erê diçe Şera ro her e. E Metîna yanî.
Yes, it goes to Şera. That's Metîna I mean.
Ewa. E Metîna ye we. Yanî ser rêka Şera ye.
Yeah. That's Metîna. I mean it's on the way to Şera.
Erê erê. E te biniyê nayê ne dî binî Meşalê ye.
Yes yes. You don't come to the bottom, the bottom is Meşalê.
Xwe ra nogo ra... Ser pî çepê de dere yek jî rast dere. E
rast dere...
For yourself wait... On the left it goes, one also goes
right. The one going right...
Ey wa welahî Metîna ji me xwestin e.
By God, they wanted Metîna from us.
Miletê gundê Metîna li me bisebirin, em ê herin înşelleh.
The people of Metîna village should be patient with us, we
will go, God willing.
Xulî min ro rîya keval da, em ê herin em ê vîdyokê xweş nav
Metîna jî çêkin nîzik da.
Let me take the old road, we will go and make a nice video
in Metîna too, soon.
Ziyareta Xanan jî her da ser pî çepê da her e dor e dûze...
İnşallah înşallah ez e vîdyokî Metîna de jî çêkim.
The shrine of Xanan also go left, it's flat around... God
willing, God willing, I will make a video in Metîna too.
Lê maşelleh milet e j'camêra derdikav e.
Look, mashallah, people are appearing from the camera.
Teqrîben bîstkî eqrin jê dere va tê xiyen e.
Approximately twenty acres go from there to here, you
betray.
Erê maşelleh mentîqeqa gî her ava xwen tê.
Yes, mashallah, all the region has its own water coming.
Ev o meselan o Kefer Miz e, o dorgir e û cûq e mûq e tê
xîye...
This, for example, is Kefer Miz, that is Dorgir, and it's
Cûq, Mûq...
Welah maşelleh. Ra çayî gewer va bixwînten.
By God, mashallah. Let them read the bright tea.
He waha ew çayê Entakyayê ye we. Çayê Entakyayê ye ne?
Yes, that's the tea of Antakya. It's the tea of Antakya,
right?
Erê we de Antakyayê... Ew e...
Yes, it's from Antakya... That is...
Biza ev gundî Xelîl a o... gundî... Te zan gundê gundî Xelîl
dî?
Know that this is the village of Xelîl... village... Did you
see the village of Xelîl?
Erê erê maşelleh gundî wek gundekî pir xweş e gundê navbera
wî de pir xweş e.
Yes yes, mashallah, your village is like a very nice
village, the village between it is very nice.
Keçika Xelîl. E e keçika min Kefer Şîl dîbî...
The girl of Xelîl. Yes, my girl, you've seen Kefer Şîl...
O o bi ya min ro Kefer Şîl e. Ema miletê cano... Gî dar ma
we xwendin. Maşallah kîbar e. Bay bay kin xaltîka bay bay ke
vê ra.
Oh oh, in my opinion, it is Kefer Şîl. But the dear
people... You read all the trees for us. Mashallah, it is
beautiful. Wave bye-bye, auntie, wave bye-bye to this.
Ew ê bay bay ke fêr a. Em ê nogo... derbasî nav gund bin em
ê leqtanek xweş kîbar werê çêkin ka bi mera bin...
She will wave bye-bye, she's used to it. Now we will...
enter the village, we will take nice, beautiful shots for
you, come be with us...
Xwedê ji we razî be... De destê xwe serê we bigre. De wa de
em ê bi evro kan derbas bin. Bay bay.
May God be pleased with you... May He keep His hand over
your head. Come, we will pass by here today. Bye bye.
[Muzîka amûrî tê lêxistin]
[Instrumental music playing]
[Muzîka amûrî berdewam dike]
[Instrumental music continues]
[Muzîka amûrî heta dawiyê berdewam dike]
[Instrumental music continues until the end]
Mam Xorto, Mam Xorto, we re qet dîtin tune.
Uncle Xorto, Uncle Xorto, we never see you.
Merhebe, merhebe.
Hello, hello.
Çi hal e, çi wext e?
How are you, how have you been?
Rihhet e?
Are you well?
Xwedê ji te razî be. Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike.
May God be pleased with you. May God prolong your life.
Maşallah gundê xêr û bereketê ye.
Mashallah, it's a village of goodness and blessings.
Elhemdulillah, elhemdulillah, bi fadlê Xwedê.
Praise be to God, praise be to God, by the grace of God.
Hemdullah, hemdullah.
Praise be to God, praise be to God.
Maşallah, ka tu hewlê gundekî bigirim, ka.
Mashallah, let me get a view of the village.
Obo...
Na na, tale tale al bint e.
No no, come come little girl.
Bye bye ke, bye bye ke, bye bye ke.
Wave bye-bye, wave bye-bye, wave bye-bye.
Sawî bye bye. Sawî bye bye.
Wave bye-bye. Wave bye-bye.
Maşallah. Kê di ke?
Mashallah. Whose is she?
Tefedelu, bo vir de.
Please, come this way.
Şukran, şukran.
Thank you, thank you.
Ehlen we sehlen, ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome, welcome.
Staz?
Sir?
Ehe, maşallah. Her gundek ser gundekî re ye, maşallah.
Ehe, mashallah. Every village is above another village,
mashallah.
Gundekî şêrîn e. Şeibî ne...
It's a sweet village. They are popular...
Evê gundî da... Maşallah.
In this village... Mashallah.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Xwarzin naleskine?
The nephew doesn't speak?
Ma tu la'îbûnî? Ma tu naleyîzî bi topê?
Are you a player? Don't you play with the ball?
Tel'eb?
Will you play?
Yalla bas arca' bedî el'eb me'akum.
Okay, but when I return I want to play with you guys.
Yalla, cehizu halekum.
Come on, get yourselves ready.
La hon. Cehiz halak hon.
No, here. Get yourself ready here.
Erebîya min jî zeîf e.
My Arabic is also weak.
Cîb el-kura dî, de.
Bring that ball, here.
De.
Here.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Ebu Ezo tu laîb e ha. Lêx?
Abu Ezo, you are a player huh. Hit it?
Lêx? Lêx?
Hit it? Hit it?
Lêx, ewa lêx.
Hit it, yeah hit it.
Ewa lêx.
Yeah hit it.
Maşallah çîçkên vê gundî, a ji serîkî lêxim.
Mashallah the kids of this village, let me hit a header.
Lêxe, şûttek lêxe.
Hit it, take a shot.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Usta intû ma bi tiftehu aleykum şî nadî hon mişan tetla'u?
Guys, don't you open a club for yourselves here so you can
go out (play)?
Efrîn sêsed û şêst û şeş.
Afrin 366.
Efrîn sêsed û şêst û şeş, lêx.
Afrin 366, hit it.
Maşallah, şebabê vê gundî pir in. Hûn dixwînin? Hûn
dixwînin?
Mashallah, there are a lot of youths in this village. Do you
study? Do you study?
Ee, hûn dixwînin mektebê?
Yes, do you go to school?
Ey saf entû?
What grade are you guys in?
Sades. Maşallah. Û tu?
Sixth.
Sixth. Mashallah. And you?
Samin.
Eighth.
Samin. Maşallah, maşallah.
Eighth. Mashallah, mashallah.
Hon bihay medrese entû btudrusu mo?
You guys study in this school here, right?
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Hela ba'd ed-dewam bitruhu... bitfutu lal-medrese betla'bu
mo?
Now after school hours you go... you enter the school and
play, right?
Bixellikum, ba'd ed-dewam tela'bu?
Do they let you play after school hours?
Bes nifteha...
We just open it...
La latiftah, la tiftah.
No don't open it, don't open it.
Riyada kewayse.
Sports are good.
Bye bye.
Çîçkên gundî ev in ha, yekemîn gundî ev in ha.
The kids of the village are these, the primary villagers are
these.
Şebab, law ma endî teswîr kuntu rihet me'akum el-medrese
kunt el'eb.
Guys, if I wasn't filming, I would have gone with you to the
school, I would have played.
Fî teswîr?
Is there filming?
Ee am nesewir. Dall endî şwey bedî xalles.
Yes, we are filming. I have a little left, I want to finish.
Bye, bye.
Erê hevalno, li vê derkê jî em hatin berê cîyê swaqa te'lîmê
ye.
Yes friends, here too we have come to the place of the
driving training.
Tê ji Heleb hetanî daxilî Efrîn.
Coming from Aleppo until entering Afrin.
Qewsê Efrînî li vê derê ye, ez meşqir nînim li ku.
The arch of Afrin is here, I don't know where exactly.
Efrîn turahhibu bikum.
Afrin welcomes you.
Erê zûtir tê re diherin Heleb. Berê ev alî Efrîn cih çêkirin
qesdê suwaqe bi alî me.
Yes, earlier they used to go through here to Aleppo. Before,
they made this side of Afrin a place for the driving test on
our side.
Erê hevalno, li vê derkê em gihîştin dawiya vîdyoyê xwe.
İnşallah ev vîdyoyê me bi we ecibîne. Saetên we xweş...
Yes friends, here we have reached the end of our video.
Hopefully you like this video of ours. Have a good time...
Da teqsîr, meqsîr hebin, hûnê qusûrê me efo bikin, bi cizyek
mal derneketi be...
If there are any shortcomings, please forgive our faults, in
case a household hasn't come out...
Em tim watedar bin. Vîdyoyê me afawî ne. Vîdyoyê me afawî
ne. Em vîdyo vîdyo dewate bin.
We always mean well. Our videos are spontaneous. Our videos
are spontaneous. We are invited video by video.
Kêsê me sêr dike, û kêsê heçî kirîye qenatê me jî am wêrê
dibin "ehlen we sehlen". Ser serê me, ser çavê me.
Whoever watches us, and whoever has subscribed to our
channel, we tell them "welcome". On our heads, on our eyes.
Xwedê pêxember ji te razî be, we em gihandinê vê, 17 hezar û
200 re em gihîştinê.
May God and the Prophet be pleased with you, you have
brought us to this, we have reached 17 thousand and 200.
Û inşallah hûnê me bi 20 hezarî jî bigihînin.
And hopefully you will make us reach 20 thousand too.
Erê, û heta em kanin, emê ji we re xizmet bikin. Ev a
tebîeta Efrîn e.
Yes, and as much as we can, we will serve you. This is the
nature of Afrin.
Maşallah, menteqe gelek xweş e, ev a Efrîn a. Hawa xelkê
bînaya lê çêkirîye...
Mashallah, it's a very beautiful area, this is Afrin. This
is how the people built the buildings here...
Badiye... pir menteqe xweş e, kîbar e.
Badiye... it's a very beautiful area, it's grand.
Nika jî em ketine seat suûd, îşta qurtax, gah baran e, gah
ewr e, gah bay e. Hecara tenik e ya.
Now we have also entered the ascending hour, here is Qurtax,
sometimes rain, sometimes clouds, sometimes wind. The stones
are thin.
Menteqe xweş e, raîq, şixulî, pir kîbar e.
The area is beautiful, calm, active, very grand.
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Dê bi me re bin. Vîdyoyê me de xweş kîbar, emê we re
bisawirînin. Îşallah milêtê gundî, Metîna. Emê înşallah
nêzîk de gundê Metîna jî we re teswîr kin.
Stay with us. In our nice grand videos, we will film for
you. Hopefully the people of the village, Metina. Hopefully
soon we will film the village of Metina for you too.
Xalo me re hewal da, rêka xwe diki re derê. Emê inşallah bas
vî carê mecal çêbî, em ê gundê Metîna jî bisawirînin.
Uncle gave us the news, he was taking his way out.
Hopefully, just this time if there's a chance, we will film
the village of Metina too.
Pir gund hana jî me xwestine, em ê yavaş yavaş marhele
marhele, em an gundê giya... em dorê qet nikin gundagî yekê
xelas kin.
Many other villages also wanted us, we will slowly, stage by
stage, go to all the villages... we can't just finish one
village in one turn.
Da yavaş yavaş, heta îşta hasebî zûruf, hasebî wezîyet.
Xwedê ji we razî be. De bi me re bin.
So slowly, until now according to the circumstances,
according to the situation. May God be pleased with you. So
stay with us.
Em jî bar mol herin, seat eva xweş.
We are also going home, have a good time.
Çavê we maç dikim. Bye bye.
I kiss your eyes. Bye bye.
Lome dê, bye bye ke. Tu dibê çi?
Look at me, wave bye bye. What are you saying?
De bosekê çêke, bosekê çêke.
Bye, dear.
Come on, blow a kiss, blow a kiss.
Ewa...
Yeah...
Hela li wî devî, qet rawestan nîne.
Look at that mouth, it never stops.
Ooo, of, fena dişixule.
Ooo, oh, it's running like crazy.