Dembaş hevalno, xwişk û birano.
Good day friends, sisters, and brothers.
Erê em hatin dîsa, gundê Qizilbaşo.
Yes, we have come again, to the village of Qizilbaş.
Vîdyokî xweş wê ra bikişînin.
To shoot a nice video for you.
Erê, li vî derî, me gundê Bêlê û Maxalo, Şikêr, me sa kirin.
Yes, around here, we watched the villages of Bêlê, Maxalo,
and Şikêr.
Me wa'd da we jî me go em ê...
We promised you and said we will...
Xelqê gundê Bêlê.. ewe gundê Qizilbaşo...
The episode of the village of Bêlê... that is, the village
of Qizilbaş...
Û gundê Mihemed... Ehmed Mistû em kê bikişînin.
And the village of Mihemed... Ehmed Mistû, we will shoot it.
Etem Şo jî diki vî gundî ra...
Etem Şo is also from this village...
Me'zetet dixwazim, ez tim pêşiya xwe, tim dixelet bikim.
I apologize, I always get ahead of myself, I always make
mistakes.
Me'zetet dixwazim, ez tim navê xwe dîn dikim... me'zete dîn
dikim lê...
I apologize, I always forget my name... apologize, I forget,
but...
Welle etem şo jî diki...
By God, Etem Şo is also from...
Erê bi zimanê we kî bim, e bihara min em derbasî gundê
Qizilbaşo bin.
Yes, speaking your language, my spring, we will enter the
village of Qizilbaş.
Û gundê Ehmed Mistû.
And the village of Ehmed Mistû.
Her kesî ji vî gundî slavên me ji we ra hene.
To everyone from this village, we send our greetings.
Û ji gundê xwa jî, me ra layk e.. îştrake pê din.
And from our own village too, give us a like... and
subscribe.
Û ta'lîqne xweş û kîbar ya zîrîşken..
And leave nice and polite comments...
Erê we ji me xwestî, em ê îşta hîrû... masî bi xwa bi, em
diki vî gundî xwa bi zivirin.
Yes, you requested it from us, so we are now here... by our
own will, we are turning towards our village.
Wekî din...
Other than that...
Saet te xweş Ma'zet...
Good hours to you, Ma'zet...
Erê hevalno, tab'an ev gundê Qizilbaşo, ewil mera ye ez kê
têkevimê.
Yes friends, of course, this village of Qizilbaş, it's the
first time I'm entering it.
Lê sêr kin, tebî'etkî pir xweş e... Kîbar e...
But look at it, it has a very beautiful nature... It's
nice...
Û em ê gundî din jî wê ra bikişînin.
And we will shoot the other villages for you too.
Miletî vî gundî... slavê me ji we ra hene. Çavê we yê gişa
maç dikim.
People of this village... we send you our greetings. I kiss
the eyes of you all.
Gundekî xweş e, kîbar e. Her kes li malê xwe sêr kin.
It is a beautiful, nice village. Everyone, look at your
homes.
Înşellah em ê nêzîk da em ê... vî xelqano daxin.
Hopefully, soon we will... upload these episodes.
Û çavê we yê gişa maç dikim, Xwedê miletê giştî mehefeze ke.
And I kiss the eyes of you all, may God protect all the
people.
Bîr mekin, herin xelqê Bêlê jî sêr kin. Gundê Bêlê me sa
kirin dî.
Don't forget, go watch the Bêlê episode too. We shot the
village of Bêlê.
Herin wê xelqê jî sêr kin. Û vê diki... niha ku... ev
diki...
Go and watch that episode too. And this from... now that...
this from...
Erê.. û Xelqoka me jî, herin... me dîroka masî ya çê kir wê
ra..
Yes... and our episode too, go... we made the history of the
fish for you...
Erê welle, welle tişkî din... nek bi... em li mala Muxtar
rûniştin.
Yes by God, by God another thing... not that... we sat at
the Mukhtar's house.
Gundê Bêlê... Semsûma jî... Muxtar ti na bî.
The village of Bêlê... Samsum too... Mukhtar, don't forget.
Ev Birahîm, çavê wî maç dikim.
This is Birahim, I kiss his eyes.
Malbatên giş derketin, me qehwek vexwar me got em leze
bikin...
All the families came out, we drank a coffee, we said let's
hurry...
Cehwo... erê me çim divêcî me ra... difasile. Germ e.
The device... yes, because we need it... it disconnects.
It's hot.
Lênî mokî me reş e, û cehwo jî ba rûbe...
Because our vehicle is black, and the device is facing the
sun...
Înzar e dide... ma dibê... ne... cehwo germ bûye...
difasile.
It gives a warning... it says... no... the device has gotten
hot... it disconnects.
Me go me leze tişkî din, nebe.
We said let's hurry with the other thing, lest it happens.
Û gotinek min din jî...
And another thing I want to say...
Vîdyoyekî xwedin re jî weke ku... vîdyoyên derê no.
For another video too, like... the videos of these places.
Miletî Efrîn ê... yê li min sêr diki.
People of Afrin... who are watching me.
Hûn dikevin rêko de, çûn, zibalê xwa, avm çima kin. Ev yek!
You hit the roads, you go, gather your garbage. That's one!
Bi şiklê a'm! Esasen... tab'an yê Uropo, yê Uropo ye!
In a general way! Basically... of course the ones in Europe,
are in Europe!
Em... bi şiklê a'm miletî gundîyo, Efrîn..
We... in a general way, the village people, Afrin...
Hûn dikevin rêk o de çûn, zibalê xwa çima kin, ev o yek!
You hit the road and go, gather your garbage, that's one!
Û ê di di ya jî, hûn di rêk o de çûn, berê avkê, rıhloyîkê,
seyranekê hûn çûn.
And the second one, you hit the road, you went by the water,
on a trip, on a picnic.
Di meknî xwa de... Cuxrê xwa avm çima kin!
In your places... gather your cigarettes!
Cuxr a we we xwar... nıfadê meknî xwa heye. Tê de, bikişin.
Akîd kin, bikişin û qepeqê xwa bigirin.
You smoked your cigarette... there is an ashtray in your
place. Put it in there. Make sure, put it in and close the
lid.
Cuxrê di bilûrê ra çima kin!
Throw the cigarettes through the window!
Milet... daxil çandî! Daxil jî niko gelek dîna...
People... the crops have been planted! The crops are also
now quite...
Hîn potûz lênê nakatina..
They still haven't put trousers on...
Ew çîkoka we bi fir herin nav daxilê xelkê, or e bi rısqî
xelkê keve! Yûnê sebeb seri xelkê bin!
If that spark of yours flies into people's crops, fire will
catch on people's livelihood! You will be the cause of it
for people!
Guneh e... Heram e.. Ewa mekin! Bi şiklê a'm kî bi bê molo
ke elvîdiya mîsêr ker e!
It's a sin... It's forbidden... Don't do that! In a general
way, whoever does this, the video shows it!
Yoxş.. rısqî xelkê hebın. Îşta heram in.. guneh e.. şoşpîno
mekin!
Look... people have their livelihoods. So it is forbidden...
it's a sin... don't be careless!
Heve... yene.. le ser ve tiştî em keyf berbisknin.
Yes... you know... we are enjoying this thing.
Yene ez dibînim, ba'zî daxilî na xelkê a na, e ser cîhaz ez
harê dibînim. Or tê dakeve!
I mean I see, some of the crops of people, I see it on the
device. Fire is catching on it!
Bi kê yeka cuxra çêkirî. Yox... dinê germ e... tu zanî. Here
çil pênc e. Çil e! Na we ye ma'zet?
Someone caused it with a cigarette. No... the weather is
hot... you know. It reaches forty-five. It's forty! Isn't it
so, Ma'zet?
Erê...
Yes...
Hoş mulkê xelkê hebın, hûn çûn berî avkê. Mılkê xelkê
macilîbînin..
People have properties, you went by the water. Don't damage
people's property...
Di rîkê xwa re hîrin. We xwar we xwar jî.. zibalê xwa rakin!
Bi şiklê a'm!
Be careful on your way. If you ate, you ate... pick up your
garbage! In a general way!
Mi le menatiqa ma xweş e hû..
Our region is beautiful, you know...
Miletî ma ji yolî hu de ge fitilî hatî!
Our people have started wandering around from everywhere!
Malbata xwa, subehe çema'a heleb e tîn, subehe çema'a Uropa
tîn.
Their families, tomorrow the people of Aleppo will come,
tomorrow the people of Europe will come.
Tîn xor o... minteqeyê digerin... etîn di meqş o... di vî
derê dibin.
They come... they tour the region... they come and settle
in... these places.
Aleyê sosiyara me o ke levra bin.. Hefta gel vir bin.
They will be in our social areas... They'll be here for a
week.
E... E'fşiye... Ma'dî macî af.. bikevê di raf in der nane.
Ewe a'lebê ne pekbîne.
Yes... It's Afrin... Some of them... leave it on the
shelves. Most of them don't clean it.
Te zanî? Bi yik di Uropo gê mor dikî! Mera qanûnî ye... mera
heps êke!
You know? If you do this in Europe, they will fine you! We
have laws... we will put them in jail!
Û cezo xeran elix ê... zibalê xwa çima nekê. No! Uropo xêr
xweş e. Nîzam haye.
And they give heavy penalties... if you don't gather your
garbage. No! Europe is very nice. There is a system.
Nîzam haye! Her derkî nefedê xwa danîn e. Hewyok xwe ha ne.
There is a system! They have put their ashtrays everywhere.
They have their bins.
Ta der navê durt e.. pak e... tib xo... zibalê xwe çima
nekê. Co ma... em di bi rihan zibal e.
They clean it all... it's pure... if you yourself... don't
gather your garbage. But us... we throw garbage on the
roads.
Da a.. ba red le xwa... le ma may tûrî zibale... pirr ...
depencerê ro dabin!
And... you see... they throw a bag of garbage... full... out
of the window!
E no.. maçe ... yek a nameşe. Mediyê?
That's it... I mean... one doesn't know. Have you seen it?
Me dî... xelkê d pencê ro ve tîne we? E şe.. e ma roke har
e..
I have seen it... people throw it out of the window, you
know? Yes... this day is crazy...
Ji min re... bi gir o har e. Silavên me ji kiyê we re
hene... Çavê we ge maç dikim wê...
To me... it's really crazy. We send our greetings to all of
you... I kiss the eyes of you all...
Hûn gin miletê mane. Te zanî. Ta iro ki.. em ke... havdî
iştê.. eh eqlî... makirti bikirî. Î hay..
You are all our people. You know. Until today... we... with
each other... should use our minds... act maturely. Yes...
No cir e işt.. em ki abdir o hîdor a kin.. Iştam ki menetiqa
xweş bi kin... e he...
This is how it is... we should manage and take care of it...
We should make our region beautiful... yes...
Jê we xweştir... eve mêdan kileku ambarmîn he..
Better than this... this square has everything...
Meydank e!
It's a square!
Biçînin daro biçînin.. kese hısime ki.. dar o bi çînin pêşi
di şqopî xo..
Plant trees, plant them... whoever wants... plant trees in
front of their property...
Li ser rey keke... bi çînin! Tebi'e çekin! şenkin! Tişt nobe
mere nav mîri bi şixul dera mero rast nebe.. mene nav mire.
On the roadsides... plant them! Create nature! Make it
lively! Nothing will happen, a person doesn't die from
working, a person doesn't become straight... they don't die.
Xwe lûkê me 'emrê xwe nûs sal bi tim dişixulî.
Our old people would work all the time even at ninety years
old.
Bi şixulîn doro biçînin... xizmetkin!
Work, plant trees around... serve!
Jı wî.. jı wî.. jı wî... jı wî.. xweş dibe... her meqamk...
he mişru'êk ne dEfrîn dawedibên.
From this... from this... from this... from this... it
becomes beautiful... every place... every project they are
doing in Afrin.
Wallahi me'xêxê 100 hezar, 200 hezar dolar e. Ewa mileti
qaro çuye..
By God, they are spending 100 thousand, 200 thousand
dollars. That's for the people who have left...
Oropa ehaye rismul ki... go hindî havde... tî meşro e veda
qê! U tî liva kır ne.
Europe is a capital... so this much... you come and do
projects here! And you work here.
Efrîn! Mezraî çelo ve dikın. Ma'meli Pêşkowê to va di qen...
pîr tişti xweş dî bin e mantîqi ma de. Pir tişti xêçe bina.
Afrin! They are opening cow farms. They are opening biscuit
factories... many beautiful things are happening in our
region. Many nice things are happening.
Em kêf dikeyn! Me yîna dike rukbê baware... eno.. de Efrin
de otêl habin...
We are happy! We hope to see... that... there will be hotels
in Afrin...
Bi serehi mî yîna na di qere. Eno va ro we re... mesela...
Honestly, we don't expect it. That on these roads... for
example...
Ye qerêb û ke... wara xwe... û o telû û dare rinde.
Someone close... comes here... and there's a nice hotel and
place.
Masabê xe mîn e... de gundo dê nok e... masabê hî cîdara
hene..
I see pools... in the villages now... they have pools...
De bihara bim... em ha wera dervaz.. gind bim.
Let me start... we will pass to... the village.
Em.. wîdî ki.. xeş... nafu gind çekim..
We... will shoot... a nice video... inside the village...
Kîsûri ma ci av qên.. şêweşbîn, maşbîn hene.. afqin. Em.
wîdî. bi af avîn e... af avi. Yalla xatiri wa!
Forgive our shortcomings... if there are any flaws...
forgive them. We... didn't intentionally... forgive us. Come
on, goodbye for now!
Are.. ma desta pêqir.. No... nok e... hindak... yezmîşke..
aba bi 'zzet.. Leş ma hesb.
Yes... we have started... This... now... a little bit... is
writing... maybe Ma'zzet... Why is she angry.
Lewala e xêl e nobe min ... no no... ye min den qirnê min
eva... as bır..mentîqi dekefım... aza bar tebi'eto xwed di
kavim dare dî kavam.
No, by God, she is not angry at me... no no... it's just my
loud voice... I'm looking at the region... I fall into its
nature, I look around.
Demirşit... do xazidanke bi be vî si... Bê es waqidên.
It shows... I want her to speak a little like this... So we
can talk.
Cuxra qiqik çekin, sake, as mikî çe dike.
Smoke a little cigarette, look, see what asthma does.
Le cuxrake asmekî çedike di a mi.
But the cigarette doesn't cause asthma in me.
E neh qelî dıbî mawadim... az niheyta dike am.
I am telling you... I am just giving advice.
Maru lazi kes siraru pînine.
A person shouldn't harm anyone.
Are...
Yes...
Hawa dıye... Hawa dıye... hax hevç in te di va darî dî hane.
O fêq o qı pirne! Maşallah...
See this... See this... every courtyard has trees like this.
They are full of fruit! Mashallah...
Axile biye mage dı qît e lbîzn ne nebin...
Most of them are... I guess... they are not sheep...
Teb'an gendê Bêlê lîk o lam par may ava lî man nîzîk biken
heçikê
Of course, the village of Bêlê is on this side, get a little
closer to it.
O .. nezîqbi qe.. ma va gen dûsa erandî harênê we hil
qicî... sêrqin. Gi dî belu.
Get closer... we also watched these villages in the other
episodes... go watch them. Bêlê village.
Mîziqi qa ma va mawlne ev kurt te.. di bi... dizaçê..
qende.. daran naket ve mawi.
Get closer so we can see these short ones... maybe... it'll
pass... the village... I can't catch this part.
Lenan dı xof e ro cwîn. Barvîma lüca lefırve
Because we passed from the edges. We are heading to the
village over there.
Seka vereqe do xwelî... ve qindi dware.. nahe hêy nekî ça..
seh sebinê le hê!
Look, entering this side... the village around it... now a
little... wait let me see!
Çox sa no rinda. Hîşîne habê! Dar vîw lîvî lîvî. Ava gzim
gin dü gîr na qînin.
Look how beautiful it is. Having greenery! Trees everywhere.
Let's make the villages like this.
Ye me liti qen.. nafa havt o .. çan dûro hi.. xwem se biş...
qıren. Arza ne. Na ha hărqas o norb aqen saki tabi a xoşi...
cuxraf qixeşi ni menezir xeş dertikefên.
I am telling the people... in the area... plant some
trees... and shrubs. It's cheap. Now everyone can plant
them, look what a beautiful nature... a beautiful geography,
beautiful views appear.
Mı rokat i nê. E.. wele mintqo qi xeş e... qiqen di ve tîne?
I was looking at this. Yes.. by God it's a beautiful
region... what village are we passing?
Ye ye ye... Wele mohzetey mever dû gin pîr ne. He He..
Yes, yes, yes... By God, Ma'zet, the villages around here
are many. Yeah, yeah...
Eh as... eve qendena ni zonîm.
I... don't know these villages.
Han selefziftê rare?
Shall we go on this paved road?
Mı dere ran se lif..
Let me look this way...
Erê ha wele ne li gundê Cûcekan binî me, ev gundo ye, gundê
Ehmed Misto ye.
Yes, by God, I am not below the village of Cûcekan, it's
this village, the village of Ehmed Misto.
Bes wê gundê ha niha li hember me ye, kîder e, qutan e,
kîder e, me ere te'lîqek dît.
But that village right there opposite to us, where is it, is
it Qutan, where is it, we just saw a comment.
Min şk nedikir ev gundo kî derê ye. Wele min pê bihîstî, bes
min jibîr kirî ka gundo kîjan e.
I didn't suspect where this village was. By God, I had heard
about it, but I forgot which village it was.
Qutan e, kî der e ye vî der e ye wele nizanim.
Is it Qutan, where is it, is it this place, by God I don't
know.
Wele mentîqeya vira heta hîn pirr mezin e o ho ho hato çavê
te firq deke gund o ye.
By God, the area here is very big, oh oh oh, there are
villages as far as your eye can see.
Erê xûşk û birano em li vê derê jî em li mala Xalê Cemal in,
em li nîvê gund ne.
Yes brothers and sisters, we are here too, we are at Uncle
Cemal's house, we are in the middle of the village.
Em ku derbasî mala mixtar bûn, wî qala me ra xeberek da got
xalo we gotinek zanî ser vî gundî.
When we passed by the mukhtar's house, he gave us some
information and said "uncle, you know a word or two about
this village".
Em hatine gundê we, gotina pirskin ji xalo ser vî gundî, min
go me ra xeber de.
We came to your village, to ask you some words, uncle, about
this village, I said tell us about it.
Ev gundo çawa ye, çiqas hewşek tê de heye? Bi kîjan malbatê
ava bûye ev gundo? Ka me ra xeber de.
How is this village, how many courtyards are in it? By which
family was this village built? Tell us about it.
Min go merheba jî ji te ra xalo.
I said hello to you as well, uncle.
Waeleykûmselam, ser çavên min, ser serê min, hûn bixêr
hatin.
And peace be upon you, on my eyes, on my head, welcome.
Wele gundê we xweş e, ecêb e.
By God, your village is beautiful, it's amazing.
Erê gundekî xweş e.
Yes, it is a beautiful village.
Gundin jiyan hîn zêde xweştir ne tê de.
Living in villages is much more beautiful.
Ku bilindbûniya wê wek tepe ye ku menazerê der dor me ra
xûya dike.
Its elevation is like a hill, the surrounding scenery is
visible to us.
Wele dikarî me ra noka xeber de, ev gundo çiqas hewş tê de
heye? Çiqas malbat e?
By God, can you tell us now, how many courtyards are in this
village? How many families?
Wele xalo gundê me, ne mezin e. Ne gundekî mezin e, dorê
şêst heftê malî heye. Ew e, ne mezin e.
By God uncle, our village is not big. It's not a big
village, there are around sixty or seventy houses. That's
it, it's not big.
Hûn tabî kî ne?
What are you affiliated with?
Em tabî navçeya Bilbilê ne.
We are affiliated with the district of Bilbil.
Navçeya Bilbilê?
The district of Bilbil?
Erê, em di tixûbê navçeya Şera û Bilbilê da ne. Ji me wê da
navçeya Şera ye.
Yes, we are on the border of the districts of Şera and
Bilbil. Beyond us is the district of Şera.
Ji vê da Bilbil e.
On this side it is Bilbil.
Jê vir va çiqas dûr e Şera?
How far is Şera from here?
Dûr e deh, panzde kîlometro.
It is far, ten, fifteen kilometers.
Deh, sêzde, deh, panzde, tiştekî wilo, te pîvan nedikirî?
Ten, thirteen, ten, fifteen, something like that, haven't
you measured it?
Xalo te karê me ra xeber de vê gundoyî bi kîjan malbatê ava
bûye?
Uncle, can you tell us by which family this village was
built?
Bi kîjan malbatê ava bûye. Ê asasiyê di vî gundî de, kîjan
malbat e...
By which family it was built. Basically, in this village,
which family is...
Vî gundo yanî dive bi yekî ji bingehî re zane bî. Çawa ava
bûye, kes nîne, kes nizane.
This village, I mean, you need someone who knows it from the
foundation. How it was built, there is no one, no one knows.
Çimkî, min pirs kirî wez pirs dikim, kesên temen bilind et
ku zemanê berê da hinekî jiyan kirin e.
Because I asked, I ask the elderly people who lived a little
in the old times.
Û dîbînin... ez pirs dikim dibên kevn e.
And they have seen... I ask and they say it's old.
Kevnor e?
It's ancient?
Çimkî heta noka xaniyekî kevn heye, heta noka heye, jê ra
dibên xaniyê Çenqit.
Because until now there is an old house, it's still here
until now, they call it the house of Çenqit.
Çenqit?
Çenqit erê. Xaniyê Çenqit kî bû, heta noka kes nizane yê kî
ye.
Çenqit, yes. Whose house Çenqit was, until now no one knows
whose it is.
Kî bû malbata wî kî bû, kuda çûn e kes nizane.
Who was he, who was his family, where did they go, no one
knows.
Lê hema et ku hatine li vir rûniştin ne noka ne, li vir ne
noka ne.
But those who came and settled here are not the current
ones, the ones here are not the current ones.
Paşê yên noka hatin na...
Then the ones who came now are...
Paşê ew nokayê ku hatin na li vir rûniştin.
Then the current ones who came did not settle here.
Hatin li hembarê gund rûniştin, sê bira bûn.
They came and settled opposite the village, they were three
brothers.
Yek navê xwe Heso bû, wek ez zanim ha!
One of their names was Heso, as far as I know!
Yek Heso bû, yek Xelo bû, yek Silo bû.
One was Heso, one was Xelo, one was Silo.
Çimkî heta noka şikestkên wan hene, şûnê wan di nav dara
hene, wek giranê me. Zeytûnê gundiyên li vir hene, dibên
zeytûnê xirab e.
Because until now their ruins are there, their places are
among the trees, like our hills. The villagers' olive trees
are here, they call them the ruined olives.
Ewana xiraba wan bûn.
Those ruins were theirs.
Xiraba wan bûn.
The ruins were theirs.
Çawa hatin vira, berê go çawa bûn e dema, xwedan pez bûn.
How they came here, how they were back then, they were sheep
owners.
Ewna komir kirin, bi komirê diketin. Hatin li vê derê, şûn
va xaniyê me va der û dor e ye, komir li vê derê kirin.
Those guys made charcoal, they dealt with charcoal. They
came here, instead of these houses of ours around here, they
made charcoal here.
Wî bapîrê Xwedê jê razî daxuyakirin, koka xwe ji kîderê
tînin. Hesû û qeleb bûn. Diqulîçûn e.
My late grandfather declared where they trace their roots.
They were Heso and Qeleb. They were two branches.
Qele, ne Xaziye ne ji çi ye, ana Sûr aviyê... Qele, bi
kurmancî qele ye.
Castle (Qele), not Ghazi or what, now it's Sur... Castle. In
Kurmanji it is castle.
Ê Qeleb bûn. Hesû, ber ku me ra jî dîyar kir, ku meriv êdî
dikarê rahat bibêjin, temam. Hîn Hesû şûnde bû. Sûr de bû.
They were Qeleb. Hesû, since it was explained to us, so one
can now easily say it, fine. Hesû was behind. He was in Sur.
Cewar... diyar kirin dihatin du qut rûn, ew ji Hesû în bûye
Qizil Paşa.
The surroundings... declared they were divided in two parts,
and from Hesû it became Qizil Pasha.
În bûye Qizil Paşa. Xwe de Sûr bûye. Ê Qizil Paşa, Qizil
Paşa, Qizil Paşa, onnav lê kirin bû Qizilbaşa.
It became Qizil Pasha. In Sur itself. Qizil Pasha, Qizil
Pasha, Qizil Pasha, they named it Qizilbasha.
Qizilbaşa.
Qizilbasha.
Ku meriv... Ku meriv li vê derdorê awir kirîbû, hat naka hîn
axa gund gawir e yanî...
When one... When one looked around here, until now the
village land is still infidel, meaning...
A gawir e, hey.
Infidel, yeah.
Paşê ji wê, hatin nava vê rûniştin. Êwa... Hatin a, ji berî
malbatên me li vê derê rûniştin, ê me malbata Êmira...
After that, they came and settled here. Yeah... They came,
before our families settled here, we are the Emir family...
Hatin nava malbata Gurdê, vêre rûniştin.
They joined the Gurde family, they settled here.
Malê Gurdê?
The Gurde house?
Malê Êmir.
The Emir house.
E hûn, wek Malbata Êmir ne?
Are you the Emir family?
E, a jî yek Mala Gurdê. Vê na wan hatin vê derê, li vir
rûniştin û bi wî navê gund ban hate navkirin.
Yes, that is also the Gurde house. They came here, settled
here, and the village was named after them.
Qizilbaşan bi wan hate navkirin.
Qizilbashan was named after them.
Bi wan navkirin. Li ber wê da digotin Xiskê Qizilbêş. Qiskê
Qizilbaşa, tê ta li wêderê dîtî Xiskê Qizilbaşa.
They named it after them. Before that, they used to say
Xiske Qizilbesh. Qiske Qizilbasha, you can still see it
there as Xiske Qizilbasha.
Jê wê da, bû Qizilbaşa. Qizilbaşa, qata naka bû Qizilbaş.
Teba... Pêşka tirkî ye yanî, ne... Ne bi kurmancî ye, ne jî
bi erebî ye, Qizilbaş.
From that, it became Qizilbasha. Qizilbasha, up to now it's
Qizilbash. Of course... It is a Turkish word, meaning, no...
It's not Kurmanji, and it's not Arabic, Qizilbash.
Erê.
Yes.
Û hat... belav kirin, bi navê... Qizilbaşan.
And it was... spread out, with the name... Qizilbashan.
Qizilbaşa.
Qizilbasha.
Malbat jî am li Êmira ne, du mal in ne... du malbat in e.
Mala Gurdê û Êmira.
Our family is in the Emirs, they are two families. The Gurde
house and the Emirs.
Malek, qismek Malbata Gurdê ye, qismek malbatên Êmir in ne?
One house, a part is the Gurde family, a part is the Emir
families, right?
Mala Gurdê, Êmir in. Are.
The Gurde house, they are Emirs. Yes.
Are, û bi van navê malbatan ve tên nas kirin, vê gundî da.
Yes, and by these family names they are known, in this
village.
Erê. Erê.
Yes. Yes.
Silavê min ji van milata, ev malbata giş re, çavê wan gişka
maçî dikim.
My greetings to these people, to all these families, I kiss
the eyes of them all.
Û her yekî di vê gundî da we... ez silav dikim, çavî we maçî
dikim. Ser serî me, ser çavî me ne. Û malbatên ku jî hene...
And everyone in this village... I send greetings to you, I
kiss your eyes. You are upon my head, upon my eyes. And the
families who are also there...
... me xeberek neda yan tiştek, me qusûr bike. An jî ser
çavê wan gişkana maç dikim.
... if we haven't given news or something, forgive our
shortcoming. Or else I kiss the eyes of all of them.
Xalo, vê gundî da, karbe ne gihîştiye vê gundî, ne?
Uncle, in this village, electricity hasn't reached this
village, right?
Noka na.
Not right now.
Ne gihîştiye.
Has not reached.
Na. Lê waha şemsiye ne... am alwaha şemsiyen e.
No. But we use solar panels... we use solar panels.
Eynen a ye.
Exactly like that.
Erê.
Yes.
Û... mekteb heye li gund?
And... is there a school in the village?
Mekteb jî heye, av jî heye.
There's also a school, there's also water.
Av heye? E şerîke e?
There's water? It's a network?
Erê, ya rande heye.
Yes, there's a good one.
Firne?
Bakery?
Firne tine e.
There is no bakery.
Û hûn ku... ka gundî hûn ê xwa, îhtiyacên xwa hûn ji kû
tînin?
And you... where do you, the villagers, bring your needs
from?
Efrîn... Sedî reba gundiyan... belkî ji sedî nod jî sedî
reba... ser zeytûnê ye.
Afrin... Seventy percent of the villagers... maybe even
ninety percent, seventy percent... depends on olives.
Ser zeytûnê ye.
Depends on olives.
Ser zeytûnê ye. Efrîn gişk ser zeytûnê ye. Sedî hevtê, yan
pê.. heştê, ewe dît tu gîşk ser zeytûnê ye.
Depends on olives. All of Afrin depends on olives. Seventy
percent, or... eighty percent, it's all seen depending on
olives.
Xalo... gotineke te li dawîyê... Naha şora me te... me ra
xeber da.
Uncle... your final words... Now we have talked... you spoke
with us.
Gotineke te ew dawiyê... Tu, me re çî nesîhetî dikî, ku...
re ... tu emrekî derbaz kir... û te dî ye yanî û te pir
tiştan ra derbaz bî yanî.
Your final word... What advice do you give us, that... you
have lived a lifetime... and you have seen, meaning, and you
have been through many things.
Am ki cîl in noka, am ki xurt... yani pir tişt hene, am
nizanin. Am ji ew wek we, am tiştê ew şore kî ji we dibin.
Gotin kî ji we dibin.
Us current generation, us young people... meaning there are
many things, we don't know. We are like you, we learn those
things, those words from you. We learn those words from you.
Am ew dikin... Yanî gotinên te ji me re... ku am xort... e,
te çi gotinê de heye me ra?
We do that... So what are your words for us... since we are
young... uh, what words do you have for us?
Gotina min o yekem, bo xortan... O hîn e... wek erebî
dibêjin "cîl el mustaqbel e".
My first word, for the youth... The ones who are... as they
say in Arabic, "the future generation."
Hêvîya min e, ew tav û silav... am, hezkirinê ev der de
bikin... Hûn kî xwe re qise mezin in. Zimanê xwa nexin der.
My hope is, those rays and greetings... we, spread love
around here... You who are older to yourselves. Don't throw
out your language.
Zimanê te tunebê, tu jî tuneye.
If your language is nonexistent, you are also nonexistent.
Rast e.
True.
Zimanê xwa nexin der. Zimanê xwa bernadin. Heta îmkan e be,
zimanê xwa dane axafin.
Don't throw out your language. Don't let go of your
language. Speak your language as much as possible.
Û em bêjin a din jî, a wa... am pir qisê de, gotin ê ne
garak e... na gereke.
And let's say the other thing too, that... we, in many
talks, unnecessary words... shouldn't be needed.
Ne garak e, are... Însanê giştî zanin, wisa we gotina we ne
garak in...
Shouldn't be needed, yes... People generally know, that your
words are not needed...
Û însan e... O ji we re... Yanî pir însan hene e mesele di
xarabî ye... Di xarabiyê de diqin, am kanin pîşe doxre lamîş
kîn. Am kê wî rêk e doxre. Am kê am kefî kanin...
And people... And for you... Meaning there are many people,
for example in badness... They do badness, we can fix their
forefront. We can set them straight. We can forgive as much
as we can...
Naxdî vî... naxdî we e... am kê naxdî ya we efî kîn.
Neither this... neither that... we should just forgive.
Xarez e, te dinya rindiyê xawa keve, paşê rindîya we tu
neye... te nedîye.
Outside of this, if you find goodness in the world, then you
won't have goodness... you haven't seen it.
Ma rast divê xalo.
You speak truly, uncle.
Meriv kefî de, efî ka. Û em birakên ev in a.
When one enjoys it, they forgive. And we are brothers of
each other.
Are lê, em birakên in... Xwedê xêrê te binîvse, Xwedê emrê
te dirêj ke.
Yes indeed, we are brothers... May God write your good
deeds, may God give you a long life.
Em jî razî bin.
We should also be pleased.
Xalo, te çi silavê dişkine jin... ji mileta re? Ew milete
naho pir li mesêr dikeye... û... çi kesî te heye...
Uncle, what greetings do you send from... to the people?
Those people are watching us a lot right now... and...
whoever you have...
Silavê me jê xwe re dî... Wela.
Send our greetings to them... Wow.
Silavê me, yê gîha ne li dere wîne... Ew di... Silavê me ji
ew gundiya re hene... Ji wan xortê serxweş û xwaşî bi wa be.
Our greetings, those who have arrived are outside... They...
Our greetings are for those villagers... May it be pleasant
and nice with those handsome youths.
Wî inşelleh ser serî me û ser çavên me ne... inşelleh wê
cabek li we derê.
And hopefully upon our heads and upon our eyes... hopefully
a message will come to you there.
Ser serî me û çavên me sax bi, xalo.
Long live our heads and our eyes, uncle.
Am jê pir keyf xweş bûn ku am dikavin nav gundana, malbatana
û bi wek wa de... însana mezin de am di rûnin, em jî yek pir
kêfxwaş dibin ku we xêr û bereketên... man e, ne xêreka wisa
e.
We were also very happy that we enter villages, families and
with like that... we sit with great people, we also become
very happy that your goodness and blessings... meaning, it's
not a common goodness.
Saeta we ya baş qet tune be...
If your good hour doesn't exist at all...
Yanî, hûn tune bin... Hûn, hûn tune bin, em jî tunen.
Meaning, if you don't exist... You, if you don't exist, we
don't exist either.
Em, em her bedû ki hene.
We, we always follow each other.
A... na wa wa... am bi bedû hene. A... Na... Çaxê di bi,
em... meselen am xort in am nizanin, bas hûn... amrê ke
derbaz kirîyê we zane.
Ah... no, yeah... we follow each other. Ah... No... When you
talk, we... for example we are young we don't know, but
you... you've passed a lifetime, you know.
Mera pirskê, însan mera zanebê.
One should ask, one should learn from someone.
Nizanibê mera pirskê.
Indeed.
If they don't know, they should ask.
Mera pirskê... Mera tiştê ke nizanibê, nexêr eyyûb e...
pirsekî ke.
They should ask... It's not bad if one doesn't know
something... they should ask.
Pirskê. Cihê nizanibê pirs ka, ne eyyûb e. Tu nizanibê
pirskê. Ti tişt nizanibê pirskê.
They should ask. They should ask what they don't know, it's
not bad. If you don't know, ask. If you don't know anything,
ask.
Cihê dima, elimî ye... bes te pirs nakir, tu nê elimî.
Where you are left behind, you learn... but if you don't
ask, you don't learn.
Te na elimîye... tu nizane.
You won't learn... you don't know.
Naho maşelah, miletê ma... e... her gundeke kî am kavinê,
evale, em pir kî kêfxweş dibin. Xwezî te dî yek tiştek ew de
pena kavin... Lên am ne... me ihtîmam xwu da tiştî, û na
darbaz be wî wextî...
Now mashallah, our people... uh... every village we enter,
thankfully, we become very happy. If you ever find yourself
needing anything... But we don't... we've paid attention to
things, and time has passed...
Ema, tabiyet û cur... cografya am... vîdeoyê we ji da aw
cur... am bîn vîdeoyê me û em ew diki e.
But, the nature and kind... geography we... your video here
is also of that kind... we see our video and we do it.
Saeta te gelek xaş û pir xaş... tevan e... am dar kavin
boştêk nandin diki e, me gund... a miletê we da dertên
wek... em nas diki.
Your time was very nice and so pleasant... with you... we go
out doing a little something, we... are showing your village
people... we are getting to know them.
Heta wê kanê dî ji da... ku we go zamînê xwar barmatin..
Zamîn ta e...
Up to the moment you say... that you said our grounds are
blessed.. Your grounds are...
Zimanî xa... baqa bî.
May your language... be eternal.
Pir ka se hene, na wa pir weka xa ne xwe re xwe bo mirad
ne... der dika we ser telefonê dibîn Ebu Ahmet, ev bir gandî
ew naha efrîn wane...
There are many people, they are not really doing very well
for themselves... they are saying on the phone Abu Ahmet,
this village is now in Efrin...
Da em mecûra ew di ke, am nizanîn ev gund e, çi qêrêk wêne..
Çû we. Wek rêkek de te rê... we da... û tu da e zane de
mantike te lî çû kanê we weke..
We are forced to do it, we don't know this village, what is
its status.. It's gone. As a way you give... to them... and
you know that your logic went from what...
Namasiyek êk di... şêx er dêt...
An incomplete thing... a sheikh comes...
Yek tîştî ne... mesel.
It's one thing... for example.
Rukî e ji... ez ew hiş... na, çûn Halep. A wa mêjin, me
çaxek ez... ba... stembû.
One day from... I and her... no, we went to Aleppo. That's
true, when I was... at... Istanbul.
E... şêweya wa, em dakatin... we ma katar bu stem bu wa..
Uh... their way, we went down... we were waiting in line in
Istanbul..
Şofer yek ew ke me şal sipî di wane.. da qet.. amerê kî di
wa ke şofer te de e.. ne wina.
The driver was someone with white hair over there.. that
completely.. a life for a driver is.. not like that.
La mi... xu re mingo da, ew ser ke em tê wew... tu waker mi
stembul ew kar we derbaz ke kî.
So I... to myself I said, he's leading us there... what can
you do in Istanbul to pass the time.
Min got te di kar qermi duk de kî amr diki de wina re ta wa
re ta erdi go qurmiduk ta wa ta.. La wina.
I said you work with wrinkles making life go round with
these people until it hits the ground he said your
wrinkles.. Like that.
Migo xa ... xale kî we we we min go xal kî ku der kî gund kî
ye?
I said uncle... an uncle we we we I said uncle where is your
village?
Migo qizil baş u ame, go qizil paşe... la go ew kuder a e
kuder a di qizil paşe nizane ye di...
I said I came from Qizilbash, he said Qizil Pasha... he said
where is that, where is Qizil Pasha, he doesn't know it...
Mingo a a a wa gundê Efrîn e ne.. we ew de mane ji tew da
wew kuder kî ne mingo ne we we... wate xewe rî xwa di qise
ka nasik gund de am di wan kî wanî..
I said those are villages of Efrin.. he stood there thinking
from where they are I said no... meaning you are speaking by
yourself knowing villages we are like them..
La go tu çû we we ewa te bu mi ruka ma sa kî ma ew we ew
kude di ma go filan filan yek der ew mir ke çewê ye cem wene
... wa we go a ma wa xam wane wane... tiji kî qizilbaşe u...
nizane edî e.
So he said what do you know about that I sat back there
where we stayed he said so and so one died his eye is with
them ... and they said ah they are still there... what about
Qizilbash and... he doesn't know it anymore.
Garake mari zane be de.. Afrîn sî se de u şest kî şeşt go ew
de go mari mî di ewe de we zana di a wa da te...
A person needs to know it.. Efrin three hundred and sixty-
six he said it's a person who knows everything there...
Ew se se de o çes e sî se de e çeş te şew mola te te hawe a
re ye ruşti.
That three hundred and sixty-six three hundred and sixty-six
you have a duty to sit back down.
Roşta ew raqew la û wadi rabe de te wa bo kurmanci da go
wawa wî da na ka we ra da wawa wati ma rî rî a ka ma ma wa
we go wî ra te xebare ye ...
You sat down and then got up you were going for Kurmanji
saying this saying we didn't do it you said we didn't do it
with him you have news...
We de wa ma tu bo gund... ra xa ew na. O e min di pirs ker û
me de we ka wa da.
At that time you are for a village... asking them no. Oh I
asked and we gave them there.
Wa he raşta we dî waz pîr ka nî ye me wa bo wawa dîn we am
de re kandin. Da e de te ne ye re xarî qeb... e...
It's true when I saw an old person we thought for them we
laughed. And then you couldn't eat it... uh...
Xel wî na ku me gund ê me de a wa bo gund ê Ahmadi Mustiye
wî bo me mîn e ma tawe xabar dîn we raber a gundê Ahamdi
Mustiye.
Uncle it's true when we have our village it's for Ahmadi
Mustiye village he stayed for us talking showing Ahmadi
Mustiye village.
Tê na de wa gundê am pirs ker da am de wa Abu Ahmed.
You didn't give the village we asked then we said Abu Ahmed.
Abu Ahmed.
Wa mer de la kî re ka ew sê ka ma rî ha.
They died a man with three lines.
Tê he ra ca wa ta na xabara ta ma e we tu ra pirs ka ew ye
wina la raste.
You went and told them news of us they ask you if it's true.
Xal na am bo de e... a go wa... ew... da bîn na re he?
Uncle no we were saying... uh saying... to... seeing no
here?
E... wa wa na wa rabe xwe ewe e rabe wina rabe... wî ew bî
gund da xabara ne mistî da we am te...
Uh... like that don't get up here just get up... he became a
village saying not completely and we came...
Wa wa bî ew ewe de e baqa ti raste da re he he wi di wi
mingo ka mi nî mingo ew mingo az ê bo wa pirs ke we pirs.
Like that it was without you true so you had it he gave he
gave I said I don't see I said he said I will ask them you
ask.
Wa we la qabel we dîn da na ka wa da rabe te ye raber de
xale bîna ma kî a de qabel ne da. U xaw pîr a ra di wina wî
go wati me Ahmadi...
They didn't accept us then saying get up you give an example
uncle another one won't accept. And having an old man
walking like that he said my word Ahmadi...
Abu Ahmed he me zî mingo a mingo Abu Ahmed we am ti bo ra
wîne xal a di xal ha e... e
Abu Ahmed yes we also said ah I said Abu Ahmed we came for
you pointing here uncle... yes
A qaye ka ew we... a la e mingo ka me rî ne wa wa da emê dî
bo qala wina ne gund ma ti go xa de...
Something that he... and so I said maybe we shouldn't do it
like that we will go talk there our village you said no...
Na e dî tike xabara di bo de bo bî kî bo we xe de barx a...
da wa de...
No and you give news saying for talking to make him happy...
so you say...
Raşte mingo hey raşte la mingo ew de qala na mingo he e e
mingo ne ka xwa...
True I said hey true then I said that talks no I said yes
yes yes I said no to yourself...
Û ne we de ma se re ne a wa te ma rabe wina qale gund bî
ser... kî e we ne... bî ye nî xel?
And you weren't standing there it came so getting up like
that talking village on... who are they... they are without
uncle?
Ew se bî ew... xaw wa te he te.
It was three of them... walking towards you.
...xweş û saet xweş. Serkeftin be j'te re.
...good times and good hours. Good luck to you.
Saet xweş be, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Have good hours, may God be pleased with you.
Xwedê we neke bin destan.
May God not leave you under oppression.
Saet xweş, ser çavê min.
Have good hours, upon my eyes.
Ser çavê me, saet xweş... Ehlen û sehlen.
Upon our eyes, have good hours... Welcome.
Silavên me ji miletê te yî gundî, xortên kofî mezin...
Saetên we xweş, gundê we xêr û bêr e.
Our greetings to your village people, the youth with big
hats... Have good hours, may your village be full of
blessings.
Gundê me xêr û bêr e, miletê te jî xweş û kibar e.
Our village is full of blessings, your people are also good
and kind.
Erê, silavên me ji miletê we gundî giyara re.
Yes, our greetings to all your village people.
...em çûçek mezin...
...we a big bird...
Xwedê gotine te aniye, ku silav ji...
God brought your words, that greetings from...
...û silav ji gundiyan re heye, hecî dervan...
...and there are greetings for the villagers, pilgrims
outside...
...û çavên giya maşallah... qeçkê me jî li dervan in, saetên
we xweş.
...and the eyes of all mashallah... our girls are also
outside, have good hours.
O têne wa jî, ehlen û sehlen.
Oh they are coming too, welcome.
Ser serê min...
Upon my head...
Saet xweş xaltîka min. Silavên me ji qeçkê xalên we re
hene...
Have good hours my aunt. We have greetings for the girls of
your uncles...
çavê giya maşallah, heta ciyên gundî yê din, e mîlê holê
hewşê wan e...
all eyes mashallah, up to the places of other villagers,
that side is their yard...
em ê niha leqteyekî serxaniyê wan, gund giyî bigirin.
we will now take a shot of their houses, the whole village.
Erê saet xweş xalê, em leqteyekî j'wan re bikşînin...
Yes have good hours uncle, let's take a shot for them...
ji milet re j'xortan re, bikşîne...
for the people, for the youth, shoot...
Belê gundekî kevnar e, sekne hewşekî gundî ye.
Yes an ancient village, look it's a villager's yard.
Pir kevnar e, hey hewşê axî di vê gundî de hene.
It's very ancient, there are still earth yards in this
village.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Welle sekne gund, bê ber heftiyan e, mogo qey ser bi havînan
e.
By God, look at the village, it's towards the end of the
week, I'd say it's towards the summer.
O qeçkên xalo, gokê dinav xwera dileyzin, ha ray tê...
Oh uncle's girls, playing ball among themselves, oh she's
running...
Erebên me li nav gund ketin...
Our Arabs entered the village...
Çima mentîqa xweş e û kîbar e, sekne...
Why is the area nice and kind, wait...
Cewekî xweş e. Xortên me li maha rê...
It's a nice atmosphere. Our youth are on the road...
Qeçkê xalo, li hewşê xwe sêrkin...
Uncle's girls, look at your yard...
Ev av hemî sa piştê xaniyê wan e. Evna moldetên, evna...
This water is all behind their houses. These are molds,
these...
Welle, ser xanî pir kîbar e... mentîqê ga xaniyê te...
By God, the roof is very nice... the area of your house...
Dinda, lê... dinda erê...
Look, but... look yes...
Avna herdu dar, xaniyê abu lîman e... van darê we çîçak o
sekne.
Those two trees, it's Abu Liman's house... those trees of
yours are full of birds, wait.
Qeçkê xalo, lê sêrkin, van ro bîra min, min hewşa we xwaro
kirine...
Uncle's girls, look at it, today I remembered, I ate your
yard...
Xaltîka, ev çîçakno... çitin ev navê viyatno çine?
Auntie, these birds... what kind of plant is this called?
Bi xwedê ev çîçakê quşte re ye, xwedê zane ev mizerene
navno...
By God these are meat birds, God knows what these are
called...
Welle çi manzar yek xweş û kîbar e... mizerene...
By God what a nice and kind landscape...
Dînik e têne têne... dînik dî, ecêb bûye gelek?
It's crazy, it's coming... you saw the crazy one, was it
very strange?
Dînik dor e ketiye.
The crazy one is spinning around.
Dînik anobe, xweş e nav dîroka xwe qonca xwe da girt...
The crazy one is spinning, it's nice in its history it took
its corner...
Dînik anobe, ev anobe... ev qers in, ne?
The crazy one spinning, this is spinning... these are big,
right?
Ha dînik anobe welle...
Yes the crazy one spinning by God...
Ev anobe jî, wek taniya zeytûnê gers dibe, ne?
This spinning one also, gets big like an olive pit, right?
Eh, wekî e...
Yes, like that...
Lê... wek e gers dibin...
Yes... they get big like that...
Sekne, çi manzarek xweş e...
Wait, what a nice view...
Xortan, rê me herê... O, amî... nêk û bilaxtin hê jêr be,
sewirîna me...
Boys, let's go on our way... Oh, uncle... look and let it be
lower, our reflection...
Xwedê ji we razî be, saetên we xweş...
May God be pleased with you, have good hours...
Xwedê ji te jî razî be... saetên we xweş...
May God be pleased with you too... have good hours...
Wî, înşallah... wakî dibêje...
Him, God willing... as he says...
Saetên we ji we re xêr be... em diçin cîhekî re herin...
May your hours be blessed... we are going somewhere...
Xwedê ji we razî be, Xwedê we neke bin destan...
May God be pleased with you, may God not leave you under
oppression...
Saetên we xêr... ehlen û sehlen... urfên xwe bixwîne...
Blessed hours... welcome... read your traditions...
Saetên we xweş... înşallah...
Have good hours... God willing...
nah, xalû, dibê... gelek her gundekî di dostek, ahbûbekî me
re be...
no, uncle, saying... many every village has a friend, an
acquaintance of ours...
Çêbî... wekî di bî... bi navê xwedê çêbî... he he he...
It happens... as it happens... in the name of God it
happens... he he he...
Xwedê ji we razî be, saetên we xweş, Xwedê we bixefilîne...
May God be pleased with you, have good hours, may God
forgive you...
Yellah, em ê nav gund temam bikin.
Let's go, we will finish the village tour.
Ev dar e, cîhe maddexê avê ye. Lewha şemsiyê reka bandin e
j'miletî gund re avê daxil dikin.
This is a tree, it's the place for water material. They tied
an umbrella board to bring water to the village people.
Saetên we gundiya xweş.
Have good hours villagers.
Teba' ser rûyê. Ev jî makteba vê gundî ye.
Nature is on the face. This is also the school of this
village.
Akîd milet pir hatine vê mektebê xwendî, zikreyatên giyî li
vir in.
Surely many people have come and read in this school, all
memories are here.
Av çend mola navê neçûye?
How many times has water not gone by this name?
Maşallah çi bînek daxm di vir de çêkirine. Xwedê rastî
gundiya bikşîne.
Mashallah what a great breath they have built here. May God
draw the truth of the villagers.