...însan ki mezin... em jî direvin...
...we are adults... we are also fleeing...
Xwedê can ki sax pê dê... [unclear]
May God give a healthy soul... [unclear]
Noka hevalno, li gundê Metîna, emê derbasî mala xalê Yûsiv
Hec Ebdo bin...
Now friends, in Metina village, we will proceed to Uncle
Yusef Hec Ebdo's house...
Ne ka xêr min, noka maqlube ye û kebab e û lehma bi sînî
ye...
Not just that my dear, now it is Maqluba and Kebab and meat
on trays...
...şevî zikê me êşiya...
...at night our stomachs hurt...
Ez maşallah dengê te...
Mashallah your voice...
Teslem.
Thanks.
Ez ji te têr nabim.
I can't get enough of you.
Teslem.
Thanks.
Miro şerefek e însanêkî wek min, evvel emrê xwe, were cem te
rûne.
Man, it is an honor for a person like me, at the beginning
of his life, to come and sit with you.
Barekallah fîk.
God bless you.
Pir însan daxwazin... însanekî wek te rûnin, ji xibra bi
'elimin, ji tecerba bibînin.
Many people want... to sit with a person like you, to learn
from your speech, to see your experience.
Teslem.
Thanks.
Naha jî ez dixwazim tu nasihetekê bi me de... ew hemû miletê
li me seyr dikin... tu kîjan nasihetekê bi me de...
Now I want you to give us a piece of advice... all those
people watching us... give us a piece of advice...
...di rûniştinê da... nasihetekê bi me de, ez piştre wî
nasihetî îstîfade bibînim, ew tikîne nasihetî te bibînin.
...in this sitting... give us a piece of advice, so I can
benefit from that advice later, and they can see your
advice.
Ez pir kêfxweş bûm, saeta te xweş... Xwedê ji te razî be.
I was very happy, thank you... God be pleased with you.
Xwedê ji te razî be, te istiqbalek pir xweş da me.
God be pleased with you, you gave us a very nice reception.
Saxbî... saxbî... Ela eyne... walla ya hela û ya merhabî.
Long live... long live... Welcome... by God, welcome.
Naha jî ez dixwazim tu xaltîkê... dêka Fêras... tu qiçikek
telqînî derva hene... tu kanê silav bikê...
Now I want you to... Auntie... Feras's mother... you have
kids abroad... if you can greet [them]...
Merheba miletê hêja û delal, em hatin bi vîdyoyekî xweş û
vîdyoyekî aceb... vîdyoya me îro li gundê Metîna ye. Silav û
rêz ji şêniyê gundê Metîna ra. Em bi xêr hatin ser qenata
Hatim li Efrîn.
Hello dear and precious people, we came with a nice video
and a wonderful video... our video today is in Metina
village. Greetings and respect to the inhabitants of Metina
village. Welcome to the Hatim channel in Afrin.
Ka naha bi me ra bin, bi dilekî xweş, bi dilekî geş, em
derbasî gundê Metîna bin.
Be with us now, with a happy heart, with a joyful heart,
let's enter Metina village.
Saeta we xweş û bîr nekin me de'm bikin.
Thank you and don't forget to support us.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ya ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Hûn bi xêr hatin bira.
Welcome brother.
Navê te bi xêr xalo?
What is your name uncle?
Navê min Mihemed Mihemed e, bi bernavkê Bavê Azad.
My name is Mohammed Mohammed, nickname Bavê Azad.
Bavê Azad... ser serê min, Xwedê emrê dirêj de Bavê Azad.
Bavê Azad... upon my head (respect)... May God give Bavê
Azad a long life.
Saxbî.
Long live.
Ez Xelîl ji gundê Me'edîna, ji qenata Hatim li Efrîn, îro em
mîvandarê gundê Metîna ne.
I am Xelîl from Me'edîna village, from Hatim channel in
Afrin, today we are guests of Metina village.
Ser serê min... ser herdû çava ye.
Upon my head... upon both eyes.
Çavê te sax bin û serê te sax be Bavê Azad.
May your eyes be healthy and your head be healthy Bavê Azad.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Xwedê ji te razî be. Ser serê min.
God be pleased with you. Upon my head.
Wad'ê te çawa ye? Roja we çawa derbas dibe?
How is your situation? How does your day pass?
Welle... em kar... baş e... nebûye başbûniyek zêde ye bes
yanî...
Well... we work... it's good... there hasn't been much
improvement but...
...gor emr...
...according to age...
Emr diçîne...
Age goes by...
Xwedê emrê dirêj de te, siheta xweş de te.
May God give you a long life, give you good health.
Ê Bavê Azad, em naha... em dixwazin... çîçikek ser gundê
Metîna ji me ra xeber de... em bi hevra nas bikin.
So Bavê Azad, we now... we want... talk to us a little about
Metina village... so we can get to know it together.
Destpêkê, xê nav lê kirin Metîna? Tikîne ji me ra xeber de.
First, who named it Metina? Talk to us a little about this.
Navlêkirin Metîna... bi navê... Çiyayê Metîna...
The naming of Metina... by the name of... Mount Metina...
Çiyayê Metîna li Kurdistanê.
Mount Metina in Kurdistan.
Bi wî navî lêkirin. Û yê lêkirî biddabet navê wî çiye... em
nikanin... em nizanin...
It was named with that name. And the one who named it,
exactly what his name is... we can't... we don't know...
Ez nikanim tehdîd kim, bes nav... bi navê Metîna ye. Çiyayê
Metîna.
I can't specify, but the name... is by the name of Metina.
Mount Metina.
Ê ser wî esasî... bi navê gund bû Metîna.
So on that basis... the name of the village became Metina.
Çiyayê Metîna li Kurdistanê, piştre li navê vê gundî, li ser
wî çiyayî nav kirin.
Mount Metina in Kurdistan, then the name of this village was
named after that mountain.
Gundê Metîna... destpêkê, kîjan malbat hat li vî gundî gund
çêkir? Tikîne ji navê wê malbatê nav de, ew tikîne ji xeber
de, em nas bikin û xelk bi me ra nas bike.
Metina village... in the beginning, which family came and
built the village in this village? Talk to us a little about
the name of that family, talk to us a little about it, so we
can know and the people can know with us.
Temam.
Okay.
Gundê Metîna... bi xwe... bi tenê bû... li vî derî çol bû...
tişt tunebû... belam bûn...
Metina village... itself... was alone... this place was a
wilderness... there was nothing... but there were...
...ya kela'm hebûn... berê, teb'an ev beriya vê bi dused û
bîst û pênc sal... heta dused û çel salî... dused û pêncî
salî va dornê...
...some caves... before, naturally this was before 225
years... to 240 years... 250 years around that...
...li şikeftkê... vî derî jêrî gund, ser rêka şahrê... di wê
derê da bûn Malê Selmo.
...in a cave... here below the village, on the Shara road...
inside that place were the Selmo Family.
Me wa verdigo ten Malê Selmo.
We call them the Selmo Family.
Hewna di wê derê da bûn, paşê jî malbata me jî, Malê Nebê...
hewna jî hatin, tev bûn, ketin, ketin wê şikeftê, li cem
wan.
They were there in that place, then our family too, the Nebo
Family... they also came, were together, fell, fell into
that cave, with them.
Paşê pezê xwe anîn şûna gund... diçêrandin... serkirin...
cîcîkê xwarin da, ciyê gund rinde.
Then they brought their livestock to the village site...
they grazed them... looked... a place for eating, the
village site is good.
Hewna du bira bûn. Selmo û 'Emo bira bûn.
There were two brothers. Selmo and Amo were brothers.
Ma ne du mal ê wan bûn, malek jî ê malbata me, Malê Nebê
verdibên...
Weren't there two houses of theirs, and one house of our
family, called the Nebo Family...
Hatin... sê mal girtin wek mûseles...
They came... they built three houses like a triangle...
...hano... wek sêkûçê...
...here... like a trivet...
Girtin û dora xwe girtin... gî kirin wek... gî kirin hewşek.
Yani sê mal bi hewşekî... gî dumnî hewşekê da.
They built and enclosed their surroundings... made it all
like... made it all a courtyard. Meaning three houses with
one courtyard... all inside the tail of a courtyard.
Û pez û mezê xwe hebû, berdan wî... ortê xwe... û bi tenê
dajiya heryê... ev sê malbatna.
And they had their livestock, they released it... in their
middle... and lived alone in the mud... these three
families.
Paşê gund, ji gund... ji wî gundî hatin... ji mîsalen ji
Sînka hatin... ji...
Then the village, from the village... from that village they
came... for example from Sinka they came... from...
...gundê din hatin... el-muhîm hatin gund temam kirin, mezin
kirin heta noka.
...other villages they came... anyway they came and
completed the village, expanded it until now.
Heya noka gund bi hevra çêkirin û pêkve bûn û xweş û delal
bûn.
Until now the village was built together and were together
and were good and beautiful.
Êwa, biddabet.
Yes, exactly.
Bavê Azad, li gundê Metîna, bîrê avê çend in? Tikîne ji me
ra xeber de.
Bavê Azad, in Metina village, how many water wells are
there? Talk to us a little about it.
Welle bîrê avê... teqrîben yanî... di malan da... zêdeyî çel
bîrî heye.
Well water wells... approximately... inside the houses...
there are more than 40 wells.
Zêdeyî çel bîrî... di malan da. Û derveyî malan jî hene... ê
ji gund ra, gund kamil ra... ew bo 'am, yanî verdibên bîrê
'am...
More than 40 wells... inside the houses. And outside the
houses there are also... for the village, for the whole
village... those are for public, meaning they call them
public wells...
Hewna jî teqrîben... şî deh bîr hene. Yani dor pêncî bîrî
heye di gund da.
There are also approximately... some ten wells. Meaning
around fifty wells exist in the village.
Bavê Azad, li gundê Metîna karebê xwe noka taqa şemsiye yan
karebê dewletê, yê ew giştî ye?
Bavê Azad, in Metina village is your electricity now solar
power or state electricity, the general one?
Noka karebê şîrketê... ji Tirkiyê, şîrketê ye...
Now it is company electricity... from Turkey, it is the
company's...
Şîrketê nîzamî giştî...
The regular general company...
Şîrketê nîzamî giştî. Noka gundê Metîna karebê xwe nîzamî
şîrketê ye.
The regular general company. Now Metina village's
electricity is regular company [electricity].
Karebê xwe nîzamî ye û... û her yekî jî taqe jî heye... bi
nefsil wext, him taqe heye, him jî karebe heye.
Its electricity is regular and... and everyone has solar
energy too... at the same time, both solar exists, and
electricity exists.
Bîst û çar saeta karebe heye?
Is there electricity 24 hours?
Bîst û çar saeta karebe heye nîzamî.
There is regular electricity 24 hours.
Seyda li vî gundî da tune ne? Ê camî...
Are there no Seydas in this village? Uh mosque...
Seyda tune ne...
There are no Seydas...
Ê camî li vî gundî hene Bavê Azad?
Uh are there mosques in this village Bavê Azad?
Camî heye, erê. Camî heye... kevn e... ji teqrîben...
There is a mosque, yes. There is a mosque... it is old...
since approximately...
...heftê û pênc sal hene.
...it's been seventy-five years.
Camî heye, kevn e... heftê û pênc sal hene.
There is a mosque, it is old... it's been seventy-five
years.
Beriya min...
Before me...
...nehatiye girtin.
...it wasn't built.
Emrê min şêst û pênc sal in... hîn nehatiye girtin.
My age is sixty-five years... it still wasn't built.
Ê emrê gundê Metîna çiqas sal e? Dorê çiqas sal... tikîne ji
me ra xeber de.
Uh how many years is the age of Metina village? Around how
many years... talk to us a little about it.
Teqrîben wek miştara gotî, bidaye, wextê hatina gund çêkirin
e...
Approximately as the Mukhtar said, the beginning, the time
of coming to build the village...
...bi dused û bîst û pênc... mabeyna dused û bîst û pênc û
heta dused û çel salî... dused û pêncî salî va dornê.
...by two hundred and twenty five... between two hundred and
twenty five and up to two hundred and forty years... two
hundred and fifty years around that.
Gundê Metîna dorê dused û pêncî salî ye.
Metina village is around two hundred and fifty years old.
Êwa... dused û pêncî sal.
Yes... two hundred and fifty years.
Bavê Azad, gundê Metîna niha bi çi karî mijûl dibin? Yanî çi
kar dikin niha?
Bavê Azad, what work is Metina village busy with now?
Meaning what work do they do now?
Welle niha haliyen karî... karî dikin... ji berê da jî û
noka jî... karê ziraetê ye... bes xeyrî ziraetê tune ye...
çandinî... çandinî.
Well now currently work... they do work... from before and
now too... it is agriculture work... but other than
agriculture there isn't... planting... planting.
Yanî... zeytûn in, bi şeklê 'am.
Meaning... they are olives, generally.
Yanî e tewrî pir zeytûn in.
Meaning the majority are olives.
Û nav ra jî, e hinik û yek erdê xwe bûş hene, deşt in, ew...
zeytûn... genim diçînin... ji... berê ye teb'an.
And among them too, there are some who have abundant land,
fields, they... olives... they plant wheat... from... before
naturally.
No haliyen tatwîr bûye, pêşketiyek çêbûye, em 'elimin
tiştinê nû... mîsalen kizber in... kemûn in, reşreşk in...
tiştê hano... heta 'esfir... ewê zer... ewê dikeve dikeve
şîrva.
Now currently it has developed, a progress has happened, we
learned new things... for example coriander... cumin, black
cumin... things like this... even safflower... the yellow
one... the one that goes into the milk.
Hewna jî wana diçînin. Yanî tiştinê nû çêbûne, berê tune bûn
ew tiştinê cem me.
Here too they plant them. Meaning new things have appeared,
before these things didn't exist with us.
Noha... noha gundê Metîna berê genim û cehê xwe pir
diçandin, niha jî haliyen deşta gundî... kizbera... tiştê
dwanha hîn diçînin, pê ra diçin.
Now... now Metina village before planted lots of their wheat
and barley, now too currently the village plain...
coriander... things like that they still plant, they go with
it.
Diçînin bes ê pir bûn zeytûn... şûnê erdê vala... tev da ê
pir gi bûn zeytûn. Nema... yanî berê nîsk, nok... yanî...
julban... hîç mîşî wana... ti pir bûn.
They plant but the majority became olives... place of empty
land... all together the majority became olives. There isn't
left... meaning before lentils, chickpeas... meaning...
vetch... nothing like them... the majority.
Le'nû gund... ew gund... wek gundê di mintiqê tev da.
Because the village... that village... like villages in the
whole region.
Gi çûna bûn, ew jî teqrîben wena bû. Lê noka hişta çîçike
tatwîr bûye û ê pir jî bûn zeytûn. Nema erdê... sayî... vê
ew... vê dar... nema. Kêm bûn... ê, pirra kêm bûn.
All were going, that too was approximately like that. But
now still a little development has happened and the majority
became olives. No land left... empty... or that... or
trees... none left. They became less... uh, they became very
less.
Gi naha darê zeytûna ye?
Is it all olive trees now?
Gi darê zeytûna ye. Yanî teqrîben gi şî... şûna deh şimlo
nemaye erdê vala.
It is all olive trees. Meaning approximately all not... not
ten shimlo of empty land is left.
Deh da û pênc şimlo.
Ten to five shimlo.
Bavê Azad, gelek spas ji te ra. Saeta te xweş, Xwedê ji te
razî be, Xwedê emrê dirêj û siheta te xweş de te... te emr û
istiqbal kirin, em pir kêfxweş bûn, hûn mîvandarê gundê
Metîna bûn.
Bavê Azad, many thanks to you. Thank you, God be pleased
with you, May God give you long life and good health... you
commanded and welcomed [us], we were very happy, you were
the host of Metina village.
Berî ku ez dest derim, te emrê te... te gotinek te li mahnê
heye?
Before I leave, you your age... do you have a word to say?
Ser sera û ser çava... û wîn hatin vî derî û bi xêr û
silamet... û wîn... yanî em dixwazin... hîn ji vê pê pirtir
hebe ev tiştina, ev me'lûmatana wîn koonin bi xelkî me
gînin, bi 'alemê gînin... nû wad'ê miletê me yê Kurmanc...
nû wad'ê xwe rind in... û... yani... qanûnê xwe bidebrînin.
Upon head and upon eyes... and you came here and with
goodness and safety... and you... meaning we want... still
more than this there be these things, these informations you
can bring to our people, bring to the world... now the
situation of our Kurmanj nation... now their situation is
good... and... meaning... enforce their laws.
Welew çiqas zor hatin ser... çiqas zor hat ser... kanin
sernivo... [xwe ava?] bikin.
Even though no matter how much force came upon... how much
force came upon... they can anew... [rebuild] themselves.
Emê destê xwe bidin yek in... rojê pêşda, hemû bi hev...
We will join our hands together... in the future days, all
together...
Înşallah hemû bidin yek û... û pîroz dikim ji te ra jî vê
qenatê te... yanî tu ew dikî... dimeşînî... yanî wek em
dibîsin... nû... rind e... pir rind e.
God willing all join together and... and I congratulate you
too for this channel of yours... meaning you do that... you
run it... meaning as we hear... now... it is good... very
good.
İnşallah, rojê pêşda hînî xweş û kîbar bibê.
God willing, in the future days it becomes even better and
grander.
Bavê Azad, naha... berî ku ez derim, te qiçik te li derva
hene? Tikîne ji me ra xeber de.
Bavê Azad, now... before I leave, do you have kids abroad?
Talk to us a little about it.
Hîn dost û ehbobê xwe... lê kîme were ber nêgîya selam ke.
Also your friends and loved ones... whoever comes in front
of the camera, say hello.
Ê ehlen we sehlen... Ê me jî û ê Kurdên teva da.
Welcome to you... To ours and to all Kurds.
Ê min jî û ê Kurdên teva da.
Mine and all Kurds.
Yanî em dixwazin yanî hewno bibînin û şkora lê sêr kin...
I mean, we want them to see each other and look at the
screen...
Û kanibin te'lîqatna jî nîn in bişînin.
And if they can, let them send some comments.
Hîn hîn ê çêtr be.
Some [comments] might be better [than others].
Û ê wadê gund zanibin çiye.
And so they know what the situation of the village is.
Û teb'en ji min jî û ji xêrî min jî.
And of course, from me and from others besides me.
Mumkine xêrî min jî kanibe wi şuxlî bike.
It is possible that others besides me can do this work.
Tiştina ji min çêtr hewaldê.
Perhaps conveying things better than I do.
Yanî em dixwazin, aa... vo me'lûmatna bi gîyo gihînin.
I mean, we want to... convey this information to everyone.
Û ê pir jî meselen em qîçkê me lo derin em silav na...
And many too, for example, our kids go out, we send
greetings...
Mekin germ jêr dişînin, jêr dişînin.
Don't send too many [greetings] down to them, down to them.
Û em dixwazin selametîya wan. Eve.
And we wish for their safety. That's it.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Ez pir kêfxweş bûm, her bijî.
Be healthy.
I was very happy, long live.
Ser serê min.
You are welcome [on my head].
Ez nîvandare gundê Metîna bûm, em cem bavê Azad bûn.
I was the guest of Matina village, we were with Azad's
father.
Ser serê min... tita jî û qenata we jî û miletê Kurd tev da.
You are welcome... you, your channel, and the Kurdish people
as a whole.
Saet xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Good times, may God be pleased with you.
Saxbî.
Be healthy.
Bi hevra çêkin seyranê... dawetên mel ser bêderan.
Let's have a picnic together... our weddings are on the
threshing floors.
Bi hevra çêkin seyranê... dawetên mel ser bêderan.
Let's have a picnic together... our weddings are on the
threshing floors.
Li bagên şal û desmala... sergovendî û 'ewîla.
With shawls and handkerchiefs tied... the head of the dance
and the youngsters.
Li bagên şal û desmala... sergovendî û 'ewîla.
With shawls and handkerchiefs tied... the head of the dance
and the youngsters.
Sergovendî û 'ewîla.
The head of the dance and the youngsters.
Dê dîsa rabin werin... em Efrîna xweşê bibînin.
Come on, get up and come again... let's see beautiful Afrin.
Dê dîsa rabin werin...
Come on, get up and come again...
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen bira.
Welcome, brother.
Çawayî baş?
How are you, good?
Xwedê ji te razî be. Navî te bi xêr xalo?
Thank God, good.
May God be pleased with you. What is your name, uncle?
Navê min Nûrî Hesen.
My name is Nuri Hasan.
Xalê Nûrî.
Uncle Nuri.
Bavê Hesen.
Father of Hasan.
Bavê Hesen, Bavê Hesen.
Father of Hasan, Father of Hasan.
Saeta te xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Good times to you, may God be pleased with you.
Saxbî, Xwedê te bihêle.
Be healthy, may God keep you.
Ez pir kêfxweş bûm, ez Xelîl, nîvandarê gundê Metîna me.
I was very happy, I am Khalil, the guest of Matina village.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser çava.
Welcome, upon my eyes.
Alî saet xweş.
Good times to you, Ali.
Bavê Hesen... ez xelîc gundî ba'dînaş, qenaya hatim li
Efrîn.
Father of Hasan... I am a native of a Badinan village, the
channel came to Afrin.
Em îro nîvandarê gundê Metîna bûn. Em kê çiçkê li ser gundê
Metîna bi hevra deyn kin.
Welcome.
Em îro nîvandarê gundê Metîna bûn. Em kê çiçkê li ser gundê
Metîna bi hevra deyn kin.
Today we are guests of Matina village. Let's talk a little
bit about Matina village together.
Mite ser çava.
You are welcome upon my eyes.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Tu roja xwe çawa derbas dikî? Hîn roja xwe çawa di vî gundî
de derbas dikin?
How do you pass your day? How do people spend their day in
this village?
Yanî çi karî pê radibin halîyen niha?
Meaning, what work are they doing right now?
Bixwe karê me î noka... ziraet e.
Personally, our work right now... is agriculture.
Hewşê da.
In the courtyard.
Ziraet jî wekê berê huriye nema, yanî em herin bi kêf...
Agriculture also isn't free [easy] like before, meaning we
go with pleasure...
Nav dara, dar neman.
Among the trees, trees are gone.
Ziraet kêm bû, av tine.
Agriculture has decreased, there is no water.
Ew jî wekê têra xwe pê dikişînim.
Even that, we struggle enough with it.
Wada' çetine.
The situation is difficult.
Ê çetine, em çi doren kin, şuxul tine.
It is difficult.
Yes, it's difficult, what can we do, there is no work.
Hawa vala digerin. Şuxul tine.
We walk around empty [idle]. There is no work.
Û emrê me jî gîhişt şêst... şêst pênc.
And my age has reached sixty... sixty-five.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bide.
May God give you a long life.
Ê şêst pênc.
Yes, sixty-five.
Lê maşalla li te bel na ke xolê min.
But Mashallah, it doesn't show on you, my uncle.
Em hewîl in.
We are young/tough.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Saxbî.
Be healthy.
Bavê Hesen...
Father of Hasan...
Dibê însan di kariyê cefo bike... pişêra dikewe, zû dikeve.
Rast e lê ne rast e?
They say if a person struggles/suffers in work... later they
fall [age quickly], fall early. Is it true or not?
Na, rast e.
No, it is true.
Rast e.
It is true.
Ê teb'en rast e.
Yes, of course it is true.
Û însanê ku di karê cefo jî neke, dibê emrê xwe bi şêst
heftê be lê bel neke.
And a person who doesn't do hard labor, even if their age is
sixty or seventy, it doesn't show.
Lê bel neke, belê.
It doesn't show, yes.
Me bixwe pir ne kir...
Personally, I didn't do much [hard labor]...
Me 'ezê kirin, ta 'emrê xwe da me tît şuxlî we zêde ne kir.
I lived at ease, in my life I didn't do much of that [hard]
work.
Heseb yanî.
It depends, I mean.
Ewîş miç kem cankî me têne.
That's why I look a bit young.
Maşalla li te bel nake, Xwedê emrê dirêj bike.
Mashallah, it doesn't show on you, may God grant you long
life.
Saxbî.
Be healthy.
Ez û Muxtêr cîlê hev in.
The Mukhtar and I are of the same generation.
Aa, hûn bi hevra.
Ah, you are together.
Erê, sinê hev in, cîranê hev in.
Yes, same age, neighbors.
Tu gund va bi hevra xwend lê ne xwend?
Did you study together in the village or not?
Belê.
Yes.
Ew ji min miştehî tir bû.
He was more eager/hardworking than me.
Şatir bû?
Was he clever?
Şatir bû maşalla. Me krtêb bil meqlûb dikir, 'stêz' bil
meqlûb dixwend.
He was clever, Mashallah. We would hold the book upside
down, the "Teacher" would read it upside down.
Genda?
Really?
Erê. Şatir bû.
Yes. He was clever.
Bes temam ne kir zora me.
But he didn't complete it, unfortunately.
Xondin rinda.
Education is good.
Wele me berda... em pir poşman bûn.
By God, we quit... we were very regretful.
Yek bê ewled me...
One of my children...
Yek kurê min bû...
I had one son...
Lo yaram bixwîne. Tim go "Waxer berda".
I told him "Study, my dear." He kept saying "Others quit."
Lo yaram ma berda... em poşman bûn e bixwe hesin.
I said, "My dear, we quit... we were regretful, feel it
yourself."
Wî ber me dan.
He gave up on us.
Ê... û teb'en zirûfê însên jî noka ne wekê berê ye.
Yeah... and of course, a person's circumstances now aren't
like before.
Berê hurîyet bû, em diçûn mektebê, em diçûn şara me dixwend.
Before there was freedom, we went to school, we went to the
city to study.
Î'dadî me li vir xwend, Metîna.
We studied middle school here, in Matina.
Ê paşê jî... senewî, hinek çûn bajar, me berda.
And then... high school, some went to the city, we quit.
Em jî xwendekar çûn ma Heleb, miswal kî bû, xwendime berda.
We students went to Aleppo, there were issues, I quit
studying.
Bavê Hesen heyata berê çîçkê tinebûn bî û cefo bî jî...
Father of Hasan, life in the past was scarce and was a
struggle too...
Ser wê xwendin pir temam ne dikirin.
Because of that, many didn't complete their education.
Bixwedê yekê bixwenda dixwend.
By God, if one wanted to study, they studied.
Noko pismam keyê bê pere bî...
They studied.
Now the cousin [referring to regret]... it was without
money...
Se'î tinebûn bî, cefo pir bî.
It's true there was scarcity, there was much struggle.
Bes heskirin hebî.
But there was love.
Heskirin hebî, tefahum...
There was love, understanding...
Di nav însên da pir bî.
Among people, there was a lot [of it].
Aa, dîsa berê.
Ah, still the past [was better].
Bavê Hesen, wek te jimara gotî, yekê bixwenda ê bixwenda.
Father of Hasan, like you told me, if one wanted to study,
they would study.
Teb'en yekê bixwenda ê bixwenda.
Of course, if one wanted to study, they would study.
Û yêkê naxwenda jî...
And the one who didn't study...
Aa, naxwîne, napêşkeve.
Ah, they don't study, they don't progress.
Em a xwendin bazingê zêrîn e.
But education is a golden bracelet.
Wele bazingê zêrîn e.
By God, it is a golden bracelet.
Xwendin û zanaet bazingê zêrîn e.
Education and craft are a golden bracelet.
Xwendin, xwendin.
Education, education.
Min vî xwend heta Bekelorya, Ma'hed jî xwend...
I studied this until Baccalaureate, I studied Institute
too...
We tuwalêt bî bzare 'e.
And [even] being a toilet cleaner/farmer [is better with
education].
Dîsa elhemdillah ji Xwedê re.
Still, thanks be to God.
No her tiştek hebe çêtir e yanî. Tinebûn ne rinde.
No, having anything is better, really. Having nothing is not
good.
Wele xwendinê te be, mûzarê' be, mehe... bikol, market, bi
çi...
By God, if you have education, be a farmer, monthly
salary... digger, market, whatever...
Xweş e.
It is good.
Bavê Hesen, heyata te berê cafo derbas bî.
Father of Hasan, your life in the past passed with struggle.
Erê berê gîm cefo bî.
Yes, before it was all struggle.
Noha wextê em derbas gindkî dibin, em cem...
Now when we pass through a village, we are with...
Dimezinê me rûdinin, em gil dengê bavu kala dinin.
We sit with our elders, we listen to the voice of the
ancestors.
Hinek dibên heyata te berê cefo bî, xweş bî. Hinek dibên na
nexweş bî, bi ezab derbas bî.
Some say your life in the past was a struggle, [but] good.
Some say no, it was bad, it passed with torture.
Em kê reyî te bibin, çû derbas bî? Ti kînej mara xeber de.
Bi wicûd nezerî te rind bî lê ne rind bî?
Let us get your opinion, how did it pass? Tell us a little.
In your point of view, was it good or not good?
Bixwedê rindbîna we çaxî jî he bî... û rindbîna noka jî he
bî.
By God, there was goodness in that time too... and there is
goodness now too.
Berê cefo hebû, bes tefahum, no...
Before there was struggle, but understanding, in...
Milet da he bî.
Among the people, there was [understanding].
Pêre te hebûn, te ê perê te tinebûn, te ê tine.
If you had money, you had it. If you didn't have money, you
didn't.
Manê we bî ye.
No?
The meaning was like that.
Yanî qîçkikî, tivanî wekî vî, me banî kuro, ban me dikirin,
war her poketkî merû nê dû kûnê, em dibezîn.
Meaning a kid, a youngster like this, we would call "Boy,"
they called us, "Come get a packet [of cigarettes] for this
man," we would run.
E noka tu ban lawê xwa dikî, gol te nake.
But now, you call your own son, he doesn't listen to you.
Noha çîçkê tefahum kêm bî û ihtiram jî û heskirin jî em
kênin bêyn kêm bî li...
Now understanding has decreased a little, and respect and
love, we can say, have decreased in...
Heskirin kêm bî ye, ihtiram kêm bî ye.
Love has decreased, respect has decreased.
Hemû tişt kêm bî ye.
Everything has decreased.
Berê ji noka çêtr bî.
The past was better than now.
Tefahum hebî, ihtiram hebî, însankî mezin jwê da hat, em di
rabûn, me xodê da, yan me diqûl, me nebînî.
There was understanding, there was respect. If an older
person came along, we stood up, we hid ourselves, or we
ducked so he wouldn't see us.
E noka xu 'udkav di me dikin, em jî diravin noka.
But now they act aggressively toward us, so we run away now.
Welle pêşketin çêbî, teknolojî çêbî, bes însanê me hinek
paşde man.
By God, progress happened, technology happened, but our
people fell behind a bit.
Asa dikim şûnde pêketin e, ne pêşketin e.
I feel it is regression, not progress.
Ne pêşketin e?
Not progress?
Na welle, ne pêşketin e, ewa...
No, by God, it is not progress, this...
Kêmanîya 'eqle ewa.
This is a deficiency of the mind.
Yanî vê televizyonê, vê xelewîna, milet pir şûnde xist.
I mean this television, these cellphones, set the people
back a lot.
Se'î tiştna pêşda bir, bes tiştna jî şûnde xist.
True, it moved some things forward, but it set some things
back too.
Erê yanî, nefs el wext, yanî mekanek rohiye.
Yes, exactly, at the same time, meaning a spiritual
mechanism.
Bavê Hesen saeta te xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be, ez pir
kêfxweş bûm.
Father of Hasan, good times to you, may God be pleased with
you, I was very happy.
Îro ez nîvandarê gundê Metîna bûm.
Be healthy.
Today I was the guest of Matina village.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser çava.
Welcome, upon my eyes.
Em Bavê Azad silav dikin, xudanê hewşê, maşalla hewşek kîbar
û delas, silavê me lê heye.
We greet Father of Azad, the owner of the courtyard,
Mashallah a graceful and beautiful courtyard, our greetings
to him.
Saqbî, em silav dikin, saeta te genda xweş, westiya. welek
xweş da me.
Be healthy, we greet him, really good times to you, you got
tired. You gave us a good time.
Mite selam, mite selam.
Peace to you, peace to you.
Silavê min ji hemî... miletê gundê Metîna ra heye.
My greetings go to all... the people of Matina village.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser çava.
Welcome, upon my eyes.
Berî ez rabim Bavê Hesen, te emrê te... te gotin telme hene?
Before I get up, Father of Hasan, your age... do you have
any last words?
Saeta we xweş...
Good times to you...
Û serkeftin ji wera, ez dixwazim vê pirtir pêşda herin
înşalla.
And success to you, I want you to progress more in this,
Inshallah.
Û... ew tişta pir xweş e, ku milet hev bibînin... 'adet û
teqalîd.
And... this thing is very good, that the nation sees each
other... customs and traditions.
Xweş e.
It is good.
Tu qeçka te derva hene, Bavê Hesen? Tu kanî selamê jêr
bişînî.
Do you have children abroad, Father of Hasan? You can send
greetings to them.
Ê welle, noka vyerda ne kir, erê yekî me lê derva.
Yes by God, now... yes I have one abroad.
Xwedê wa bhelê.
May God keep them.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Teb'en silavê me ji...
Be healthy.
Of course our greetings to...
Pismam, metî, me heye, derva giyora dişînin.
We have cousins, aunts, abroad, we send to all of them.
Û Xwedê cankî sag pê dê.
And may God give them a healthy soul.
Bi giyo de, bi hemûwa de.
To everyone, to all of them.
Û em bi wan hene... û ew jî bi me hene.
And we exist through them... and they exist through us.
Saeta te xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Good times to you, may God be pleased with you.
Wextê te xweş, mite selam.
Have a good time, peace to you.
Yarê...
Oh beloved...
Stenbol bûrî...
Istanbul passed...
Pel girt bayî zê...
The leaves caught the wind...
Herdem û...
Every moment and...
Berf li çiya ye...
Snow is on the mountains...
Halê yarê...
The state of the beloved...
Her tu nehatî...
You still haven't come...
Zalim yarê...
Cruel beloved...
Li benda te me...
I am waiting for you...
Her wext û gavê...
Every time and step...
Şev tarî bûn şevê...
The nights became dark nights...
Li min hewar bû.
It was a cry for help to me.
Li min dereng...
To me it's late...
Zalim yarê...
Cruel beloved...
Li benda te me...
I am waiting for you...
Her wext û gavê...
Every time and step...
Şev tarî bûn şevê...
The nights became dark nights...
Li min hewar bû.
It was a cry for help to me.
Li min dereng...
To me it's late...
Şêrîn yarê...
Sweet beloved...
Miletê kîbar û delas, noka hero li gundê Metîna em ê derbasî
malê xalê Yûsif Hec Ebdo bin.
Graceful and beautiful people, now in Matina village we will
enter the house of Uncle Yusuf Haj Abdo.
Baş darva dinêrî, hewşek pir xweşik e. Noka em ê bi hevra
xudanê vê malê nas bikin.
Looking from the outside, it is a very beautiful courtyard.
Now we will get to know the owner of this house together.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Navê te bi xêr?
What is your name?
Elhemdillah... ti çûyî serxatî... navê min... min Fîraz.
Thank God... how are you... my name... I am Firaz.
Dayika Fîraz.
Mother of Firaz.
Wadê te çawa ye? Îşê te çawa ye Dayika Fîraz?
How is your situation? How is your work, Mother of Firaz?
Wadê min elhemdillah... elhemdillah, ji qaçka da û ji giya
da elhemdillah, bes em çîçkê te'bûna, nexweş e.
My situation, thank God... thank God, in legs and
everything, thank God, but we are a little tired, sick.
Rûkê ona yek, ona yê derbas be, elhemdillah.
As long as one's face [honor/appearance] is okay, let it
pass, thank God.
Dîsa gora xelkê dîsa em bi heft ne'metan e, elhemdillah.
Still, compared to other people, we are in seven blessings,
thank God.
Dayika Fîraz, em pir kêfxweş bûn. Huru em nîvandarê gundê
Metîna bûn.
Mother of Firaz, we were very happy. Today we were guests of
Matina village.
Ez Xelîl, ji gundê Ba'dîna, ji qenaya Hatim li Efrîn.
I am Khalil, from Badina village, from the channel "I came
to Afrin".
Hewşê da rabin rûnin.
Let us sit in the courtyard.
Saqbî.
Be healthy.
Navê te çi ye dayê?
What is your name, mother?
Navê min Feyroz e.
My name is Feyroz.
Dayîka Feyroz tu bixwe ji gundê Metîna yî yan te mêr kiriye
gundê Metîna?
Mother Feyroz, are you originally from Metîna village, or
did you marry into Metîna village?
Na, ez bi nefsa xwe ji Efrînê me.
No, I am personally from Afrin.
Çend salin tu li vî gundî rûniştî?
How many years have you lived in this village?
Ê ma ez lê rûneştibûm? Ez li Latqiyê bûm.
Well, had I really lived here? I was in Latakia.
Ebû Firas esker bû.
Abu Firas [her husband] was a soldier.
Paşê em hatin Helebê, ji Helebê, noka di vî herbê da em
livir in.
Then we came to Aleppo, and from Aleppo, now during this
war, we are here.
Di vê çar sala.
In these [last] four years.
Piştî... di vê çar sala nin, tu hatî li gund rûniştî?
After... it's been these four years that you came to live in
the village?
Piştî hewş... hewşa me ya berê, herbê girt.
After the house... our previous house, the war took it.
Di vê çar sala nin tu hatî li gund rûniştî?
Is it within these four years that you came to live in the
village?
Tu rojê xwe çawa derbas dikî?
How do you pass your day?
Weleh, îşta qeçik tên, lawê min lê Efrîn e, liver e, tên
daran... îşta emê wena derbas dikin.
By God, well, the kids come, my son is in Afrin, he is here,
they come around... well, we pass it like that.
Xwedê jêra razî be, Xwedê jêra bihêle.
May God be pleased with them, may God keep them for you.
Rojê, yanî tu tên vê hewşê, vî karî dikin?
During the day, meaning, you come to this courtyard and do
this work?
Belê, rûyê êvarê tê, hevnanoz dikim zotir, ewad (??),
rahiet, gîtên cemaa...
Yes, evening comes, I clean up earlier, [checking] the solar
panels, the battery, all of it together...
Royê nayên, em hindava dibin.
[If] the sun doesn't come [for solar power], we are left
without it.
Belê.
Yes.
Meraqê bînî xwe bi qeçka va dikî?
You satisfy your longing/boredom with the kids?
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Îşta noka kalê min ro bi ro kerr dibe, lê hay ji min nîne
weyê Firas.
Well, now my old man [husband] is getting deaf day by day,
Firas's father is not aware of me anymore.
Darê cem neyê û pîlê cî bişuxulin.
[As long as] the wood is near him and the battery [hearing
aid or radio] is working.
Darê wî hebin, hetanî barî nêt, sabir nake, îşta... erê
weleh, sax be.
If he has his wood [for fire], until it snows, he won't have
patience [he prepares early], well... yes, by God, thank
you.
De heyatê gunda jî hûnê derbas dibe?
Is the village life passing [well] for you?
Erê wele, em ne 'elimî bûn ber behra yarab...
Yes, by God, [though] we weren't used to it, in front of the
sea, oh Lord...
Li Heleb, qeçik li dûr me bûn, der... em hatin vir jî
îşta... awa yek..
In Aleppo, the kids were around us, outside... we came here
too, well... it's the same.
We 'elimî, çunke hewa, bas, baş û xweş e.
You got used to it, because the air/weather, enough, is good
and pleasant.
Lakin... erê, em ne 'elimî ne gund ê, em îjbarî noka derbas
dikin.
But... yes, we aren't used to the village, we are forced to
pass time now.
Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God.
Dîsa gora yê xelkê, dîsa em rind dibînin elhemdulilah.
Still, compared to others, we still see it as good, praise
be to God.
Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God.
Xwarinê berê û yê niha wek hevin?
Is the food of the past and the food of now the same?
So, exlebiyê... yanî, ê şor, şîvê berê pir noka nakin.
So, mostly... meaning, the salty [stews], the dinners of the
past, they don't do much now.
Berê kubik bûn, şorbe bûn, av û bûran bûn...
Before there were Kubeh, soups, stews...
Noka kêm in, noka mexlûbê ne, û...
Now they are less, now it's Maqluba, and...
Kababê...
Kebabs...
Kababê û lehmê bi sêniyê û...
Kebabs and meat in trays [Siniyah] and...
Şewî... şewî zota qeçkê me rehet qelbê xwe av û puxarê
çêkirine, me 'eyşewî.
Grilling... grilling, since my kids have made the water
[pipes] and steam [heating] for their own comfort, [we
represent] living together.
Erê wele.
Yes, by God.
Xwedê jêra razî be, emê niha hewşê jî bişewirînin, gelekî
xweşik e cem te tenê.
May God be pleased with them, we will film the courtyard now
too, it is very beautiful at your place.
Sax be... no, no, adî.
Thank you... no, no, it's ordinary.
Xasiyê wer têda rûnin jî mişkîla.
Sitting in such a nice property is also a problem/challenge.
Ne xasiyet e.
It's not that nice.
Xwedê jêra razî be.
May God be pleased with them.
Ez gundî be'dî name...
I don't pay attention to the village...
Sax be.
Thank you.
Xaltîkê bikim ji we ra...
Let me make [tea/coffee] for you as an auntie...
Berî ku te dest bi karê xwe kir, te dixwast tu silava li kî
bikî? Te gotin te hene?
Before you started your work, who did you want to greet? You
had some sayings?
Wele sihet û tebatya xweş ji we ra.
By God, good health and stability to you all.
Xwedê jêra razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Te emrê me tenê, emrê emrê xwedê ye, xwedê we bêle,
bixefirîne ya reb.
You [asked about] our age only, age belongs to God, may God
keep you and protect you, oh Lord.
Amîn ya reb.
Amen, oh Lord.
Emê vê xeleqê, înşallah nêzîk da emê daxin ser qenayê Hatim
le Efrîn, tu mişkîla cem te hene?
We will upload this episode, God willing soon, on the
channel "Hatim in Afrin", do you have any problem with that?
No wela, elhemdulilah.
No, by God, praise be to God.
Xwedê jêra razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Tu silava li zarokê xwe nakî yên derveyî welat?
Won't you greet your children who are outside the country?
Silamê mi ji Hemûdê lawê mi re li Emêrîka, xwedê bêle ew û
qeçkê gindê.
My greetings to Hammoudi, my son in America, may God keep
him and the village kids.
Û qeçka giya ez maç dikim, xwedê bixefirînin, û qîza mi jî
li wera, bes çiçke, her yek li wîlayetekê.
And I kiss all the children, may God protect them, and my
daughters are there too, but what to do, each one is in a
[different] state.
Yek Şîkago, yek jî Kintakî ye.
One is in Chicago, and one is in Kentucky.
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê bixefirînin û bêlin, înşallah êkê werê cem ziyara, û
nê werin dîsa bisawirin înşallah.
May God protect and keep them, God willing one will come for
a visit, and they will come to film again, God willing.
Înşallah.
God willing.
Bes ku hat, emê werin, emê bisawirin.
As soon as they come, we will come, we will film.
Înşallah, înşallah, êkê werê vir înşallah.
God willing, God willing, one will come here, God willing.
Bê eydê ya eydê.
Before the feast [Eid] or during the feast.
Xwedê jêra razî be, sax be.
May God be pleased with you, thank you.
Xwedê we jî bêle ya reb.
May God keep you too, oh Lord.
[Music starts playing]
Emrê borî...
The life passed...
Şerîn yarê...
Sweet love...
Bejna te zrav e...
Your waist is slim...
Bê ciwahr e...
Without a place/home...
Li min kûr tê...
It affects me deeply...
Kul û xem e...
Pain and sadness...
Her sîn e hatî...
Every grief has come...
Zalim yarê...
Cruel love...
Çavê min rê...
My eyes are on the road...
Te bu yarê...
You became the lover...
Ber evîna te...
Because of your love...
Melûl im yarê...
I am miserable, love...
Bê hal im yarê...
I am helpless, love...
Ehlên we sehlên, ya hela we ya merhabî, newartû.
Welcome and greetings, oh hello and hello, you have lit up
[the place].
Xwedê jêra razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Sax be.
Thank you.
Navê min Xelîl, ez gundî Ba'dîna me, ji qenaya Hatim li
Efrîn.
My name is Khalil, I am from the village of Ba'dina, from
the channel "Hatim in Afrin".
Eywe, ne'em wela, hûn jî û qenaya we jî sed ehla we sehla.
Yes, yes indeed, you and your channel are a hundred times
welcome.
Xwedê jêra razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Û ez jî Yûsif Ebdo, ji Metîna me, Ebû Firas.
And I am Yousef Abdo, from Metîna, Abu Firas.
Xwedê jêra razî be, emrê dirêj te dî.
May God be pleased with you, may you see a long life.
Sax be, 'ela eynî wela.
Thank you, upon my eye [you are welcome], by God.
Bavê Firas, bi xwedê em îro mêvanê gundî Metîna bûn, û me
tebîeta gund teswîr kir.
Father of Firas, by God, today we were guests of Metîna
village, and we filmed the nature of the village.
Me şînî gund ra çiqas dastan. Em derbas bûn hewşek pirr
xweşikî bar medî, me got emê derbas bin.
We saw how beautiful the greenery of the village was. We
passed by a very beautiful, grand courtyard, and we said we
would enter.
Tislem.
May you be safe [Thank you].
Û em hatin, ba'dê ku hewş çiqas kîbar e, hîngirê hewşê jî,
maşallah, pir kîbar derket.
And we came, and [we saw] just as the courtyard is grand,
the owner of the courtyard, Mashallah, turned out to be very
grand/noble too.
Tislem, hada min lutfek.
Thank you, this is from your kindness.
Xwedê jêra razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Me got emê derbas bin, germ istiqbal kirin, emê teswîrek
xweşikî kîbar di hewşê de çêkin.
Thank you.
Me got emê derbas bin, germ istiqbal kirin, emê teswîrek
xweşikî kîbar di hewşê de çêkin.
We said we would enter, you welcomed us warmly, we will make
a beautiful, grand video in the courtyard.
Mît ehla we sehla.
A hundred times welcome.
Piştî em hatin, em cem dayîka Feyroz rûniştin, xwedê emrê
dirêj bide, çiqas te'ban bî jî, me çend gotin kirin.
After we came, we sat with Mother Feyroz, may God give her a
long life, even though she was tired, we had a few words.
Sax be.
Thank you.
Xwedê jêra razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Bavê Firas, tu bixwe ji gundê Metîna ye.
Father of Firas, you are personally from Metîna village.
Erê.
Yes.
Wele, em... tewaludê me, tewaludê gunda.
By God, we... our birth, is the birth of the village.
Ê.
Yeah.
Di sala hezar nehesed û pêncî û sîsya da tewaludê min.
My birth was in the year one thousand nine hundred and
fifty-three [1953].
Em li viderê welidîn.
We were born right here.
Aha.
Û me li viderê xwand, hetanî nîma kefa'a (Brevet) a bir...
And we studied here, until half of the Brevet [middle school
diploma]...
Paşê em çûn Efrîn.
Then we went to Afrin.
Ji Efrîn jî, bi hesbê wezîfê, em çûn Latqiyê.
From Afrin, due to the job, we went to Latakia.
Me heyata xwe sî salî jî li Latqiyê derbas kir.
We spent thirty years of our life in Latakia.
Paşê em hatin Heleb.
Then we came to Aleppo.
Wekî daw û pênc sala, bîst sala em li Heleb bûn.
Like fifteen years, twenty years we were in Aleppo.
Bû mişkîla Sûriyê bû.
The Syrian problem happened.
Em hatin, serniba, gundê xwe, Mesqet Rasna.
We came, finally, to our village, our birthplace.
Erê.
Yes.
Ji gundî mera û ji mesqet rasî mera rintir tinne.
There is nothing better for us than our village and our
birthplace.
Erê.
Yes.
Û em noka haliyen, li viderê teqayîşin.
And we are now currently, retired here.
Şêr...
[Pause/Filler]...
Û elhemdulilah, elhemdulilah. Şêr.
And praise be to God, praise be to God. [Pause].
Axê welat şirîn e, na Bavê Firas?
The soil of the homeland is sweet, isn't it Father of Firas?
Wela, Welat bixwe, el 'erd... yanî 'erd ji şeref e.
By God, the Homeland itself, the land... meaning land is
honor.
Erê.
Yes.
'Erdî mera, şerefê mera ye.
Our land is our honor.
Merî 'erdê xwe tinne, qusîra efke, yanî... hew jî tinne.
If a person doesn't have their land, excuse the expression,
meaning... they don't have that [honor] either.
Hew jî tinne.
They don't have that either.
Îzen, el... el-welat û şeref yek e.
Therefore, the... the homeland and honor are one.
Yek e.
One.
It is one.
Û her însanek, gî heniyê xwe li ser welatê xwe tinnebe...
And any human, if they don't have affection for their
country...
Û heniyê xwe li ser lixetê xwe tinnebe...
And if they don't have affection for their language...
Şêr?
Mhm.
You see?
Yanî, ez dibêm, Xwedê xêrî neqawe doun tinê.
Meaning, I say, God won't put goodness in them.
Tew tinê.
Not at all.
Însan, el-welat, û lixetê mera, foq... kul şî ye.
[For] a human, the homeland, and our language, are above...
everything.
Em perwerê miletê xwe bin, em perwerê axê xwe bin.
Let us be devoted to our people, let us be devoted to our
soil.
Kurmanc, şe'bekî musalim e.
Kurds are a peaceful people.
Mhm.
Şe'bekî sadiq.
An honest people.
Îza daqê me bi yekî ra gû merheba, em ji qelb û rebê xwe da
vêrdibin merheba.
If our path crosses with someone and we say hello, we
deliver that hello from our heart and soul.
Merhebiya me ji dil da ye.
Our hello is from the heart.
Dil da ye.
From the heart.
Şêr, ne mesalih.
You see, not for interests.
Ne menfiet e.
Not for benefit.
Teniyan, em hingî 'el-fitra, û bi qelbî pak...
Secondly, because we are [acting] on instinct/nature, and
with a pure heart...
Em bi hevalê xora û bi 'alemê ra didin distînin, tim me
istixlal dikin.
When we deal with our friends and with the world, they
always exploit us.
Erê.
Yes.
Va... em... va 'atifya me, va hezkirinê me, va ixlasê me...
This... we... this emotion of ours, this love of ours, this
sincerity of ours...
Hinek hene me istixlal dikin.
There are some who exploit us.
Bi 'atifyê me istixlal dikin.
They exploit us through our emotion.
'Atifiya cem me pirr e, em însanek...
The emotion in us is abundant, we are a human...
Em însanek xerîb bibînin, em hnîn 'elê.
If we see a stranger, we are compassionate towards him.
Û qusîra efke, yanî em werin tarîxê, tarîxê...
And excuse the expression, meaning if we come to history,
history...
Çiqas hadarat hene, qeblel mîlad, noka hadarat...
How many civilizations there are, BC [Before Christ], now
civilizations...
Wan rono li Misrê ma hadaya... el-hadarat, noka haliyen gî
hadarat, Kurmanc in.
Those lights in Egypt [referring to civilization], whatever
that is... the civilizations, currently all civilizations,
are Kurds.
Kurmanca hadar çêkir.
Kurds created civilization.
Şêr?
You see?
Yanî gita hadaratê Kurmanca, di rasekê û derbekê...
Meaning all the civilizations of the Kurds, in a heading and
a path...
Yanî teqrîben, em şe'bekî... ewel hadarat em in.
Meaning approximately, we are a people... the first
civilizations are us.
Em pêşketî ne.
We are advanced/pioneers.
Şêr?
You see?
Înşallah Bavê Firas, gam dest bidin yek in, ê biftile, na
ftile?
God willing, Father of Firas, when we join hands, it will
turn [change], won't it turn?
Teben, noka haliyen, seket terîx çûna fitilî.
Of course, now currently, look at how history turned.
Le innî el-heq...
Because the truth...
Êkê îlla daîmen intisar be 'elel batîl.
One [truth] must always triumph over falsehood.
Seke noka çû bû.
Look at how it has become now.
Yanî qusîra efke, şe'bê Kurdî, rebbil 'alemîn ji jor da, û
taniyen 'alemê xerbî...
Yes.
Yanî qusîra efke, şe'bê Kurdî, rebbil 'alemîn ji jor da, û
taniyen 'alemê xerbî...
Meaning excuse the expression, the Kurdish people, [by] the
Lord of the Worlds from above, and secondly the Western
world...
Gîya seker innî heva şe'bekî muxlis, şe'bekî zana.
All of them saw that this is a sincere people, a
knowledgeable people.
Em joker in, joker. Joker... dikuderê ke dimeşe.
We are jokers [versatile/universal], jokers. A joker...
wherever you put it, it works.
Erê.
Yes.
Em jî şe'bekî 'eyne joker e.
We are also a people just like a joker.
'Elmanî, museqef, siyasi, dînî, em gî...
[We are] German [industrious/capable], educated, political,
religious, we are all [of that]...
Bes, em tên mustesmer kirin, istismar dikin...
But, we are getting exploited, they exploit [us]...
Û em tedhiyatê çêdikin fî sebîl innî hev welata, hev
welata...
And we make sacrifices for the sake that this country, this
country...
Wek 'alemê bipêş da keve...
Moves forward like the [rest of the] world...
Wek 'alemê rojava.
Like the Western world.
Wekî te dibê, em em jî 'elmanî bûn, em kê min.
Like you say, we were also Germans [industrious/advanced],
are we any less?
Nexşo sehih.
Correct blueprint/map [Exactly].
Bitûlatê me bûn, terîx ê me, hadarat ê me ne.
We had heroism, our history, our civilizations.
Şêr, û em hatin, ya exî...
You see, and we came, oh brother...
We netemenna...
And we hope...
Şêr, înşallah...
You see, God willing...
Yanî hev welata, êkê pir pêşda here.
Meaning this country, it will go very far forward.
Bavê Fêraz, ez maşallah te dibînim, te sihet xweş e.
Bavê Fêraz, mashallah I see you, your health is good.
Tislam, ya rebbî.
Bless you, oh Lord.
Ez ji te ra spas dikim.
I thank you.
Miro, şerefek e mirovekî gicuwakî (ciwanekî) wek min, evvel
emrê xwe were cem te rûnê.
Man, it is an honor for a young person like me, at the
beginning of his life, to come and sit with you.
Barekellah bîk.
May God bless you.
Pir însan dixwazin, însanê gicuwak (ciwan) te ra rûnin, ji
xebera we bielimin, ji tecerûbên we bibin.
Many people want young people to sit with you, to learn from
your words, and to gain from your experiences.
E naha ji te dixwazim tu ji nesihetekê ji me de.
And now I want you to give us a piece of advice.
Ew hemû miletê me seyr dike, tu karî nesihetekê ji me de?
All our people are watching, can you give us some advice?
Di rûniştinê da, em nesihetekê ji me de, ez pişê nesihetê
îstîfade bibim, ew tikanê nesihetekê li min bike, biheys ez
şînî li wek te bim.
In this gathering, give us advice so I can benefit from it
later, something that will impact me so I can become like
you.
Xweş e. Naka (niha) binisbet qîçik (keçik).
Good. Now regarding the girl (daughter).
Ehem.
Ahem.
Qîçik mirat, dê û bavê xwe ye li nav rûna.
The girl is the mirror of her parents among the people.
Mirat e. Eynik e.
She is a mirror. She is a looking glass.
Naka (niha) fî hal ku te herrekî der ke, qîçikek herrekî der
ke...
Now, in the case that you make a move, if a girl makes a
move...
û deng ke, ef'ala bike, şayif? Meqabîlî yê din, meqabîlî yê
din lê dinêrî.
And makes a sound, acts out, you see? The person opposite,
the person opposite is looking at her.
Dibê haf (ev) qîçika, mektebê vî qîçikî, mektebê ji xaricî
ye, mektebeke selîm e.
He says this girl, the school of this girl, the school from
the outside, is a sound school.
Ehem.
Ahem.
Mektebeke însan, edeb, exlaq, hinî ye...
It is a school of humanity, politeness, morality,
tenderness...
Te mektebê xwe, yanî telîmatê dê û bavê te, tî terh dike ji
alemi ra.
Your school, meaning the teachings of your parents, you
present/project them to the world.
Naka qîçik bi xwe, eynika dê û bavê xwe ye.
Now the girl herself is the mirror of her parents.
Qîçikî fehman, qîçikî zana, qîçikî ademî, xelûq, însanî...
An understanding girl, a wise girl, a decent, moral, human
girl...
Îzen maneta, mektebê vî qîçikî, dê û bavê vî qîçikî, tedhîye
kirine heta haf qîçika gihandine.
Therefore it means, the school of this girl, the parents of
this girl, have sacrificed until they raised this girl.
"Men cedde, wecede." Ereb we dibê.
"He who strives, finds." As the Arabs say.
"Men zera'e, hesede."
"He who plants, harvests."
Gava te di va qîçikê ra rehet bû, teb xwendinê da, terbiyeyê
da ye, edeb da ye, exlaq da ye, însanet da ye...
When you worked hard for this girl, gave her education, gave
her upbringing, gave her politeness, gave her morals, gave
her humanity...
Haf qîçika dibê kan ji te ra.
This girl becomes a treasure for you.
Û Xwedê neke, meselen însan in heye, li qîçikê xwe, ewnake,
tedhîye nake.
And God forbid, for example, there are people who, for their
girl, do not... do not sacrifice.
Haf qîçikana, meselen, wis, yalla şari'.
These girls, for example, just go, straight to the street.
Qîçikî li şari'ê mezin bû, êkê çi însan leqî ye?
A girl raised on the street, what kind of human will she
meet?
Êkê çi xizmet ji milet û ji wetenê xwe ra bike?
What service will she do for her nation and her homeland?
Le enî li şari'ê mezin bûye.
Because she was raised on the street.
Haf qîçika faşil e.
This girl is a failure.
Dibê li mal û xêr li ehlu, mal û xêr li nas.
She becomes of no good to her family, of no good to the
people.
Felîzalîk, qîçik, nesihet inî meselen, ya axî, gava te da
xwest eyî xelet bikî, li ser dê û bavê te tê hesîb.
Therefore, the girl, the advice is, for example, brother,
whenever you want to do anything wrong, it is counted
against your parents.
Yanî gava qîçikek şaşbînekê bike, ji dê û bavê xwe ra dike.
Gerek dê û bav destpêkê qîçikê xwe bi elimînin terbiye û
edebê.
Meaning when a girl makes a mistake, she does it to her
parents. Parents must first teach their girl upbringing and
manners.
Lekan, naka ta'a... xêra dibê "El walîdên".
Of course, now obedience... the good refers to "The
Parents".
Ta'eta walîdên, min ta'eta Rebbûl 'alemîn e.
Obedience to parents is part of obedience to the Lord of the
Worlds.
Xêr we dibê? Le enî dê û bavê te rehet dibin.
Why is it good? Because your parents suffer (work hard).
Dê û bavê te esasê malê ne.
Your parents are the foundation of the home.
Esas e. Mekteb e.
They are the foundation. The school.
Mekteb e.
The school.
Felîzalîk da xwest haf mekteba selîm be, haf qîçikoke selîm
derkeve.
Therefore, if this school is sound, this girl will come out
sound.
Nadic (netîce) derkeve. Êkê haf însanoke, întacê bi milet de
û bi wetenê xwe de, bi erdê xwe de.
A result will come out. This person will provide output
(production) to the nation, to their homeland, to their
land.
Emman da xwest gava te terbiyeyê te nebe, elim te nebe,
însanliqa te cem te nebe, tiştek te nebe...
But if you have no upbringing, no knowledge, no humanity
within you, nothing in you...
Ne weled zane, ne luget zane, ne tiştekî nizane.
She doesn't know the child (implying manners), doesn't know
language, doesn't know anything.
Xêr e? Le enî li şari'ê mezin bûye. Vî qîçikê ezyet nedî ye.
Why? Because she was raised on the street. This girl has not
seen hardship (effort meant for raising her).
Yanî, nesihetê min, ku tu we la xêrî te, wîn mirat in ji dê
û bavê xwe ra.
So, my advice, whether you or others, you are mirrors for
your parents.
Gava te da xwest îcabî be ji milet ra, bikûn dê û bavê te
ezyet li te dîne heta te gihandine vê mertebê.
If you want to be positive for the nation, it means your
parents have put effort into you until they brought you to
this level.
Wê maneyê Rebbûl 'alemîn mera digota "Rîdal-lah we rîdal-
walîdên."
In that meaning, the Lord of the Worlds told us, "The
satisfaction of God is in the satisfaction of the parents."
Lekan, lekan, lekan.
Of course, of course, of course.
Eger di mezinê xwe ji ihtîram neke, eger di mezinê xwe tune
hew ji tune.
If one does not respect their elders... if one does not have
elders, they have nothing.
Îhtîram cebde (cebda) tune. Û gava însan ji ihtîram cem tune
be, teqadîr tune bin...
There is absolutely no respect. And when a human has no
respect in them, no appreciation...
Felîzalîk, hew însana, wucûdê wî yê însanî heram e. 'Ib e,
'ib e lel mûcteme'.
Therefore, those people, their human existence is forbidden.
It is a burden, a burden on society.
Yanî serê marê kê...
Meaning the head of the snake...
Vêra dêşe.
Hurts for it.
Noko (niha) însanî, qîçikî faşil, me'a îhtîramî îlek...
Now a human, a failed girl, with my respect to you...
Cîran, xaret, alem, gî, vêra serê xwe dêşe.
Neighbors, the district, the people, everyone, gets a
headache because of her.
Û însanî, însanî, ademî, xelûq, muhezzeb, muntec...
But the human, the person, the decent, moral, polite,
productive one...
Ji xara û ji xudanê xara. Û ji milet ra.
Is for herself and for her owners (parents). And for the
nation.
Wê maneyê Bavê Fêraz, şîret te pir xweş in maşallah. Ez pir
kêfxweş bûm.
In that sense, Bavê Fêraz, your advice is very beautiful,
mashallah. I was very pleased.
Û şerefek e ku ez însanekî wek min, evvel emrê xwe, digihîje
gidhî însanê wek te rûnin û nas kin.
And it is an honor that a person like me, at the beginning
of his life, manages to sit with and know a person like you.
We ez jî dixwazim hemû miletê me hev nas kin, em bi hev ra
nas kin.
And I also want all our nation to know each other, for us to
know each other.
Wê maneyê şûrek me kîderê cîhanê hebe, dibê qîçik bajarokî
xwe ra bike, û qîçik bajarokî çê bike.
In that sense, wherever our roots are in the world, the girl
must act for her town, and make the girl of the town good.
Tebe'an. Lekan, lekan, lekan.
Naturally. Of course, of course, of course.
Naka mirov, gava di nav mûcteme'a xwe da nebe...
Now a person, when they are not within their society...
Gava tu bi miletê xwe ra nebe, wucûdê te sifir e.
When you are not with your nation, your existence is zero.
Însan qîmetê xwe di mûcteme'ê da ye.
A human's value is in the society.
Qîmetê xwe di alemê da ye.
Their value is among the people.
Gava te xwe îne'zal kir, tu tenê ma, tu bû sifir.
When you isolate yourself, and stay alone, you become zero.
Malê gindir û însanliqê gindir, di nav mûcteme' da heta hew
aîla serê xwe ra dike...
The rolling wealth and the rolling humanity, within the
society, until that family raises its head...
Dibê heva xelfê min e. Heva netîcê te'bê min e.
They say this is my descendant. This is the result of my
toil.
Afa întacê min e.
This is my production.
Întacê min e.
It is my production.
Bavê Fêraz, ez pir kêfxweş bûm.
Bavê Fêraz, I was very pleased.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
Be healthy.
May God be pleased with you.
'Ela êynî, wellahî.
You are welcome, by God.
Xwedê ji te razî be, te istiqbalek pir xweş da me.
May God be pleased with you, you gave us a very nice
reception.
Naha jî ez dixwazim tu xaltîkê... dêka Fêraz...
And now I want you [to ask] Auntie... Fêraz's mother...
Tu qîçikê te li kîderê hene, niha tu kenê (kanê) silav ke.
Wherever you have daughters, you can greet them now.
Ê nît, ehle we sehle.
Yes, one hundred welcomes.
Îmta seyr kin, pir kêfxweş bin, niha jî tî qîçika ji me ra
silav ke.
When they watch, they will be very happy, now greet the
girls for us.
Ehle we sehle.
Welcome.
Na silavê te yê qîçka ra bişîne.
No, send your greetings to the girls.
E, wella lawikê min li Emerîka ye.
Eh, well my boy (son) is in America.
We qîzik li Emerîka ye.
And the girl is in America.
Em dixwazin şte (ji te) silavê me bi qîçikê me gînin.
We want you to convey our greetings to our children (girls).
Û Xwedê selametiye bi wa de, û bi wan de, û bisitirin.
And may God give them safety, and to them, and protect them.
Û heyat seîdê be.
And may it be a happy life.
Û Xwedê bisitirînin ya Reb.
And may God protect them, oh Lord.
Ne tebeh ne wekewî gotî...
Not merely as he said...
Dengê me pê gine (bigihîne).
Convey our voice to them.
Û înşalla 'en qerîb em bi hev de gînin.
And God willing, soon we will reach each other.
We heva hevdu jî bibînin. Şayif?
And see each other like this. You see?
Û mît ehle we sehle, û se'eta we xweş û serkeftin be.
And a hundred welcomes, and have a good time and success.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Sax be.
Be healthy.
Tu emrê te?
Do you have any command (request)?
Ti gotinê te li me hene berî ku em xilaz kin?
Do you have any words for us before we finish?
Wella, em dixwazin cuhûdê we, şte (tiştek) hana zêde be.
Well, we want your efforts, things like this to increase.
Emê berdewam kin înşalla.
We will continue, God willing.
Sax be. Û em dixwazin hanakî wî li nav milet bigerin.
Be healthy. And we want ones like this to circulate among
the nation.
Şayif? Yanî qusira ef ke, dibê tiril tiril dinêre, reş dibe.
You see? Meaning, excuse me, if you look at the grapes
(idiom), they turn black (ripen/imitate each other).
Felîzalîk, meselen, emê meselen, fi'lekî îcabî ji wa bibin.
Therefore, for example, we will take a positive action from
them.
Wînê ji me bibin. Felîzalîk emê bi qomê îcabî kevin.
You will take from us. Therefore, we will fall into a
positive group.
Seh.
Correct.
Xweş e.
Good.
Naka meselen, te ji me mimkin îcabîyatan bibîn.
Now for example, you might take positives from us.
Lê gava tu nehatiba cem min, îcabîyatê min kî zikî (ji kî)
bidaba? Ne we?
But if you hadn't come to me, to whom would I give my
positives? Is it not so?
Erê.
Yes.
Û ez jî ji te elimîm, tu jî ji min elimî.
And I learned from you, and you learned from me.
Û înşalla emê serkeftin bin.
And God willing we will be successful.
Înşalla.
God willing.
Bavê Fêraz, ez pir kêfxweş bûm.
Bavê Fêraz, I was very pleased.
Sax be, sax be. 'Ela êynî wellahî, ya hela we ya merhabî.
Be healthy, be healthy. You are welcome by God, oh hello and
oh welcome.
Xwedê ji te razî be, te îstîqbalek pir xweş da me.
May God be pleased with you, you gave us a very nice
reception.
Naha jî ez dixwazim tu û xaltîkê... dêka Fêraz...
And now I want you and Auntie... Fêraz's mother...
Ta (da) qîçikê te li kî der ve hene sê (tu kanê) silav ke.
So wherever your daughters are, you can greet them.
Ê nît, ehle we sehle.
Yes, one hundred welcomes.
Îmta seyr kin, pir kêfxweş bin. Naha jî tî qîçika ji me ra
silav ke.
When they watch, they will be very happy. Now greet the
girls for us.
Ehle we sehle.
Welcome.
Na, silavê te yê qîçka ra bişîne.
No, send your greetings to the girls.
Wexta tu çû, diyamın.
When you left, my mother.
Diyamın, diyamın, diyamın î.
My mother, my mother, you are my mother.
Tu roniya dilê min î.
You are the light of my heart.
Tu dermanê êşê min î.
You are the cure for my pain.
Êş ketiye canê min î.
Pain has fallen into my soul.
Dewer, canê min, dewer.
Come back, my soul, come back.
Dewer, derdê min giran e.
Come back, my grief is heavy.
Ez qediyamim, ez qediyamim.
I am finished, I am finished.
Dewer, bîna te mîna gulan.
Come back, your scent is like roses.
Diyamın, diyamın, diyamın î.
My mother, my mother, you are my mother.
Tu roniya çavê min, diyamın.
You are the light of my eyes, my mother.
Diyamın, diyamın, diyamın î.
My mother, my mother, you are my mother.
Miletê kîbar û delal, saeta we xweş.
Noble and dear nation, have a good time.
Hûn bi me ra bûn heta dawiya vîdyo.
You were with us until the end of the video.
Em mêvanê Gundê Metîna bûn.
We were guests of Matina Village.
Silavê me ji we ra hene, hûn bi xêr hatin ser qenata Hatim
la Efrîn.
Our greetings to you, welcome to the channel Hatim la Afrin.
Heta goka nî (gawek din) derketa na, me ji we ra derxist.
Until another time appeared, we brought this out for you.
Saeta şînî gundê Metîna xweş.
A good time to the residents of Matina Village.
Îstîqbalek pir xweş û kîbar û delal dan me.
They gave us a very nice, noble, and dear reception.
Li hêviya me bin, vîdyokî acer (nû).
Wait for us, for a new video.
Û bîr nekin me da'em (piştgirî) kin.
And don't forget to support us.
Emê bi da'ema we serkevin.
We will succeed with your support.
Ez Xelîl, ji qenata Hatim la Efrîn.
I am Khalil, from the channel Hatim la Afrin.