Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Host: Welcome, a hundred times welcome.
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Woman 1: Welcome.
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Host: How are you? Are you well?
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Woman 1: Praise be to God, praise be to God, God willing it
is good, praise be to God.
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Host: How old are you, Aunt Fat?
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Woman 1: I am eighty-five. Eighty-five exactly, maybe even
up to sixty-something (referring to birth year or decade).
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Host: May God give you a long life and give you good health.
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Woman 1: Be healthy, be healthy, may you also see happiness.
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Host: We want to... since you have come to the best...
spending a very nice [time], back in the day with our
elders, things that fall, things that they gather in
heritage, they bring up examples.
Host: Gotinekî biçûk mera ser berê xeber de. Ser canliqê xwe
da weçqa ceafata.
Host: Tell us a small word about the past. About your
vitality and the time of hardship.
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: Welcome, to you, and to this gathering of ours.
Woman 1: We are mostly the House of Haji, we are settled
inhabitants. We are happy.
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: In the past there was poverty, and in the past
there was destitution, and in the past we raised children.
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: There was poverty, great poverty. We saw poverty,
we raised children.
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: Praise be to God for this day. Praise be to God for
this day.
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: My husband went to the mercy of God (died), I put
my two hands together (I worked doubly hard).
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: I drew water for...
Woman 1: At Ali Bakri Ali the tyrant's place, he became a
landlord/wealthy.
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: We had no water. We had no cisterns.
Woman 1: I carried water home, I dedicated myself to the
service of my children.
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: I used to do my work with it.
Woman 1: There was no water, later on we dug our own
cisterns, we had water, praise be to God.
Woman 1: Me qaçikê xwe mezin kirin. Û e barê şita...
Woman 1: We raised our children. And regarding that thing...
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: And regarding that load, I carried it.
Woman 1: I made rosary beads. I made a lot of rosary beads.
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: I would pick my seeds/grapes, I would select
them...
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: I would put the dye/paste on them, select them.
Woman 1: And uh... it would go... I would clean/rub them,
the birûş (beads).
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: I would coat/glaze them... Coat them with liquid...
Woman 1: Like the glazing syrup, it would settle.
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: We would empty it into basins, and stir our starch
and our things into it.
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: We would make the pelûl (coating paste).
Woman 1: We would crack our walnuts with it (make a living).
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: Those who wandered for labor.
Woman 1: We made our beads. We would give it a long
wander/process.
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: There were four kids, five kids, they would pull
(help/work).
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: And the woman was covered in the pelûl (paste).
Woman 1: It was a one-man job (hard work). One would
beat/work it, and the woman would put it on the drying rack.
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: We made our beads, praise be to God, we took them
to Aleppo, we sold them.
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: We were fit, we were good. We did the stiq
(stringing?). We did the fig branches.
Woman 1: Boçqê hejîra, e hov o, e pêşiya min, e hov o.
Woman 1: The fig branches, like that, in front of me, like
that.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Host: You are telling me from the very beginning, how did
you make it?
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: If from the very beginning, we made fig branches,
right?
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We would harvest our figs with force (hard work).
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: And I would clean/prepare them.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We would clean them purely.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: And we would put the elmok (seeds/beads) on the
dough/paste.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Host: After picking figs, you cleaned them, you put the
elmok.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We put the elmok.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We cleaned them.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: And we put the elmok on the dough, and then it
became like sîzoke (bead strands).
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We made sîzoke.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: Meaning in the new times (?).
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We put sîzoke on them, meaning straight, meaning
all together.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We cut a layer from the cmoknî (?), we made it into
sîzoke.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We would leave it on the plain (flat surface), so
it would become straight.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We made it into birûşe (beads).
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We took our beads to the market/collection point.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: We would sprinkle little black spots on them, those
black ones, they call it Habb al-Barakah (Nigella seeds).
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Host: They put it inside.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: They put it inside, we used a little Habb al-
Barakah.
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: They made it into beads, put it on the xozê
(pile/market).
Woman 1: Gil kal ket, min e tab da, tab da, tab da, gil kal
ket.
Woman 1: When the old man fell (died?), I struggled,
struggled, struggled, when the old man fell.
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: God gave... God gave the machine, God doesn't give
a sign (?).
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: He doesn't give me a sign. But it's good, I am a
master (of this craft).
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: I don't know! I don't know! I don't know! I used to
starch/glaze them.
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Host: You starched them so they would become thick/solid,
right?
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Host: Meaning so it becomes solid.
Woman 1: My brain knows, the age is old, I don't hold on (to
memories), my mother, since my mother did it, I did it too,
since I...
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: My wages, hands were cut (working hard), my mother,
she was a very smart woman.
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: And I would drop my pelûl (paste) onto the henna.
Woman 1: And that potato sack, you've seen the potato sack,
the ones in shops.
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: I would wash the potato sack well, rub it.
Woman 1: Make it dry, and I would spread it out, I would
spread my pelûl (paste) on it.
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: And all of it... make it bloody (red), in the hot
keftî (?), make it like shoes (tough/leather-like?).
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: And that day, it was facing the sun.
Woman 1: Until it went (dried).
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: After it went...
Host: I say... meaning that wasn't it.
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Woman 1: My kids would catch it... it would become a xoz
(good batch/pile).
Woman 1: Ji tûrik jê dikir, ma ji tûrik jê dikir.
Host: You took it off the sack.
Woman 1: Removed it from the sack, indeed removed it from
the sack.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: One would hold the sack, and one would hold the
board...
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: It would come off nicely.
Woman 1: I made my bundle on the wire.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: The sun is synonymous, it hit it, an hour passed,
the sun hit it, when it became dry.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: I took my bundle inside.
Woman 1: I starched/glazed it.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: I made the starch, put it in the şerbe (solution).
Woman 1: I made the starch into a solution.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: I starched my bundle.
Woman 1: So it's good, meaning kerm... meaning it holds
together, meaning nothing falls off.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: If the grain isn't slippery, nothing falls off.
Woman 1: I starched it, and gave it yeast (leavening/time?),
and I put it in the jar.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: Lowered it into the jar.
Woman 1: And I would buy my grain/seed.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: At Ahmed Zaki's place (shop).
Host: Are they in the shop?
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: They are in the shop. That grain, a chickpea
wouldn't fit in a handkerchief (metaphor for size/quantity).
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: I would bring a hundred grains for my bundle, so
that nothing falls out, so the stringing is clean.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: So that our womanhood/labor is not lost.
Host: Yes.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: Our womanhood/labor is not lost.
Woman 1: So it went.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Host: Then we... let's analyze the mûja (beads/seeds). Let's
come to the topic of mûja.
Woman 1: Mûje bi kirona mitir kirî.
Woman 1: Yes.
Woman 1: We bought the mûja by the meter.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: Bought the meter, washed my meter well.
Woman 1: Made my meter into sîzoke (strands).
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: The thread is thick (?).
Host: Excuse me for cutting your speech Aunt Fat. In the
time of mîja, types of grapes/seeds come out, but there is a
special grape/seed for mîja.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: Did you see the grape/seed?
Host: The mîja one is different.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: The mîja one, it is different, the mîja grape/seed,
a black one doesn't become mûj.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Host: It doesn't become.
Woman 1: The xal (speckled?) grape doesn't work. That other
one, that other one that is yellow and long.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Host: That one.
Woman 1: That is the mûja.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: I would bring my grapes/seeds, one comes, I would
wash it, put it in sîzoke to dry, and I would go buy soda,
so the bead becomes big.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: Kosok (Caustic) without coffee, oil.
Woman 1: And what is Kosok? Soda.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: I would put it in, stir, stir, stir.
Woman 1: I would dip my thread/grapes in it, lift it, dip
it, lift it in there, until the clear water, it would cool
down.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: Then I would put it in çûzokê (?), and I would take
it to the henna.
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: I would wash the henna well.
Woman 1: I would dry it, and I would spread out my mîja
(beads).
Woman 1: Heftokê, deh ro, deh û pênc ro, el saxîna bono.
Woman 1: A week, ten days, fifteen days, it would stay on
the henna.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: Then I, I would turn them over.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Host: Who does the turning?
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: Not the ears (?). Correction: Maybe "Na goşin e"
means "Not meat" or "Na guhêrin e" (don't change). Actually
sounds like "Na guşin e" (Not squeezing).
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: Squeezing... so the top becomes the bottom (no?),
it becomes red, it becomes face (color).
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Host: So you turn it.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: So every few days I would turn them, my mûja became
dry on the henna.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: Then we made our mûja, the heavy basins.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: We brought our mûja home, we cut the tails off the
ends.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: And we put our mûja in jars, and we ate (sustained
ourselves).
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Host: Yes.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Host: Bless you (Health be).
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: Welcome to you, and to your hunting/gathering of
happiness.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Host: May God keep you. Come tell me, who were your
neighbors, who were around you?
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: Our neighbors, the ones close to us, our neighbors
were our elders.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: We were in poverty, they made mud-brick houses.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: They made mud-brick houses, whoever made one, they
put the mud mold down, they hit it.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: Small kids, there were no diapers/clothes.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: They went to their place, kitix (sound of
falling/walking).
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Host: Barefoot (slang/local term).
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Woman 1: Barefoot, the barefoot ones of Khalil Azzat.
Host: E ko şî, e biçona borik ox bonyono botono, di go em kê
mûbînî qçko kin.
Host: Those who went, they went barefoot on the snow...
saying we will provide for the kids.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: It was poverty, poverty, poverty. Poverty was hard.
Woman 1: Some brought food from the plains for themselves.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Host: Brought from the plains, like that food, barefoot ones
of the land of Khalil Azzat.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: Like this finger, like a bent stick.
Woman 1: Like a stick, women would go, the women went, not
the men.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: They had expenses, working expenses, they gave to
the work.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: All the expense, to buy something to eat, bring it
home.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: They made their stew/food.
Woman 1: Like holding the misteq (handle/tool?), they do
misteq daily, under those kids.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Host: They did it under the kids.
Woman 1: Under the kids. Oh man, how they did it.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: They put so much effort into it, so much effort.
Woman 1: Misery, meaning there was misery, and there was
poverty.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: And it was hard, giving birth was hard.
Woman 1: Now the world has become good, my life is gone.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: And their life is gone.
Host: May God give a long life.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: Yes indeed, yes indeed. Life, until life became
good.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: Until the world became good, I raised ten children,
right.
Woman 1: Elhemdlillah, ez na kuc mo mn e.
Woman 1: May God keep them, and keep me too.
Woman 1: Praise be to God, I am not lacking/crippled.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 1: And Abu Marwan was also very comfortable with me,
and I was comfortable with him.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 1: And we raised them, and we sent them (to
school/life).
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 1: Praise be to God for this day.
Woman 1: Thanks to my kids, we educated/placed them. Praise
be to God.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 1: May God keep my kids, the women, and may He keep
Auntie Muhammad (referring to the other woman).
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 1: And have a good time.
Host: May God be pleased with you, may God give you a long
life.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Host: And if we have shortcomings, you will forgive.
Host: Hello, Aunt Sabah.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 2: Welcome, to you.
Host: How old are you?
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 2: Well, how many years, sixty-four.
Host: May God give you a long life.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Host: How many kids did you bring? How many kids did you
raise?
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 2: Well, may God keep them, keep me too, I raised
seven kids.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 2: Three boys and four girls.
Woman 2: We raised them, made them households, brought out
[brides/grooms], married them all.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Woman 2: So praise be to God, may God keep them, keep me
too.
Host: Xalkê Sabah, tkê mro ççkê ser berê denkê.
Host: Aunt Sabah, tell us a little about the past.
Berê weha li ser tiştekî, we di şûşt, we dikir?
Before, for example, regarding washing [wool], how did you
do it?
Berê weha li ser tiştekî daberê, êem diçûn ber avê.
Before, regarding those things, we used to go to the water.
We dikute gerê?
Did you beat it at the pool?
Heee em diçûn ber avê, kuta... em diçûn ber ava reş.
Yes, we went to the water... we went to the black water
[river name or description].
Hêre, dîwan, me herya xwe dişûşt, xê dibirin. Digu berê digu
bi xê bişû.
Yes, [with] a mallet. We washed our own mud [wool], took out
the dirt. They used to say "wash it with the sweat/dirt"
back then.
Digu me'ney ritûbet daroxe, ma xê dişûşt, hêre dugu, dikir
avê, hêre dişûşt.
They meant the humidity would drain out. We washed the dirt.
Yes, they put it in the water, yes, they washed it.
Ovi spî, pak jî diçûy, me herya xwe ra dikir.
The water ran white and clean, we laid out our wool.
Betîna mal, ziya dibû, me çêdikir ser têle.
The courtyard of the house, when it dried, we fixed it on
the wire.
Ser têle jî ziya dibû, me girê dida, me dikir bolge, dikir
doşek.
When it dried on the wire too, we tied it up, we made
pillows, we made mattresses.
Dikir orxon, me'ney nîvîn.
We made quilts, meaning bedding.
Me'ney mîvana, mîvanê me ra dihatin me didanê.
Meaning for guests, when guests came to us, we gave it to
them.
Ê de noka gibînî îsfenc, qa noka dînin.
But now they are all sponges, they don't bring [wool]
anymore.
Noka modê hêrya nema.
Now the fashion of wool is gone.
Nema. Me kifrûtin.
It's gone. We got rid of it.
Bes di malan gî ya da tiştê di hêrî hene, yanî mesela bolge
be, doşek be hene?
But in all the houses, are there still wool items, like
pillows or mattresses?
Hene lê, hene lê.
There are, yes, there are.
Ê xêr berê jî nîvînê wan ji wan ra radikirin? Bes e berê
hebî, dînadan ser xew nedikirin?
And the good things from before, did they lay out the
bedding for them? But before, if they had it, didn't they
sleep on it?
Ser xew nedikirin?
They didn't sleep on it?
Go tu nîvînê kû werî?
They said, "Where did you bring the bedding from?"
[Laughs] Go tin ê tû?
[Laughs] They said you don't have any?
Digo hewa ê mîvana ye.
They said, "This is for the guests."
Helîna, hewa kîça mîvanek hat, betanî, orxon, pak kîş dînan.
Look, if a guest's daughter came, blankets, quilts, they
brought out the clean ones.
Dîdinan me'ney mîvana.
They laid them out, meaning for the guests.
Me'ney nîvînan.
Meaning the bedding.
Lê hewê mîvana ye. Mîvanê te hat, te doşeka xwe, çarşefa
sipî serê daxist.
Yes, that belongs to the guest. If your guest came, you laid
down your mattress, the white sheet over it.
Bolgê qenewîçe te dîdan.
You placed the hemp pillows.
Pak te orxona xwe dida ser, heft dane lê diqilibîn.
You put your clean quilt over it, folded over seven times.
Heway mîvana, bes mîvan kî xod na kî, orxona xwe bikşîne ser
xwe.
That is for the guest, just so the guest can sleep
comfortably and pull the quilt over themselves.
Hêre dişûştin, we gerê dida, û orxon jî we çêdikirin?
So they washed the wool, beat it, and did you also make the
quilts?
Lêêê orxon jî.
Yeeeess, the quilts too.
Orxon jî hêrî ye, lê bes doşek?
The quilts were wool too, but what about the mattresses?
No, orxon, orxon, bolge gî hêrin.
No, the quilts, quilts, pillows, all were wool.
Berê çêdikirin, gote nîvînê hilîdinan, ser isqê gî didan hev
du?
Back then when they made them, you said they stored the
bedding, did they stack them all on the rack?
Lê me li tîno mal, nîvînê kîça mîvana, nîvînê me ra didan,
me dîtinan.
Yes, in the house, the bedding for guests' daughters,
bedding they gave us, we laid them out.
Ê nîvînê dawatî didan?
Did they give wedding bedding (dowry)?
Noka dêkê min jî çêkir, nîvînê dawatî didan.
Now my mother also made them, they gave wedding bedding.
Paşê me dawat kir da, her yekî me da.
Then when we had the wedding, she gave it to each of us.
Paşê bela dikin, her qîçikekî mesela, nikîkî didinê?
Then they distribute it, for example, giving a piece to each
girl?
Lê ta her qîçika xwe zewicand, didanê, sê orxon, sê doşek, û
pênc bolge me didanê.
Yes, until she married off every daughter, they gave them to
her: three quilts, three mattresses, and we gave her five
pillows.
Hewa ê qîçko, bin heqê xal mero namînin.
That belongs to the girls, so the uncle's right [debt]
doesn't remain on us.
Hewa ê qîçkê mero ne, tişta cebê mero, dîna mero didê.
That belongs to our girls, our belongings [pocket
money/resources], our religion gives it.
Heqê qîçko.
The girls' right.
Tiştê berê wani kê bûn.
Things in the past were like that.
Ê bes duşekî hêrî, ji vana rintir in? Yanî dibên mesela
berê, gote pişta mero nedişiyan.
But are wool mattresses better than these? For example, they
say that back then, you said our backs didn't hurt.
Berê sahî bî ta, ser isfenc duşekê xaw dikir, tu sahî bî.
Before you were healthy, if you slept on a sponge mattress,
you were healthy.
Lê noka pişta mero diêşê, ser isfencê, gî çik do dikeve, gî
çik radibe.
But now our backs hurt, on the sponge, it all sinks down, it
all rises up.
Pişta mero diêşê, tu radibê tu xiş e.
Our backs hurt, when you get up, you are stiff.
Ê berê ne wa bû?
Before it wasn't like that?
Berê gî hêrî bû, serê hêrya de ro.
Before it was all wool, on the wool [it was better].
Bolgî te hêrî, orxon hêrî, duşek hêrî, gî hêrî bû.
Your pillow was wool, quilt wool, mattress wool, it was all
wool.
Ê noka ne waye, noka gî isfenc e.
But now it's not like that, now it's all sponge.
Satonyo, bolgî sufik, yanî tiştê hazir.
Synthetic, fiber pillows, meaning ready-made things.
Lê, noka tiştê berê neman. Gî tişta, ê di hazir in.
Yes, now the things of the past are gone. Everything, they
are ready-made things.
Ne, tiştê wa, noka wa biye.
No, things like that, now it has become like this.
Arê.
Yes.
Noka dinê, jin hedîs bine, hedîs.
Now the world, the women have become modern, modern.
Haw biye çikê? Dema hedîs biye, tetewur biye gî tiştê.
Is that so, dear? The time has become modern, everything has
developed.
Ê lê, tya hedîs bine.
Yes yes, they have become modern.
Xaltîka Sebah, berê, mesela gî combona, gona cihil, cem dê û
bavkê xwe rûdiniştin mesela, cem xosiyê xwe?
Aunt Sabah, back then, for example, when they gathered, the
young people, did they sit with their mother and father, for
example, with their father-in-law?
Gil mesela di berê dinan?
Did they pay attention to words/speech back then?
Ê mala bavkê me, buxarî hebûn diniske.
Yes, at my father's house, there were heaters (stoves) in
the middle.
Buxarî hebû, eba buxarê rûdiniştin.
There was a heater, they sat around the heater.
Çençûxa keldan, me qiswan dîdinan, mîz dîdinan.
They boiled dried figs, we served dried figs, we served
tables [food/snacks].
Bavkê min rehmetî, xirmatînan.
My late father, they respected him.
Berê digon kajik.
Before they called it "kajik" [mute/quiet/modest].
Ma kajik dêkom rehmetî dikir, dîdino.
My late mother acted modest, she served.
Mesxere dikirin, meselo hawa didan.
They joked around, they told stories like that.
Ma ca dikir, sa dikir, sa dibû, nê heşt nihe. Em pê na
dihesîn.
We listened, watched, watched, [until] eight or nine
o'clock. We didn't notice [time passing].
Mesela tam hawal didan.
They told really good stories.
Meselê berê?
Old stories?
Ê îngî rodiniştin dur buxarê, weke mesela hawal didan.
Yes, when they sat around the heater, they told stories like
that.
Lê buxara bî soba dar tune bîn?
Yes, it was a heater, there were no wood stoves?
Were beş tune bî, ber çirê qozixê.
Come on, there wasn't even that, [we sat] by the light of
the kerosene lamp.
Ber çirê qozixê bûn?
You were by the kerosene lamp?
Luks bîne, mala bavkê min luks bî, me luks vêdixist.
There were Lux lamps, my father's house had a Lux, we lit
the Lux.
Yanî ê dimal mezinan, luks bî.
Meaning, in the big houses, there was a Lux.
Ê me luks bî.
Yes, we had a Lux.
Luks bî.
It was a Lux.
Ê û nigan rodiniştin, û ser meseled me hawal dida.
And they sat together, and told stories about those topics.
Lê ve mesela no dibîrî tê da mînin, an vî ronê xweş, însan
bîrê dike, lê bîrê nakê?
Yes, but do those stories stay in your memory, or those good
days, does a person remember them, or not?
Wel mero bîrê dike, me ji bîr kirine.
Well, one remembers, [but] we have forgotten them.
Ne bîr?
Not remember?
Me ji bîr kirine lê, tê bîra mero. Mero dibê berê hesîrê
pûşî bûn.
We have forgotten them, yes, [but] it comes to one's mind.
One says, before there were straw mats.
Berê mînderê paçî çêdikirin, me ber puxarê rûdidan, bolge
dîdinan, rûdiniştin.
Before they made rag cushions, we laid them out by the
heater, placed pillows, and sat.
Qana sor bî, puxara te jê zing dikirin, qe hender na sor bî
sarma tune bî.
It was so red [hot], the heater would ring [make noise] from
it, it was so red inside, there was no cold.
Înoko sobiye zingoye, em li pa sobê rûştine, mero diqerimê.
Now the stove is ringing [hot], we sit by the stove, [but]
one freezes.
Lê.
Yes.
Heyatê berê xweş bî.
Past life was good.
Xweş bî, ne?
It was good, right?
Xweş bî, bîrehetî bî.
It was good, it was comfortable.
Ê noka dinê, gî heye, bes bîrehetî tune.
But now in the world, everything exists, but there is no
peace of mind.
Tune, bîrehetî tune.
No, there is no peace of mind.
Berê siqet hebî, hezkirin pir hebî.
Before there was trust, there was a lot of love.
Lêê.
Yes.
Ihtîram hebî.
There was respect.
Giştek hebî, berê giştek hebî.
There was everything, before there was everything.
Îsanê gbotan, dugu xalo, xaltîkê, metê.
The older people, they called them Uncle, Aunt, Paternal
Aunt.
Dî noko, qa navê xalo û xaltîka tune. Lê?
But now, there is no name of Uncle and Aunt anymore. Right?
Ê.
Yes.
Lê wa bî, lê wa biye.
Yes it was like that, yes it has become like this.
Ihtîram, erê.
Respect, yes.
Berê, ge di mezin şûr bikirana, şûra xwe nedibîndita?
Before, if the elders scolded [someone], they didn't see
[acknowledge] their scolding? [Meaning: Did the young accept
the scolding without arguing?]
Lê, şûra xwe şûr bî, şûr dimeşî.
Yes, their scolding was a scolding, the scolding worked [was
effective].
Xalis otî, em şûra genda naşkînin.
It was pure authority, we didn't break the word of the
village elders.
Hewa şûra genda ye, xalis, şûra xwe naşkînin.
That is the word of the village elders, pure, they don't
break their word.
Şûra merê mezin na, dibîndita?
The word of the old man, no, did they accept it?
Lê.
Yes.
Şûra merê mezin, dorê bî.
The word of the old man was valid [current/law].
Dê noka îşta.
But now, look at it.
Xwedê mero erê rehmê.
May God have mercy on us.
Xwedê gyorin bike.
May God make a change.
Te emirtane, te gotin ta hene.
Long life to you, your words are valuable.
No saeta we xweş, Xwedê we razî be, Xwedê saeta we xweş bî
wade.
No, bless your time [health], may God be pleased with you,
may God bless your time too.
Bî wade jî yaram, Xwedê saeta xweş bî wade jî. Elen we
selen.
With you too my dear, may God bless your time too. Welcome.
Ser çava.
You are welcome [On my eyes].
Merheba Xal Nezmi.
Hello Uncle Nezmi.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Ser çava.
You are welcome [On my eyes].
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God keep you.
Cayî te sax be.
May your place be sound [May you be well].
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Tu çend salî Xal Nezmi?
How old are you Uncle Nezmi?
Wellahî heftê û pênc, yan kete heftê û şeşan, kelame.
By God, seventy-five, or entering seventy-six, words
[approximately].
Heftê û pênc kete heftê û şeşan.
Seventy-five entering seventy-six.
Xwedê emrê kî dirêj bide te, siheta kî xweş bide te.
May God give you a long life, give you good health.
Xwedê sihetê xweş bide we, Xwedê we bihêle ji me ra.
May God give you good health, may God keep you for us.
Saet xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be. Xal Nezmi, qenatê hotim li
Efrîn.
Bless you, may God be pleased with you. Uncle Nezmi, I came
to the Afrin channel.
Tişkî pir xweş d qedimîne, darbaz gindo dibe.
You are presenting something very nice, passing through the
villages.
Jam d mezinê... mezinê me l kiderê be, vêra rûdinê, gil
tiştê di berê dinê.
Gathering with the elders... wherever our elders are,
sitting there, complaining/talking about things of the past.
Seta we xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be. Hîşta jî razî be.
Bless you, may God be pleased with you. May He be pleased
even more.
Ka o çîçkê li ser berê me ra deng ke, heyatê berê wa çû
darbaz kir? Çiqas xweş bî?
So tell us a little bit about the past, how did past life
pass? How good was it?
Heyatê berê, wextê em... bi dinyê ketine.
Past life, when we... came into the world.
Siftah me fîstan li xwe dikirin.
First, we wore dresses/tunics.
Fîstan?
Dresses?
Fîstan. Em diçûn... mala, mektebê.
Dresses. We went to... the house, the school.
Mualimekî hebû, çar şaf dixwendit didan.
There was a teacher, he taught/gave four classes.
Ê paş... berî wê jî xuce hebû. Em diçûn ber xuce.
And then... before that there was a religious teacher
(Xuce). We went to the religious teacher.
Paşê, paşê dereng dereng mekteb çêbûn. Em ketine mektebê,
teqrîben ew wextê jî em şoter bûn.
Then, then later on schools were built. We entered school,
roughly at that time we were clever/grown.
Xêrê me l ber xuce xwend.
We studied well with the religious teacher.
Wa berê xuce bar wada elimand?
So before the religious teacher, regarding knowledge?
Lê, xuce hebû. Elîf bê, me hifiz kiribû, orta em gihîştibûn
ebced.
Yes, there was a religious teacher. Alif Ba [Alphabet], we
had memorized it, until we reached Abjad [advanced
alphabet].
Ebcedê, hawz.
Abjad, Hawaz.
Paşê re mekteb vebîn, ketin mektebê.
Then the schools opened, you entered school.
Awa, în... yanê êşta rewal dim, mektebê me lê xwendî, kitêb
jî me ra dihatin, digu "Tara, tara".
Yes, look... meaning I'm telling the truth now, the school
we studied in, books came to us, saying "Tara, Tara" [Arabic
rhyme].
Nizam... "hedîqetî"... neşîden hano. Me wana hifiz dikir.
I don't know... "my garden"... anthems like that. We
memorized those.
Ê noka na, qehwe tişta tune. Na, bi carê kî.
Not like now, there isn't coffee and such. No, not at all.
Ê hişta heyat... ê...
Yes still life... uh...
Me hîç likey reş li xwe kirin. Sofê şeşê bûn, me dîşlikê reş
li me dikir.
We put on black gowns. We were in sixth grade, we wore black
dishdashas/gowns.
Hema me qelemî xwe pê paş dikir. Qelemî şînî lûb... ev bî...
şîşî boyax bî.
We just rubbed our pen on it. The blue pen... that was... it
was a bottle of ink/paint.
Ê elew ê kî boyax bibê, me hema bi î reş paş dikir.
Yes even if it [the collar] became painted/stained, we just
covered it with that black.
Paş dikir.
Covered it.
Are welle.
Yes, by God.
Ê de şta heyatekî zehmet bî. Paşê... em mezin bûn, çîçkê...
So look, it was a hard life. Then... we grew up, a little...
Pantor li me kirin, îşka... min ecêb dît.
They put pants on us, look... I found it strange.
[Laughs] Ez çûm Heleb go... pantor û xofofok.
[Laughs] I went to Aleppo saying... pants and slippers.
Ê we wextê şerm bî?
At that time was it shameful?
Şerm bî. Yanê, heta ku mirov ne zewicîba, pantor li xwe
nedikir.
It was shameful. Meaning, until a person got married, he
didn't wear pants.
[Laughs] Yanê xura lêdan dixwarin?
[Laughs] Meaning you would get beaten for it?
Lêdan dixwarin.
We got beaten.
Wextê bê pantor bî.
When it was without pants.
Wextê bê pantor bî, bi fîstan bî.
When it was without pants, it was with a dress/tunic.
Ortox ti cahêl bî wekî dibêjin?
Even though you were a young man as they say?
Bes erebî tune bî.
But there was no Arabic.
Erebî tune bî?
There was no Arabic?
Xol Nezmi, xwendinê berê wa nebî.
Uncle Nezmi, past education wasn't like that.
D berê, noka mesela... wateyî noka mesela gimerîk bimrê ser
telefonê em dibînin, ser internet... du deqe naşir dibe.
In the past, now for example... meaning now for example if a
person dies, we see it on the phone, on the internet... in
two minutes it's published.
Li gundot, d xûca camiyê da tê bang kirin. Berê wextê
gimerîk wefat bibo, çû aw dikirin?
In the villages, it is announced from the mosque speakers.
Before, when a person passed away, how did they do that?
Wextê g yek rehmetî dibû... dewar hebû.
When one passed away... there was a town crier [dewar].
Arê.
Yes.
Me yê we l qotirê kiru... d şêm erê... meriyê me l kîjan
gundî hene... me yê bugotê herê...
We sent him on a route... sent him... wherever our relatives
were in which village... we would tell him go...
Sibê zû tê, ere xeberê pê de.
Come early in the morning, yes give him the news.
Wa her merinê dişand gindîkî?
So they sent a man to each village?
Eywa.
Exactly.
Ge ne wa be, xeber nagihiyê.
If it wasn't like that, the news wouldn't reach.
Î... î... yanê g pêgiştor a... ê zû botana me... dewar e.
Uh... uh... meaning generally... the quickest for us... is
the crier.
Belkî m rodin pigîştono.
Maybe he ran generally.
Arê.
Yes.
Û... ew... çodir modir tune bûn. D molo da bûn.
And... those... there were no tents and such. It was inside
the house.
Xonên ser qanterm bûn. Teştre dixistin, walan mere dihatin,
digu Xwedê rehma xû lê kê.
The houses were arched. They laid out mats, people came
anyway, saying God have mercy on him.
Lê mûhim... we wextê wa nebî.
But importantly... that time wasn't like that.
Dimerik dimrî, li qonterê dikir, mesela digot filan dê herê
filan gimdî.
If a man died, they did it on the slope, for example, saying
so-and-so would go to such-and-such village.
Filan gimdî, tikê herê cem r’ajû, tikê herê cem, mesela,
Şêx, tikê herê cem gulyê, tikê herê filan derê.
To such-and-such village, you have to go to the elderly man,
you have to go to, for example, the Sheikh, you have to go
to the leader, you have to go to such-and-such place.
Heta orteqmerîyekî, pîrekî, tiştekî dişandin...
They would even send a middleman, an old woman, or
something...
Bedewêr... makîna tinebûn. Heta bigihînya, diçûn bazara
r’ajû, bimeşê.
By turns... there were no cars. Until they reached him, they
went to the elderly man's gathering, on foot.
Yanî ew tinebûn, makîna kêmbûn.
Meaning those didn't exist, cars were rare.
û niko jî, min bihîst, go berê, mesela wextê gimerîk dimir,
diçûn ser tila jî bang dikirin? Diçûn ser tila, bang
dikirin.
And now too, I heard that in the past, for example, when a
man died (or eloped), would they go on the hilltops to
shout? They went on the hilltops and shouted.
Bang dikirin?
They shouted?
Bang hew dikirin? Çu dikir? Wana deng lê dikirin?
Did they shout out loud? What did they do? Did they call out
to them?
Ee ser tila, gige nêzîk ba, bang dikirin.
Yes, on the hilltops, if they were extremely close, they
shouted.
Bang dikirin, mesela, ya şaba, gindî, be’dîna mesela, merik
filan lê rehmetî bûye, yekane, seheta we xweş.
They shouted, for example, oh youth, villagers, afterwards
for example, "so-and-so has passed away," singly, may you be
healthy.
û xeber didan hevdû. Ê bîst, xeber da ê din.
And they gave news to each other. The one who heard gave
news to the other.
Berê, gimerîk wefat ba, wana xeber belav dikirin?
In the past, if a person passed away, did they spread the
news like that?
Lê xeber wek çetin bî, çikê, 'alem kê xeberê bidin.
But the news was difficult, because, who would give the news
to the people?
Nika gi ser înternetê, gi ser telefîzyona, gi belav dibe.
Now it's all on the internet, all on television, it all
spreads.
Nika vê deqê.
Now, in this very minute.
Vê deqê. Ê der va jî, barî ma dibîzin.
In this minute. Even those outside (abroad), hear about us
instantly.
Erê. Xalê Nezmî, berê dawet wextê dikirin, mesela jilyekî ra
dikirin, em bêjin daweta te.
Yes. Uncle Nezmi, in the past when they held weddings, for
example for someone, let's say your wedding.
Dibê heft roja dikirin? Heftoka dikirin?
They say they did it for seven days? Did they do a whole
week?
Besîdî... berî gya, bêraxik, li malê zêvêk, bêrax çêdikirin.
Usually... before everything, a flag, at the groom's
celebration house, they made a flag.
Paçikî sipî, serê darê, wekî şûr.
A white cloth, on the end of a stick, like a sword.
û ê pîvazik, yan jî porteqalek.
And an onion, or an orange.
Ew daliqandin, me'ne zanibûn, ê xerîb, malê zêva li filan
derê ye.
They hung that up, meaning they knew, the strangers knew,
the wedding house is in such-and-such place.
Erê.
Yes.
û cema jî, wextê g’e ban kilîfa kirina, e’e ban tana, darê
gulê, her gindekî gulek hebî.
And the gathering, when they came to dress her (the bride),
when they brought her, to the entrance of the alley, every
village had an alleyway.
Gulek hebî. Her gindekî.
There was an alleyway. In every village.
Seh.
Correct.
E... û l’axê wê gulê jî, çêdikirin kêlekê, me digot, evna
k’e’kê gulê ye.
Uh... and at the end of that alley, they built a side part,
we called it, "this is the cake/stone of the alley."
Da dîkancî gind, kî hebona, ê tiştî xwe bikşandana wî derî,
sibê.
So the shopkeepers of the village, whoever was there, would
pull their goods to that spot, in the morning.
E şeş-heft ro temana, û gi xwende hebona, krîfê biçûk, mal
bi mal bigerîyan, xwende bianîna, jibo ku şekir bidana rê,
dixisitan.
Uh, six or seven days would pass, and if there were students
(kids), the little godfathers, would go house to house,
bring the students, so they could give them candy on the
way, they threw it.
Heta qîçikê çûçik jî, diçûn, dîkana... da wekî... qidum...
eya... yanî kiçê bikirin.
Even the little children went to the shops... so that
like... ancient... uh... meaning to buy the girl.
Haa.
I see.
Hev... dendik bûn.
Those... were seeds/nuts.
Me'ne teselîyê bînin.
Meaning to bring consolation/joy.
Lakin, ihtiramek hebî, teqdîrek hebî, û wê wextê da merliqêk
hebî.
However, there was respect, there was appreciation, and in
that time there was a distinct etiquette.
û hezkirin hebî.
And there was love.
Ee... gi ne ji hezkirinê be, wana şîn ne dibî.
Uh... if it wasn't for love, those things wouldn't happen.
Erê. Heft roja dawet dikirin?
Yes. They had the wedding for seven days?
Ebeden. Heft roja, tikê darbê, û nîzamî.
Absolutely. Seven days, you have to hit (the drums), and
orderly.
Tikê nîzamî?
It has to be orderly?
Hîn nîvêna tînin, ê xelkê gundê din.
They bring bedding still, the people from other villages.
Gundê din dihatin?
Did other villages come?
E, yanî malyê zêvayê, tikê sê-çar malyê bibê mal...
Yes, meaning the wedding house, it has to be three or four
houses becoming home...
Nikarin anor obro, her gindîyê xwe biftilin, na.
They can't just go here and there, every villager wandering
on their own, no.
Her hinekî nîvîna dibin.
Everyone takes some bedding.
Ebeden. Berê wana bî.
Absolutely. In the past, it was like that.
û li merya jî we dikirin berê?
And did they do that with the people (guests) too in the
past?
û li merya jî, ser tirba jî, bê... her merîkî me, ê min, kî
li gind rehmetî dibî, mi şîvê xwe pişta dikir, ji ber ku em
gimerîyên hev bûn.
And regarding people, even at the graves (funerals), be
it... every person of ours, mine, whoever passed away in the
village, I would put my dinner on my back (bring food),
because we were each other's people.
Îcbarî, nîvînê me kê heban. Na mela şîvê me hazir bî.
Compulsory, who would have our bedding? No, mullah, our
dinner was ready.
E de, tiştê zemanê berê, rind bî. Ê nokna, na. Çadir
derketine, filan derketine...
Well, the things of the past times were good. The ones now,
no. Tents have come out, such things have come out...
Ne tu xûndra têxê, ne tu filan dikê, û...
Neither do you put them inside the room, nor do you do such
things, and...
Wanan jî...
Those things too...
Ewa...
That...
Ema, sê r’o ya r’oj, ê sîyê diçûn ê kingiyê.
But, three days or a day, the third (day) they went to the
evening gathering.
Erê.
Yes.
Wana bî.
It was like that.
û berê, mesela, gibafkê digot, mesela, ekê filan qîzê ji
lawê xora, dibê hevdû jî nedîbana, 'adî bî.
And in the past, for example, if the father said, for
example, "I will take such-and-such girl for my son," even
if they hadn't seen each other, it was normal.
Na... wextê k', e... çkê serxwa mera denk e.
No... when... uh... because pay attention to yourself
regarding us.
Ê min, wextê gim... ekê kulfetê xwe bixwazim, min nedîbî.
As for me, when I... I was going to ask for my wife, I
hadn't seen her.
Te nedîbî?
You hadn't seen her?
E... go... a hatim, malê 'opî min, go em kê filanê iştera
bixwazin.
Uh... they said... I came, my father's house, they said "we
will ask for so-and-so for you."
Walla mi go glên, î min nadî, jimra dixwazin, min nadî ye.
I swear I said, look, he won't give her to me, they are
asking for me, but he won't give her.
Te nedîbî?
You hadn't seen her?
Walla qîza pîmin, Xwedê rehma xolîkê... çû banî kir, honya
hat serxênê.
By God, my aunt's daughter, may God have mercy on the
earth... went and called, she came like this onto the roof.
E da şîn, cawîd ma, xurab gela dînizim.
So they went, our request/engagement, the engagement got
tied up (finalized).
Mi dî îşaret me kir, e... ewna giçîçikê hatim, fehm bî, çû
bî midî ravî.
I saw we made a sign, uh... that one came as a little girl,
understood, she went, I saw she ran away.
E, da mi go wala... ji xora dixwazin... yanî ê min...
Uh, so I said I swear... they are asking for themselves...
meaning as for me...
Te ew nedî ye.
You hadn't seen her.
No no, we... ene çîmû derê jî.
No no, and... I didn't go there either.
Te neçû jî.
You didn't go either.
No, no, no. Tişta berê wana bî.
No, no, no. The things of the past were like that.
û tînîn, xelas. Rind bî, ne rind bî, hav nesîbê xoyê.
And they brought her, finished. Beautiful or not beautiful,
that is your destiny.
Elmuhim, no bê, ê me, 'adeta me, gi tij 'oylakê zewicî,
xelas, hev nesîbê te y, tikê qebûl key.
Importantly, don't say it, ours, our custom, if you married
from a family, finished, that is your destiny, you have to
accept it.
Tu wê 'aylê dibê.
You become (part of) that family.
Tu wê 'aylê dibê, û, û tikê merliqê bikê yanî.
You become part of that family, and, and you have to show
respect/etiquette, meaning.
Ne eno bes eno, ecbê 'aylyê ber... eno hewakî va xelkê...
Not just that, the likes of the family before... that sort
of people...
qewtînin, bavêr, dema, filan, hewa tine ye.
...chasing, giving up, periods, so-and-so, such things
didn't exist.
Berê tine bî.
In the past it didn't exist.
Xelas, no, xelas, hev xudê nesîbê te hewa.
Finished, no, finished, that is what God destined for you.
Welhemdulilah.
And praise be to God.
Tu razî ye.
You are satisfied.
Elhemdulilah. Em wekê gotî, em ji hevdu razî bûn, û em ji
xuda no razî bûn.
Praise be to God. As was said, we were satisfied with each
other, and we were satisfied with God (for this).
Ew xoltîka rûdê me xoltî kê, û xolî miro dibê xol, û
elhemdulilah ji xudê ra, no.
That aunt sits with us as an aunt, and the uncle becomes an
uncle, and praise be to God, no.
Ihtiramek heye.
There is respect.
Erê.
Yes.
E wekî din, işta, em kê bêjin çi...
And other than that, well, what shall we say...
Halyê dinyê ye.
It is the state of the world.
Halyê dinyê hev bî.
The state of the world was this.
Xalê Nezmî, niha em bêne ser wextê nika. Wextê nika, yanî
cîwazî gellek ketiye navbera wextê berê û yê nika.
Uncle Nezmi, now let's come to the present time. The present
time, meaning a lot of difference has fallen between the
past time and the present one.
Belê.
Yes.
Mesela berê, heyanî, em bêjin bîst sal berê jî, mesela
mirovekî bi telefonê bi qîzekê ra xeber da ba, 'eyb bî.
For example, in the past, until, let's say even twenty years
ago, for example if a person talked to a girl on the phone,
it was shameful.
'Eyb bî.
It was shameful.
Şerm bî.
It was disgraceful.
'Eyb bî, 'eyb.
It was shameful, shameful.
Qedexe bî.
It was forbidden.
Nika bûye tiştekî 'adî.
Now it has become a normal thing.
Nika 'adî ye.
Now it is normal.
Bi dîtina te, ew wext baştir bî, yan ew wext?
In your view, was that time better, or this time?
Bira, ew wext, wekî e... sîstema, şeref û namûs, û exlaq, ew
wext bî.
Brother, that time, regarding the... system, honor and
reputation, and morality, it was that time.
Nika, serbestî ye.
Now, it is freedom.
Serbestî, tu zanî çiye? Mesela, ez lawê xora dibêjim, "kurê
min, eve ne rê ye."
Freedom, do you know what it is? For example, I tell my son,
"my son, this is not the way."
Dibê "babo, tu nizane."
He says, "Dad, you don't know."
Tu nizane, zeman hatiye guhertin.
You don't know, the times have changed.
Zeman hatiye guhertin. Ez zanim, zeman hatiye guhertin, lê,
esil nayê guhertin.
The times have changed. I know the times have changed, but,
the essence (roots) does not change.
Esil nayê guhertin.
The essence does not change.
Hîn, hîn tişt hene, nayên guhertin.
Still, there are things, they don't change.
Nayên guhertin. Ê nika, mesela, dibê "babo tu fêm nake."
They don't change. The one now, for example, says "Dad you
don't understand."
Temam, ez fêm nakim.
Okay, I don't understand.
Lê tecrûba min, jiyana min, eza borandî, bêtirî te ye.
But my experience, my life, that I have passed through, is
more than yours.
Sedî sed.
One hundred percent.
Te çi dî ye? Te hîn... te hîn dinya nedî ye.
What have you seen? You still... you haven't seen the world
yet.
Hema te çavê xwe vekir, te go "wa".
You just opened your eyes, you said "wah".
Te go "wa".
You said "wah".
E em, me dinya dî, me 'alem dî, me...
But us, we saw the world, we saw people, we...
Xeberê medê, kîl ber şêrê boma.
Don't speak, the bit was in the lion's mouth (times were
extremely hard/dangerous).
Em têra derketin.
We came through it.
Hûn têra derketin.
You came through it.
E... E nika, lawikê nika, qîzikê nika, hema şîretê lê bike,
dibê "tu nizanî."
Uh... And now, the boy of today, the girl of today, if you
just advise them, they say "you don't know."
Dibê "em zana ne."
They say "we are knowledgeable."
E "em zana ne, em li mekteba çûne."
Uh "we are knowledgeable, we went to schools."
Zana bûn, ne bi xwendinê ye, ne bi mektebê ye.
Being knowledgeable is not by reading, it is not by school.
Ebeden. Zana bûn, bi aqil e.
Absolutely. Being knowledgeable is by wisdom/intellect.
Bi aqil e.
It is by wisdom.
Bi aqil e. Mirovê bê aqil...
It is by wisdom. A person without wisdom...
Bê feyde ye.
Is useless.
Xalê Nezmî, pirsîyarek dî.
Uncle Nezmi, another question.
Ciwanya te... wextê tu ciwan bî, xort bî.
Your youth... when you were young, a young man.
Wextê tu diçû ser kaniya, te av tanî...
When you went to the springs, you brought water...
Dilê te diket qîza?
Did your heart fall for girls (did you fall in love)?
Welle bavo...
Well, father (dear)...
Rastî.
Honestly.
Rastî, dilê me diketê.
Honestly, our hearts fell for them.
Diketê.
Fell for them.
Ee. Lê me nedikarî em bi devê xwe bêjin "em ji te hez
dikin."
Yes. But we couldn't say with our own mouths "we love you."
We nediwêrîya.
You didn't dare.
Me nediwêrîya.
We didn't dare.
Tirs hebî.
There was fear.
Şerm hebî.
There was shame.
Exlaq hebî.
There was morality.
Namûs hebî.
There was honor.
Te çawa nîşan dida ku tu jê hez dikî? Mesela, bi çava?
How did you show that you loved her? For example, with eyes?
Hema bi çava.
Just with eyes.
Hema bi çava. Yan jî, me çav li rê dikir, kengî diçê kanyê.
Just with eyes. Or else, we kept an eye on the road, (to
see) when she goes to the spring.
Wextê diçû kanyê...
When she went to the spring...
Wextê diçû kanyê, em diçûn pêşîyê.
When she went to the spring, we went in front of her
(crossed paths).
We xwe nîşan dida.
You showed yourselves.
Me xwe nîşan dida.
We showed ourselves.
Da fehm bike.
So she would understand.
Da fehm bike ku filan kes...
So she would understand that so-and-so...
Hatin û çûn çêdibî.
Coming and going happened.
Ee.
Yes.
Heta fehm dikir.
Until she understood.
Eger fehm nekiriba?
If she didn't understand?
Eger fehm nekiriba, me yê dî dişand.
If she didn't understand, we sent another (person/signal).
We qasid dişandin.
You sent messengers.
Me qasid dişandin.
We sent messengers.
Qasidê we kî bûn?
Who were your messengers?
Qasidê me, pîrek bûn.
Our messengers were old women.
Pîrek bûn?
Old women?
Pîrek bûn.
Old women.
Pîrek, diçûn mesela, digot "filan kes, mesela silava li te
dike, filan..."
Old women, went for example, saying "so-and-so, for example
sends greetings to you, so-and-so..."
Wana digot.
They said that.
Heger qîzik, mesela, e...
If the girl, for example, uh...
Kiçik gi bîr hişk bî, digot "here, ez wî, filan nakim."
If the girl was hard-headed/stubborn, she would say "go
away, I won't do that/him."
Heger dila hebî...
If she had a heart (interest)...
Nerm dibî.
She would soften.
Digot "silavê lêke."
She would say "greet him."
"Silavê lêke," em zanibûn ku riya me vebû.
"Greet him," (then) we knew that our path was opened.
Riya we vedibû.
Your path opened.
Riya me vedibû.
Our path opened.
Ee.
Yes.
Xalê Nezmî, zemanê berê xweştir bî, yan zemanê nika?
Uncle Nezmi, was the past time better, or the present time?
Welle bavo, zemanê berê, zehmet bî.
By God father (dear), the past time was difficult.
Zehmet bî.
It was difficult.
Lakin, xweş bî.
However, it was good.
Xweş bî.
It was good.
Mirov rihet bûn.
People were comfortable (peaceful).
Mirov rihet bûn. Feqîr bûn, hejar bûn, em, lakin, dilê me
fireh bî.
People were comfortable. They were poor, they were
destitute, we (were), however, our hearts were wide
(generous/happy).
Dilê we fireh bî.
Your hearts were wide.
Dilê me fireh bî. Me ji hevdu hez dikir.
Our hearts were wide. We loved each other.
Nika, bira ji birê xwe hez nake.
Now, a brother does not love his brother.
Bav ji kurê xwe hez nake. Kur ji bavê xwe hez nake.
A father doesn't love his son. A son doesn't love his
father.
Cîran ji cîranê xwe hez nake.
A neighbor doesn't love his neighbor.
Hemû bûye menfiet.
Everything has become about benefit (self-interest).
Bûye menfiet. Bûye pere.
It has become benefit. It has become money.
Bûye madde.
It has become material.
Bûye zikê min têrbe, bira cîranê min bimre.
It has become "let my belly be full, let my neighbor die."
Berê ne wa bî.
In the past it wasn't like that.
Hûn têr bana, cîranê we birçî ba, we xwarin dibirê.
If you were full, and your neighbor was hungry, you took
food to them.
Welle me dibirê. Welle me parve dikir.
I swear we took it. I swear we shared it.
Welle me parve dikir.
I swear we shared it.
Me nanê xwe parve dikir.
We shared our bread.
Welleh.
I swear.
Jiyana berê...
The life of the past...
Jiyana berê, şîrîn bî.
The life of the past was sweet.
Rast e, zehmet bî, em diwestîyan.
It's true, it was hard, we got tired.
Em diwestîyan.
We got tired.
Em pêxas digerîyan.
We walked barefoot.
Em birçî diman.
We went hungry.
Em tî diman.
We went thirsty.
Lakin, me ji hevdu hez dikir.
However, we loved each other.
We ji hevdu hez dikir.
You loved each other.
Me ji hevdu hez dikir.
We loved each other.
Dilê me li hevdu dişewitî.
Our hearts burned for each other (we had compassion).
Xalê Nezmî, tu gelek şîretên ciwan dikî.
Uncle Nezmi, you give very beautiful advice.
Welle bavo, em şîreta dikin, lakin, kê guhdarî bike?
Well father (dear), we give advice, however, who will
listen?
Kê guhdarî bike.
Who will listen.
Kê guhdarî bike?
Who will listen?
Tu şîretên ji dil dikî.
You give advice from the heart.
Em ji dil dikin.
We do it from the heart.
Em ne, mesela, ne ji dev e.
We are not, for example, not (speaking) from the mouth
(superficially).
Em ji dilê xwe dipeyivin.
We speak from our hearts.
Em tiştê rast dibêjin.
We speak the true things.
Em tiştê ku...
We say things that...
Têra derbas bûn.
We passed through them.
Têra derbas bûne, em dibêjin.
We have passed through them, we say.
Xalê Nezmî, gelek spas ji bo vê bernameyê.
Uncle Nezmi, many thanks for this program.
Xwedê we bihêle, ez jî spasîya we dikim.
May God keep you, I also thank you.
Hûn hatin, we zehmet kişand.
You came, you took the trouble.
Ser çava.
Upon (my) eyes (You're welcome).
Hûn ser seran û ser çavan hatin.
You came upon heads and upon eyes (Welcome).
Tu sax bî.
May you be healthy.
Xwedê emrê we dirêj bike.
May God prolong your life.
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God keep you.
Mala we ava.
May your house be prosperous (Thank you).
Tu her he bî.
May you always exist.
Spas.
Thanks.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike.
May God prolong your life.
Xwedê ji we jî razî be, Xwedê sehetê bide we.
May God be pleased with you too, may God give you health.
Xoşbo Xalê Elî.
Welcome, Uncle Ali.
Weleh elhemdulilah, hetî şolê?
Well, praise be to God, did you come to work?
Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God.
Ahlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Tijî ye û qenatêr, Afrîn hat tijî ye û...
It is full and the channel... Afrin came, it is full and...
Ezbenî, sax bî. Êvar baş, xêr hatin Afrîn, ahlen we sehlen,
ser seran ser çavan.
Sir, be healthy. Good evening, welcome to Afrin, welcome,
upon my head and eyes.
Çay ta sax be, destê te sax be.
Thanks for the tea, may your hands be healthy.
Te xwendina xwe xoş e Afrîn?
Is your reading good, Afrin?
Lê, hatim lê Afrîn, gerîm, fitilîm û hatim lê Afrîn.
Yes, I came to Afrin, I wandered, I turned around and came
to Afrin.
Temam.
Okay.
Ortex hat, Afrîn ortex debelişe, tiştê dixoşe wû didê.
The friend came, Afrin, the friend is starting, giving good
things.
Temam.
Okay.
Go Xalê Elî tu çend salî bûyî vê rêkê?
Tell us, Uncle Ali, how old were you at this time?
Weleh xwedê emrê kî tê de, emrê min şêst pênc.
Well, God give you life, my age is sixty-five.
Şêst û pênc.
Sixty-five.
Xwedê emrê dirêj tê de û siheta xweş tê de.
God give you a long life and good health.
Dê îro emê piçekê ser avê deynin, avê berê.
Today we will talk a bit about the water, the water of the
past.
Ser avê.
About the water.
Hûn çûn, çûn avê, çûn masiya...
You went, went to the water, went for fish...
Em diçûn avê berê.
We used to go to the water in the past.
E... Es'edê Sîno, Mistefayê Mamê Hecî, Nezmî Arifê Alê,
Eliyê Hebeşê Hemzê, Evdê Hebeşê Hemzê.
Uh... Es'ed Sino, Mistefa Mame Heci, Nezmi Arif Ale, Ali
Hebesh Hemze, Evde Hebesh Hemze.
Em şevê, hemî şevan em şilî masiyan bûn.
At night, every night we were wet from fishing.
Deh, donzdeh maran, babê de ketin, ya em di çiyê ra diçûn bi
meşê...
Ten, twelve men, oh father, we fell to it, either we went
through the mountain on foot...
...û ya jî dilaqtor, gemaq nîne, wê zemanî hebûn, em diçûn.
Batmanê.
...or tractors, there were no Gamaks [pumps/engines], in
that time they existed, we went. To Batman.
Hûn diçûn bi meşê, hûn diçûn Batmanê?
You went on foot, you went to Batman?
Erê.
Yes.
Çiqas yekî desê nan dikir berîka xwe, hûn tisyê.
Just as someone put a loaf of bread in his pocket, you know.
Erê.
Yes.
We diçûn.
We went.
Em diçûn, mamosta digirtin...
We went, teachers [guards/police] caught us...
Her çar meriv pşê hevdû.
Every four men behind each other.
Mamosteyekî... ê pşê têk... û hat ê dûndar dighîniyê.
A teacher... the one behind alone... and the follower
reached him.
Kî şebekê berdin tina ye.
Whoever drops the net is gone.
Erê.
Yes.
Weleh mîrogek ketin bendê...
Well, a man fell into the trap...
Ezme, Henîfê Şewketin, Mistefayê Mamê Hecî, Es'edê Sîno
wanan...
It was me, Henife Shevket, Mistefa Mame Heci, Es'ed Sino,
them...
Emê ketinê... weleh me mamostek girt.
We fell into it... well, we caught a 'teacher' [huge fish].
O... me got bofkê mose girt.
Oh... we said we caught the father of the fish.
Erê. Mezin bî?
Yes. Was it big?
B'xwedê mezin bî.
By God, it was big.
Henîfê Şewket pêm, go o... me dêka mose girt.
Henife Shevket told me, said oh... we caught the mother of
the fish.
Erê.
Yes.
Ê reş bî, ê gewr bî.
It was black, it was grey.
Weleh me girtin, girtin, girtin...
Well, we caught, caught, caught...
Heta em çavê derketin.
Until we came out to the source/eye.
Do, ê gundî qedexe hene, Es'edê Sîno xwedê rehma xwe lê ke,
heval ê hevalê xwe. Aqîl aza tine, ebeden.
Then, those prohibited villagers, Es'ed Sino may God have
mercy on him, a friend is a friend to his friend. No
wise/free mind, never.
Em çiqas bav reşxelekîn, ketbî cimerbî ça dera, 'ezet heval
ê hevalê xwe bî, xwedê rehma xwe lê ke.
However black-complexioned we were, fell into mud or
whatever place, a friend was a friend to his friend, may God
have mercy on him.
Emrê Xwedê kîş.
God's command.
Do win gundî qeda hebûn lo?
Then there were the prohibited villagers, man?
Wan dore xew kirin, doxî em... we çaxê îsoneta bî, merlaqet
bî.
They surrounded us while sleeping, then we... at that time
there was humanity, there was decency.
Erê.
Yes.
Em deh donzdeh mer e, kê girt nagirt, yê nagirtî jî xistê da
ye.
We are ten or twelve men, whoever was caught or not, the one
not caught also jumped in.
Yê bav re heval diçûn, yê nagirtî jî xistina xistê.
Those who went as friends together, the one not caught also
jumped the jump.
Xistê da, wî jî didanê.
He jumped, he also gave it [jumped].
Wî gundî qedexe hebûn, bin dore xew kirin, qer ne mirr, ne
çûne, 'ezet hew jî dikir xistê.
Those prohibited villagers, under surroundings slept,
[meaning unclear], he also did the jump.
Xistê da, wî jî didanê.
He jumped, he also gave it [jumped].
În xew dayê.
Look, he gave sleep.
Erê.
Yes.
Gene p'ewkî cêmor, cêmor.
A muddy place, muddy.
Weleh me mamosta girtin, roke...
Well, we caught the 'teacher' [fish/event], one day...
Ez û Eliyê Hebeşê Hemzê, Xalidê Eslan wanan...
Me and Ali Hebesh Hemze, Xalid Eslan, them...
...û Raşîd rehmetî...
...and the late Rashid...
Me mamosta girtin, lo me mamosta girtinê, gî reşpoşî pişt
hene.
We caught the 'teacher', man we caught the 'teacher', all
black-clad ones are behind.
Me cokusa girt, dewre hafa me ket.
We took the corner/turn, the patrol fell on our side.
Erê.
Yes.
Hafa me ket, de... pşka me yê xaçû jî cemad ne.
Our side fell, then... our [net?] Xachu was also freezing.
Erê.
Yes.
Bê menî çi cemad ne? Yani bi mehnî t'em noko ter herrim.
What meaning freezing? Meaning with meaning that we are now
wet with mud.
Erê.
Yes.
Es'ed go, xistê şepox bo pî de.
Es'ed said, jump, slap/kick to the leg.
Vê çaxê jî masî memnû bûn.
At that time fish were forbidden.
Memnû bûn wa bigirtana?
Forbidden to catch them?
E'h, ew digirtin yanê, digû memnû ye.
Yeah, they caught [people] meaning, saying it is forbidden.
Es'ed go, her yekî yanê xistê şepox bo pî de.
Es'ed said, everyone meaning jump, slap/kick to the leg.
Bi Es'ed ra fitilîm, go tu gî mîha dî xistê me mede...
I turned with Es'ed, he said don't you give all the other
[stuff] to our jump...
Zeman hedê winin.
The times [guards] see.
Te mi fam kir çi hedê?
Did you understand me what [hedê]?
Ere, ere.
Yes, yes.
Lo diçûn, hatin, cîb e bi rê ketin...
Man went, came, the Jeep set off...
Hatin, ya xayê bi terefê xistin, masîyê me gî xwarin.
Came, either put the owner to the side, ate all our fish.
Gîştek? Ne yek ne didu? Gî xwarin?
All of it? Not one not two? Ate all?
Kuro masî reş wanan, mezin, her yek şilûq...
Man, black fish them, big, each one a slap [big]...
Ez û Xalidê Reşîd û Eliyê Hebeşê Hemzê, em derbêjin, Xalidê
Eslan tev wanan hewa vedixwin.
Me and Xalid Reshid and Ali Hebesh Hemze, we say, Xalid
Eslan with them drink air [do nothing/watch].
Eliyê Hebeş dîtin ser darê gûzê...
Ali Hebesh was seen on the walnut tree...
...bê dîtin pat! Wî pşî, ez û Xalidê Reşîdê rehmetî va lo...
...seen suddenly pat! He behind, me and Xalid Reshid the
deceased here man...
...em kelemê berê pexet masiyê me gi xwarin.
...we fell in the previous trap, [damn] they ate all our
fish.
Em jî xovê dixwin.
We also eat fear.
Hûn jî xofê dixwin?
You also eat fear?
Em xofê dixwin, i darê, i tim li darê.
We eat fear, he on tree, he always on tree.
Weleh, elmem em çûn, me masi xelas kirin, em hatin mal...
Well, anyway we went, we finished the fish, we came home...
...be'dî çaw pênc sal e, bîst sal e.
...after how [many], five years, twenty years.
Ere.
Yes.
Em çûn Lîbya.
We went to Libya.
Ma ewraq, mewraqê xwe şî me turî diwalî do çêkir şomê...
Our papers, we made something in a sack bag in Damascus...
...cip, ew meriv rast b hat.
...suddenly, that man came straight.
We'y gundûkî ye.
Oh, he is a villager [from a small village].
Ne sê merivnê, masiya gî xwarin.
Not three men, ate all the fish.
Wê mernê masî, me vira biriştnê, li wû derê rast me hatin.
Those fish men, we fried here, over there came straight to
us.
Weleh çûn rûyê hevda, hevdu maç kirin, ehlen we sehlen, çi
emrê we heye li vî derî bişxuli...
Well went to each other's faces, kissed each other, welcome,
what order do you have here working...
Go kabra qey mi da nişî wa bi meşînim.
The man said as if gave me to walk you.
Ere.
Yes.
Be'dî weqa sal ha, ev bîr nehat kirin?
After so many years ha, was this not remembered?
E bes ma ewraqê xwe gî xelas kiribûn.
Ah but had finished all his papers.
Xelas kiribûn.
Had finished.
Me xelas kiribûn.
We had finished.
E're el hal tel mose çûn.
Yes the situation [of] the teacher went.
Mose çûn.
Teacher went.
Em roke çûn avê...
One day we went to the water...
...bi motora, çar motora em çûn.
...with motorcycles, four motorcycles we went.
Çûn Kelawîrî.
Went to Kelawiri.
Tev Raşîdê Xaçû ye, Eliyê Hebeş in, Es'edê Sîno ye rehmetî
xwedê rehma xwe lê wan ke...
With Rashid Xachu, Ali Hebesh, Es'ed Sino the deceased may
God have mercy on them...
Em çûn, o ci... çar çîft e.
We went, oh [something]... four pairs.
Çar çîft e. No, îneke du çîftan tê bîra re bî. Du çîft e.
Four pairs. No, one [time] two pairs comes to mind. Two
pairs.
Hana avî kergû û kewa kir...
Like water made rabbits and partridges...
Em şivqê gihîştin Kelawîrî.
We reached Kelawiri at dawn.
Û hine jî mamosta girtin.
And some also teachers caught.
Hina kew û kergû û hina jî mose.
Some partridges and rabbits and some teachers.
Hina kew û kergû, hina jî masî...
Some partridges and rabbits, some fish...
Wê jî royê çêkir, Eliyê Hebeşê Hemzê...
He also made the day/sun, Ali Hebesh Hemze...
...wekê mose biqewirînin. Mose teze acer qewirandin.
...like chasing away fish/teachers. Fish fresh new chasing.
Kir germîya masiyo.
Made fish soup.
Masî tav da.
Fish gave sun/heat.
Ner bîn?
Were they male?
Ner bî, go germîya masiyo minî kirî.
Male was, said I made the fish soup.
Weleh me zik da girt.
Well we held the belly [ate a lot].
Damê xwinî jî ma dîsa mase...
Time of eating also remained again fish...
Ke'nîkê wî derê heye, nizanim Amûdê ye, ne Amûdê ye, ez
nizanim.
There is a spring there, I don't know if it's Amude, not
Amude, I don't know.
Kanîka nava xosar... no...
Spring inside Khosar... no...
Şêxanî çî me.
Shekhani what of us.
Xendeka ne Cizîra Botan?
Trenches not Cizira Botan?
Weleh dîsa me şîv çêkir, Eliyê Hebeş teb'en...
Well again we made dinner, Ali Hebesh of course...
Guştî kewa, kergûyo û masiyo.
Meat of partridges, rabbits and fish.
Û banedor bi mera, e xwinê çêkir, do te pêçî xwe vêra
bixwara.
And tomatoes with us, ah made the food, man you would eat
your fingers with it.
Xweş bî?
Was it good?
Her borîk te xwar te, devê xwe t'ke'nîkê bikşînin.
Every tube/bite you ate, you would pull your mouth to the
spring.
Tiştekî cûle xweş e, ber avê dera.
Something nicely moving/active, by the water side.
heyata berê xweş bî.
Life of the past was good.
Heyata berê xweş, destê wan elimî bûn.
Life of the past good, their hands were accustomed.
Wa bi desta digirt berê?
Did you catch with hands back then?
Berê bi desta bûn.
Before it was with hands.
Em çûn gola dera bûn, desta bûn.
We went to the lake side, it was hands.
Gijî heval ê hevdû.
Hair [fighting?] friend of each other.
I noka em darin, lo? Gote kûp negre yekî nadin te.
This now we pass/go, man? Said don't hold the cup, they
won't give you one.
Berê tu, tu diçûyî te xew kira xwestî te hatiba.
Before you, you went you slept your wish would come.
Ebeden, heval ê hevalê xwe bûn.
Never, friend was friend of his.
Bes ê noko em darin, gijgij her yek du kîlo sê kîlo digre,
dikun mi yek negirtiye na, no bê eşk no biniye yekî me ra
de.
But the one now we pass, [fighting sound] each one catches
two kilos three kilos, [saying] look I haven't caught one
no, not without obvious not without seeing give one to us.
Hekes li xwe heyirî ye.
Everyone is amazed/worried about themselves.
Noka newq e berê, berê siqet, emniyet he bûn, hevaleqe bûn.
Now is not like before, before trust, security existed,
friendship existed.
Hezkirin jê hebû.
Love existed in it.
Hezkirin hebû, dilsozî hebû.
Love existed, loyalty existed.
Hezkirin teb'en lê, şuşa dilê min Azat rehmetî, xêr hatina
wî gava li ben.
Love of course man, glass of my heart Azat the deceased,
welcome to him when on [ben].
Wî di xew da hew jî kir xistê.
He in sleep also did the jump.
Qe ne hevalê me ye.
Not at all our friend.
Bes gundî qeda ye, da merî xwe li gundî qeda hene? Yanê
hevdû nas dikin lo?
But village [prohibited], man has his people in prohibited
village? Meaning they know each other man?
Ere.
Yes.
Hew jî kir xistê.
Also did the jump.
Te cêmolaqê berê wanekî bûn, însanetî, siqet, emniyet he
bûn, min kerpîç çêdikirin.
You [know] the twins of the past were like that, humanity,
trust, security existed, I made mud bricks.
Kerpîç?
Mud bricks?
Kerpîç. Ezm Xidirê Hentêmbat. Cem Reşîdî Mislim. Û cem
Es'edê Sîno.
Mud bricks. Me and Xidir Hentembat. With Rashid Muslim. And
with Es'ed Sino.
Wa kerpîç çêdikirin.
Making those mud bricks.
Heyata me hew bû.
Our life was that.
Îno kî kerpîçî vêk in no? Gime çêkir ne.
Look who gathers the mud bricks right? [Sound] made them.
Xulê kerpîça jî Xalê Elî çetin e.
The soil of mud bricks is also difficult Uncle Ali.
Pir çetin e, emrê me bir.
Very difficult, took our life.
Çetin e.
Difficult.
Xoş e em jî, gime çêdikir, ez benatê Hesen.
It's good we too, [sound] made, I [benat] Hesen.
Heta mi xilos ne kir o, benatê Hesen.
Until I didn't finish, [benat] Hesen.
Ez û Ofitê Ezazê dişixulîn.
Me and Ofit Ezaz worked.
Hewa çiqo mi alimim xilofet e rehmetî.
The air/weather how I learned [khilofet] deceased.
Çar tûş çêdikiran.
Made four [molds].
Mi çend çêdikiran? Şeş.
How many did I make? Six.
Şeş.
Six.
Wî, ewqê xwe wanî veda bû.
Him, his [something] like that had opened.
Eme mi çêdikirin şeş, eme tingî gînde pir tir.
But I made six, but [sound] roll much more.
Û xeyê min nedahat, rehmetî Ehmedê Seîdê Xwedêdo serkê
pîşxew dikir. Xeyê min nedihat.
And my Agha didn't come, deceased Ehmed Seid Xwededo on the
[something] took a nap. My Agha didn't come.
Mi kerpîçê xwe liblib nanê heb da.
I [something] my bricks...
Mi ket dan ser ev da, mi bi meşê diçûm kargehê, bofkê xwe
rehmetî.
I fell put on this, I went walking to the workshop, my dear
father deceased.
Hin berê yê mesele korik bûn jî hin pir diçûn Lubnanê
dişixulîn meselen, paşê dihatin wa... qitçik ba şîr ba dar
ba wa.
You before the issue of boys were also you went a lot to
Lebanon worked for example, then came like that... small or
milk or tree or that.
Le erê. Pir berê diçûn Lubnanê Xalê Elî ne?
Man yes. A lot before went to Lebanon Uncle Ali right?
Ere ere. Korê min î tembî diçûn.
Yes yes. My lazy son went.
Bê tînî.
Without bringing.
Heyata berê Cefo bî, û...
Life of the past was Jefo [hardship], and...
Cefo bî, çetin bî.
Hardship was, difficult was.
Heta mara jî yekî didiya nava halî.
Even man one gave into the situation.
Le elhemdulilah.
Man praise be to God.
Elhemdulilah şikir dê dîsa dixweşe, qiçik xweş ne, sihet...
Praise be to God thanks again it's good, small good,
health...
Te jî xweş bî, siheta te xweş bî, elhemdulilah jiber vê royê
ra, qiçka em zehmetî didin.
You also be good, your health be good, praise be to God for
this day, a little we give trouble.
Ez no şixulim noko li layê Mamê Hecî me.
I don't work now, now I am at the side of Mame Heci.
Te rûniştî ye, piçekî te da ye rehetê.
You are sitting, a little you gave to rest.
Kor gi noken, elhemdulilah.
Son all are [something], praise be to God.
Xwedê peyximber jê razî bin, Xwedê emrê...
May God prophet be pleased with them, God [give] life...
Gelî Xalê Elî kî dibê bila bibê, wextî teng bav bifik, ta
mezin dike, biriyona re.
Listen Uncle Ali whoever says let him say, time of tight
father [something], until makes big, for the eyebrow.
Nexweşîk bê, ê dewrê qutkî lê birrîne.
A sickness comes, the one of surrounding cuts the short
jacket on him.
Û maro çiqo bike, ji dêk bavkera maro neke reb kiwan maro
kiriye.
And man whatever he does, from mother father man doesn't do
God who made man.
Rebê alema, rebê hemu tiştî ye.
Lord of worlds, Lord of everything.
Weleh elhemdulilah em na poşman in.
Well praise be to God we are not regretful.
Saeta te xweş.
Your health good.
Saeta te jî xweş.
Your health also good.
Ser sera ser çava.
On head on eyes [Welcome].
Ahlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Em pir şa bûn. Te gelek...
We were very happy. You a lot...
Ez pirtir şa bûm.
I was happier.
Te em kêfxweş kirin.
You made us happy.
Te, te ez kêfxweş kirim.
You, you made me happy.
Saet xweş Xalê Elî, Xwedê şîfa bide.
Health good Uncle Ali, God give healing.
Te hişt ez vê cimeatê xweş bibînim.
You let me see this good community.
Ez vê cimeatê şirîn, muterem û şerefe bibînim.
I see this sweet, respected and honorable community.
Tu xwedanê malê yî, tu qisûra me nebinê, te efû ke.
You are the owner of the house, don't look at our faults,
forgive you[rself/us].
Rebê alemê qisûrê me te efû ke.
Lord of the world forgive our/your faults.
Û roza Rebûl alemn saet xweş, emrê kî dirêj.
And will of Lord of worlds health good, a long life.
[Muzîk]
[Music]