Em hatine vandanê, em hatine vandanê.
We have come to this side, we have come to this side.
Li deşta Xezewiyê, vandan jî gundê Hecî Habû ne.
In the Ghazawiya plain, and this side is the village of Hecî
Habû.
Û zeytûn jî îsal î...
And the olives this year are...
Berê min tebeqo digot.
I used to call it "tebeqo".
Erê berê min tebeqo digot.
Yes, I used to call it "tebeqo".
Bîra te qerşî ye.
Your memory is messy.
Ton derd dikirin.
They used to grind tons.
Înakê jî kes wî istixdam nake.
Now, no one uses it.
Wî tenê xirab bibe.
It will just get ruined on its own.
Gelî kîbar û delal, em îro li ser kaniya gundê Habû bûn.
Dear noble and lovely people, today we were at the spring of
Habû village.
Belê, av hişk e.
Yes, the water is dry.
Vê xaniyê jî... li deştê gundê Habû dikeve. Pir kevnar e.
And this house... falls within the plain of Habû village. It
is very ancient.
Li ser jî yazmîş kirine... yazmîş nekirine, bes wek ji min
ra xeber dane...
They have written on it... well not written, but as they
told me...
Mîrê vê bîrê û vê darê, hav pê...
The prince of this well and this tree, summer with...
Merheba miletê kîbar û delal, ez hatim bi vîdyoyeke xweş,
vîdyoyeke ecêb.
Hello noble and lovely nation, I have come with a nice
video, a wonderful video.
Vîdyoya min îro li gundê Habû ye.
My video today is in the village of Habû.
Kanê mera bin, bi dilekî xweş û eşq, em ê derbasî gundê Habû
bin.
Stay with us, with a happy heart and love, we will enter the
village of Habû.
Em ê adet û teqalîdê wî gundî nas kin.
We will get to know the customs and traditions of this
village.
Em ê guldengê di bav û kalan in.
We are the echo of the ancestors.
Em ê çîrokê di berê mera bêkin.
We will tell you the stories of the past.
Saeta we xweş, û bîr nekin me de'm kin, em ê bi de'mê we
serkevin.
Bless you, and don't forget to support us, we will succeed
with your support.
Em îro, em hatine vandanê, em hatine vandanê li deşta
Xezewiyê.
Today, we have come to this side, we have come to this side
in the Ghazawiya plain.
Vandan jî gundê Habû ne.
This side is the village of Habû.
Û zeytûn jî îsal îyanî...
And the olives this year are, you know...
Ê berhem tebeqo ye çaxe.
Well, the harvest is "tebeqo" (average/middle level) at this
time.
Û pa xosî... em el-tebqo bêjin... birê qerşî ye.
And specifically... let's say "al-tebqo"... the yield is
mixed.
Ji me wî da.
From us to him.
Ê bîr li cih e.
Yes, the memory is in place.
Em jî li vandanê hacî yê, mesîr dikin.
We are here as pilgrims, walking around (or pressing
olives).
Saeta we gelekî xweş. Silavê me ji we gelekî re hene.
Many blessings to you. We have many greetings for you.
Û Xwedê ji we giya razî be. Û da vandan jî... hêşta ortix
bergane maye, em newîrin pê ve herin.
And may God be pleased with all of you. And on this side...
there are still leftover obstacles, we don't dare go
further.
Yanî elhemdulîlah, şebab jî giş gundî hebû ne.
So praise be to God, the youth are all from the village.
Saeta we gelekî xweş. Xwedê ji we razî be.
Many blessings to you. May God be pleased with you.
Pêkenok lêviyê me bin, ser qenetê 'Hatim li Efrîn'. Saeta we
gelekî xweş.
May smiles be on our lips, on the channel 'Hatim li Efrîn'.
Many blessings to you.
Wê neşkîne!
Don't break it!
Ha wilo!
Just like that!
Ê hişyar be ha!
Hey, be careful, ha!
Na welle na... na weke berê lazim...
No really no... no, like before, it's necessary...
Tu nizanî, tu nizanî.
You don't know, you don't know.
Ha wilo!
Like that!
Maşallah, maşallah.
Mashallah, mashallah.
Ha te şûtî li erdê xist!
Ha, you hit the watermelon on the ground! (Metaphor for
hitting too hard/clumsily).
Ha te şûtî li erdê xist!
Ha, you hit the watermelon on the ground!
Merheba.
Hello.
Merheba, ehlen we sehlen, ser çava.
Hello, welcome, you are esteemed.
Navê te bi xêr?
May I ask your name?
Navê min Şukrî ye.
My name is Shukri.
Xalê Şukrî.
Uncle Shukri.
Xalê Şukrî. Çend salî ye?
Uncle Shukri. How old are you?
Ez pêncî û şeşame... mewalîdê pêncî û şeşame.
I am fifty-six... born in fifty-six.
Pêncî û şeş, Xwedê emrê dirêj bide, û sihetê xweş bide.
Fifty-six, may God grant a long life, and grant good health.
Ez Xelîl, ji gundê Ba'dîna, ji qenala 'Hatim li Efrîn', îro
em mêvanê gundê Habû ne.
I am Xelîl, from Ba'dîna village, from the channel 'Hatim li
Efrîn', today we are guests of Habû village.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser çava, û ser seran.
Welcome, upon my eyes, and upon my head.
Xwedê te selam bike ya Reb.
May God keep you safe, oh Lord.
Xalê Şukrî, li her gundekî 'delîb' hebi berê. Delîbê vê
gundê jî min dît.
Uncle Shukri, every village used to have a 'roller' in the
past. I saw the roller of this village too.
Hîn istixdam dikin, li ney, aw nekin?
It exists.
Do they still use it, or no, they don't?
Welle berê istixdam dikirin. Genim, derd, pê dikutan, derd
dikirin.
Well, in the past they used to use it. Wheat, [threshing],
they pounded with it, they ground it.
Înakê jî kes wî istixdam nake. Wî tenê xirab bibe.
Now, no one uses it. It will just get ruined on its own.
Neha delîb waye sikirandin?
Now the roller is stopped (parked)?
Ê wane sikirandin î, û me...
Yes, it is stopped, and we...
Êdî her kesekî karê xwe cotkarî bî dikirin.
Everyone used to do their own farming work.
U şti... genim diçandin, ceh diçandin, tiştê wana diçandin.
And things... they planted wheat, planted barley, planted
those things.
Û zeytûn û darra heve, no gundê Habû.
And there are olives and trees, now in Habû village.
Gundê Habû, korê çûlê.
Habû village, deeper in the countryside.
Kûlê çûlê, û darra bûn.
Deeper in the countryside, and there were trees.
Xudan pez bûn.
They were sheep owners.
Xêr nav lê kirine 'Gundê Habû'?
Why was it named 'Habû Village'?
Gundê Habû, 'î otî' vira xwe Habû bî.
Habû village, [the ancestor] himself was Habû.
Ji me'mila...
From dealings...
Lê êxist hat vira...
He set out and came here...
Û vira girt...
And took this place...
Û gon şên kir, navê gundê Habû bî.
And populated the place, it became the name of Habû village.
Însanek bî...
He was a person...
Însanek bî.
He was a person.
Jî me'mila hat, li deştê vike...
He came from dealings, to this plain...
Piştî gihîşt viderê, malbatek li vir çêkir, aîletek li vir
çêkir...
After he reached here, he built a household here, built a
family here...
Paşê nav lê kirin gundê Habû.
Later they named it Habû village.
Bi vî me'neyê dibêjin gundê Habû.
With this meaning, they call it Habû village.
Gundê Habû.
Habû village.
Gundê Habû niha, Xalê Şukrî, çiqas însan rûdiniştin tê de?
Habû village now, Uncle Shukri, how many people live in it?
Welle yê berê pir bî.
Well, in the past it was a lot.
Berê... 'eke bim, dûrê...
Before... if I say, around...
Dused mare, sêsad mare tê hebûn.
There were two hundred, three hundred households in it.
Dest niha kêm bûn.
But now they have decreased.
Niha dora çiqas mal tê heye?
Now around how many households are there?
Niha dora teqrîben... têke bi hespînê...
Now around approximately... if you calculate...
Heşt, bîst û heşt naha mare ne.
Eight, twenty-eight, twenty-nine households.
Yanê belê malin e.
Meaning, yes, they are households.
Dora bîst û neha mala li gundê Habû rûdiniştin.
Around twenty-nine households live in Habû village.
Li gundê Habû da ne, erê.
They are in Habû village, yes.
Gah çûne, çûne Helebê, û dest vî meşakil no jî çûn...
Sometimes they left, went to Aleppo, and due to these
current troubles they also left...
Xwedê canê sax bide. Xwedê avkî li nêrîkê...
May God grant health. May God put water in the churn
(restore prosperity)...
Xalê Şukrî, saeta te xweş. Xwedê ji te razî be.
Uncle Shukri, bless you. May God be pleased with you.
Ez pir kêfxweş bûm, îro ez mêvanê gundê Habû me.
I was very happy, today I am a guest of Habû village.
Sax bî, ehlen we sehlen, ser çava, ser serî min.
Be healthy, welcome, upon my eyes, upon my head.
Berî ez derkevim, te mirtek, gotinek, tiştek heye, tu bêjî?
Before I leave, do you have a wish, a word, anything you
want to say?
Na, saeta te xweş, û Xwedê ji te razî be, û tu bi...
No, bless you, and may God be pleased with you, and you
with...
Tu bi mihmê hat, û te...
You came with importance/care, and you...
Te çêkir, saeta te xweş.
You made it (the video), bless you.
Ehlen we sehlen.
You are welcome.
Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê alîkar be.
May God be pleased with you, may God be your helper.
Sax bî, ehlen we sehlen.
Be healthy, welcome.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Navê te bi xêr?
May I ask your name?
Habîba.
Habiba.
Habîba?
Habiba?
Me'nî navê Habîba çi ye?
Yes.
What is the meaning of the name Habiba?
Ê welle me'nasiya gundê min... hez kirine? Hez kirin e.
Habîba.
Well, the meaning of my village (people)... loved? It is
love. Habiba.
Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê te bihêle.
May God be pleased with you, may God keep you.
Xwedê te rabigre, ehlen we sehlen.
Aunt Habiba...
May God sustain you, welcome.
Çend salî ye?
How old are you?
Şêst û du dime.
I am sixty-two.
Şêst û du dim, maşallah. Welle belê naki jîrt e.
Sixty-two, mashallah. By God, you don't look it, you are
lively.
No, ne hêj tum ne xweş me.
No, I am not that well/healthy yet.
Xwedê rehetî bide te.
May God grant you comfort.
Ji te ra jî, spas.
To you as well, thanks.
Te pîr xweş gundê Habû lê?
Do you like Habû village very much?
Ez gundê Habû me, û bûka gundê Habû me.
I am from Habû village, and I am a bride of Habû village.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Allah yselmek.
God keep you safe.
Min xwest pirs bikira, dabe berê wextê...
I wanted to ask, back in the day...
Bûkik... berya derbasbûyî gundî kirin, le hespê dikirin?
A bride... when they passed through the village, did they
put her on a horse?
Na, welle ne dikirin.
No, by God they didn't.
Tu li hespê nekir?
They didn't put you on a horse?
Ha, berê min tebqo ye çaxe.
Ha, back then I was [walking/strong] at that time.
Û pa xwe sî... em li tebqo bûn.
And for ourselves... we were [on foot/using basic
transport].
Em nakinê nîşta cîbê.
We don't get inside the Jeep.
Digû ne tera, em nakinê derketibûn?
Saying [if it wasn't for you], we wouldn't have gone out?
Lê cîbî... De teksî dernayên qeyna, tenê bên, de hesabî
zirifî milet.
But the Jeep... Taxis don't come out anyway, only if they
come, it's at the expense of the people.
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê sihetê xweş bide te.
May God grant you good health.
Ji te ra jî, canikê sax bide jî, inşallah.
To you as well, grant you a healthy life too, God willing.
Ehlen we sehlen bi tina we.
You are welcome, with your presence.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Zarok li derve hene?
Do you have children abroad?
Hene.
There are.
Hene?
There are?
Erê.
Yes.
Ê noka tu bibînin.
Yes, now they will see you.
Tê vira silavê bikî jî baş e.
If you send greetings here, it is good too.
Ehlen we sehlen, saeta te xweş.
Welcome, bless you.
Ez pîr kêfxweş bûm, îro ez hatim gundê Habû.
I was very happy, today I came to Habû village.
Dilok min li Almanya ye.
My Dilok is in Germany.
Yek li Tirkiyê.
One in Turkey.
Silavê min ji giya ra hene.
My greetings to all of them.
Û ji milletî Kurd...
And from the Kurdish nation...
Kurdistan e, giyan e inşallah.
It is Kurdistan, it is soul, God willing.
Xaltîka Hebîba, li her gundekî berê meselen nan dikirin...
Aunt Habiba, in every village back then, for example, they
used to make bread...
wextê mesele hênik ba, kincik va dibirin ber kaniyê
dişûştin.
when, for example, it was cool, they would take clothes to
the spring and wash them.
Erê. Me diçûn bîra Qaşliyê. Ji me wîda... bîra li jêr heye,
vêra dibên bîra Qaşliyê.
Yes. We used to go to the Qaşliye well. Beyond us... there
is a well down there, they call it the Qaşliye well.
Kaniyê jî heye qastal jî heye?
Is there a spring and a fountain too?
Lê, em diçûn, me av tîna, me baz diçûn ber kancan dişûştin,
der dikirin, hêra dişûştin.
Yes, we went, we brought water, sometimes we went to wash
clothes, took them out, washed them there.
Û li her gundekî... cil çêdikirin... cilê li berê...
And in every village... they washed clothes... the clothes
of the past...
Tevd... em pîçik bûn çêdikirin.
All... we were small when we washed them.
Hûn pîçik bûn çêdikirin.
You were small when you washed them.
Bîra te tê, digotin, yorim hela vê glokê, jimar a bibin û
hûn e...
Do you remember, they used to say, dear, watch this bundle,
count them and you...
Ma dikir ser kevir dibir û tînan jêra.
We put them on the stone and beat them back and forth.
Daku ew tahrn ji dar dixistin.
So that the dirt would come out by beating with wood.
Wextê diçêdikirin, ji wara jî digotin, vê glokê, zerqî kin
ha...
When they were washing, they would tell them, make this
bundle shine, huh...
Daku çêdikirin.
So they washed them.
Xaltîka Hebîba heyata li berê xweş bû?
Aunt Habiba, was life in the past good?
Wele xweş bû yorim, tiştek nebûn, xweş bûn.
Well it was good dear, we had nothing, but it was good.
Û da nanê rûniştî bixwara, liqî bî dîsa rind bî.
Even if you ate bread sitting down, even if it was dry, it
was still good.
Noko jî xweş e, dinê mitewer bî, rind bî...
Now is also good, the world has developed, it's good...
pîçik, yanê ne wekî berê ev bî ye.
a little bit, meaning it's not like the past anymore.
No wele şikir, noko jî pir e.
No well, thanks to God, now there is plenty.
Te hez kir te hez ke?
Did you love, did you fall in love?
Ha wekî bi destê me ra bî, te hez nekir zote... te sebtand û
hez ne dikir.
Ha, as if it was in our hands, if you didn't love... you
endured and didn't love.
Berê jî, yanî gadek bavê kaşûrek bikra, şûrek gêle nedibî
dida.
In the past too, meaning if a father made a hint, a sword...
wouldn't give.
Maro... nekelem berê biskin yanê rast çiqas te zana bidara
maro... maro rind te zana.
Man... don't let me speak about the past, truly however much
you know... man knew well.
Tişt bûn rûdarbaz bibîbî, meriv rûdarbaz nebibîbî.
Things were tolerable, people were not tolerable.
Û piştî demekê, danê paşê dighalmî ser şeyî dikirin.
And after a while, later on, they would get used to the
thing.
Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God.
Na na bereket versin.
No no, may God give blessings.
Xaltîka Hebîba, her însanek, tiştek divê rûdarbaz bî, bîr
neker.
Aunt Habiba, every human, something must be experienced,
don't forget.
Di heyata xwe da, ga rind be, ga xirab be.
In their life, whether good or bad.
Tiştî piçûk e aqilê meriv naqete. Rast e.
Small things, a person's mind doesn't grasp. It's true.
Tu tişt aqilê te damayî têkine ji mera hewaldê?
Do you have anything stuck in your mind to tell us?
We dî yorim, aqilê me, ê tê damayî, em li vî gundî bûyn, li
vî gundî mezin bûyn.
Well dear, our mind, what's stuck in it, we were in this
village, grew up in this village.
Gam kuta çûne... çûne... noko me ştarol duser Kaniya
Berbîra, Berberxa, Berkara... gi fikrê me damayî.
When we went... went... now we have wandered to Kaniya
Berbîra, Berberxa, Berkara... all stuck in our thoughts.
Di zirûfê noko da, dû maçî şikirî, orta şikirê me da nemayî.
In the current circumstances, two kisses of thanks, in the
middle of our thanks there is nothing left.
Yanê holê dinê, tedîb çitûnî bî.
Meaning the state of the world, there was no discipline.
Yanê pîçik di aqil serê me da jî hebî, di vê wextê noko
da... yanê dinê ne rehet bî, tedîb çitûnî bî.
Meaning if we had a little brain in our head, in this
current time... meaning the world wasn't comfortable, there
was nothing.
Elhemdulilah, dîsa ê ji berê çêtir be, w’ê rind bibê.
Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God, again it will be better than the past, it
will be good. Praise be to God.
Înşallah rojê tê jî hînê xweş bibin.
God willing, the coming days will be even better.
Înşallah.
God willing.
Her kes, yanî ê ortax, biftile ser axa xwe, welatê xwe.
Everyone, meaning the youth, return to their land, their
country.
Weşê tengî yo, înşallah, ê fereleqe be, giyê werin ser axa
xwe, nav dar û berê xwe, ser milkê xwe.
The hardship, God willing, will be relief, all will come to
their land, among their trees and produce, on their
property.
Elhemdulilah, em ê hînkê pif kin.
Praise God, we will revive it.
Hûn çend sal in?
God willing.
How old are you?
Rastî bêjim ez azib im.
To tell the truth, I am single.
Na, min tenê, mi le biçûkê l’omî kir.
No, I thought, I mistook you for the little one of [name].
Na tşit nabe.
No, it's fine.
Yanî, yanî ne qîçkê me mane, heval cîran man e, xkbirakî,
pîder ketin.
Meaning, meaning our kids remain, neighbor friends remain,
brothers, fathers fell.
Jiber zilm zorê, ê da çû Ewrûpa, ê çû Tirkî, ê çû dera...
Because of oppression and force, one went to Europe, one
went to Turkey, one went somewhere...
Yanê bime jî çetin bî. Rast em ser axa xwe man lê, lê çetin
bî. Xerîbî, xerîb e.
Meaning for us too it was hard. True we stayed on our land
but, but it was hard. Exile is exile.
Boyî xerîbiyê çetin e.
Because of exile it is hard.
Lê çetin e. Em noko ba’s dibînin. Ne ji vê telefonê be
yorim, em ê dîn bibin.
Yes it is hard. We now see each other barely. If not for
this phone dear, we would go crazy.
Bes telefona ne şikir, em hevdu dibînin, derd dikin, farqê
xwe pir e.
But the phone is thanks, we see each other, share troubles,
it makes a big difference.
Ne? Ne dîsa wekî cem hev e.
No? Not again like being together.
Na welle. Înşallah yorim.
No really. God willing dear.
Berî ez herim, te emr e, te gotin e, te ji miletê me ra,
xelkê me ra?
Before I go, do you have a command, a saying, for our
nation, for our people?
Siheta te xweş. Xwedê barê we feqî ne, rebbil alemîn.
Health to you. May God grant you success, Lord of the
worlds.
Û dinê ji berê çêtir bibe. Û vîn qîçkê me ne, ewladê me ne,
înşallah ji berê çêtir û xweştir bibe.
And may the world become better than the past. And these
kids of ours, our children, God willing may it be better and
nicer than before.
Sihet xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Health to you, may God be pleased with you.
We jî xweş, ehlen we sehlen.
You too, welcome.
Her kesî me seyredike, tikeyne silam ke, tikeyne sê gotina
bike, gi bîr nekin.
Everyone watching us, send a greeting, say three words, so
they don't forget.
Ew nesîhatekî tikeyne, bu hemî miletê li me temaşe dike.
A piece of advice you give, for all the people watching us.
Ehlen we sehlen, selamê min ji Kurd û Kurdistanê ra, gişkar
mûnce, giyara hene.
Welcome, my greetings to Kurds and Kurdistan, all generally,
all exist.
Hono gi, wekî yek gotiye, çavê giya maç dikim.
All of them here, like someone said, I kiss the eyes of all.
We taca seran î.
You are the crown of heads.
We jî xweş.
You too.
De ta gi, wekî qîçkê me ne, gi xkbirakê ne, gi heval cîran
in. Miletê Kurd xoyîna me ye.
May God be pleased with you.
De ta gi, wekî qîçkê me ne, gi xkbirakê ne, gi heval cîran
in. Miletê Kurd xoyîna me ye.
So all of you, like our kids, all brothers, all neighbor
friends. The Kurdish nation is our blood.
Tifaqê bin, tilivizyon, bin kehrebê, bin der... ji çira ne
we?
Be united, television, be electricity, be out... isn't it
from the lamp?
Pêşketin.
Development.
Pêşketin yanê.
Development meaning.
Na noko jî rûyê dinê, na çên çûrek neder, ê xilayê xwe
fakir... li vî tiştî seykin. Tîk tok seykin, li Feysbûk
seykin.
No now too the face of the world, no going out to pastures
outside, they... their emptiness... watch this thing. Watch
TikTok, watch Facebook.
Tîk Toka te heye? Ê te qenahîm mutabe'a ke. Te li me seyr
ke.
Do you have TikTok? Will you follow my channel? Will you
watch us?
Ez tarê qenahî ya xwe têk im.
I will put my channel in yours.
Yê ehlen we sehlen.
Yeah welcome.
Tê mutabe'a ke?
Will you follow?
Ehlen we sehlen lawo.
Welcome son.
Û me'nîna vî ta pir xweş e.
And this sentiment of yours is very nice.
Ehlen we sehlen. Û însanê gi d’wa kû mezin, cîyê xwe li ser
serê me ye. Serî û çav be.
Welcome. And humans who are... great, their place is on our
head. On head and eyes.
Însanê gi di mezinê xwe tê ne, hew jî tê ne.
Humans who don't have their elders, don't have that either.
Erê, lê divê kebnî mera tinebe, xêrê ecerî mera tine.
Yes, but if we don't have the old, we don't have the good of
the new.
Ehlen we sehlen yorim.
Welcome dear.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Hîn jî gi qîçkê me ne. Xwedê ji te razî be.
You are all our kids. May God be pleased with you.
De bi xatirê te.
So goodbye.
Bes bên merikê kurmanc e... wele el-ezîm ji min re, yanê
qîçkê me ne. Ewladê me ro ne.
Just say a Kurdish man... I swear to God for me, meaning
they are our kids. They are our children.
Ehlen we sehlen, ji qenewa ra jî, û siheta we jî xweş, û
Xwedê hîn we pêşxîne înşallah.
Welcome, to your channel too, and health to you, and may God
advance you further, God willing.
Kurmanco gi pêşxîne.
Advance all Kurds.
Amîn.
Amen.
Sihet xweş.
Thanks.
We jî xweş, ehlen we sehlen.
You too, welcome.
Miletê kîbar û delal, heva bîrêt gundî Hemo ye.
Noble and dear nation, this is the well of Hemo village.
Wek jim re xeber danim, darî Çinare, emrê vê, gundî dibêjin
ser 500 sal raye.
As I tell you, the Plane tree, its age, the village says it
is over 500 years.
Me ji pîrê xwedê ye, ser bîrê me got tarîxî gundî yazmîş
kirine? Yazmîş nekirine.
We asked the elder of God, on memory we said did they write
the history of the village? They didn't write it.
Bes wek jim re xeber dan e, emrê vê bîrê û vê darê, hafizê
min xelkê gundî gotiye, ser pêncsed sal raye.
But as they told me, the age of this well and this tree,
according to my memory what village people said, is over
five hundred years.
Û jim re yazmîş ken, înkî hatine ber vê bîrê û ber vê darê.
And write for us, who has come to this well and this tree.
Û bimînin, heta talî vîdyo, em kê çin tiştê de xweş û kîbar
pêş we kin.
And stay, until the end of the video, we will present some
nice and noble things to you.
Miletê kîbar û delal, em darbas bûn ser Kaniya Gundî Hemo.
Noble and dear nation, we passed to the Spring of Hemo
Village.
Wekî min ji we re behs kir, li vê derê, berê milet dihatin,
kincê xwe dişûştin.
As I mentioned to you, in this place, in the past people
used to come, washed their clothes.
Heta me got em herin jêr, em hinekî avê vexwin.
We even said let's go down, let's drink some water.
Heger av hebe.
If there is water.
Werin em bi hevre herin jêr.
Come let's go down together.
Em sekin, li vê derê, kaniyê av heye lê tune ye.
Let's see, in this place, if the spring has water or not.
De werin bi hevre, em dakevin jêr.
So come together, let's go down.
Miletê kîbar û delal, em darbas bûn ser Kaniya Gundî Hemo
bîn.
Noble and dear nation, we passed to the Spring of Hemo
Village.
Belê av hişk e. Hessa l'boran pir ne bariya û wê ma'nê...
kanî nake.
Yes the water is dry. Now not much rain fell and that
meaning... the spring doesn't flow.
Cem e, darî tûyê heye. Heva tûyê spî ye, û guhawayê reşik e.
Next to it, there is a mulberry tree. This is a white
mulberry, and the other is a black one.
Tûyê reşik, gu pîştî heva xilas dibê, hewa çêdike. Belê
gîndî hişîn dibê.
Black mulberry, when this one finishes, that one produces.
Yes the village becomes green.
Û cem me jî darî tûyê belê hew kaniyê heye. Manzerê gundî
pir xweş e, pir kîbar e.
And next to us is the mulberry tree, yes, it's just the
spring. The view of the village is very nice, very noble.
Bi mera bin, heta talî vîdyo, em kê hinek tîştê de xweş û
kîbar pêş we kin.
Stay with us, until the end of the video, we will present
some other nice and noble things to you.
Vê dara, heqî orta gopkê gundekî dipaqe...
This tree, rightfully in the middle of the peak of the
village...
Heva tûyê reş e. Heva jî darî tûyê spî ye. Darik pir mezin e
maşallah.
This is the black mulberry. And this is the white mulberry
tree. A very big tree mashallah.
Pir kevnar e.
Very ancient.
Belê kaniya di vira derdike, kanî jî hisol tine ye.
Yes the spring comes out from here, the spring is not there
this year.
Wek me ji we re xeber daye... heva deştî gundî Hemo ye.
Kaniyê gundî Hemo.
As we told you... this is the plain of Hemo village. The
spring of Hemo village.
Pir xweş e, pir kîbar e. Bi mera bin, em kê çiqo vîdyo pêş
we kin.
Very nice, very noble. Stay with us, we will present a bit
of video to you.
Li deştî gundî Hemo dikeve, pir kevnar e.
It falls in the plain of Hemo village, it's very ancient.
Tarîx ser hebe, em ê ji we re bisekinin lê...
If there is history on it, we will stop for you but...
Tarîx ser yazmîş nekirine.
They haven't written history on it.
Heva poxer e, ez ne şaş bim.
This is a conduit, if I am not mistaken.
Belê poxer di vir da bû.
Yes, the conduit was in here.
Û heva no jî, wek berê, avî xwe dikirne, tiştî xwe dikirne.
And this one too, like before, they did their water, did
their things.
Belê pir kevnar xwan e.
Yes, they look very ancient.
Li deştî gundî Hemo dikeve.
It falls in the plain of Hemo village.
Werin em darbas bin, ser sirinca avê.
Come let's pass to the water cistern.
Heva sirinca avê ye.
This is the water cistern.
Heva ji jêr tê?
Does this come from below?
Ji jêr tê, baranê dikeve derê, darbas...
It comes from below, rain falls there, passes...
Maşallah deşt pir xweş e, pir kîbar e.
Mashallah the plain is very nice, very noble.
Meletê kibar û delal, ma kanîk li vêr hebe ma neyê vexwarin?
Gentle and dear people, if there is a spring here, won't it
be drunk?
Me bîrek li vêr hebe ma neyê vexwarin?
If there is a well here, won't it be drunk?
Noha jî bi me ra bin, em kê derbasî me'serê bin.
Now stay with us, we will move to the 'me'ser' (wine press).
Go me'serek li vêr heye, hek em ji we ra bisiwirînin.
They said there is a 'me'ser' here, let us film it for you.
Bîr nekin me de'm bikin... ên ceme binê dikin maşalla, ê li
me seyr dikin hene, bes iştîrak nakin.
Don't forget to support us... those who join us are
mashallah, there are those who watch us, but they don't
subscribe.
Qenalê me iştîrak kin, em ê bi de'mê we serkevin, û ez bi we
heme.
Subscribe to our channel, we will succeed with your support,
and I exist because of you.
Meletê kibar û delal...
Gentle and dear people...
... me'serî gundî Xabû heva.
... this is the wine press of Xabu village.
Pir kevnar e. Berê vderê meqbes bî, mekbes.
It is very ancient. Previously this place was a press, a
press.
Pir kevnar e.
It is very ancient.
Bile ez nizanim em kênin têkhevlênî kênin, em seh kin.
But I don't know if we can mix (enter?), let's look.
Pir kevnar e, berê vderê Mekbez bî.
It is very ancient, this place used to be a Press.
Wek ji we ra xeber dane, go Mekbezê cilka jî li şînê hene.
As they told you, they said the Clothes Press is also in the
place.
Bile ez nizanim em kênin têkhevlênî kênin, em seh kin.
But I don't know if we can mix (enter?), let's look.
Meletê kibar û delal, noha jî lehzek, tirba Ziwara muşareke
kin.
Gentle and dear people, now for a moment, partake in the
tomb of Ziwara (Pilgrims).
Xudê rehma xwe li mirîyê we giya ke.
May God have mercy on all your dead.
Silav û rêz, ji şênîyê gundî Xabû re.
Greetings and respect, to the residents of Xabu village.
Bûra li erdê deşta me seyr dikin, yanî kî dera bin saeta we
xweş.
Brothers who are watching our plain land, wherever you are,
have a good time.
Istîqbalek pir xweş we da me.
You gave us a very nice welcome.
Noha jî ez ê sa we tirba ji we re teswîr kim.
Now I will film the tomb for you.
Xudê rehma xwe li mirîyê we giya ke.
May God have mercy on all your dead.
Ê ku tê... di kofkê Gendiso... Xudê emrê dirêj bidê...
The one who comes... in Gendiso's hut... May God give him
long life...
Yek ji rehmetî be, Xudê rehma xwe li dê û bavê we ke, li
kalkê we ke, li pîrkê we ke.
If one is deceased, may God have mercy on your mother and
father, on your grandfather, on your grandmother.
Ji noha jî we re tirba bisewirînim.
From now on I will film the tomb for you.
Û deşta gundî Xabû jî ji we re sewirînim.
And I will film the plain of Xabu village for you.
Ka bi me ra bin heta dawîya vîdyo.
Stay with us until the end of the video.
Serê malan darek lê lê, darek lê.
There is a tree above the houses, oh my, a tree.
Dinya malan darek lê lê, darek lê.
The world of houses is a tree, oh my, a tree.
Her malek da yarek lê lê, yarek lê.
In every house there is a lover, oh my, a lover.
Serê yarê şarek lê lê, şarek lê.
On the lover's head is a scarf, oh my, a scarf.
Serê malan gûzek lê lê, gûzek lê.
Above the houses is a walnut tree, oh my, a walnut tree.
Dinya malan gûzek lê lê, gûzek lê.
The world of houses is a walnut tree, oh my, a walnut tree.
Her malek da qîzek lê lê, qîzek lê.
In every house there is a girl, oh my, a girl.
Serê qîzê zêrek lê lê, zêrek lê.
On the girl's head is a gold coin, oh my, a gold coin.
Serê malan nûkek lê lê, nûkek lê.
Above the houses is a bud, oh my, a bud.
Dinya malan nûkek lê lê, nûkek lê.
The world of houses is a bud, oh my, a bud.
Her malek da bûkek lê lê, bûkek lê.
In every house there is a bride, oh my, a bride.
Serê bûkê kofik lê lê, kofik lê.
On the bride's head is a headdress (kofik), oh my, a
headdress.
Serê yarê şarek lê lê, şarek lê.
On the lover's head is a scarf, oh my, a scarf.
Serê malan darek lê lê, darek lê.
There is a tree above the houses, oh my, a tree.
Dinya malan darek lê lê, darek lê.
The world of houses is a tree, oh my, a tree.