Merheba cîran, hogir û heval, silav û rêzên min ji miletekî
me yê tebahî ra heye.
Hello neighbors, friends and companions, I have my greetings
and respect for our entire nation.
Ez xwas nes silavan dişînim ji qenalê "Hatim li Efrîn".
I send greetings to everyone in general from the channel "I
came to Afrin".
Piştgirîya xwas nes Kek Xelîl Sîno, kurtekî vîyî piştî nîyo.
I ask for the special support of everyone for Brother Xelîl
Sîno, this is a short [clip] from this afternoon.
Ez hêvî me, gimeletî me yî xweş û şêrîn û delal, vê qenalê
"Hatim li Efrîn" daem ke, û îştîrak ke.
I hope that our beautiful, sweet, and dear nation will
support this channel "I came to Afrin" and subscribe.
Û destek ke bi Kek Xelîl Sîno de.
And give a hand of support to Brother Xelîl Sîno.
Çunke tiştekî xweş û şêrîn ji miletê qedîmî ne.
Because these are beautiful and sweet things from our
ancient nation.
Û em dixwazin roj bi roj pêşkeve û tiştên pur xweş û şêrîn
li ser Efrîn û ser turasê Efrîn ji me ra biqedîmîne.
And we want it to progress day by day and present to us very
beautiful and sweet things about Afrin and Afrin's heritage.
Ku em jî di vê gurbetîyê, sebrê xwe û kêfa xwe bi vî tiştî
bînin, bi vê nerînê hînin.
So that we, in this exile, may find our patience and joy in
this thing, and through this viewing.
Wek hunermendekî ji hunermendê Efrînê, ez kak Hemûde Stêr,
silav û rêzên min ji miletekî me yê tebahî ra heye. Spas.
As an artist among the artists of Afrin, I am brother Hemûde
Stêr, my greetings and respect to our entire nation. Thank
you.
...û lezel. Duxtor hene, muhendis hene, muhamî hene. Yanî
seqafeta xwe pir pêşda ne.
...and eternity [by God's will]. There are doctors, there
are engineers, there are lawyers. Meaning their culture is
very advanced.
Wela pê ne kirim, ebeden. Jina ewle mirî min da.
Well, He [God] didn't do it for me, never. The first wife
died on me.
Pênc ji me ra revî.
Five ran away from us.
Her şûlekî gotî... "hewa ke".
Every task, he said... "do it like this".
Nesîb e ka.
It is fate, uncle.
Nesîb e ka. Xwedê ne kir qismetê min.
It is fate, uncle. God did not make it my destiny.
Du çel û rûnişt mişt têne. Hêlik têne. Yanî bê gundê me
şikandina xwe pir e.
Two hundred and forty residents are in it. Some come [and
go]. Meaning, our village is very broken/empty.
Te got çi heye?
You said what is there?
Erê. Êêê... mûna ka şebab deryin, me sefe...
Yes. Uh... now the youth are outside [abroad],
unfortunately...
Me kinin mewadê xwe. Ne bi hormona taye. Em dikin şûna
fewata.
We don't put [chemicals] in our ingredients. Not with
hormones. We put it in the place of death [natural].
Mame çûndina berê... bes fewat bîn, em dikevine şûna
gindikan.
Regarding the way of the past... as long as there was death,
we would fall into the place of the little villages.
Merheba miletekî buha û delal. Ez hatim bi vîdyoyekî xweş û
vîdyoyekî ecêb.
Hello precious and dear nation. I came with a nice video and
a wonderful video.
Vîdyoya min îro li gundê Birîmce ye. Silav û rêz ji xelkê
gundê Birîmce ra.
My video today is in the village of Brimja. Greetings and
respect to the people of Brimja village.
Hûn bi xêr hatin ser qenata "Hatim li Efrîn".
Welcome to the channel "I came to Afrin".
Ka naha bi me ra bin, bi dilekî xweş û geş. Emê derbas gundê
Birîmce bin.
Now stay with us, with a happy and bright heart. We will
pass into the village of Brimja.
Saeta we xweş û bi me ra bin heta tola vîdyoyê.
Have a good time and stay with us until the end of the
video.
Min dil da te... te çil min kir...
I gave my heart to you... you made me wither...
Hêvîya te bûm... te min jibîr kir...
I was your hope... you forgot me...
Xanî ye bî... te bi xwe re bir...
It was a house... you took it with you...
Ci xwayînî... te çil min kir...
What a betrayal... you made me wither...
Ne kul û derdên te... ne naz û xemên te...
Not your wounds and pains... not your coquetry and
worries...
Ne name ên naşînin...
Nor the letters they don't send...
Ne tas e şava te... ne nanek destê te...
Not the bowl of your nights... not a bread from your hand...
Welleh ez naxwazim...
I swear I do not want it...
Ne kul û derdên te... ne naz û xemên te...
Not your wounds and pains... not your coquetry and
worries...
Ne name ên naşînin...
Nor the letters they don't send...
Ne tas e şava te...
Not the bowl of your nights...
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Çawayî te bi xêr?
How are you, are you well?
Henîf Xelîl Omer.
Xalê Henîf. Çend salî ye Xalê Henîf?
Uncle Henîf. How old are you Uncle Henîf?
Heyştê.
Eighty.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bide te.
May God give you a long life.
Ê te ra jî be.
To you as well.
Ez Xelîl ji gundê Baedîna, ji qenala "Hatim li Efrîn", îro
em mêvan darê gundê Birîmce ne.
I am Xelîl from the village of Baedîna, from the channel "I
came to Afrin", today we are guests of the village of
Brimja.
Ye ehlen we sehlen. Bi ser çava û bi ser seran.
Oh, welcome. On my eyes and on my head [You are very
welcome].
Bi te û Baedîna jî.
To you and to Baedîna as well.
Xalê Henîf, em kî nehat, tişkî, tikî ji me ra xeber de ser
gundê Birîmce.
Uncle Henîf, since we came, tell us a little something about
the village of Brimja.
Eywa.
Yes.
Despêkê, em derbas bin, xê nav lê kirin Birîmce? Ji me ra
xeber de.
Initially, let's start, why did they name it Brimja? Tell us
about it.
Eywa. Bi Xwedê, navê xwe, yanî... berê me "Xidirk" bûn.
Yes. By God, its name, meaning... formerly we were "Xidirk"
[Little Khidir].
Û Xidirk xera bû, hin hatin vir, hin jî çûn Xidirya.
And Xidirk was destroyed/ruined, some came here, and some
went to Xidirya.
Û li vê derê yek hebû, wekî me bîstî he, me'ne xilaf tê tine
be.
And in this place there was one person, as I've heard,
meaning may there be no mistake in it.
Go navê xwe Birîm bû. Ceh difrût.
They said his name was Birîm. He sold barley.
Nav lê nan "Birîmê Ceh", "Birîmce".
They named him "Barley Birîm", "Birîmce".
Û vî gundî du aîle ne.
And in this village, there are two families.
Yek Birîmce, yek jî Usê, Ûskar e? Na.
One is Brimce, one is Usê [Yusuf], is it Uskar? No.
Despêkê, însanek li vir hebû navê xwe Birîm bû?
Initially, there was a person here whose name was Birîm?
Eywa.
Yes.
Ceh difrût?
He sold barley?
Eywa.
Yes.
Piştî wî nav li ser gund sebitî Birîmce?
After him, the name stuck to the village as Brimja?
Birîmce. Yek ji aîla Birîmce bû, û yek jî ji mala Usê bû.
Brimja. One was from the family of Brimja, and one was from
the house of Usê.
Yek ji mala Usê bû?
One was from the house of Usê?
Eywa.
Yes.
Xalê Henîf, gundê Birîmce, dore çiqas sal e?
Uncle Henîf, the village of Brimja, how many years old is it
[approximately]?
Welle ez bi deqet nizanim, bes teqrîben gerek çarsed sal
hebe.
Well, I don't know exactly, but approximately it must be
four hundred years.
Dore çarsed sal e vî gundî.
Around four hundred years for this village.
Eywa.
Yes.
Xalê Henîf, niha gundê Birîmce dore çiqas mal e?
Uncle Henîf, now regarding the village of Brimja, about how
many houses is it?
Sed û çel.
One hundred and forty.
Dore sed û çel malî ye.
It is around one hundred and forty houses.
Eywa.
Yes.
Çiqas di aîle de rûdinin?
How many families [clans] live in it?
Wek heftê aîle heye.
There are like seven families.
Wek heftê aîle di gundê Birîmce da niha rûdinin.
About seven families are living in the village of Brimja
now.
Eywa.
Yes.
Gundê Birîmce, Xalê Henîf, wextê te giştî, însanê mezin,
mêrekî, pîrekî, pir çi kar dikirin li vî gundî?
The village of Brimja, Uncle Henîf, in your general time,
the old people, a man, a woman, what work did they mostly do
in this village?
Karê vî gundî muzare' ne.
The work of this village is farming [agriculture].
Û seqafe... yanî ji... teqrîben çoyî kurmancî pir e, seqafî
vî gundî.
And culture [education]... meaning from... roughly more than
any Kurdish place, the culture of this village [is high].
Museqefîn têda pir in, û mubteda û guh salê hezar nehsed
pêncî û heyştan...
There are many educated people in it, and starting from the
year nineteen fifty-eight...
Wek deh û du... musaqef me hebûn, bekelorya wergirtin.
About ten or two [twelve?]... we had educated ones, they
obtained the Baccalaureate.
Gundê Birîmce pir ecyal derxistin.
The village of Brimja produced many generations.
Pir ecyal derxistin. Û lezel.
It produced many generations. And until eternity.
Duxtor hene, muhendis hene, muhamî hene.
There are doctors, there are engineers, there are lawyers.
Yanî seqafeta xwe pir pêşda ne.
Meaning their culture is very advanced.
Erê.
Yes.
Seqafeta xwe pêşda ne, le êno yek li vî gundî hebû, dixwast
zîl, seqafî bibe.
Their culture is advanced, because there was one person in
this village, he wanted the generation to be educated.
Yek li vî gundî hebû, dixwast zîl seqafî bibe, digotin
Hemîdê Fîlik.
There was one person in this village, he wanted the
generation to be educated, they called him Hemîdê Fîlik.
Naha xweş e?
Is he well now?
Na.
No.
Rehmetî bûye.
He has passed away.
Rehmetî bû, rehme li mirîyê te be.
He passed away, mercy upon your dead.
Mektebê î'dadî, make çêkir, du gund li me ra bûn, Mabeta û
gundê Hisê.
A preparatory school, he built it, there were two villages
[competing] with us, Mabeta and Gundê Hisê.
Vê însanî, wereqek da me, û gul gunda bigerin.
This person gave us a paper, and [said] go around the
villages.
Wake le mektebê li vî gundî çêkim, û çêkir.
So that I can build a school in this village, and he built
it.
Û çêkir, piştî wî jî gundê didûr Birîmce jî, ecyal hatin
dixwand li gundê Birîmce da.
And he built it, and after that, from villages far from
Brimja, generations came to study in the village of Brimja.
Dihatin dixwandin, erê.
They came and studied, yes.
Û gundê Birîmce pir...
And the village of Brimja is very...
Seqafê xwe zêde ye.
Its culture/education is high.
Seqafê xwe mekin e.
Its culture is strong.
Eywa. Wekî din, sen'etê xwe zîra'a ne.
Yes. Otherwise, their profession is agriculture.
Û meşhûr e bi simaqê, bi... yebrax, bi tirşê... ewê bi
zeytûna, bi tir... yanî tişt hene, fistiq, filan, hewa
meşhûr in. Vî gunda meşhûr e bi vî işî.
And it is famous for sumac, for... grape leaves, for
pickles... for olives, for figs... meaning there are things,
pistachios, and so on, they are famous like that. This
village is famous for this work.
Xalê Henîf, em niha dixwazin tiştekî ji me ra xeber de, di
heyata te da derbas bûyî û heyata niha te bîr nekirî.
Uncle Henîf, we now want you to tell us something that
passed in your life and you haven't forgotten in life now.
Û tu ji me ra xeber de, însanekî dilê me sar dikin, guneh û
be'l min, ewê gulê min in, însan nesîbê xweşbînê neke.
And tell us, [about] a person who cools our hearts [hurts
us], my sins and bad luck, those are my complaints, a person
shouldn't make their fate optimistic [in vain].
Ez dixwazin tiştek di heyata te da derbas bûyî, tu ji me ra
xeber de, eger rind be, eger ne rind be, tu ji me ra xeber
de, ku em te bîr nekirî heyata niha û ke em jî pê ra bin.
I want something that passed in your life, tell us about it,
whether it was good, whether it was not good, tell us, that
you haven't forgotten until now so that we can be with it
[understand it] too.
Welle, tiştê me jibîr nekirî... da berê, seqafe hindik bû, û
xelk gil palê bû, li şixra bû, li car cara bûn, ewa xweşbîna
dinyayê noka rind bî ye.
Well, the thing we haven't forgotten... back then, education
was scarce, and people were all laborers, in forced labor,
in hard times, regarding the optimism of the world, now it
has become good.
Vê çaxê dinya... texellef bû, noka rind bî ye.
At that time the world... was backward, now it has become
good.
Û însanek li vî gundî hebû, şimara dihat, êvarê çêrokê wel
didan. Heta sibê me xew nedikir, me guh lîyê çêrokê dikir.
And there was a person in this village, coming at night, in
the evening he told stories like that. Until morning we
didn't sleep, we listened to the stories.
Çêrnûka difirûşo... Navê rehmetî jî Cemîlê Wehîd bû.
Selling stories... The name of the deceased was Cemîlê
Wehîd.
Çêrnûka wel didan, te bes qiloqê xwe ser dan.
He told stories in such a way, you just rested your head on
it [listened intently].
Qosî xweş ewle didan, ne radyo hebûn, ne tilfîzyon, tişt
tunebûn yanî.
He told them so beautifully, there were no radios, no
televisions, there was nothing, meaning.
Hêşta dinya her çû... rind bû noka.
Still, the world kept going... it is good now.
Û tiştê me ji gundê hilînanî, yanî me yekşûl jê hilînan...
mesele firoşo çêkir, û hevalê gundê çêkirin, û diboqa çêkir,
û heta vê çaxê... baş xora gulê dinê de... ê bû pêncî sal me
jibîr kir.
And the things we picked up from the village, meaning we
picked up a craft... for example making shoes [footwear],
and village friends made them, and making specialized shoes,
and until that time... well, putting it in the words of the
world... it's been fifty years [since] we forgot it.
He, heyata me da hev derbas bû.
Yes, in our life it passed like that.
Wekî din, karê me pale bû, şixre bû, car car bûn, he. Evê
karê dikir.
Otherwise, our work was labor, forced labor, hard times,
yes. They did this work.
Heyata berê... cefa bû.
Life in the past... was suffering.
Cefa bû. Noka bû hêsin... bû hêsin, qûlayî bû. Bes milet
nema.
It was suffering. Now it has become easy... it became easy,
[before] it was slavery. But the people didn't remain.
Milet nema ge... derket derva. Kori qûlayî digerim. Ev işta.
The people didn't remain... they went outside [abroad]. I am
looking for the son of slavery [hard workers]. That is it.
Xalê Henîf, naha em dixwazin nesîhetekî bidî miletê me.
Uncle Henîf, now we want you to give a piece of advice to
our people.
Nesîhet, berê digo nesîhet bi hêşterikî ye. Noka fidîhe ye.
Advice, before they said advice is [worth] a camel. Now it
is a scandal.
Vê şexsî noka, eger vêra bibêjî, bira, ma re şaşe, dibê tu
nizanî, tî xerifî ye.
This person now, if you say to him, brother, don't walk
wrong, he says you don't know, you have become senile.
Yanî ew kêm bûye. Sîqat hindik maye.
Meaning that has decreased. Trust remains little.
Sîqat hindik maye û însanê ku dixwazin de nesîha bigirin, ew
jî kêm bûne.
Trust remains little and people who want to take advice,
they have also decreased.
Kêm bûne. Eywa. Yanî nesîhetê gel yekî bikî, dibê her la tî
xerifî, ê axerifî me bina gerek, axa nesîhetê nakim. Mesele
hewa ye.
They have decreased. Yes. Meaning if you give advice to
someone, he says go away you are senile, [so I say] I don't
need to be senile, sir, I won't give advice. The issue is
like that.
Saeta te xweş Xalê Henîf.
Bless you Uncle Henîf.
Saeta te xweş, ehlen we sehlen.
Bless you, welcome.
Ez pir kêfxweş bûm, îro ez mêvandarê gundê Birîmce bim.
I was very happy that today I was a guest of the village of
Brimja.
Bi ti selamê, ehlen we sehlen.
With peace, welcome.
Berî ku ez dest bidim te, merte te got te l'me hene?
Before I shake your hand, a while ago you said you have
[children] with us [abroad]?
Saeta te xweş û Xwedê emrê kî bide te.
Bless you and may God give you life.
Amîn ya reb.
Amen, oh Lord.
Niha her kesê li te seyr dike, ew qîçkê te li derva hene,
tikanî silam ke.
Now everyone watching you, those children of yours outside,
you can greet them.
Ê teben, silavê mi ji garan hene, heçî il derva, û gib xêr
bin û gib silamet bin.
Yes of course, my greetings to the neighbors/all, everyone
outside, may they be well and safe.
Gi ti zewicî ye, qîçkê te hene, Xwedê qîçkê te bihêle. Û gi
tu ne zewicî, Xwedê yekê bi qismetê te ke.
If you are married, you have children, may God keep your
children. And if you are not married, may God grant one to
your destiny.
Lawik heft in, li derva nin. Yekî li Heleb e, yekî li
Holenda ye, sisê li Fransa ne, û didil Almanya ne.
The boys are seven, they are outside [abroad]. One is in
Aleppo, one is in Holland, three are in France, and two are
in Germany.
Î tev... jî hindik... bekelorya û jor da ye. Ê din jî
muhendis ne.
All of them... are a little... [educated to] Baccalaureate
and above. The others are engineers.
Navê wan jî bibêje ji me ra.
Tell us their names too.
Navê wan...
Their names...
Û ez jî razî me, Xwedê ji wan razî be û Xwedê rizqê wan
bişîne.
And I am pleased too, may God be pleased with them and God
send their provision.
Û Xwedê emrê kî bide te jî, ji wan de jî.
And may God give a [long] life to you, and to them too.
Amîn ya.
Amen.
Dikinî navî gihenda hewal de û silava ji wan ra bişîne, ey
gel te seyr kin, pir kêfxweş bin.
You can give all their names and send greetings to them, hey
when they watch you, they will be very happy.
Emê ji bîdayê de werin, Şerîf, lawê minî mezin e. Muhendizî
kehrabe bû.
We will come from the beginning, Şerîf, is my eldest son. He
was an electrical engineer.
Wa pir silav dikim, wa pir jê razî me.
I greet him a lot, I am very pleased with him.
Didûra 'Umer e, mu'awinê mudîrê matarê Heleb bû, hew jî
muhendis e, ez wî jî razî me.
Second is 'Umer, he was the deputy director of Aleppo
airport, he is also an engineer, I am pleased with him too.
Didûra Emîr e...
Second [Next] is Emîr...
...muraqebê zevî, ew jî muhendis e, ew jî li Rozîme.
...field monitoring, he is also an engineer, he is also at
Rozime.
Û yek li Holenda ye, ew jî bekelorya ye, ew jî li Rozîme,
min têj Efrîn.
And one is in Holland, he also has a bachelor's, he is also
at Rozime, I say in Afrin.
Û yekê din li Fransa ye, wî teqrîben nexwend, du-sê sal
xwend hindik, ew jî terzî bû.
And another one is in France, he almost didn't study,
studied two-three years a little, he was a tailor.
Û ê din jî... kuafer bû.
And the other one... was a hairdresser.
Ew jî xwend heta bekelorya û paşê jî bû kuafer.
He also studied until his bachelor's and then became a
hairdresser.
Noka elhemdulila îşê wan rind e, û Xwedê qîzkê te bihêle û
wan jî bihêle.
Now, praise be to God, their work is good, and may God spare
your daughter and spare them too.
Amîn, amîn ya reb. Spas.
Amen, amen oh Lord. Thanks.
...
... (Music starts)
Tu ji hemya ciwantirî / Nazik şêrîn gulperî.
You are more beautiful than all / Delicate sweet angel.
Ev canê te bê hempa ye / Ser erşê dil tu serwer î.
This soul of yours is matchless / You are the ruler on the
throne of the heart.
Tu ji hemya ciwantirî / Nazik şêrîn gulperî.
You are more beautiful than all / Delicate sweet angel.
Ev canê te bê hempa ye / Ser erşê dil tu serwer î.
This soul of yours is matchless / You are the ruler on the
throne of the heart.
Min bibe ji waran, dil bibe ji xwarê / Ey yarê, ha hevalê.
Take me from the lands, take the heart from below / Oh love,
oh friend.
Min bibe, dil bibe.
Take me, take the heart.
Min bibe ji waran, dil bibe ji xwarê / Ey yarê, ha hevalê.
Take me from the lands, take the heart from below / Oh love,
oh friend.
Min bibe, dil bibe.
Take me, take the heart.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlên we sehlen.
Welcome.
Navê te bi xêr?
May I have your name?
Sebah e.
It is Sabah.
Xaltîka Sebah, çend salî ye?
Auntie Sabah, how old are you?
Pêncûsê, pêncûçar.
Fifty-three, fifty-four.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bide û siheta xweş bide.
May God give a long life and good health.
Ez xelkê gundê Baedîna me, ji qenata "Welatê Me Efrîn", hûn
mêvanên me ne, xwediyê malê ne, em mêvanên we ne.
Amen.
Ez xelkê gundê Baedîna me, ji qenata "Welatê Me Efrîn", hûn
mêvanên me ne, xwediyê malê ne, em mêvanên we ne.
I am from the village of Baadina, from the channel "Our
Country Afrin", you are our guests, [actually] you are the
hosts, we are your guests.
Ehlên we sehlen. Bi xêr û silametî.
Welcome. In goodness and safety.
Xaltîka Sebah, çend qîz û kur te hene?
Auntie Sabah, how many daughters and sons do you have?
Welle ez azeb im ez.
Well, I am single.
Aa tu hîn negiha ye mêr nekiriye?
Ah, you haven't reached [that stage], haven't married?
Na, welle min mêr nekir.
No, honestly I didn't marry.
Tu bi hesret mayî? Çima?
Are you left with longing? Why?
Welle wilo bû nesîb.
Well, that's how fate was.
Yanî sedeb çi bû? Tu kînî, sedeb jêra xeber de.
I mean what was the reason? You are holding back, tell us
the reason.
Welle pê neikirî ebeden. Jê ewelî emrê min da... wilo zû min
rê nekir.
Well, it didn't happen at all. From the beginning of my
age... I didn't engage quickly like that.
Hêwşî wekî gotî... Hawa ke... nesîbeke.
Whatever as they said... Like this... it's a destiny.
Xwedê nekir qismetê min.
God didn't make it my fortune.
Û tu razî ye?
And you are content?
He, razî me, welle ne poşman im. Ez bi kêfa me, elhemdulila.
Yes, I am content, honestly I am not regretful. I am happy
[as I am], praise be to God.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bide û siheta xweş bide.
May God give a long life and good health.
Siheta te xweş.
Health to you.
Xwedê her hebe.
May God always exist [for you].
Sihet xweş, erê.
Good health, yes.
Xaltîka Sebah noka tu kê ji me ra xeber de, berê we dirûn
çawa bi destan dikir? Wextê te kiştîye.
Auntie Sabah, now you will tell us, how did you do the
harvest by hand in the past? The time of agriculture.
Dirûnî... Ez giştime, bi parzûn çêdikirin û bi dasê
didirûtin.
The harvest... I reached it, they used to make finger guards
and harvest with the sickle.
Her sê çar parzûn dixistin ser... tiliyên destan.
They used to put three or four finger guards on... the
fingers of the hands.
Paşê mokîna destan derketin.
Later, hand machines came out.
Du destar hebûn, lingan derketin.
There were two handles, legs stuck out.
Du ye lingan ra jî, noka yek car hebûn (xerebûn?). Heba
çîçke sa’be.
Two for the legs too... (unclear). If there were thorns, it
was difficult.
Ka ewa çî ye?
What is that?
Ewa das e.
That is a sickle.
Tu karî nîşanî me bidî çawa hûn pê dixebitîn?
Can you show us how you worked with it?
Ewa, mesela hûn wilo digirtin û wilo didirûtin.
This, for example, you held it like this and harvested like
this.
Destê we ne diêşiya?
Did your hands not hurt?
Ee destê me diwerimîn, qerqaş dibûn, lingê me qerqaş dibûn,
diêşiyan.
Uh, our hands would swell, become cracked, our feet became
cracked, they hurt.
Zor bû yani?
It was hard, you mean?
Ee zor bû, welle zehmet bû.
Yes it was hard, honestly it was difficult.
Noka mesela cilê we çawa bûn? Fîstan bûn yan pantor bûn?
Now, for example, how were your clothes? Were they dresses
or pants?
Welle fîstan bûn.
Well, they were dresses.
We çawa dikir wextê ku kereng û tişt hebûn?
How did you manage when there were thorns and things?
Wextê kereng û tişt hebûn, me bin va pantorê... şelê erebî,
me bin va li xwe dikir.
When there were thorns and things, underneath we wore
pants... Arab style shalwar, we wore underneath.
Yan jî, ewa nekira fîstan hildikirin, hewa dikirin şele.
Wekî şela li xwe dikirin.
Or, if not that, they lifted the dress, made it like pants.
They wore it like pants.
Hawa, ev e destoya.
Like that, this is the style.
Hawa e destoya.
Like that is the style.
Mokîna berê hebûn xaltîka Sebah?
Were there machines in the past, Auntie Sabah?
Ee destan, wey noka paşê derketin... Noka bûye kehrebe.
Kehrebe.
Yes, manual ones, like later came out... Now it has become
electric. Electric.
Ê tettrîs in, ê tişt e, ê pantora didin cêz warşe, heb ke.
The ones for embroidery, for things, they give pants to the
workshop ready-made, sew them.
No, heb ne, orta qe ev gihiştinê. Orta wina têda.
No, there weren't, in the middle (back then) they didn't
reach this. In the middle of them.
Bes noka di malan da hene, hûn di malan da tinînin?
But now they are in homes, do you not have them in homes?
Lê tinînin, erê. Yê nezanin karebe bişuxilînin.
Yes, they have them. Those who don't know how to operate
electric ones.
Yê heye ser destan?
The one that is manual?
Doğrî.
Correct.
E berê kincê xwe jî bi vê mokîna didirûtin?
And in the past, did they sew their clothes with this
machine?
Erê bi vê mokîna didirûtin, û fîstanê kurmancî... tiştên
rewal dingbî. Yanê...
Yes, they sewed with this machine, and Kurmanji dresses...
colorful things. I mean...
Ew kincên noka pê nabin, noka tegro ecab derketiye der.
Those clothes now don't fit/aren't used, now strange fashion
has come out.
Derket der?
Came out?
Lê tegro noka, gî xwa dikin. Tiştê berê çûn, noka tegro git
derket der.
Yes, fashion now, they all do it. Things of the past are
gone, now all the fashion has come out.
Fîstanê kurmancî çêdikirin?
Did they make Kurmanji dresses?
E bi kurmancî, e bi nav, e ribe, el-muhîm. Tûmbetûn yani.
Yes in Kurmanji style, with names, with lining, anyway. All
kinds I mean.
Noka dîsa veitilî wek berê.
Now it has turned back like the past.
Noka dîsa...
Now again...
Erê pantorê xwe dikin, noka dîsa gî bî fîstan.
Yes they wear their pants, now again everything has become
dresses.
Fîstan rind in, lê?
Dresses are good, no?
Lê rind in, lê. Tiştê, ewî kurmanc e. Kurmanc ewî xwe ji bîr
nake.
Yes they are good, yes. The thing, that is Kurmanji. A Kurd
does not forget their own.
Tu çiqas bikî, Kurmanc ewî xwe ji bîr nake.
No matter how much you do, a Kurd doesn't forget their own.
Xaltîka Sebah em dixwazin tu ji me ra xeber de, ser berê, we
dilîst, kêfa berê we çawa dilîst?
Auntie Sabah, we want you to tell us about the past, how you
played, the fun of the past, how did you play?
Welle berê... lîstikê me "kevir" hebû.
Well, in the past... our game was "stones" (jacks).
"Şîş kompanya" ser hebû. "Xîta" hebû.
There was "Six Companies". There was "Rope".
Ê em... tişta dilîstin. Heta deh-yanzde şev em... şirtûnek
dilîstin.
And we... played things. Until ten-eleven at night we...
played a game.
Û ji wê şûnda jî, bitûşê me qebir dan ser hevdu. Qîzik kom
dibûn rûyê êdê.
And after that, in our gatherings we put things together.
Girls gathered for the holidays.
Û li bar maleke diskinîn û dilîstin.
And stood in front of a house and played.
Û xanîk çêdikirin. Hefte ezîme dikirin, xanîka da.
And made playhouses. Every week they made feasts in the
playhouses.
Vê bûkê, lebkê paçikî.
This doll/bride, the game of kissing.
Derziya didirûtin. Teşî dikirin. Fîstanê dikirin. Tiştê...
îşê yani... ê berê bî.
They sewed with needles. Spun wool. Made dresses. Things...
work I mean... of the past.
Û cilet paçî. Paçka dikirin. Û direqisîn.
And clothes kissing. They kissed. And danced.
Li berê cama Gundê Husên ewa ye.
In front of the community of Gundê Husên, that was it.
Ewa genda ye.
That Genda.
Me hewê gulukna bibirana. Û ê bi jelkerana. Û heta noka jî
nehene.
We would cut the flowers (?). And with the (?). And until
now they are not here.
Digotin te jî paçî. Wana gi... her çar pênc şitûnekî.
They said you too kiss (?). They all... every four or five
pillars.
Tiştê berê girrî bî, meşk hebû.
The thing of the past was important, there was the churn.
Dav têda dikeyand, ya pîna helak dibî. Noka xesale ne.
Churned the yogurt in it, the person would get exhausted.
Now there are washing machines.
Aa ma xesale vêxe?
Ah, does the washing machine churn it?
Ooo, nî tenikî dikirin, têda dimrin. Heta nîvro, nî tenikî
dibîn.
Oh, they put it in the tin, churned in it. Until noon, half
a tin would be done.
Ê noka firne ne. Nanî tenûr hemcamek me naxwar.
And now there are bakeries. Tannour bread, we didn't eat a
bite.
Me du... em cake elimî bûn nî tenikî.
We... we once got used to the half tin (method).
Î noka em î tenikî naxwin.
And now we don't eat the tin one.
Ê berê çû, ê noka... tişta din e, xeyrî.
The past is gone, the present... is different things, other.
Xaltîka Sebah saheta te xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be. Ez pirr
kêfxweş bûm.
Auntie Sabah, thank you, may God be pleased with you. I was
very happy.
Saheta te jî xweş. Ehlên we sehlen.
Health to you too. Welcome.
Spas ji bo te.
Thanks to you.
Jibo te ne werra. Gundê Baedîna ra.
To you and those with you. To the village of Baadina.
Mentîqa me ye, dekê me xwaletê me jwê mentîqê ne. Ehlên we
sehlen.
It is our region, our mothers and aunts are from that
region. Welcome.
E berê gî destderim te me, te gotin te nene.
In the past were they all your friends, you said you don't
have [husband/kids].
Saheta te xweş. Gule gule. Em pê hatina we kêfxweş bûn.
Health to you. Goodbye. We were happy with your coming.
Û ehlên we sehlen ji we ra.
And welcome to you.
...
... (Music starts)
Şevên çavan, dil lerizî / Pêngavên hêvî û xuzi.
Nights of the eyes, the heart trembled / Steps of hope and
desire.
Û meşeyda, çavê direş / Têrnebûm ji lêvên qirmizî.
And the lover, the black eyes / I didn't get enough of the
red lips.
Şevên çavan, dil lerizî / Pêngavên hêvî û xuzi.
Nights of the eyes, the heart trembled / Steps of hope and
desire.
Û meşeyda, çavê direş / Têrnebûm ji lêvên qirmizî.
And the lover, the black eyes / I didn't get enough of the
red lips.
Min bibe ji waran, dil bibe ji xwarê / Ey yarê, ha hevalê.
Take me from the lands, take the heart from below / Oh love,
oh friend.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlên we sehlen.
Welcome.
Navê te bi xêr?
May I have your name?
Navê min Arif e, ez xelqê Gundê Brimje me, ji mala Ehmo.
My name is Aref, I am from Brimje Village, from the House of
Ehmo.
Xalê Arif. Xalê Arif çend salî ye?
Uncle Aref. Uncle Aref, how old are you?
Emrê min... pêncûyek ketim pêncûduda.
My age... fifty-one, I entered fifty-two.
Maşella, bê le nake.
Mashallah, it doesn't show.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bide û siheta xweş bide.
May God give a long life and good health.
Buwa te jî. Xalê Arif, noka li Gundê Brimje, em derbasî
Gundê Brimje bûn, tu dikinî ji me ra xeber de, noka mekteb
çend in li Gundê Brimje?
To you as well. Uncle Aref, now in Brimje Village, we passed
into Brimje Village, can you tell us, how many schools are
there now in Brimje Village?
Mekteb xalê, li gundê me didu ne. Pirr kevn e.
Schools, uncle, in our village there are two. It's very old.
Yeka dadî... yeka îbtîdayî ye.
One is... one is primary.
Baş e ya dadî, milet gerr çû, hindik mane. Noka îbtîdayî
tenê maye.
The good one, many people left, few remain. Now only the
primary one remains.
Seydeli di vê gundî da çend in?
How many pharmacies are in this village?
Seydeli yek hebû, bê fatrekê da bû şeş heft sal in...
Seydeli hebû, Seydeli jî xira kir, mêrik çû welatê xwe,
Seydeli tine ye.
There was one pharmacy, in a period about six-seven years
ago... There was a pharmacy, he closed the pharmacy too, the
man went to his country, there is no pharmacy.
Ne zihbî li vir bû?
Wasn't it much/long here?
Na zihbî li viderê bû, û ê meriya... hem xûcî came bû, hem
seydeli vekiribû, û çû.
No, it was over there, and the people's... he was both a
mosque caretaker and had opened a pharmacy, and he left.
Bîrê d’avê, dikinî ji me ra xeber de, çend in li Gundê
Brimje?
Water wells, can you tell us, how many are in Brimje
Village?
Gundê Brimje, bîrê avê wek bîst bîr, bîst û pênc bîr heye di
malan da. Hene.
Brimje Village, water wells, there are like twenty, twenty-
five wells in the houses. There are.
Bes bîra em jê avê dikişînin gund noka, bîra hukmet xira bû.
Motora gund, el-muhîm ew bû, çênekirin.
But the well we draw water from for the village now, the
government well broke down. The village motor, anyway that
was it, they didn't fix it.
Bîrek din heye, dibêjin Bîra Gûş. Darek mezin çinare, heye
li binî gund e.
There is another well, they call it Bîra Gûş. There is a big
plane tree, it is at the bottom of the village.
Em darrin, wal de ser heye, em... sîtera dadigirin.
We go, there is a trough on it, we... fill the cisterns.
Yek jê avê dikişîne jî ez im. Xeyrî min gund tine ne.
One who draws water from it is me. Other than me, there is
no one in the village.
Ez avê dikişînim, telebiyata gund ez dimeşînim.
I draw the water, I fulfill the village's requests.
Bîrê d’avê jî li Gundê Brimje da hene?
Are there water wells in Brimje Village too?
Hene, wek bîst bîr, bîst û pênc bîr heye di malan da ne, her
kesî bîrek li ber derê mala xwe kolaye.
There are, like twenty, twenty-five wells inside houses,
everyone has dug a well in front of their house door.
Ê ku bîrê xwa heye, heye. Ê tina ye jî bi sîtera em jêra
dikişînin. El-muhîm umûr îdare dikin.
Those who have their own well, have it. Those who don't, we
draw for them with cisterns. Anyway, they manage affairs.
Kîbar in. Xalê Arif, noka li Gundê Brimje, meqbes di vê
gundî da çend in?
Very nice. Uncle Aref, now in Brimje Village, how many
presses are in this village?
Meqbes didu ne.
There are two presses.
Meqbes yek, pirr kevn e. Berê li orta gund bû, meqbesê...
cilka bû.
One press is very old. It used to be in the middle of the
village, a press of... "cilka".
Me teper dida nav da, egîştimê, bizûre tê bîra min wek
xewna.
We used to put a stone in it, I remember it, barely comes to
my mind like a dream.
Di pey ra ê lîfî çêkirin. Meqbes jî a Malê Mixtêr e, ji gund
e, Malê Şêxî Fîlik.
After that they made the fiber ones. The press belongs to
the House of Mukhtar, from the village, House of Sheikhi
Filik.
Ê jor jî rakirin, birin dervayî gund. Nav gund teng bû, û
bînê bêrînê dero...
They removed the upper one too, took it outside the village.
Inside the village was narrow, and the smell of the waste...
Derxistin dervayî gund. Halyen jî yek şixûl e heye. Ser rêka
Gundê Husên.
They took it out of the village. Currently one is working.
On the road to Gundê Husên.
Noka du meqbes di Gundê Brimje da hene, ê cilka be yek noka
girtî ye?
Now there are two presses in Brimje Village, if one is
"cilka", is it closed now?
Ê tometîk heye dişuxile, meqbeseka heye, ê din jî bîna heye,
çênekirin e. Ê sinte tê tine ye.
There is an automatic one working, there is a press, the
other one has a building, but not fixed. There is no
machinery in it.
Meqbes kevn dar... li gundî...
The old wooden press... in the village...
Kevn dar heye, yani pirr kevn dar e.
There is an old one, I mean it's very old.
Xalê Arif, em noka ser we’dê noka dain. Noka îroja we çawa
derbas dibe?
Uncle Aref, let's talk about the situation now. Now how does
your day pass?
Gundê Birîmce hindî... Piştî ku hûn radibin û roja xwe çawa
derbas dikin? Tikaye ji me ra xeber de.
Brimje Village is a bit... After you get up, how do you
spend your day? Please tell us about this.
Wella li gund a bixwe, gund derece derece ye, yanî tişt tê
pey hev du tê.
Well, in the village itself, the village is step by step,
meaning things come one after another.
Halê anha wextê çilû ye.
Currently, it is the time of the "Chilu" (winter plowing).
Dû çilû ra mişmiş tê, hîlîk tê, yanî vê gundê me işxolî xwe
pir e. Daku çi heye.
After the Chilu, apricots come, plums come, meaning this
village of ours has a lot of work. So that's what there is.
Erê.
Yes.
Ee... Em noka şabab derên meselen sibe, ikindî derên çilû. I
razî xwe ne.
Uh... We, the youth, go out now, for example in the morning,
[until] late afternoon we go for the Chilu plowing. They are
content with themselves.
Wî tenê jî bi ucreta xwe sêk verra derê...
The other one goes with him for his wage...
Ee.. Danê çilû... Noka karê çilû ye.
Uh... The time of Chilu... Now is the work of Chilu.
Wî heye jî cûtari ye, yek jî ez mam cûtarî me, dan cûtê xwe
dajon. Elhemam traktor e, sêgemke, cût bajon.
There is the one who is a plowman, and I remained a plowman,
constantly driving their plow. It is mostly tractors, three-
disc plows, driving the plow.
I cût dajo. Wî din jî derê çilûyê rezan beraf dike, noka
karê yan halê noka çilû ye.
He drives the plow. The other one goes and hoes the "Chilu"
of the vineyards, now their work or current situation is the
Chilu.
Çilû ye.
It is Chilu.
Mm.
Noha em bên ucretê... Amil gava wextê ki heye çilû, danê
sibe û ikindî derê.
Now let's come to the wage... The worker, when it is the
time of Chilu, goes out morning and afternoon.
Danê çiqasî derê? Tikaye zama meblex ji me ra hewal de,
meselen bên divê gunda ucret haqas didin.
How much does a shift go for? Please transfer the amount to
us, for example, say in this village they pay this much
wage.
Bi seeta ra didin.
They pay by the hour.
Vra bi saeta darne. Sibe zû saet pênc û nîv şeşê de dest pê
dikin, heta saet deh.
Here they go by hours. Early morning at five thirty or six
they start, until ten o'clock.
Mokinê beraf dikeve, dare efrîn...
The machine falls to hoeing, going to Afrin...
Saetê meerya bi bîst û pênc wereqe çilû beraf dikim. Saeta
ye.
The hourly rate for a man, I hoe the Chilu for twenty-five
papers (notes). It is hourly.
Erê.
Yes.
Çar saeta beraf ke, yanî sed wereqî dibe. Ewa betûnî yaw
dikin.
If he hoes for four hours, that means it becomes a hundred
papers. That is how they calculate the concrete [total].
Danê sibe sedî, danê ikindî sedî?
The morning shift is a hundred, the afternoon shift is a
hundred?
Danê ikindî jî qismek heye derê beraf dike bi sedî. Ê pirrik
jî hene naçan, bes danê sibe beraf dikin.
For the afternoon shift, there is a portion that goes to hoe
for a hundred. And many of them don't go, they only hoe the
morning shift.
Bes danê sibe.
Only the morning shift.
Xwedê quwetê bide we û siheta we xweş bide.
May God give you strength and give you good health.
Bide we da jî.
May He give it to you too.
Ee.. Hatî em ya hewş... Te dibil ya hewş ge darber e.
Uh... You came to the courtyard... You said the courtyard
implies neighbors/gathering.
Erê.
Yes.
Em li vira, jdari, şînî, dawet dikin. Yanî... merî jî
diçînin, elmuhîm... giştk manê ew be.
We here, in neighborliness, mourning, we hold weddings.
Meaning... we also bury people, the important thing... is
that everything is like that.
Millet, ê dûr tana xwar jî, dûr ta rêkê bixwe.
The people, those from far down too, stand far on their own
path [implied meaning: everyone knows their place/role].
Erê. Em bên zanîn, gundê Birîmce li nahiya Mabatê dikeve.
Yes. Let us know, Brimja village falls in the Mabeta sub-
district.
Erê.
Yes.
Çend kîlometre ji nahiya xwe dûr dikeve?
How many kilometers is it far from its sub-district?
Em pênc kîlometre ji nahiya Mabatê va dûr ne.
We are five kilometers far from Mabeta sub-district.
Dûr ne.
You are far.
Tikaye ji me ra xeber de, piştî gundê Birîmce wa mişmişê
xwe, behîvê xwe kum kirin. In çawa dibin ji tuxlar? Yanî
ticare wa çawa ye in çû darbaz dikin?
Please tell us, after Brimja village gathers their apricots
and their almonds. How do they take them from the branches?
Meaning how is their trade, how do they manage it?
Me beraf dikir, gund beraf dikir, em ê bi rê diketin.
We used to harvest, the village used to harvest, we would
hit the road.
Berê me dibir Heleb. Yek jî ez me, min ji pênc şeş sala min
dibir Heleb, çilû, sîkê, daro, tirşê gişt min da dixist.
Before, we took it to Aleppo. I am one of them, for five or
six years I took it to Aleppo; plums, market goods, wood,
pickles, everything I would unload there.
Babo bî çend sal ne me berdayî.
Man, it has been a few years since we gave that up.
Ê şabab li gund hene, da dixin sîkê.
The youth in the village, they take it down to the market.
Em ê mokinê hûnin... bi nav gund bigere.
We bring the vehicle... it goes around inside the village.
Ê da xwin sîkê, bibin suqulal, bifroşin.
Those who take it down to the market, become grocers, they
sell it.
Faturê xelkê je ra rûnin, hûnin, belav kin.
They sit down for the people's invoices, bring them,
distribute them.
Belav kin.
Distribute them.
Yanî, gukarek bêjî, xelkê gundê Birîmce li her gundê, li
karê gundê, bi hev ra harîkar dikin.
Meaning, a helpful deed you could say, the people of Brimja
village in every village [matter], in village work, they
help each other.
Liv darê lê, mirik be, şabînekî ke be, em bav di ra yarm
dikin, em harî dikin.
In this place, if there is a death, if there is a wedding
engagement, we help each other with it, we assist.
Yanî ji xwa berê xerîb xumal, mêrê tena, mêrê te em kê, pê
ra bin. Vê wecîbê me ye, hewa ji berê da.
Meaning since before, strangers or locals, a lone man, your
man whoever, we go with him. This is our duty, since the old
days.
Erê. Gerek li her gundekî gukarek bî ku mer hev ra harî ke.
Yes. In every village there needs to be a helpful spirit so
people help each other.
Mer hev du ra harî ke, hezkirin hebe.
People should help each other, there should be love.
Erê.
Yes.
Xalê Arîf saeta te xweş, ez pir kêfxweş bûm, her wisa ez
nîvandarê gundê Birîmce bûm.
Uncle Arif, thanks for your time, I was very happy, likewise
I was a guest of Brimja village.
Saeta te jî xweş, ser xêr se, ehlen we sehlen.
Thanks for your time too, you are welcome, welcome.
Tu jî ji qenalê te ra jî, û ji wekî te bî hotinê we, cemel
ser çavê me, ser çavê me.
You too, and for your channel, and for those like you coming
here, beauty upon our eyes, upon our eyes (you are very
welcome).
Xwedê ji te razî be. Ê berî kî dest darim te emir ta, tu
gotinê te l’me hene?
May God be pleased with you. Before I leave, at your
command, do you have any words for us?
Gotinek tina ye. Wekî din miletê me giçûye derva.
There is not a word. Otherwise, our people have all gone
abroad.
Saeta giya xweş. Yanî birakî min çûye Lubnanê, xokne min gil
Elmanya ne, qîçkê gund ne.
Good times to them all. Meaning, a brother of mine has gone
to Lebanon, my sisters are with Germany, the kids of the
village.
Elhemam merîyê me, pişmamnê me gi belav bûne.
Mostly our relatives, our cousins are all scattered.
Silavê me ji giya ra hene.
We have greetings for them all.
Tikaye giya selam ke.
Please greet them all.
Em selam dikin, her yekî li enîka wî maç dikim.
We greet them, I kiss the forehead of each one.
Bes ê gund jî hene, û dûr welatî jî hene.
But there are those in the village, and there are those in
far countries.
Yanî heta nî, le ji Badîna da bigir, ji Korka da bigir, tişk
jan gundî de herê.
Meaning until now, take it from Badina, take it from Korka,
going out from the village painful things go.
Ê ma me digot bizrê tûşke. Kida çûye merîyê me lî gundî
hene.
We used to say "raspberry seeds" (meaning scattered
everywhere). Wherever they went, we have relatives in the
village [meaning they are connected].
Ê merîyê me li gunda giya hene. Silavê me ji giya ra jî
hene.
We have relatives in all the villages. We have greetings for
them all too.
Silavê me hemî miletê Kurd ra heye.
We have greetings for all the Kurdish people.
Hemî miletê Kurd ra heye, û ji qenala wa ra jî heye, û saeta
wa jî xweş bî, dindirê wa, ehlen we sehlen.
For all the Kurdish people, and for your channel too, and
may your time be good, your viewers, welcome.
Tim hotinê wa rind e, milet on a pê şad dibe.
Your coming is always good, the people become happy with it
like this.
Erê. Xwedê ji te razî be, spas.
Yes. May God be pleased with you, thanks.
Wa te jî xweş. Û ser û spas, ji te razî be.
You too. And thanks, may He be pleased with you.
[Music Starts - Traditional Song]
Geryam ez, hemî eywanan.
I wandered, through all the porches.
Min tirkî çû, xûn azdara.
I left the Turks, blood of the mourners.
Evîna te berda bû dil.
Your love was released into the heart.
Min jê re ne kirt çara.
I did not find a remedy for it.
Axata zêr û zewhera.
Your land of gold and jewels.
Deşt û mêrg û ta cennet in.
Plains and meadows and they are paradise.
Ava te paq û kewser e.
Your water is pure and like Kawsar (river in paradise).
Erbus bînir xûqî metin.
[Unclear dialect phrase, possibly regarding scent or value].
Efrîna min... Efrîna min...
My Afrin... My Afrin...
Jan û êşa bî dînî.
Pain and ache without religion (limit).
Keç û zînî... bi şîrînî...
Girls and saddles... with sweetness...
Derman û dîn birîna.
Remedy and religion for wounds.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen, şer bu selame.
Welcome, goodness and peace.
Navê te xalê?
Your name, uncle?
Navê min Ehmedê Hemedî nebî.
My name is Ahmed Hamadi Nabi.
Xalê Ehmed.
Uncle Ahmed.
Bi selame.
With peace.
Xalê Ehmed çend salî ye?
Uncle Ahmed, how old are you?
Bi Xwedê pêncî û pênc salî me.
By God, I am fifty-five years old.
Pêncî û pênc. Xwedê emrê dirêj te de û siheta xweş te de.
Fifty-five. May God give you a long life and give you good
health.
Sax be.
Be healthy (Thanks).
Em pir kêfxweş bûn te xwas, em bûn mêvan darê gundê Birîmce
bûn.
We were very happy to see you, we became guests of Brimja
village.
Sax be.
Be healthy.
Tu bixwe ji gundê Birîmce ye?
You yourself are from Brimja village?
Erê ji gundê Birîmce me.
Yes, I am from Brimja village.
Gundê Birîmce me.
I am Brimja village.
Ez xelîk ji gundê Badîna, ji qenatîm li Efrîn, hûru em
nîvandare gundî we ne.
I am a native of Badina village, from my channel in Afrin,
today we are guests of your village.
Ehlen we sehlen bi hatina we, bi selame. Tu jî miletê Efrîn
teav da.
Welcome to your coming, with peace. You too are of the
people of Afrin completely.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Xalê Ehmed, noha tikê ji me ra xeber de ser mêwa.
Uncle Ahmed, now please tell us about the fruit trees.
Tu çû destpêkê, tu çû diçînê, tu çû aw dikê? Ji me ra hinekî
behs bike.
How do you start, how do you plant, how do you water?
Discuss it a bit for us.
Bi Xwedê evê mêwna em Sîbatê tînin. Ji çûlê, mêwê rind.
By God, these fruit trees, we bring them in February. From
the wild, good fruit trees.
Ê dibên Lemy.
The ones they call "Lemy" (Greengage/Plum variety).
Mhm.
Em ji çûlê tînin, dikin tûrka, em axa sor jî ji berbawişê
tînin. Xas axa sor, ma kin e me wadiye xwa.
We bring them from the wild, put them in bags, we bring red
soil from the sunny slope. Specifically red soil, we don't
put it in our valleys [without it].
Ne bi hormonata ye. Em dikin şûnê fewata. Ma mêw çandine
berê.
It is not with hormones. We put them in place of the empty
spots. We planted fruit trees before.
Bes kî fewat bîn, em tkin şûnê genda kin. Hev mêwna.
But whichever ones failed/died, we make fresh ones in their
place. These fruit trees.
Erê.
Yes.
Mehê Şibatê em diçînin, teben.
In the month of February we plant them, naturally.
Mehê Şibatê, tikê hîne şitil, û te axê, te got axa sor em ji
deştê berbawişê tînin.
Month of February, you bring the seedling, and the soil, you
said we bring red soil from the plain of the sunny slope.
Erê em deştê berbawişê tînin.
Yes, we bring it from the plain of the sunny slope.
Û ev mêwna jî, yan em dikin tûrka, tûrî xwa jî reş me, manê
tesîr sermê pê neke.
And these fruit trees too, either we put them in bags, our
bags are black, meaning so the effect of the cold doesn't
hit them.
Saqa dero, mefûlî xwa mekin bî tûrî reş, mekin e, oxê sor jî
rind e.
The stem is outside, its effect is solid with the black bag,
we put it in, red soil is also good.
Erê.
Yes.
Mehê Şibatê, bidabıt.
Month of February, exactly.
Di mehê Şibatê da gerek te aw bikî.
In the month of February you must water it.
Erê, em ke da erdê ke şifê.
Yes, we put it in the ground [unclear word: shife].
Xalê Ehmed, çend meha gerek e gi bi şitil bê, gi te li nav
xêr biçînê?
Uncle Ahmed, how many months does it need to be a seedling,
for you to plant it in the soil?
Li nav xêr, bar xwa dide, sê sala teqrîben bar xwa dide.
In the soil, it gives its fruit, in three years
approximately it gives its fruit.
Bes tanî kikir e, em her roj yewmiye ji av didin.
But until it establishes, we give it water every single day.
Yanî rûk erê, rûkê na. Zû digihî ne mêw.
Meaning one day yes, one day no. The fruit trees mature
quickly.
Piştî te şitil hîna, te çand, û te kir axê, hin dibên çûlê
diçînin.
After you brought the seedling, you planted it, and you put
in soil, some say they plant wild ones.
Erê.
Yes.
Gi heger wextê te li çûle neçand, li xêr nav xêr te neçand,
gerek te av de, ne?
If at the time you didn't plant it in the wild, in the good
soil you didn't plant it, you must give it water, right?
Elê em kê av din, teban e. Sahrijê me jî heye, em da’ran av
didin. Bi traktorê.
Yes, we have to water it, naturally. We have cisterns too,
we go and water them. With the tractor.
Erê.
Yes.
Em daren avêj, meselen ji berbawişê tînin, ji bîra gwis
tînin. Em bi xertûm jî av didin.
We go for water too, for example we bring it from the sunny
slope, we bring it from the walnut well. We also water with
hoses.
Ha xusî.
Just like that.
Xalê Ehmed em noha bên meselê raz. Noêd tevrind çi ye, gi
heger mera biçînê li nav xêrê xwa?
Uncle Ahmed, let's come now to the issue of the
vineyard/orchard. What are the varieties of "Tevrind" (early
crop), if one wants to plant in their soil?
Noêd tevrind, em bên dikurgon, ev vera dibên kirmanc.
Varieties of Tevrind, we say "Dukurgan" (Double/Red), here
they call it "Kirmanj".
Dukurgonî Lemy heye.
There is Dukurgan of Lemy.
Ha wa noêd tevrind e.
Ah, that is the variety of Tevrind.
Ave tevrind e, em wî şitlî ji qelemî siftah, ma ji abîdanê
mantiqê ma ketî.
That is Tevrind, we [take] that seedling from the first
grafting pen, it has fallen into our region from Abidan.
Li cem me tine bî, ev qelemo.
We didn't have it, this grafting pen/scion.
Ji abîdanê ev avdarê ketî cem me. Mantiqê Efrîn, tine bî
berî cem me.
From Abidan this watered one fell to us. Afrin region, it
wasn't with us before.
Piştî wa şitil hat, û ortê xelkê girt.
After that seedling came, and it took hold among the people.
Erê. Orto ma mêw çandin, ew mêwna jî mezin bûn, û qelemî
genda belav bî li mantiqê me Efrîn bûn.
Yes. Then we planted fruit trees, those trees grew big, and
fresh scions spread in our region of Afrin.
Gundê Birîmce.
Brimja village.
Dukurganî odî jî heye, û hêvîtkî jî heye. Hêvîtkî na mexrûbe
sûkê.
There is ordinary Dukurgan too, and there is Hêvîtkî too.
Hêvîtkî is not desirable for the market.
Bes î mexrûb dikurgon e, we ye he. Em dibên Lemy.
But the desirable one is Dukurgan, that's the one. We call
it Lemy.
We ye tav, esasî de me cem me. Mantiqê me.
It is the sun/best, fundamentally with us. Our region.
Û hûsor jî mişmişa ma çilû ye teben.
And besides that, our apricots are "Chilu" naturally.
Erê.
Yes.
Erê gundî me jî, bi çilû derece yek e em berkin.
Yes our village too, with Chilu apricots we are number one
to harvest.
Çilîyê rês.
Real Chilu.
Di gundê Birîmce da, derece yek e me birî.
In Brimja village, we took first place.
Çend.
How much.
Dûr ma heye hindik e.
We have plenty, it's a little [humble brag or comparison].
Hindik e.
It is little.
Bes bizat gundê Birîmce, derece ûla birî.
But specifically Brimja village, took first place.
Rezê xwa t’pir e.
Your orchards are full.
Rezê me pir e, elhemdu lillah. Aa.
Our orchards are full, praise be to God. Ah.
Xalê Ehmed, piştî meselen, çend qûra gerek merê çilû beraf
ke? Noha dibê çilû pir beraf ke, tesîrê b’qûrax dikeve.
Raste ev gotina?
Uncle Ahmed, after for example, how many passes/rows must
one hoe the Chilu? Now they say hoe the Chilu a lot, the
effect falls on the roots/stump. Is this saying true?
Na, em tesîrê b’qûrax nakin.
No, we don't effect the roots.
Heger gi te qîmetê milk pê de, quwetê pê de, ew jî quwetê
dede te.
If you give value to the property, give it strength, it also
gives you strength.
Tesîrê pê nake, na.
It doesn't affect it, no.
Hûrûk meselen gi av e, gi semad e, gi cût e, kukulandin e,
tike wa be.
Like for example if it is water, if it is fertilizer, if it
is plowing, digging, it has to be like that.
Temam?
Okay?
Gi te xizmet nekir, ê teban yekê tesîrê t’re bike, a.
If you didn't serve it, well naturally one will affect you
[negatively], yeah.
Piştî wa sê çar qûr çilû kum kirin.
After you gathered three or four piles of Chilu
(apricots/plums).
Paşê ro qûrax dibe. Ortox dibe qûrax.
Afterwards it becomes stripping/drying. Then it becomes
stripping.
Dibe, dibe qûrax, lê.
It becomes, it becomes stripping, yes.
Qûrax, i heye meselen, tirî xwa dike dimis.
Stripping/drying, there is one for example, he turns his
grapes into molasses.
I heye dike bastêq. I heye dibe sûkê yanê.
There is one who makes fruit leather. There is one who takes
to the market.
Dibe suqulal meselen, difroşe.
Yes.
He goes to the grocer for example, he sells.
Bes exlebiye cem em dikin bastêq. Em dikin dimis, û dikin
mîj.
But the majority with us make fruit leather. We make
molasses, and make dried fruits (mîj).
Li gundê Birîmce, razê xwa, dikin bastêq.
In Brimja village, their orchards, they make fruit leather.
Û dikin mîj, û dikin dimis.
And they make dried fruits, and they make molasses.
Dimis.
Yes.
Molasses.
Paşê hîndimsî xwa difroşin.
Then they sell their molasses.
Em dimisê xwa difroşin, meselen bastêq em hebibêd me hene,
em ji fistoqê didinê, bi behîva, bi gûza dixwin.
We sell our molasses, for example fruit leather, we have our
pills (pieces), we put pistachio in it, with almonds, with
walnuts they eat it.
Wakî nîn bastêqî me, wakî nîn e. Donî adî.
Yes.
Our fruit leather is not like that, not like that. Ordinary
stuff.
In bastêqê xwa b'fistoq û b'behîv û b'gûz çêdikin.
They make their fruit leather with pistachios and almonds
and walnuts.
Erê.
Yes.
Em dikin nav nên ji vistanî, wek nîn bîstiq yanê, ma behîvê
xwa, gûzê xwa pê dixwin.
We put it in bread in winter, like a sandwich, meaning we
eat our almonds, our walnuts with it.
Em behîva jî bi avrû me’rûf in, û bi behîva jî.
We are famous for almonds by grafting, and for [wild]
almonds too.
Baxçêd gundê Birîmce, bi razê xwa me’rûf e, û bi behîvê xwa,
mişmişê xwa.
The gardens of Brimja village are famous for their
vineyards/orchards, and for their almonds, their apricots.
Teb’an, a.
Naturally, yes.
Hejîr li cem pî wa da kêm e xalê Ehmed?
Are figs scarce in your area Uncle Ahmed?
Na hejîrê me jî hene elhemdu lillah.
No we have our figs too, praise be to God.
Merhele hene, hejîr jî, hejîrê me jî rind e. Aa.
There are stages, figs too, our figs are also good. Ah.
Xalê Ehmed, saeta te xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be, ez pir te
spas dikim. Te qebûl kirin te istiqbalek pir xweş da me.
Uncle Ahmed, thanks for your time, may God be pleased with
you, I thank you very much. You accepted, you gave us a very
nice reception.
Sax be, saeta wa xweş, malê me ji qapiya ra vekirî ye, her
dostkî, ehbabkî ra, qapî me vekirî ye. Her merîkî kurd.
Be healthy, thanks for your time, our house is open for
guests, for every friend, loved one, our door is open. Every
Kurdish man.
Wa li cem me.
That is with us.
Xalê Ehmed, berî ke dest darim te emirt ta, tu gotinê te
l’me hene?
Uncle Ahmed, before I leave, at your command, do you have
any words for us?
Saeta wa xweş, silavê min yekê berî giya ji qîçkê xwa ra
bişînim, ji merîyê xwa ra.
Good times to you, my greetings, one before all, I send to
my kids, to my relatives.
Her kesî l’me seyr dike, tikene silav ke, û kî tikene qîçkê
xwa, û birakê xwa, û xalet xwa, xwarzî xwa, giya silav ke.
Everyone watching us, please greet them, and who, please
your kids, and your brother, and your aunt, your nephew,
greet them all.
Silavê min berî giya ji bira hene.
My greetings before all are for the brother.
Ji xokê bira hene.
For the sister of the brother.
Û ji birakî min mezin ra hene.
And for my big brother.
Hawa l’Fînlenda ye.
He is in Finland.
Û dilê min Danîmarka, xakê min Danîmarka.
And my heart is Denmark, my soil is Denmark.
Xwarzîyê min heye Şaban, li Elmanya ye.
I have a nephew, Shaban, in Germany.
Û xalkê min heye li Tirkîyê ne, silavê min ji giya ra hene.
And I have maternal uncles in Turkey, my greetings to all of
them.
Û her merivekî Kurd li Ewropa...
And every Kurdish person in Europe...
Ez dixwazim werê, biniftile gundê xwe jî.
I want them to come, to return to their village too.
Û gund rûn biniyen, mentîqa rûn biniyen.
And settle in the village, settle in the region.
Û silavê min ji ehbabê min ji Hollanda ra jî hene.
And my greetings to my friends in Holland too.
Ewa zava divim Kêro.
That son-in-law, I call him Kero.
Silavê min ji giya ra hene.
My greetings to all of them.
Hatina we jî ehlen we sehlen.
Your arrival is also very welcome.
Û her miletê Kurd, şêz û şêz gundî, mentîqa Efrîn silavê min
ji giya ra hene.
And the whole Kurdish nation, three hundred and sixty
villages, the Afrin region, my greetings to all of them.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Sax bin, ehlen we sehlen, bi xêr hatin, serî min, ser çava.
Be healthy, welcome, you came in peace, upon my head, upon
my eyes.
Sax bin.
Be healthy.
We sehlen ji we re, rûspî...
And welcome to you, elders...
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Tu çawa yî, baş î?
How are you, are you good?
Hemûdê?
Praise [be to God].
Hamude?
Çend salî ye?
Hamude.
How old are you?
Bîst û du.
Twenty-two.
Ez Xelîl ji gundê Baedîna ji qenatê me, Efrîn Hêv û Nîvandar
e, gundî pirr ji me hez dikin, ji me re dişînin.
I am Khalil from the village of Baedina from our channel,
Afrin Hev u Nivandar, many villagers love us, they send to
us.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser çava.
Welcome, upon my eyes [with pleasure].
Xwedê ji te razî be. Hemûdê em biniftilin werin ser tembûrê.
God be pleased with you. Hamude let's turn back and come to
the tanbur [instrument].
Te çend sal e, na, te lêdixist te ji me re xeber da?
You have been playing for how many years, no, you told us?
Û kîjan wextê da te dest pê kir te'lîmî?
And at what time did you start learning?
Û bi xwe tembûr hîbe ji kê bir te ji me re xeber de.
And personally who did you take the tanbur talent from, tell
us.
Teqrîben, yanî...
Approximately, I mean...
Yanî ê bi xwe çar sal in, ketime sala pênca ye lêdixim.
I mean personally it's been four years, I've entered the
fifth year playing.
Bavê min bi xwe zane.
My father himself knows [how to play].
Bavê min ne kêm zane yanî 'emrê xwe teqrîben...
My father doesn't know little, I mean his age
approximately...
...berî min bizewice, yanî biçûk bû pirr biçûk bû.
...before he married [my mother], I mean he was small, very
small.
Yanî tembûrek hewan, halîyen tembûrek jê heye.
I mean a tanbur..., currently he has a tanbur.
E'ser wî tembûrî ez 'elimîm.
On that tanbur I learned.
Ez 'elimîm, hewa kidê bîn, min lêxist, terik kir.
I learned, ... I played, I quit.
Pişê min deskê niha dîsa der dikir.
Then I started again recently.
Ne bîya 'elimandin.
It wasn't by teaching.
Yanî bi destê xwe min der dikir.
I mean I brought it out with my own hands.
Te mewhîbe ji bavê xwe bir?
Did you take the talent from your father?
Belê.
Yes.
Naho Hemûdê mesela em gotinekê bikin.
Now Hamude, for example let's say a word.
Naho wextî ku însan kî bi 'elmê tembûrê, bigereke meraq hebe
lê?
Now when a person learns the tanbur, must there be curiosity
for it?
Meraq kî hebe.
There must be curiosity.
Ku meraq tunebe nîke bi 'elimê?
If there is no curiosity, can he not learn?
Meraq kî hebe, divê kî zanebûn, fenîkî têda hebe.
There must be curiosity, there must be knowledge, an art in
it.
Yanî fenî têda nebe, tu nikanî livî darî bixînî.
I mean if there is no art in it, you cannot play on this
wood.
Hawdora bindirva be, pşî çavê te nate xuyan.
If the surroundings are [distracting], it doesn't appear
before your eyes.
Bes fenî biter a be, dikênî yanî dikin eya deqa di bîst
saetî lêxe tu jê ne'iciz e.
But if the art is good, you enjoy it, meaning if you play
the same piece for 20 hours you won't get annoyed.
Gerek meraq dilê te da hebe û te bi 'elmê.
Curiosity must be in your heart and you learn.
Wexta gotî jî te mewhîbe ji bavê xwe 'elimî tembûr.
As you said, you learned the talent/tanbur from your father.
Belê.
Yes.
Destê kî min di rakir.
I picked up a hand [skill].
Niha em sual pirs kin, tu derdikevî dawata lê na?
Now let's ask a question, do you go out to weddings or not?
Na, hezar na, dernakevim bes, teqî dewate d'gund çêdibin...
No, a thousand times no, I don't go out but, sometimes
weddings happen in the village...
...em jixwe re... em şên dikin yanî.
...we for ourselves... we liven it up I mean.
Kêlek hevedu dikin.
We gather together.
Rojê pêşda kî da'we li ser dawata ew kir...
In the future if someone invites you to a wedding...
...yanî em bêjin roje pêşda me li Hemûdê li dawata bibînin?
...I mean let's say in the future will we see Hamude at
weddings?
Înşalla yanî.
God willing I mean.
Ti mişkêle tê da nîne, ezê derkevim.
There is no problem in it, I will go out.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Xwedê ji te jî razî be, sax bî mamoste.
God be pleased with you too, be healthy teacher.
Û bi xwe sê sal e te ta'lîmî ta we got?
And for three years you have been learning as you said?
E, dersa le, çar sal, dersa sala pênca ye.
Eh, lessons..., four years, lesson of the fifth year.
Niha jî tê destê...
Now you will [play] a hand...
Adî zorê tune, ser serî bîm.
Normal, no trouble, upon my head.
[Music playing]
Saetên we xweş bin, bimînin heta dawiya vîdyoyê.
May your time be pleasant, stay until the end of the video.
Niha jî ez li deşta Tirbespiyê, gundê Dugirê...
Now I am in the plain of Tirbespiyê, the village of
Dugirê...
Xwedê rehma xwe li miriyên we gişkan bike.
May God have mercy on all your deceased.
Silav û rêz ji şêniyê gundê Dugirê...
Greetings and respect from the residents of Dugirê
village...
Silavên me ji were hene li her derê.
Our greetings to you everywhere.
Em şikirekî xas dikin Kekê Ehmedê Nebî, Xalê Ehmed.
We give a special thanks to Brother Ehmedê Nebî, Uncle
Ehmed.
Malê xwedê jê ava kir, pêşwaziyek pir xweş û kîbar û delal
dan me.
May God prosper his house, he gave us a very nice, polite,
and lovely welcome.
Arîfê Qelqezxele, xwedê jê razî be, silavên me ji were hene.
Arîfê Qelqezxele, may God be pleased with him, our greetings
to you.
Û bîr nekin me de'm bikin... bimînin heta dawiya vîdyoyê.
And don't forget to support us... stay until the end of the
video.
Saetên we xweş, ez Xelîl ji gundê Dugirê, qenata Xatûnê ya
fermî.
Have a good time, I am Xelîl from Dugirê village, the
official Xatûn channel.
Ji xwe dûr im, ne jiyan li vir heye.
I am far from myself, there is no life here.
Ne jî ez li vir im.
Nor am I here.
Gava ji te bi dûr ketim.
When I fell far from you.
Ne bi dilê min bû.
It was not my wish.
Ji xwe dûr im, ne jiyan li vir heye.
I am far from myself, there is no life here.
Ne jî ez li vir im.
Nor am I here.
Gava ji te bi dûr ketim.
When I fell far from you.
Ne bi dilê min bû.
It was not my wish.
Hêna ji dilê te kî dipirpitî.
Who is still fluttering from your heart.
Di nava girê gurbetiyê da mam e.
I have remained in the grip of exile.
Bela ez li gundê xwe bam e.
If only I were in my village.
Min li siya darekê zeytûnê.
Me in the shade of an olive tree.
Serê xwe danîba ser gurzekê puş.
If I had laid my head on a bundle of straw.
Di ber re jî difinam in.
And while doing so, I would be humming.
Bila axa pîroz bikira...
Let the holy soil make...
Bila ew derman ba ji min ra.
Let that be the remedy for me.
Hingî ez ne dimirim.
Then I would not die.
Hingî ez namirim.
Then I do not die.
Dîsa hate ber guhê min dengê te.
Again your voice came to my ear.
Dîsa hate xeyala min rengê te.
Again your image came to my imagination.
Dîsa birînê dilê min vebûn ve.
Again the wounds of my heart opened up.
Kî ve biçim xilaz nabim ji hizrên te.
Wherever I go, I will not be saved from thoughts of you.
Dîsa hate ber guhê min dengê te.
Again your voice came to my ear.
Dîsa hate xeyala min rengê te.
Again your image came to my imagination.
Dîsa birînê dilê min vebûn ve.
Again the wounds of my heart opened up.
Kî ve biçim xilaz nabim ji hizrên te.
Wherever I go, I will not be saved from thoughts of you.
Ji hêsr û ji xeyala min.
From tears and from my imagination.
Çi tiştî dî nema.
Nothing else remained.
Hemî xweşî yet min te birin.
You took all my joys.
Te hêla me nav xema.
You left me in sorrows.
Ji hêsr û ji xeyala min.
From tears and from my imagination.
...îna nû, emrê xweş yê te bir
...new love, it took away your happy life
Te hêla me na xema
You left me in grief
Min ji te via, ji bîr vekim rojên berê
I wanted you, to forget the days of the past
Min ji te via...
I wanted you...