Ev vîdyo xasnaş ji qenalê Hatem Le Efrîn.
This video is specifically for the Hatem Le Efrin channel.
Xwedanê rûpelê Xelîl Sînem.
The owner of the page is Xelil Sinem.
Cîranên gundê Ba'dîna.
Neighbors of Baadina village.
Hewil dide ku gund bi gund bigere.
He is trying to travel village by village.
Û gund bi gund digere.
And he is traveling village by village.
Noka haliyen bi merikî ra bibêje her filan gundî, çi qol ber
biger, dibê bê hene bûş im û he rehet im û he nizanim çi
biyê.
Now, currently, if he tells a man "go to such and such
village, go around that side", he might say "I am empty
[tired]" or "I am comfortable" or "I don't know what
happened".
Xo rehet kiriye, manê va miletê xerîb û gurbetiyê, filklorê
xo û tûrasê xo ji bîr neke.
He has tired himself out [put in effort], meaning so this
nation in exile and diaspora doesn't forget its folklore and
heritage.
Diçînê di serî qiçikê me da.
Planting it in the heads of our children.
Her kesî gundî gindê lê dimîne.
Every villager misses their village.
Wa qiçikê çûçik yê li xerîb û gurbetiyê, li Ewropa dibe li
ku dibe dibîne...
Those small children in exile and diaspora, whether in
Europe or wherever, when they see...
Keennî li nav gundê xo ye.
It is as if they are inside their own village.
Gundî gindê pênas kirinê dike, naxwaze filklor hinda bibe.
He introduces the village, he doesn't want the folklore to
be lost.
Pir însan heye zengîn e, zengînê pere ye, hewa jî zengînê
filklorê Kurda ye di serî me da biçîne û di dilê me da
biçîne.
Many people are rich, rich in money, but this one is rich in
Kurdish folklore to plant it in our heads and hearts.
Silav û rêzê min ji binayanê dewleta Tirkiye ji muhafeza
Îzmîrê da jê re hene heta ciyê gindê.
My greetings and respects from the buildings of the state of
Turkey, from the province of Izmir, go to him, all the way
to the location of the village.
Erca ji we dikim bes gindê çikê de'm kin, mila rûpelê xo
hebe, mara bihevdim mezin e, silav û rêzê min ji we giya ra.
I request of you, just support the village a bit, so he has
his page, let us grow together, my greetings and respects to
you all.
Mezre'et Silû.
Selu Farm.
Navê kirin Mezre'et Silû.
They named it Selu Farm.
Bi rez ay, zeytûn e, hejîr e, meselen tirî ye...
It has vineyards, olives, figs, for example grapes...
Husam ajot.
Husam drove.
Bavê Husam erê ajot.
Husam's father, yes, drove.
Berê hebed ajot heta noka.
He drove a bit until now.
Xolê min te...
My uncle, you...
Elhemdulilah... Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God... Praise be to God.
Di karê gunda hebe îşale.
Let there be village work, God willing.
Hebe, çi ezab e, em ketiye şuxul heta me xweş ne.
There is, what a torment, we have been working until we got
better.
Heyat cehfe derbas dibe.
Life passes harshly.
Gurçikê xo emeliyat kirî, gurçikê xo yekî derxist.
He operated on his kidney, he removed one of his kidneys.
Pir tesîr min bûye berketim e.
It affected me a lot, I was sad.
Qehirî me, nexweş e, înşela yê rehet bibe, rizqê de jê re
heye, heke her bijî, heke bibî...
I was upset, he is sick, God willing he will get
comfortable, he has sustenance [life] left, if he lives, if
he becomes...
Ez, û Zekeriya, û Hemûdê.
Me, and Zekeriya, and Hemûdê.
Teben ne xerîb ne, pismamê min ne.
Of course they aren't strangers, they are my cousins.
Teqrîben nîzîkî 35 hezar muşterek e.
Approximately close to 35 thousand subscribers.
Çend sal e?
How many years?
Dêkê me da ye.
He gave us a spot [on TikTok].
A xo naşêxim, ser Tîktok jî heta mirovê şîret dikin.
Oh I don't act like a Sheikh, on TikTok people even give
advice.
Bes xo dêkê min nîşan ke.
Just show my spot [face].
Dêkî te yê nîşan ke.
He will show your spot.
Makin ji, dest data lê na data.
Don't do it either, he gives a hand but doesn't give.
Merheba miletê kîbar û delal.
Hello noble and dear nation.
Em hatin bi vîdyokê xweş û vîdyokê ecêb.
We came with a nice video and a wonderful video.
Vîdî min îro li gundê Selû ye.
My video today is in the village of Selu.
Silav û rêz ji şêniyê gundê Selû ra, silavê min ji we re
hene hîn bi xêr hatin ser qenata Hatem Le Efrîn.
Greetings and respect to the inhabitants of Selu village, my
greetings to you, welcome to the Hatem Le Efrin channel.
Saeta we xweş û kana abone bin, bi dilekê xweş û geş emê
derbasî gundê Selû bin.
Good tidings to you and if you subscribe, with a happy and
bright heart we will enter the village of Selu.
Emê adet û teqalîdê vî gundî nas kin.
We will get to know the customs and traditions of this
village.
Emê gel dengekî bav û kalan in, emê çîrokê berê mara kin
bahevra.
We will correspond with the voice of the forefathers, we
will share the old stories together.
Û gundê Selû da Yûtiyûber hene teben.
And in the village of Selu there are YouTubers of course.
Emê wan jî wera bi muşareke kin.
We will share them with you as well.
Û lextêd gund em ji we ra bîr nakin û lextêd turba jî em ji
we ra muşareke kin.
And shots of the village we won't forget for you, and shots
of the cemetery we will share with you.
Saeta we xweş, û Xwedê ji we razî be, û bîr mekin me de'm
kin emê bi de'mê we serkevin.
Good tidings to you, and may God be pleased with you, and
don't forget to support us, we will succeed with your
support.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Çû ye işxol?
How are things?
Navê te bi xêr?
Your name please?
Navê min Mihemed.
My name is Mihemed.
Xalê Mihemed.
Uncle Mihemed.
Bavê Cangîn.
Father of Cangîn.
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Ez Xelîl ji gundê Ba'dîna ji qenaya Hatem Le Efrîn.
I am Xelil from Baadina village from Hatem Le Efrin channel.
Îro em mîvandarê gundê Selû ne.
Today we are guests of Selu village.
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Bavê Cangîn ser serê min.
Bavê Cangîn, you are highly respected.
Tu çend sal î bixwe?
How old are you yourself?
Walahi heyşt û pênc.
By God, sixty-five.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bide û sihetê xweş bide te de.
May God give long life and good health to you.
Tu kanî ji me ra xeber de xêr nav lê kirin gundê Selû.
Can you speak to us about why they named it Selu village.
Yanî me'nê gundê.
Meaning the meaning of the village.
Walahi tema heba... jimêj da ye teqrîben dusid sal sêsid sal
da ye.
By God, it has been... since long ago, approximately two
hundred years, three hundred years.
Bil esil navê ev vayî... vî gundî... malbatek bê gundî, ê
reîsî.
Originally the name of this one... this village... there was
one family of the village, the main one.
Navê xwa Silêman bû.
His name was Silêman.
Silêman... wele digotin Selû.
Silêman... by God they called him Selu.
Silêman... ewile... vê gund da tesîs bîra tê da rûnişt.
Silêman... first... in this village established, came into
it and settled.
Ewel wahid hewa navê xwa Silêman bî.
The first one, that one, his name was Silêman.
Ma'a murûr el zeman, aw bî teb'en navê bîna Silêman ah...
With the passage of time, that became naturally the name
became Silêman uh...
Meselen hikûmet niyam çêbû dabê nav bil Erebî Selû.
For example the government system happened, called the name
in Arabic Selu.
Mezre'et Silû.
Selu Farm.
Nav lê kirin Mezre'et Silû.
They named it Selu Farm.
Însanek hat vê gundî navê xwa Silêman bî, piştî demekî li vê
gundî malbat...
A human came to this village his name was Silêman, after a
while in this village a family...
Na, eşîret çêbû.
No, a tribe formed.
Eşîret çêbû malbat çêbû.
A tribe formed, a family formed.
Û piştî wê nav lê kirin gundê Selû.
And after that they named it Selu village.
Selû, na'am.
Selu, yes.
Bes eslê xwa Silêman e.
But its origin is Silêman.
Navê gindê yanî gindê Silêman nav lê kirin Selû.
The name of the village, meaning Silêman village, they named
it Selu.
Selû, na'am.
Selu, yes.
Şexsekî.
A person.
Çima?
What?
Lê kirin.
They named it.
Bavê Cangîn li gundê Selû wek em zanin û me dîye, gundê we
bi zira'etê xo pir e.
Bavê Cangîn, in Selu village as we know and have seen, your
village is full of its agriculture.
Bes neha hîn pir bi çi ra dibin? Neha wextê noka hîn bi çi
gundê Selû pir pê ra dibin?
But now what are you mostly busy with? Now at this time what
is Selu village mostly busy with?
Walahi... gund... gundê me, ew mintîqe me giya yanî...
By God... the village... our village, that whole region of
ours basically...
Ya zira'etî ye.
It is agricultural.
Gi karê çolê ye.
It's all field work.
Rez ne, zeytûn ne, gûz ne, ee tiştê hane ye... tirş e...
simaq meselen...
Vineyards, olives, walnuts, uh things like that...
livestock... sumac for example...
Gundê Selû jî pir...
Selu village too is very...
Simaqê dere tiştek.
Sumac is found somewhat.
Simaqê bi darê gûzê.
Sumac and walnut trees.
Û rezê xo pir av dibe.
And its vineyards are well watered [or productive].
Neha em bên li gundê Selû hîn, neha em ser we'dê niko, hîn
pir bi çi ra dibin?
Now let's come to Selu village, now on the current
situation, what are you mostly busy with?
Hîn rojê xo çû derbas dikin, tikanî ji me ra xeber de. Ser
gund, ser miletê wir.
How do you pass your days, can you speak to us? About the
village, about the people there.
Walahi...
By God...
Yanî ekserî gundê, gundê me, gundê me giyanî.
Meaning most of the village, our village, our whole village.
Ya zira'etî ye.
It is agricultural.
Gi karê çolê ye.
It's all field work.
Rez ne, zeytûn ne, cûta, ee tiştê hana ye, tirş, simaq
meselen.
Vineyards, olives, plowing, uh things like that, livestock,
sumac for example.
Ewa pê ra dibin nekêm çi ra bin.
That's what they are busy with, not much else to be busy
with.
Zira'et cem me wekî xelkê ard tinnene meselen.
Agriculture for us, we don't have land like [other] people
for example.
Zira'etê genim a biçînin meselen ceh biçînin û tiştê de
biçînin.
Agriculture of wheat to plant for example, barley to plant
and other things to plant.
Arda me kêm e.
Our land is scarce.
Kêm e.
Scarce.
Li gundê we... piştî neha rez... em bêjin we çilû kom kir.
In your village... after now the vineyards... let's say you
gathered the leaves.
Hîn dadixin soqlar? Dirfşîn lê? Yan hîn helîdin e?
Are you taking down the sacks? Sewing them? Or are you still
picking?
Na teb'en, çilû meselen hefte bi hefte.
No naturally, leaves for example week by week.
Meselen daren çilû xwa jî dikin.
For example they go and do [pick] their leaves too.
Hemma daren, çilû xwa jî dikin xeyo.
They all go, do [pick] their leaves brother.
Mawqî ne hazir e.
The season is not ready.
Meselen dikeve kartona.
For example it goes into cartons.
Weş kartona meselen dadixîn soqnal... Efrînê.
And from cartons for example we put down in sacks... to
Afrin.
Û li wir difroşin.
And sell there.
Bavê Cangîn gundê Selû ji nehiya Mabeta dikeve?
Bavê Cangîn, Selu village falls under Mabeta sub-district?
Teb'en na'am.
Of course, yes.
Çend kîlometir ji nehiya xwa dûr e?
How many kilometers is it far from its sub-district?
Teb'en... walahi teqrîben... çar kîlo pênc kîlometir e.
Of course... by God approximately... four kilos, five
kilometers.
Dora çar pênc kîlometir ji nehiya xwa dûr dikeve.
Around four five kilometers it falls far from its sub-
district.
E neha rêvargên ne... tişkî nasken.
And now the roads are... a bit thin/bad.
Gundê Selû bixwa tewasila xwa pir bi Efrîn rayê lê? Lê bi
Reco rayê? Hîn berkî pir daren?
Selu village itself, is its connection mostly with Afrin? Or
with Rajo? Where do you go mostly?
E walahi tewasilê me zêde la... Reco ne nehiya me ye.
Eh by God our connection mostly... Rajo is not our sub-
district.
Ne nehiya we ye.
Not your sub-district.
Mabeta nehiya me ye, teb'en bi Efrînê rayê.
Mabeta is our sub-district, naturally it goes with Afrin.
Bi Mabeta rayê. Meselen bi vê gundî durê me rayê, zanî?
It goes with Mabeta. For example via this village our turn
goes, you know?
E neha em bên gundê Selû li bilindiyaye ne we?
Eh now let's come to Selu village, it is on a height, isn't
it?
Li bilindiyaye.
On a height.
Û deşta gundê jî pêjêr dikeve.
And the plain of the village falls below it.
Bêlê.
Yes.
Bi dor vê gundana, tikanî ji me ra xeber de çi gund hene
tikanî navê gund ji me ra aboke?
Around these villages, can you speak to us what villages are
there, can you count the names of the villages for us?
Walahi... Xerbî me ve ray... Xerbî me...
By God... Our West is this way... Our West...
Xazyana didin, Xazyanî jêr heye.
They call it Xazyana, Lower Xazyan is there.
Û ê jor heye.
And the Upper exists.
Neha qulbey me teqrîben hane berîmceh ye.
Now our South is approximately here, Berimceh.
Gundê Hisê berê dibên heye.
Village of Hise they call it, is there.
Û di pîvera Şîtka ye, Kaxrê ye.
And across it is Shitka, Kakhre.
Û ya ji me xerbî da gund Ze'bin e.
And that from us in the West is Zabin village.
Erê.
Yes.
Û şerqî me... teb'en berê dibên Erebo.
And our East... naturally they call it Erebo.
Erebo şaxî.
Erebo.
Erebo Shaxi.
Hane û... qulbey me berî mabet... berî mabetê teb'en nîzîkê
mabet qentere ye.
Erebo Shaxi.
Hane û... qulbey me berî mabet... berî mabetê teb'en nîzîkê
mabet qentere ye.
Here and... our South facing Mabet... facing Mabet naturally
near Mabet is Qentere.
Bavê Cangîn saeta te xweş.
Bavê Cangîn good tidings to you.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Ez pir kêfxweş bûm îro ez hatim gundê Selû.
I was very happy today I came to Selu village.
Bi silamet.
With safety.
Te hatî ser ser, ser çava.
You came upon the head, upon the eyes [welcome].
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Te emrê te, te gotin tel me hene, tikanî bêje?
You, your age, you said you have words, can you say them?
Mina saeta xwa xweş.
Me, good tidings to you.
Em... kêfxweş bîn.
We... were happy.
Erê.
Yes.
Tu tikanî ji gundê Selû re şîretkî bidî wan, yan gotinekî ji
wan re bêjî, yan duakî ji wan re bikî?
Can you give a piece of advice to Selu village, or say a
word to them, or make a prayer for them?
Yê heyî, yê mirî, yê zindî, çi xeyran e?
The existing ones, the dead ones, the living ones, what is
the good news?
Na'am.
Yes.
Yanî her kes gerek hîfaz ke...
Meaning everyone must protect...
Li ser şexsiyetê xwe.
Their own personality.
Û li ser emrê xwe.
And their own life.
Û li ser te'bûna xwe.
And their own labor.
Wela zane be, eno xeyo huro... huro a di cewkê da dijîn
meselen xeyo cewkî...
And let them know, that brother today... today we live in an
atmosphere for example brother an atmosphere...
Canleqî ye însan.
Human is fragile.
Meselen emrê çêl û pêncî ye, bes we da emrê te bî şêst, bî
heftê, bî heyştê hema ne ta emrî.
For example age is forty and fifty, but even if your age
becomes sixty, becomes seventy, becomes eighty, it is still
not your [full] age.
Wek dibên her tiştek di wextê xwe da xweş e.
As they say, everything is nice in its own time.
Her tiştek di wextê xwe da xweş e.
Everything is nice in its own time.
Saeta te xweş.
Yes.
Good tidings to you.
Wextê ji xweş.
Good times to you too.
Ez pir kêfxweş bûm.
I was very happy.
Wa yehlen we sehlen.
And welcome.
Xwedê emrê dirêj de.
May God give long life.
Wa tewafîq.
And success.
Bi te ji de.
Give to you too.
Wa ehlen we sehlen, hatina te ser ser û ser çava.
And welcome, your coming is upon head and upon eyes.
Neha berî ke dest bidim, tu qiçik te hene?
Now before I shake hands, do you have children?
Tu kesê te li derva heye, ew hemî miletê Kurd me seyr dikin,
tikanî silav kî...
Do you have anyone outside [abroad], all the Kurdish nation
is watching us, can you greet...
Walahi...
By God...
Tikanî li kamîre binihêrîne û silav kî.
Can you look at the camera and greet.
Na'am.
Yes.
Qiçkê min zêdeyê min Tirkiye ye.
My children, most of mine are in Turkey.
Baş in ya'nî?
Are they good, meaning?
Silavê min gelek ji wan ra hene.
My greetings go to them a lot.
Û lawkê me zava ne.
And our boys are grooms [married].
Tew li Almanyayê ye.
He is in Germany.
Gelek gelek silavên me...
Many, many of our greetings...
Miletê kîbar û delal, em ê rojekê din jî...
Noble and dear nation, we will another day too...
Pêkve xweş bin, hûn hemî vandarê gundê wane.
Be happy together, you are all people of this village.
Û înşalla em ê rojekê din jî werin seyranê ke, ew xaca avê
ke biçin.
And God willing we will come another day for a picnic, go to
that water fork.
Saeta we xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Have a good time, God be pleased with you.
Merheba xalê min.
Hello my uncle.
Ehlan we sehlan.
Welcome.
Navê te bi xêr?
Your name please?
Navê min Ehmed e.
My name is Ahmed.
Xalê Ehmed.
Uncle Ahmed.
Bi Xwedê ez derbasî gundê Selû bûm...
By God, I passed through Selu village...
Me dît tu yê karê xwe dikî, heyriya te çi ye, tu karê çi
dikî?
We saw you doing your work, what are you busy with, what
work do you do?
Walla... ez cot dajom.
By God... I am plowing.
Bavê Husam ez cot dajom.
Father of Husam, I am plowing.
Berî herbad ez dajom heta noka.
I have been driving it since before the wind (?) until now.
Xalê min te cotê dêwêr dajot?
My uncle, did you plow with cattle?
Eê teka.
Yes, certainly.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Te jî razî be, Xwedê pismam ji te razî be.
You be pleased too, God be pleased with you cousin.
Te emrê dirêj bide, siheta xweş bide te.
Give you long life, give you good health.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Te jî razî be.
You be pleased too.
Te bxoş vê gundî ye?
Do you like this village?
Ez xweş vê gundî me.
I like this village.
Tişk korê xwe razî ye ma'neten?
You are essentially satisfied with your work?
Hemdilla, hemdilla.
Thank God, thank God.
Hemdilla Xwedê ra.
Praise be to God.
E t karê gund da hebe işte.
You have work in the village then.
He heye, işte ez abim, bi şixulînim heta em xweş nîn.
Yes there is, I just am... I work until we are not well.
Heyat cafa derbas dibe.
Life passes with effort.
Dê de bu derbas be.
Let it pass.
Erê.
Yes.
Xalê min, ecba sela bi qantirê dajon ne?
My uncle, I wonder do they plow with a mule?
Bergîr e.
It's a horse.
Bergîr e. Tu kînga dest pê dikî mesele ten cot?
It's a horse. When do you start plowing for example?
In çû sibê saet çenda gerek were û jû ten? Çend gîsin lê
kevin?
Coming morning at what hour must one come and plow? How many
plowshares hit it?
Em du gîsin lê didinê.
We hit it with two plowshares.
Sibê zû saet şeş heta yekê.
Early morning six o'clock until one.
Xwedê ji te razî be, siheta te xweş be.
God be pleased with you, your health be good.
Te dêjî... ştek cota me... e gunda heye.
You say too... something our plow... is in the village.
Ê ez kî tişkî hewal dim nuh a mesele em bên...
I will tell a friend a thing now for example we come...
Ku bavê kê ma, ew mesele ku dmezrî me jme xêl dibîn...
That my father remained, that for example that... we see
from us...
Goto robo, megirî, dugu ma te cot dajotî?
He said man, don't cry, saying did you drive the plow?
Ewa.
Exactly.
Yanî... madem ek... karê e cota...
Meaning... since... work of the plow...
E tefşetin e.
It's crushing work.
Tefşetin e şu karê cota.
It's crushing, the work of the plow.
Tefşetin e.
Crushing.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Û te jî razî be.
And you be pleased too.
Xwedê emrê we dirêj bike û înşalla ya Reb Xwedê rizqê we
giya bişîne.
God prolong your life and God willing Oh Lord God send
sustenance to all of you.
Û umeta Mihemed giya bişîne.
And send to all Ummah of Muhammad.
Umeta Mihemed û te jî tê da înşalla rizqê te jî bişîne
înşalla.
Ummah of Muhammad and you too in it God willing send your
sustenance too God willing.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Ştek agahî, emkêjî...
Something aware, we will too...
Em ka ji bavê Husam, em ka ji cotî boş bîn heta yek nîvê.
We will from father of Husam, we will from the plow be free
until one thirty.
Noha te danek lêxist, danê didiyê dest pê bikî.
Now you hit one round, start the second round.
He.
Yes.
Noha jî te defterê derê danaye.
Now you've put the savings out.
Heya ka qurbana min heta yek nîvê.
Yes my dear until one thirty.
Tu mişkîla te naye, em vîdeo daxin ser qenata Hatim El
Efrînî?
You have no problem, we upload video to channel Hatim El
Efrini?
Ser serê min, ser çavê min.
On my head, on my eye.
Te jî razî be.
You be pleased too.
Berî ku ez te ji da jî ewran nakim...
Before I keep you from work...
Min tî derê karê xwe... e...
I ? there your work... uh...
Ma hadîye...
It is fine...
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Berî ku ez darim, her kesî silav bike, dikine silav kê.
Before I leave, greet everyone, do a greeting.
Xwedê te bihelimîne.
God keep you safe.
Dikin e silama ji her kesî ra bişîne, ji me sêr dikin.
Send greetings to everyone who watches us.
Walla xwarziyê min jî yek li wir e elmanyaya ye.
By God my nephew, one is there in Germany.
Selam kê.
Greet him.
Silavê min ji wan ra hene.
My greetings are to them.
Û ta ra jî hene înşalla.
And to you too God willing.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Ser serê min.
On my head.
Tov şokir û dan înşalla.
Seed sugar and grain God willing.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Înşalla her... her demê mi warin.
God willing every... every time come to me.
Înşalla, ser serê min, tobe mal mala te ye.
God willing, on my head, truly the house is your house.
Saeta te xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Have a good time, God be pleased with you.
Merheba Dayika min.
Hello my Mother.
Ehlan we sehlan.
Welcome.
Navê te bi xêr?
Your name please?
Navê min Zelîxa ye, dayika Kawa.
My name is Zelikha, mother of Kawa.
Dayika Kawa.
Mother of Kawa.
Ser serê me. Çend sal e teyî hisabê?
On our head. How many years are you by count?
45.
Xwedê emrê dirêj te bide û siheta xweş te bide.
God give you long life and give you good health.
Xwedê ji te razî be, ehlan we sehlan gotina we.
God be pleased with you, welcome to your speech.
Ez Xelîl ji gundî, ba e nîşana qenata Hatim El Efrînî...
I am Khalil from the village, this is sign of channel Hatim
El Efrini...
Hûr em nîvandariyê gundî Selû ne.
Now we are guests of Selu village.
Ehlan we sehlan, ser xêrê hatî.
Welcome, you came on goodness.
Sihet xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Good health, God be pleased with you.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Dayika Kawa, tu ji gundî Selû ye?
Mother Kawa, are you from Selu village?
Erê, ez ji gundî Selû me. Bîka gundî Selû me.
Yes, I am from Selu village. I am a bride of Selu village.
Tu... tu derve ye ew ne, çi gund der neket?
You... you are outside or not, what village did not leave?
Na, na.
No, no.
Tu ne xerîbî... tu neçî.
I am not a stranger.
You are not a stranger... you don't go.
Dayika Kawa, tu dixwazî tiştekî ji me ra xeber de...
Mother Kawa, you want to tell us something...
Mesele îro roja xwe çû derbaz dikin. Û noha jî li biharê ye.
For example how you pass your day today. And now it is
spring.
Yan mewsîmê çilû ye.
Or it is the season of the forty.
Tu ji me ra xeber de, çil û çawa radikin?
Tell us, how do they pick up the forty?
Berê we heyat çû derbaz dikir... tiştekî ji me ra xeber de.
Before how did you pass life... tell us something.
Walla yarm...
By God my dear...
Çil û noka wextê çilû ye, bîdayî ye.
Forty and now is time of forty, it is the beginning.
Neqle qûrrî siah e.
It is a time of black mud.
Em malê nabin bixwedê reft dikin, rez rezê me ye.
We don't take the cattle by God they graze, we have
vineyards.
E neqle semslaham beraft dikin, em şî qîçkê or dikin sorme.
The time ? graze, we make fire/dung for small ones.
Em xêra mirîşkê xwe jê derdixin.
We take out the benefit of our chickens.
Û î îkê dilê xwe dixwaze em hinkî didinê.
And whoever's heart desires we give some to them.
Qûrrê didiyê em kum dikin, em dişînin sûkê difroşin, em pê
xezleqê xwe derdixin.
The second mud we gather, send to market sell, we make our
pocket money with it.
Bixo qûrr bi qûrr hîn radikin.
Mud by mud they pick up?
Erê.
Yes.
Qûrrê selef hîn dixin mesele... dikin sorme, şîv... û hîn
derdixin zexat...
Ancestral mud they put for example... make dung cakes,
supper... and some take out zakat...
Û qûrrê didiyê jî artix hîn gizeda bîse hîn dişînin sûkê hîn
difroşin.
And the second mud too now if it is ? they send to market
they sell.
Erê.
Yes.
Dayika Kawa ma balê xwe dayê wextê ez derbazî gundî we bûm
maşalla razî gundî we pirr ne.
Mother Kawa I paid attention when I passed your village
mashallah your village orchards are many.
Erê.
Yes.
Û çilê xwe jî rind e.
And its '40' is good.
Rindê gidê gulgo ne.
Good all like roses.
Çil û kija nûha pir rind e ji min hêra mesele?
Which '40' is very good now for me there for example?
Î tu kulgon.
The one of roses.
Teriyê xwe jî rind e û çilê xwe jî rind e.
Its grapes are good and its '40' is good.
Erê.
Yes.
Di vê gundî da mesele Dayika Kawa hîn berê çi pira dibîn?
In this village for example Mother Kawa what did they see
before?
Weci vê gundî çawa ye? Îro roja xwe çû derbaz dikin?
How is the situation of this village? How do they pass their
day today?
Çi tişkê ji me ra xeber de.
Tell us something.
Walla yarm wecî gundî işte feqîreleqî ye.
By God my dear the village situation is just simple/poor.
Jîyê tev xweş, sorme ne, kulik e, kitawî ye, şorbe ye, dew
e, boranî ye.
Life is all good, dung cakes, bread, dish, soup, yogurt
drink, spinach stew.
...
Tiştiya hokî ye.
Things like that.
Yane xweş e û rind e û em jî hez dikin û em dikin.
Meaning it is good and fine and we like it and we do it.
Dayika Kawa li her gundekî mesele em bêne li berê diçûn hêra
li ber kaniya dişûştin...
Mother Kawa in every village for example we say in the past
they went there to wash at the spring...
Kinc û cila dişûştin.
Washed clothes and garments.
We wextê gîştiye te çû?
Did that time reach you?
Walla erê ez biçûk bûm bes rind tê bîra min.
By God yes I was small but I remember well.
Av ê sar xonyo bîxo, na axî bî, berdin serî nco, diniştin
vedxwarin.
Water cold... sat and drank.
Û kincê xwe jî me dibirin ber bîra gēlê... jêrî gundî me bîr
heye.
And our clothes we took to the well of the valley... below
our village there is a well.
Berbû dare dişûştin. Me seyî qîçkê xwe lwor dişûştin.
Under the tree they washed. We washed our small children
there.
Me kincê xwe jî ser hejar, ser derya daro zia dikirin me top
dikirin didan hevdu û em dihatin.
We dried our clothes on rocks, on wood, gathered them,
folded them and came.
Noka bes makîne hene.
Now only machines exist.
Makîne hene, ceyran heye, gassale heye, hemî tişt heye.
Machines exist, electricity exists, washing machine exists,
everything exists.
Noka rehetî ye.
Now is comfort.
Lê di wextê berê da xweştir bû yan noka?
But was it better in the past time or now?
Walla wextê berê xweştir bû.
By God past time was better.
Çima?
Why?
Çunkî berê emanet hebû. Noka emanet tune.
Because before there was trust. Now there is no trust.
Rastgotin hebû.
There was truth-telling.
Emanet hebû.
There was trust.
Mirovî, cîrantî hebû.
Humanity, neighborliness existed.
Noka tune.
Now it doesn't exist.
Noka tune, heyat derbaz dibe. Bes noka ji we çaxê xweştir e.
Now doesn't exist, life passes. But now is better than that
time.
Heyata noka xweş e, bes emanet tune.
Life now is good, but no trust.
Berê sir hebû, sitare hebû, heval heval bû.
Before there was secrets, protection, friend was friend.
Yekî tengî ser şorek bikira sirê mala li cem diman.
If one was in trouble over a word, the secret of the house
stayed with them.
Noka ne waha ye.
Now it's not like that.
Bes heyata xweş, xesale derketine, berad derketine, şaşe
derketine.
But good life, washing machines came out, fridges came out,
screens came out.
Yane her malekê makîne xodî rektor xu heye, xweş e.
Meaning every house has a machine... tractor... it's good.
Em kênin bibêjin Dayika Kawa heyat pêşket, titawir bû, bes
hezkirin kêm bû.
We can say Mother Kawa life progressed, developed, but love
decreased.
Kêm bû.
Decreased.
Siqat kêm bû.
Trust decreased.
Siqata di berê jî rind bû.
Trust in the past was also good.
Hezkirine berê hezkirin bû, rind bû, şûr şûr bû.
Love of the past was love, was good, salty salty.
Erê.
Yes.
Dayika Kawa Xwedê ji te razî be, ez pir kêfxweş bûm...
Mother Kawa God be pleased with you, I was very happy...
Em bi war ro niştin û em derbas bûn malê xwuşk û kîbar bîn.
We sat with you and we passed to the house of sister and
noble.
Te emr te, tu gotina te li mehan a beriyê ez derim?
You commanded, your words... before I leave?
Gotina we ehlan we sehlan.
Your words welcome.
Silavê min şa bî waribo giya re hene.
My greetings to happy... all existing ones.
Layê min Xaseten Huseyn.
My son especially Huseyn.
Qîçkê xoke migiştiko, hecî Meryem a lê, silavê min ji giya
re hene.
My small children all, Hecî Meryem there, my greetings to
all.
Û xokê min li Nemsa ye, silavê min jî re hene.
And my sister in Austria, my greetings to them too.
Xwedê siheta xweş bide de, Xwedê bi qîçkê hindî şokre bide.
God give you good health, God give thanks with the children.
Û qîzê min jî li Tirkiyê ye, emeliyata gorçika kirî, gorçika
xwe daye qîza xwe.
And my daughter is in Turkey, did kidney surgery, gave her
kidney to her daughter.
Pir tesîr min bûye berketim a.
I was very affected.
Û nexweş e, înşalla rehet bibe, nîzîk da jê keye herim cem.
And she is sick, inshallah she gets better, soon I will go
to her.
Eke bibînim.
If I see her.
Ez pir jî hez dikim, wey jî û qîzî gundî jî.
I love her very much, her and the village girls too.
Silavê min pir û pir ji re hene, çavê giya maç dikim.
My greetings many and many to her, I kiss everyone's eyes.
Xwedê destê xwe serî giya ra bigire û ehlan we sehlan û
Xwedê soxliqê bide înşalla.
God hold his hand over everyone's head and welcome and God
give health inshallah.
Înşalla Xwedê rehetiyê bide û emrê dirêj bide.
God willing God give comfort and give long life.
Xwedê siheta xweş bide.
God give good health.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Saeta te xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be, û ehlan we sehlan gotina
we.
Have a good time, God be pleased with you, and welcome to
your speech.
Dayika Kawa ji me ra got, min çavê xwe emeliyat kirin.
Mother Kawa told us, I operated on my eyes.
Erê.
Yes.
Ez çûm cem nojdar.
I went to the doctor.
Jerkî li Têkê hîs nas nekirin, tim dîtin ser çavê çilê.
A place in Teke didn't recognize feeling, always looked on
the eye of forty.
Çare nadî.
Found no cure.
Û jimre jî hewla nadan... noka jimre hewla dana.
And didn't give number... now gave number.
Paşê ba'dî emeliyat kirin jimre hewl dan.
Then after surgery they gave number.
Hemdilla nacihî... qîzê min Zeynepê, qîza xwe... da qîza
xwe.
Thank God successful... my daughter Zeynep, her daughter...
gave to her daughter.
Navê qîzkê Esra ye, yê biçûk.
The girl's name is Esra, the small one.
Û Hemdilla nacihî, hucû kelî jî va kirin.
And thank God successful, opened.
Û rindin, rehetin, û Xwedê rehetiyê bide, û umetê Mihemed
giyare rehma ya Reb.
And they are good, comfortable, and God give comfort, and
mercy to all Ummah of Muhammad oh Lord.
Xwedê rehetiyê bide û emrê dirêj bide.
God give comfort and long life.
Em bixêrhatina Kekê Xelîl dikin, qenata Hatim Efrînî.
We welcome Brother Khalil, channel Hatim Afrini.
Hûr hat cem me, nîvandariyê gundî me bî, gundî Selû em pir
kêfxweş in bi hatina we gindî.
He came to us, guest of our village, village Selu, we are
very happy with your coming to the village.
Wekî hûn dibînin, ev ev carê dorê ye, ev carê bo vokal e,
karê me ye.
As you see, this is the turn, this turn for ???, it is our
work.
Em cot dajon ne ji ezel de em dajon, ne ji noka da.
We plow not from eternity we plow, not from now.
Teqrîben emrê min, ez 14 salî bûm cot dajom û heta noka ez
cot dajom û karê xwe ser karê xwe me.
Approximately my age, I was 14 years old I plow and until
now I plow and I am on my work.
Sisilavê me ji milet gî ra hene.
Our greetings to all the nation.
Û em bixêrhatina Kekê Xelîl dikin, qenata Hatim Efrînî.
And we welcome Brother Khalil, channel Hatim Afrini.
Hewa text e, hewa xalê Hisên şêkiş came gundî jimra hediye
aniye hewa.
This is the board, this Uncle Hussein shekish from the
village brought as a gift for us this.
Bi xwe jî xweş e.
It itself is good.
Silavê me ji gind ra jî hene.
Our greetings to the village too.
Miletê kîbar û delal, em derbaz gundê Selû bûn.
Precious and dear nation, we passed through Selu village.
Me tişkê ji gund wera teswîr kir.
We filmed something of the village for you.
Û li gundî Selû pênc YouTuber hene.
And in Selu village there are 5 YouTubers.
Noha em kê derbaz cem Kekê Mihûbin.
Now we will go to Brother Mihûb.
Em ê pirsk kin, û Kurmanc hemî dibin mila bin, em bi hev de
hene.
We will ask, and Kurds/Kurmanji all become shoulder to
shoulder, we are together.
Heger em bi hev ra harîkarî nekin, û em da hev de ra di
vîdeo ra muşareke nekin, kes nayê bi me ra harîkarî nake.
If we don't help each other, and we don't share in the video
with each other, no one will come to help us.
Kesê xerîb destê me nagire.
Strangers won't hold our hand.
Em gî Kurmanc ew Kurd em ê gî bi destê hevdu bigrin.
We all Kurmanj or Kurd we will all hold each other's hands.
Û noha jî em ê derbaz cem Kekê Mihûb bin...
And now we will pass to Brother Mihûb...
Youtube, îro em li gundê Selo ne, em ê bibin mêvanê wan.
YouTube, today we are in the village of Selo, we will be
their guests.
Û bi hevre vîdeoyeke xweş û kîbar em ê derbas bikin.
And together, we will pass a pleasant and nice video.
Em ê derbas bin, jê bipirsin.
We will proceed, we will ask them.
Hela çend sal in qenata xwe vekirî û wek jimara xeberdanê,
di gundî Selo da pênc Youtuber hen di gundî wî da.
How many years have they opened their channel, and as the
number suggests, in the village of Selo, there are five
YouTubers in this village.
Em ê derbas bin cem wan. Merheba.
We will go over to them. Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Allah selameta te bide ya Reb.
May God grant you safety, oh Lord.
Ez Xelîl ji gundê Baedîna, ji qenata Yado Efrîn, herwiha ez
nûnerê gundê weme.
I am Khalil from the village of Baedina, from the Yado Afrin
channel, and I am also the representative of our village.
Mît selamê, ehlen we sehlen birayê Xelîl. Tu bi xêr hatî.
A hundred hellos, welcome brother Khalil. You are welcome.
Saet xweş. Em te nas bikin birayê giyan. Navê te bi xêr?
Good times [pleasure to meet you]. Let us get to know you,
dear brother. What is your name [with goodness]?
Xwedê navê min Husam e. Sê navê min hene. Muho, hem Naîme
ye, hem Husam e.
By God, my name is Husam. I have three names. Muho, it's
also Naîme, and it's Husam.
Eslê navê te?
Your original name?
Heqîqî Husam. Erê.
The real one is Husam. Yes.
Ez derbasî gundê Selo bûm, pişta min... min seh kir çeye, çi
têtin e di vî gundî de.
I entered the village of Selo, behind me... I heard what is
happening, what is going on in this village.
Jimara bêlekir, pênc Youtuber gezna şaş bim di gundê we de
hene?
A notable number, are there five YouTubers, if I am not
mistaken, in your village?
Erê maşallah pênc in, erê.
Yes, Mashallah, there are five, yes.
Me dixwast, gih giha hazir nin sê, ez giya jî derxim di
îdafe xeleqekê kim çimkî ez nûnerê gundê weme.
We wanted to, not all of them are present now, only three, I
will feature them all in an additional episode because I am
the representative of our village.
Eywa.
I see.
Ez tiştekê ser te dirêj bikim, herwiha qenata min, em
dixwazin însan giş hevdû ra kevin.
I will elaborate on something for you, regarding my channel,
we want all people to support each other.
Tebeqen, şî ekîd.
Of course, that's certain.
Hemî sêngê hev, herwiha em Kurmanc me bi hevdû hene.
All side by side, moreover we are Kurds, we have each other.
Lê?
Right?
Gi qenatî te Youtube heye, gi yê min heye, gi em gi bi hevra
kar nekin, dest nedin hev, yek kesê xerîb nayê me ra kar
nake.
If you have a YouTube channel, if I have one, if we all
don't work together, don't hold hands, a stranger won't come
and work with us.
Waye, bizzat.
That is true, exactly.
Ê min hewa, wîcêt nezerî ya min e.
That is it, that is my point of view.
Bi sê dê waye şûl zêre. Gerek em bi hevra kar bikin.
Indeed it is so, it's golden work. We must work together.
Ee tebîetê gund saxbûn, em ê tirba bi sewrînin, em ê bîrê
davê bi sewrînin û ez dixwazim însanê di cem were jî derbas
bim, silamkê bu we de.
Uh, keeping the nature of the village alive, we will film
the tombs, we will film the water wells, and I want to pass
by the people with you, to greet you.
Erê mît selamê, ehlen we sehlen birayê delal.
Yes, a hundred hellos, welcome dear brother.
Kekê Muho, niha em werin ser qenata te.
Brother Muho, now let's come to your channel.
Qenata te tenê ne yan kesek jin te re di şixilê?
Is your channel yours alone or does someone work with you?
Bixwedê, bixo du qenat in.
By God, actually there are two channels.
Qenateke mezin heye, hewa em em her sêk me, ez û Zekerî û
Hemûdê.
There is a big channel, that one is us, the three of us: me,
Zakaria, and Hamouda.
Tebqen ne xerîb in, pismamê min in.
Of course, they aren't strangers, they are my cousins.
E navê qenatî te kêne jimara hewal de?
Tell the friends [viewers] the name of your channel?
Afrin Tube.
Çiqas muşterîkî xwe heye hewa?
How many subscribers does that one have?
Teqrîben nîzikî sî û pênc hezar muşterek hene.
Approximately close to thirty-five thousand subscribers.
Çend sal in hûn li ser şixilî?
How many years have you been working on it?
Bixwedê hewa teqrîben şeş sal heye me vekiriye.
By God, that one, it's been about six years since we opened
it.
Muhtewa we li ser çi diqedînin?
What content do you present on it?
Bixwedê em çû meşhûr bûn e, bi fîlmê me komêdya em meşhûr
bûn e. Erê.
By God, how we became famous, we became famous through our
comedy films. Yes.
Û niha qenata te bitenê jî heye?
And now do you have a channel of your own as well?
Erê qenata min a aîlî, Mho Afrin Tube.
Yes, my family channel, Mho Afrin Tube.
Hewa ya tu ser Mho Afrin, tu çi ew dikî?
That one, on Mho Afrin, what do you do there?
Heyat yewmî, mesela şîvna, filok, ez diherim Efrîn tê me,
webtê... diçim bazarê teswîr dikim, birêva teswîr dikim,
yanî heyat yewmî.
Daily life, for example dinners, vlogs, I go to Afrin and
come back... I go to the market and film, I film on the
road, meaning daily life.
Yanî heyat yewmîya te ji milletî xwe ra diqedînî?
So you present your daily life to your people?
Erê, erê aîlî, bi şekl aîlî. Ez û jinka xwe derdikevin.
Yes, yes, family, in a family style. Me and my wife appear.
Erê.
Yes.
İnşallah ya Reb Xwedê quwetê ke bo we giya de, û karê
Youtube jî ne qûlayî ye.
God willing, oh Lord, may God give strength to you all, and
YouTube work is not easy.
Tebeqen, tebeqen. Lê?
Of course, of course. Right?
Em çima ser qenata te dêng kin, milletî Kurd hemî lome seyr
dikê ser qenatî min li Efrîn.
The reason we are voicing this on your channel, is that all
the Kurdish people watch [content] on my channel in Afrin.
Herwiha însanê di Kurmanc li kîderê dibin bila bibin, gava
dît muhtewa vekirin, ew hedefek xwe ew kirin, ew tiştek ji
milletî xwe ra muşareke kin.
Furthermore, Kurdish people wherever they may be, when they
see content being created, they set a goal for themselves,
they share something with their people.
Gengê ne kêle gundê bi layikekê biskinin, bi iştîrakekê, ma
qesirîn nevinê lê?
Young people shouldn't just stand by in the village, with a
like, with a subscription, they shouldn't fall short in
this, right?
Waye, walla şûl zêre.
That's right, by God, it's golden work.
Gerek wabe, erê.
It must be so, yes.
Bi hês em zimanê Kurmancî diqedînin û em Kurmanc in, gerek
em bi hevdû hene.
Since we present in the Kurmanji language and we are Kurds,
we must support each other.
Erê walla, mî ji sedî. Tebeqen, tebeqen.
Yes, by God, one hundred percent. Of course, of course.
Kekê Muho niha em derbas ser qenata te ya vayê niha aîlî te
ew dikê. E tu ta got ez û jinka xwe derdikevin.
Brother Muho, now let's move to your channel, the one your
family runs. You said you and your wife appear.
Erê.
Yes.
E tu yewmîyat ji milletî xwe ra muşareke dikê?
Do you share daily activities with your people?
Erê, heyat yewmî mesela em çûn selem, herwiha şîvk me heye,
em teswîr dikin em şîv çêdikin, mesela em çûn Efrîn, mesela
em çûn zîyaretê mesela gundê Oşka, gundê Satûyo.
Yes, daily life, for example we went to greet someone, also
we have a dinner, we film while making dinner, for example
we went to Afrin, for example we went for a visit, for
example to the village of Oshka, the village of Satuyo.
Yanî filoket em teswîr dikin jî.
Meaning we film vlogs too.
Yanî minewea'at te ew dikê.
So you do a variety of things.
Erê, bideqet.
Yes, exactly.
Ededê muşterîkîn cem te çiqas gihiştiye hewa?
What number of subscribers have you reached on that one?
Xwedê heşt hezar qût kiriye hewliyan.
By God, it has passed eight thousand currently.
İnşallah eqbalê mîyakî dibê.
God willing, here's to the hundred [thousand].
Sobî ya Reb, eqbalê sed hezarî ji te ra ji bîrê Xelîl.
Amen, oh Lord, here's to a hundred thousand for you too,
brother Khalil.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Amîn.
Amen.
Niha em werin ser te'lîqo.
Now let's come to the comments.
Hm.
Te'lîqatê selbîyat te dibînê lê te nabînê?
Do you see negative comments or do you not see them?
Xwedê te'lîqê selbî la bud minnû, icbarî kî hebê. Her kasekî
nacih, nacih e, icbarî neqdê kî hebê, selb, selb, selbîyat
kî hebê.
By God, negative comments are inevitable, they must exist.
Every successful person, successful, there must be critique,
neg, neg, negativity there will be.
Lê?
Right?
Yanî te dibînê te çû vêra muamela dikê?
Meaning when you see them, how do you deal with them?
Bixwedê, adî yanî, mesela e heye, mesela e gelek giran
giran, em mesih dikim. E welle e adî adî, yanî...
By God, it's normal, meaning, for example if there is one,
for example one that is very very heavy [insulting], I
delete it. If, by God, it's normal normal, meaning...
A te'lîqê neqd ew mesela bin selbî zêde te hezif dikê.
Ah, comments of critique, or for example if they are overly
negative, you delete them.
Erê. Mesela hun çûne berê Xelîl mesela te'lîq dikin, ku bi
sîxet ku çû ku yanî istifzaz.
Yes. For example you went, brother Khalil, for example they
comment, in a format that goes towards, meaning,
provocation.
Lê? Mesela mezin binere, ha wî xû çû dike wa wa, yanî ka
yanî...
Right? For example look at the big one, ha look what he's
doing blah blah, meaning like, meaning...
Şuûrê însên dişkênê.
Breaks a person's feelings.
Bideqet, şuûrê însên dişkênê. Eywa.
Exactly, breaks a person's feelings. Yes.
Erê walla.
Yes, by God.
Tebeqen millet gi ne waye.
Of course, the people aren't all like that.
Ne, ne, tebeqen beşerê baş heye, beşerê xirab heye.
No, no, of course there are good people, there are bad
people.
Şî ekîd. Xwandavan heye, êd musaqqaf hene.
That's certain. There are educated people, cultured ones.
Erê walla.
Yes, by God.
Û bixwedê ez derbas vî gundî bûm, yanî bixo gundî we çûçik e
ne mezin e.
And by God, I entered this village, meaning your village is
actually small, not big.
Çûçik e lê? Erê.
It is small, right? Yes.
Û Youtuber têda go pênc in, ez kî giya inşallah gi yekî nû
mir derkên, yekî giya ra muşareke kim.
And you said there are five YouTubers in it, I hope all of
them, if a new one comes out, I will share/collaborate with
all of them.
İnşallah, inşallah.
God willing, God willing.
Û inşallah yanî yekî dibên em gi bi hevra serkevin û rojê
pêşda em ê we li cîyê bilind bibînin.
And God willing, meaning as they say, let us all succeed
together and in the days ahead we will see you in a high
place.
İnşallah ya Reb. Têjî walla muhtewê te pir eciband, anced
yanî. Têjî rehet dibê ser xwe.
God willing, oh Lord. You too, by God, I liked your content
a lot, truly. You too are getting comfortable with it.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Xeyo pêncî hezar be. Mebde'îyen pêncî hezar be.
Brother, let it be fifty thousand. Initially, let it be
fifty thousand.
Niha tu hûru biçînê, derbikê, siba tu nekê, bixêr e.
Now if you go bit by bit, produce it, tomorrow if you don't
do it, it's good.
Erê walla.
Yes, by God.
Tu kê biskine pişta demekî.
You will stop after a while.
Tebeqen.
Of course.
Gi te rehetî dixwazê, şixul dixwazê.
If you want comfort, it requires work.
Erê walla rehetî ye.
Yes, by God, it is comfort.
Çi dibên bila bibê kekê Muho, destpêkê pir çetin e.
Whatever they say, let it be, brother Muho, the beginning is
very difficult.
Çetin e, çetin e. Erê walla çetin e.
It is difficult, difficult. Yes, by God, it is difficult.
Niha em biftilin ser qenat dîsa.
Now let's turn back to the channel again.
Bûrum.
Go ahead.
Te'lîqeke, aw gît însanek, mesela tarîxek şerezmîş kir, te
zêde pê êşand, aw heta niha te bîr nekir. Hene te'lîqek pir
selbî.
A comment, or a person, for example wrote a history [long
comment], that hurt you a lot, that until now you haven't
forgotten. Is there a very negative comment?
Ee wextê me fîlm komêdî çêdikir, teben şexsîyek heye navê
xwe Naîme ye.
Uh, when we were making comedy films, of course there is a
character named Naîme.
Ee.. mixu dikir çû, ku jinek me.
Uh... I was making myself out to be, like I'm a woman.
Şerim, mixu dikir.. yanî huwe temsil u ser temsil e.
Shame, I was making myself... meaning it is acting upon
acting.
Temsîl, temsîl, eywa.
Acting, acting, yes.
Mesela dibên çiya walla 'amel halo mara mişan el muşahadat',
'amel halo mara mişan el' yanî 'jîb laykat'.
For example they say "By God, he made himself a woman for
the views", "made himself a woman for the" meaning "to get
likes".
Yanî hewa temsîl e. Yanî Quseyrî Sema kani Ebû Anter,
şexsîyeta Ebû Anter.
Meaning that is acting. Like Qusai al-Sema, who was Abu
Antar, the character of Abu Antar.
Tenê di xû çû kir? Mesela Eyma Rêda, hew mumesilîn sûrîyîn.
Look how he made himself? For example Ayman Reda, those
Syrian actors.
E.. yanî adî ye. İşekî adî ye.
Uh.. meaning it is normal. It's a normal job.
E ekîd yanî temsîl nayê u'teber şexsîyeta te ye, şexsîye
murakebe tîtînî hez xwe ra derdixînî.
Uh certainly, acting is not considered your personality,
it's a composite character you bring out for yourself.
Bideqet, bideqet. Fe î heye, yanî, nizam çû yanî, bûn ku çû
ku çetin e.
Exactly, exactly. So there is this, meaning, I don't know
how, being like that is hard.
Yanî heta wichet nezer muxtelif e.
Meaning even the point of view is different.
Muxtelif e, bideqet muxtelif e.
It is different, exactly different.
Yella inşallah tiş nabe.
Well, God willing, it's nothing.
İnşallah kî dibên qubat li deh hezarî be, û tu dapoqe bikê û
inşallah tu psedîgînî. Milletî Kurd em gi, wekî dibên,
binîhayê, binîhayê ji hewa babê rizq e.
God willing, as they say, may the outcome be ten thousand,
and you push through, and God willing you reach the hundred
[thousand]. We Kurdish people all, as they say, in the end,
in the end, this is also a door of livelihood.
Tebeqen babê rizq e yanî.
Of course it is a door of livelihood, meaning.
Xwedê rizqê we giya bişîne.
May God send livelihood to you all.
Waya şî ekîd.
That is certain.
Xwedê ji te razî be. Em pir kêfxweş bûn herwiha em bûn
mêvanê gundê we ne.
May God be pleased with you. We were very happy also that we
became guests of your village.
Mît selamê, ehlen we sehlen.
A hundred hellos, welcome.
Û bixwedê yanî tişt destê me darkeve heta kênim, ezê giya
bixwe ra muşareke kim.
And by God, meaning whatever comes from my hand as much as I
can, I will share all of it with myself.
Tu noqesirînî.
You don't fall short.
Kî dibê bila bibê, li kijan gundî Youtuber hebin, ferman
hebin, ez dixwazim gelek Kurmancî xwe biskinim.
Whoever it may be, in whichever village there are YouTubers,
[or] orders/issues, I want to support my Kurmanji people a
lot.
Heta lo bi kşûrekê be ez vêra bim bi tewfîq.
Even if it's with a peel [something small], I will be with
them with success.
Heta wele bi layk.
Even, by God, with a like.
Heta bi layk çi dibê bila bibê.
Even with a like, whatever it may be.
Gi ez kênim kelakê biskinim, gerek ez neqesirîm. Ez ser xwe
deyn dikim tebeqen.
If I can stand by someone's side, I must not fall short. I
consider it a debt upon myself, of course.
Saet xweş, weleh tu noqesirînî.
Good times, by God you don't fall short.
Yanî herwiha em Kurmanc wek me gotî, emê dîsa bêjin, em bi
hevdû hene.
Meaning furthermore, we Kurds, as we said, we will say
again, we have each other.
Erê, şî ekîd lê, em bi hevdû hene.
Yes, that's certain right, we have each other.
Û qenatê xwe ji aw bike, bernede, berdewam ke. Û inşallah
rojê pêş da hûn qenaya mezin be, jîşka. Xwedê rizqê giya
bişîne, ya min jî bişîne.
And work on your channel, don't drop it, continue. And God
willing in the days ahead you will be a big channel, God
willing. May God send livelihood to all, and send mine too.
İnşallah, inşallah. Amîn, amîn ya Reb. Erê walla.
God willing, God willing. Amen, amen oh Lord. Yes, by God.
Û tu karî bar qenat ra nakê?
And you don't do any other work besides the channel?
La tebeqen, ez du şixulim baro.
No, of course, I have two jobs on the side.
Tu bar du şixulî.
You have two jobs on the side.
Lê şî ekîd e hewa.
Yes that is certain.
E tu çi karî dikê bar?
Uh what work do you do on the side?
Karê çûlê, bixwedê yanî çûl û halî em daren çûl û, bêsibê em
diçûn çûl û, ba berav kir.
Field work, by God meaning field and situation, we have
fields and, in the morning we go to the field and, gathering
windfalls [olives].
Erê walla, yanî wextê be'îv em daren be'îv, wextê tirş em
daren tirş, yanî zeytûna.
Yes by God, meaning when it's almond time we handle almonds,
when it's pickles [or sour fruits] we handle pickles,
meaning olives.
Kored gundo.
Village chores.
İjbarî, kored gundo bi şekl am em dikin.
Mandatorily, village chores in a general way we do them.
Ma ka no meşê.
Otherwise it doesn't work.
No meşê, hewa seî bab rizq e bes inno yanî işkî pir remzî
tê, yanî...
It doesn't work, that is a true door of livelihood but it
means a very symbolic work comes from it, meaning...
Saet xweş, em te nas kirin. Xwedê ji te razî be.
Good times, we got to know you. May God be pleased with you.
Spasdarim ji te ra, saet xweş.
I am thankful to you, good times.
Xwedê ji te razî be birayê delal.
May God be pleased with you dear brother.
Ez tiştek ji mutabîn te ra bêjim?
Can I say something to your followers?
Bêje, keremke.
Say it, please.
Mutabîîn Birayê Xelîl, yanî her kesî bixwaze qenata Youtube
veke, qet me'yos nebe, yanî ji sifrê dest pê bike heta
bigihîje encamê.
Followers of Brother Khalil, meaning anyone who wants to
open a YouTube channel, never despair, meaning start from
zero until you reach the result.
Ewel şî, mebde'îyen mebde'îyen, muşahadat tinenin,
muşterikîn tinenin.
First thing, initially initially, there are no views, there
are no subscribers.
Bêhnek fireh dixwaze.
It requires broad patience.
Bideqet, bêhnek fireh dixwaze.
Exactly, it requires broad patience.
Yanî bixwedê Youtube alema wî cûda ye.
Meaning by God, YouTube's world is different.
Cûda ye ji alema Tîktok û Facebook, cûda ye.
It is different from the world of TikTok and Facebook,
different.
Ew sîyaseta Youtube pir zora ye.
The policy of YouTube is very tough.
Yaa bideqet, sîyaseta Youtube pir zor e.
Yea exactly, the policy of YouTube is very tough.
Mebde'îyen çetin e.
Initially it is hard.
Hiquq neşr hene.
There are copyrights.
Hiquq neşr hene, bideqet.
There are copyrights, exactly.
Tîktok çiye, klemkê dîne ser vîdyo we meşî.
What is TikTok, put a song on the video and it walks
[works].
Meşî, erê.
It walks, yes.
Youtube ne waye, Youtube gerek muhtewa te be, dengê te be,
sûretê te be.
YouTube is not like that, YouTube must be your content, your
voice, your image.
Yanî çetin e, mebde'îyen çetin e.
Meaning it is hard, initially it is hard.
E ekîd her tiştî zehmetî xwe heye.
Uh certainly everything has its difficulty.
Bideqet. Bes inno, îrarade hebe, ezm hebe, inşallah hûn ê
bighîjinê.
Exactly. But that, if there is will, if there is
determination, God willing you will reach it.
Kî dibê bila bibê, berê Xelîl jî di nav de.
Whoever it may be, Brother Khalil included.
Tebeqen, berê Xelîl jî di nav de.
Of course, Brother Khalil included.
Xwedê ji te razî be birayê delal.
May God be pleased with you dear brother.
Heta ez te'lîqê selbî bixwînim, ez guh nadimê.
Even if I read negative comments, I don't give an ear to
them.
Tu car guh nedinê.
Never give an ear to them.
Tu carî guh medê, guh bidê tu bişkê.
Never give an ear, if you give an ear you will break.
Tu bişkê bideqet, tu biskine pişta demekî.
You will break exactly, you will stop after a while.
Ma tu şixul nekî xelq bi te napeyîve.
If you don't do work, people won't talk about you.
La tebeqen, eger tu ne nacih bî kes te napeyîve.
No of course, if you aren't successful no one talks about
you.
E ku te kar kir xelq ê bi te bipeyîve.
Uh if you did work, people will talk about you.
Tebeqen. Şî ekîd.
Of course. That is certain.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Em pir kêfxweş bûn.
We were very happy.
Ser serî min.
Good times.
On my head [you are welcome].
Xwedê ji te razî be birayê delal.
May God be pleased with you dear brother.
Mît selamê, ehlen we sehlen.
A hundred hellos, welcome.
Xatirê te birayê delal.
Goodbye dear brother.
Oxir be.
Farewell.
Milete kîbar û delal, li gundê Selo me muqabele Kekê Muho re
çêkir.
Noble and dear people, in the village of Selo we did an
interview with Brother Muho.
Navê gund Husam, qenata xwe Youtube hebi, û niha Youtuber dî
tê di gundê Selo de, Kekê Alan, ew jî êlek pir mutawadîe û
pir kîbar û delal in.
The village name [speaker corrects himself] Husam, he had
his YouTube channel, and now another YouTuber comes in the
village of Selo, Brother Alan, he is also a very humble
family and very noble and dear.
Emê rojê em gund im jî, û emê silam ke gundî din, hine ez
nas dikim hine jî...
We will [spend] the day in the village too, and we will
greet the other villagers, some I know and some too...
Hine ji min re naskirin.
Some were introduced to me.
Rastî gundê Selo pir bixwe ne mezin e, me lexta de gundê jî
jiberbirin êgûn.
Truly the village of Selo is actually not very big, we
crossed the village in a short time.
Û qedrê îmkan ez se kim em vê însana jî derxin em bi hevra
derkevin.
And as much as possible I will try to bring these people out
too, so we appear together.
Û niha bimînin, emê dem derbas Kekê Alan bin, ew jî êlek pir
mutawadîe, û kîbar û delal in.
And now stay, we will go over to Brother Alan, he is also a
very humble family, and noble and dear.
Emê derbas bin, emê pirskin, hine ez nas dikim hine nayê nas
kirim.
We will proceed, we will ask, some I know some I don't know.
Selam aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Ehlen we sehlen kekê.
Welcome brother.
We aleykum selam.
And upon you peace.
Walla elhemduillah tu çawa yî?
By God praise be to God, how are you?
Êwa çawa ne?
How are you [plural]?
Walla elhemduillah. Derbas be.
By God praise be to God. Come in.
Yella.
Let's go.
Derbas be kekê derbas be.
Come in brother, come in.
Ehlen we sehlen kekê tu bi xêr hatî.
Welcome brother, you are welcome.
Berî giya em te nas bikin, xwedê ji te razî be.
Before all, let us get to know you, may God be pleased with
you.
Em navê me Alan e.
We, our name is Alan.
Û bî teqrîben bî salek e eştirkî otime vî derê.
And it's been approximately a year since I participated/came
here.
Erê.
Yes.
Tamam, kekê Alan navê xokî me?
Okay, brother Alan, the name of our [your] channel?
Alan û Heyat e.
It is Alan and Hayat.
Ser qenatê erê heyat e.
On the channel, yes it is Hayat [Life].
Heyat e.
It is Hayat.
Niha ez derbas gundê Selo bûm, min dixwast ez tişkî muxtelif
û acer jî di xelekê xwe de ew bikim.
Now I entered the village of Selo, I wanted to do something
different and strange/new in my episode.
Ahlen, ahlen we sehlen.
Welcome, welcome.
Derbas cem we bîm, bo qenatê Youtube zekirî.
To pass by you, regarding the YouTube channel mentioned.
Tebeqen.
Of course.
Maşallah min seh kir ku pênc qenat di gundê we da hene.
Mashallah I heard that there are five channels in your
village.
Erê.
Yes.
Muhtewê te ser qenatê Youtube, ma bixo ev pir meraq bim,
mesela qenatê min tine bîn.
Your content on the YouTube channel, were you actually very
interested, for example I didn't have a channel.
Em meraq bîm bes hema ser Tîktok meşhûr im.
I was interested but I'm famous on TikTok.
Yan ne meşhûr yan jî işte besît.
Either not famous or just, well, simple.
Ser Tîktok min va dikir, axirê Youtuberêt cem me, me got ko
qenatke, qenatê gundê zêde bî.
On TikTok I was doing this, in the end the YouTubers among
us, we said open a channel, the village channels increased.
Vê qenatê neku li cem min. Got ev qenato li cem me zêde ye.
These channels, not that [just] close to me. Said these
channels near us are many.
Got Alan tu jî, tu meraq e li ser vê qenatê Youtube, min go
erê.
Said Alan you too, you are interested in this YouTube
channel, I said yes.
Min go ko ez dêdim.
I said well I will give [try] it.
Teqrîben bi... mehekaye me birî.
Roughly for... we stopped for a month.
Erê welle ser vê qenetê.
Yes, by God, on this channel.
Û teb'an hemû tiştî tebîa teswîr dikin.
And naturally, we film everything [in] nature.
Me... meselen şîva deran teswîr dikin.
We... for example, we film dinners outside.
Ba'zen em teswîr dikin meselen, dereng difirin derê teswîr
dikin.
Sometimes we film, for example, we go out late and film
outside.
Hinek hevalên me dixwazin, dîsa em teswîr dikin, dîsa çi ji
me dixwazin...
Some of our friends request it, so we film again, whatever
they ask of us...
Erê welle, han em teswîr dikin.
Yes, by God, that is how we film.
Neha wextê te jimarê xeber dayî, qenet ê... Cemo û gund
bûn... Tikî navê kê navê bizerikîne?
Now when you spoke to the viewers, the channel was... Cemo
and the village... Whose name specifically did you want to
mention?
Navê qenetê?
The name of the channel?
Navê însanên didin ser ta qenetê.
The names of the people appearing on your channel.
Navê xezakeriyê...
The name is the wife's... [Xezakeriyê seems to be a compound
of Xezal/Keriyê or a specific local nickname/term].
Himmm.
Hmmm.
Usama û Hemûda ye, û aîlet... û kulfetêt gund in e.
It is Usama and Hamouda, and the family... and the women of
the village.
Vana qerar kir, bi xwe qenet ê... jinka... jinka dwan bî.
They decided, the channel itself... for the women... let it
be for the women.
Ê rabû îşten me... me go ka ginkê ne sa...
So then... we said let's give it a try...
Go em kênin vê qenetê, te dî maşallah te jî tu pir mereq î
ser vê qenetê.
She said let's put it on this channel, and you saw,
Mashallah, you are also very interested in this channel.
Me go ehlen we sehlen, ser serê min, û me go saeta te
xweş... sidqan yanî...
We said welcome, upon my head [you are welcome], and we said
health to you... truly, I mean...
Vî însanî mereqawir kir.
This person took an interest.
Fezlê genda ji bîr nakim teb'an.
Naturally, I will not forget the favor of the people.
Welle destxweş, neha te qenet dan te, paşê ro te... te ser û
berê dest pê kir.
Well done, by God. So now you gave the channel [to her], and
then you... you started managing it.
Erê, teb'an.
Yes, naturally.
Te dest pê kir, û ser TikTok... TikTokê te heye, tu layfana
vedikî, bes neha jî ser YouTube te pir mereq dikî.
You started, and on TikTok... You have TikTok, you open
lives, but now you are also very interested in YouTube.
Ez pir mereq bûm welle, fikir bike, esehî besê TikTok
vedikim, bes ez pir mereqê YouTube im.
I became very interested, by God. Just think, truthfully I
open TikTok enough, but I am very interested in YouTube.
Heta noko.
Until now.
Xwedê rizqê te bişîne, û înşallah... bi sed hezaran be.
May God send you your sustenance, and God willing... may it
reach hundreds of thousands [of subscribers].
Cemî'en ya Reb, amîn, yek giya bişîne.
For all of us, oh Lord, Amen, may He send it to everyone.
Hemû qenetên Kurmancan, YouTube teswîr dikin...
All the Kurdish channels that film for YouTube...
Xwedê bigihîne, Xwedê cankî sax bigihîne.
May God help them succeed, may God grant them good health to
succeed.
Û înşallah hana bi hev du ra harîkin... qenet rabin.
And God willing, may they help each other like this... so
the channels rise.
Ne welle?
Isn't that right?
Welle gava me hev du ra harî nekir... qenet ranabe.
By God, if we don't help each other... the channel won't
rise.
Yanî yanî em bi hev ra nebin... em ranabin. Destê yekî deng
jê nayê.
I mean, if we aren't together... we won't rise. One hand
alone makes no sound.
Hemo kulfeta malê, dêv hev de hene...
All the women of the house, are they all together [in
this]...
Hemo foka me bin... Merheba.
Let them all be my focus/group... Hello.
Ehlen we sehlan, pismam.
Welcome, cousin.
Eşta çawa ye?
How are you doing?
Elhemdulillah, şikur Xwedê ra, tu çawa yî?
Praise be to God, thanks to God, how are you?
Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê siheta te xweş bike, û emrê dirêj
bide.
May God be pleased with you, may God give you good health,
and grant a long life.
Û Xwedê te û kîkê Alan hev du ra bihêle.
And may God keep you and young Alan together.
Sax be, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Be healthy, may God be pleased with you.
Em kanin ji cem te dest pê bikin... şixulê montajê kî montaj
dike?
Can we start with you... regarding the editing work, who
does the editing?
Xwedê Alan montaj dike.
By God, Alan does the editing.
Alan montaj dike. Tu jî kûk mereq e min ser te?
Alan edits. Is he/she also interested like I am about you?
Gel te'lîqatê cîwarê... yozmîş dima, tû dixwînî lê?
Regarding the comments from the area... that are written, do
you read them?
Na, ew dixwîne.
No, he reads them.
Tû dixwînî.
I read them.
You read them.
Temam. Çend mehane teqrîben tu vîdyoya dixî ser... sehfe we
ye neha aîlet Alan e navî gund da?
Okay. For approximately how many months have you been
putting videos on... is your page now "Aîlet Alan" (Alan's
Family) in the village name?
Teb'an aîlet Alan e.
Naturally, it's Aîlet Alan.
Welle mehok heye, kêmî mehokî û der noh e.
Well, it's been a month, a little less than a month and a
half.
Vîdyohetê çi û çi di sewirînin? Ji me ra xeber de.
What kind of videos do you film? Tell us about it.
Vîdyohetê me aîlî ne... mişwarê me ne... meselen gî karê
male... gî şîv e...
Our videos are family-oriented... our outings... for
example, housework... dinner...
Weko vîdyohên Youtuberê me Kurmancan gîya, meselen... tiştek
muhteşem aîlî diqedimînin.
Like the videos of all our Kurdish YouTubers, for example...
presenting something wonderfully family-oriented.
A, yewmiyat... û mutenewi'e cimlet ra muşareke dikin.
Ah, daily logs... and variety, sharing it with the
community.
Mişwar ko hebe, em mişwarê muşareke dikin, û nî qicko û aîlî
derdixînin xeber didin.
If there is an outing, we share the outing, and we bring out
the kids and family and talk.
Erê, em aîlî daxivin.
Yes, we speak as a family.
Tu mişkîla cem we tûne, em vê xelqê daxist ser qenehatê...
ma'ne tûne?
You have no problems on your end, [that] we put these people
on the channels... no issue?
Ne, mişkîla na, welle bi eks, seheta wa xweş be, serkeftin
be ji wa ra.
No, no problems, by God, on the contrary, may they be
healthy, success to them.
Me jî bişîne... û înşallah... te em war tî gotin li me hene,
ser çavê zima.
Send [it/them] to us too... and God willing... since you
invited us here, you are upon our eyes [welcome].
Welle hî... Xwedê ji te razî be, tû hatî, tû honavê...
teswîrê diqedînî.
By God... may God be pleased with you, you came, you
represent this... you are completing the filming.
Gimetî me ra, saeta te xweş, encax...
For our value, health to you, truly...
Dexê mi bîstî got tike werê, mi go ehlen we sehlan, ser serê
min, heva hew jî însan kij me ye.
When I heard that you were coming, I said welcome, upon my
head, this person is also one of us.
Gerek yanî... em başbî xwa bikin.
It implies... we must do our goodness.
Em jî berê em ê kênin, em ê biqedînin teb'an. Em kênin em ê
jêra biqedînin.
Since we are going to do it beforehand, we will present it
naturally. Since we do it, we will present it for them.
Û hew jî mistê me derket, û encax... yîn hatin ser serî me,
ser çavê me.
And he also turned out to be our friend/kin, and truly...
you came upon our heads, upon our eyes.
Xok, biko, giştik... û ehlen we sehlan ji we giya ra.
Sister, brother, everyone... and welcome to all of you.
Mitebînê gind jî... miletî li me sêr dike, û li gind jî sêr
dike, saeta wa giya xweş.
The viewers of the village too... the people watch us, and
watch the village too, health to all of them.
Û înşallah serkeftin be bi giştkora ya Reb.
And God willing, success to everyone, oh Lord.
Xwedê ji we razî be ya Reb, miletê me Kurmanc li kîderê be,
min ra bin... Xwedê rizqê giya bişîne, înşallah gî bibin
ser.
May God be pleased with you oh Lord, wherever our Kurdish
nation may be, let them be with me... May God send
sustenance to all, God willing may all succeed.
Got... malbata we ocax in... ocax tê de hene... tivîyê ji me
ra xeber de ser wa, hinek kesêt me sêr dikê jî bihesin.
It was said... your family is an "Ocax" [Hearth/Lineage]...
there are "Ocax" among you... you must speak to us about
that, so that some people watching us may know.
E ehlen we sehlan... û pir yanî... ez dixwazim milet fêde
bibîne.
Oh welcome... and very much so... I want the people to see
the benefit.
Huru ev tişta ne eyb e, û ne heram e ev tişta.
Look, this thing is not shameful, and this thing is not
forbidden.
Yanî şêxlixî... ocax... teba'en te got ocax se...
I mean sheikh-hood... ocax... naturally since you said
"ocax"...
Yanî tiştkî pir ferq li heye... yanî heva bi duayê Xwedê...
bi Quranê... bi xwendinê...
I mean there is a very distinct difference... I mean this is
with God's prayer... with the Quran... with reading...
Bi limiyê... vî tiştî... yanî... ew dibe. Di wefiqê... di
qebilê yanî.
With prayer... this thing... I mean... it happens. It
corresponds... it is accepted, I mean.
Qebîl dibe vî tişta... yanî vê şêxlixê jî heva...
This thing is accepted... I mean this sheikh-hood as well...
Jide kê me daye.
It was given to us by my grandfather.
Eh, xwe neşixulandiye?
Ah, you didn't work for it yourself?
Na welle... babê min şêx im... ser TikTokê jî heta miro
veşêre dikin...
No by God... my father is a sheikh... even on TikTok people
hide it [or reveal it]...
Bes ez dibêjim me neşixulim... ez limê dikim... der dikim...
elhemdulillah şikur...
But I say I don't practice it [professionally]... I pray...
I go out... praise be to God, thanks...
Îmanî te mekîn e.
Your faith is strong.
Bes... ew navo... ji dilê xwedan se dikim. Ho, heta noko ji
sêr TikTokê me şiro kirî...
But... that name [reputation]... I feel it from my heart.
Look, until now even on TikTok we explained...
Ba xwdê kêm min ocax e.
By God, my house is an "Ocax".
Dekî ta ocax e.
Your house is an "Ocax".
Û me kin e jî.
And we are rooted in it too.
Dest da te lê ne da te?
Did it [the gift/power] give you a hand [pass to you] or
not?
Na welle ew tişta ez nizanim... hîn daîyê min na dayî min...
ez nizanim.
No by God, that thing I don't know... my mother hasn't given
it to me yet... I don't know.
Dixwazim... dixwazim baş bî...
I want... I want goodness...
Xwe rind im... ji milet ra... kar bikim... însan nehene
meselen... nexweş ne...
I am good myself... for the people... to work... people who
are not... for example... who are sick...
Pir însan ser TikTok hatine cem min...
Many people have come to me on TikTok...
Fedlî dayê... dayê dêkêt min... û li... ban Xwedê... banî
şêx dikir...
With the mother's virtue... my mother's prayer... and to...
calling to God... calling to the Sheikh...
Teba'en ta gû ocaxî Şêx Henan da efrîn da me'rûf e.
Naturally, since you mentioned the "Ocax", Sheikh Henan is
famous in Afrin.
Me gî şêx... bes gotin gundî Şêx... mala Şêx Henan me'rûf in
e.
We are all Sheikhs... but when saying "Village of the
Sheikh"... the House of Sheikh Henan is famous.
Destê xwe ma kin ne yanî... sidqan me kin ne.
Don't touch it I mean [it's sacred]... truly it is rooted.
Ê pir însan hatine cem me... qîzkên xwe anîne...
So many people have come to us... brought their daughters...
Yanî... mite wasil kirîb... dêkê xwere vêra deyn kirî... anî
hal mesele gundê haniya...
I mean... having contacted... the mother talking with her...
brought the situation, for example, of such and such
village...
Hono hono vêra dibê... yanî elhemdulillah...
Saying this and that to her... I mean, praise be to God...
Sê qîzik jî... û çar qîzik jî... û mêrek şo jî biya... û
heta noko dibê...
Three girls... and four girls... and a married man came...
and until now they say...
Vê ser... vê kepirê miştera... doketî ye yanî dibê bi sidqan
te çî xwest dibê ehlen we sehlan.
On this... this common bridge... it has fallen, meaning
truly whatever you asked for, it says welcome [it is
granted].
Hevû fa'il xêr... ji hev wa jî hember însên da tiştkî pir
rind e.
That doer of good... for that one too, towards humanity, is
a very good thing.
Te bi miletî xwere harî dikî.
You help your own people.
Teb'an... heta kin e.
Naturally... as much as possible.
Bi nexweşî be... gî çi be...
Whether through sickness... or whatever it may be...
Bi nexweşî be... gî tiştîk be sa... heta vî gijokî gişme...
yanî hawa tişta ne... tiştkî xrab e ji miletê Kurmanc ra
dikin... tiştkî rind e.
Whether through sickness... if it's anything... even this
dizziness/confusion... I mean these things are not... it's
not a bad thing we do for the Kurdish people... it's a good
thing.
Elhemdulillah şikur Xwedê ra... bi limiyê û bi dua... bi
Quranê...
Praise be to God, thanks to God... through prayer and
supplication... through the Quran...
Bavosîno... bi bavê... bavê çê dike... ban Xwedê dike...
Oh father... with the father... the father fixes it... calls
upon God...
Hemdulillah yanî niyeta xwe pak ke û...
Praise God, I mean purify your intention and...
Qebîl dibe.
It gets accepted.
Hebe.
Let it be.
Înşallah Xwedê emrê dirêj bide.
God willing, may God grant a long life.
Amîn, di giya de ya Reb.
Amen, to everyone, oh Lord.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Wekî ocax... te gû ocax... em nekeyn ti şûre bikim... tişkes
nekeyn li ber ocaxo biskine.
As an "ocax"... since you said "ocax"... let's not make it a
sword [conflict]... let no one stand against the "ocax".
Erê.
Yes.
Teb'an ocaxêt me Kurmanca pir in e... û Kurmanc yanî... em
berê bi ocaxo bîn, bi ziaretan bîn.
Naturally, our Kurdish "ocax" are many... and Kurds, I
mean... we used to be with "ocax", with shrines.
Bi tiştêt tûras û filoklor bîn em... em dixwazin vî tiştî ji
henda nebe, erê.
We were with heritage and folklore things... we want this
thing not to disappear from here, yes.
Saeta te xweş Kekê Alan, ez pir kêfxweş bûm... xokê me
Heyat, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Health to you Brother Alan, I was very happy... our sister
Heyat, may God be pleased with you.
Înşallah qeneta we bi sed hezaran be.
God willing, may your channel reach hundreds of thousands.
Înşallah ya Reb, qeneta te jî bi sed hezaran be.
God willing oh Lord, may your channel also reach hundreds of
thousands.
Ez gi dixwazim însanê gi dawak wa... mite wadi' û elî mite
wadi'... û tiştik va kirine, ez dixwazim ka sîr û xelî ji
qenehatim li Efrîn, ez kêla gundê biskinim.
I just want that all people... humble and humble family...
and having done this thing, I want... [unclear] from my
channel in Afrin, I want to stand by the village.
Ser serê min welle.
Upon my head, by God.
Ez pir kêfxweş bîm... bin dîtina we... Xwedê ji we razî be.
I was very happy... seeing you... May God be pleased with
you.
Ehlen we sehlan, welle mi çiqa kêf kir... ne go yek Youtuber
yeke were û muhtewa xweş çêdike...
Welcome, by God I enjoyed it so much... not just saying a
YouTuber comes and creates good content...
Mi go ehlen we sehlan ser serê min. Xeber dan... dan min, go
fewren.
I said welcome upon my head. They spoke... gave me [the
news], said immediately.
Yanî yanî wekî destim jê giyara vekiriye, û qapîm jê giyara
vekiriye.
I mean, like my hand is open to everyone, and my door is
open to everyone.
Xwedê ji we razî be, înşallah rojê pêş da me hîn herin
warin... mala we ava, ez pir kêf xweş bîm, bi ziaret cem we.
May God be pleased with you, God willing in the coming days
we will come and go more... may your house be prosperous, I
was very happy with the visit to you.
Înşallah... e berî vê ez hatim... vê carê semê xost e, semê
warin cem gundê, înşallah ya Reb.
God willing... before this I came... this time it was
requested, to come to the village, God willing oh Lord.
Xwedê ji we razî be, xwedê siheta xweş be. Tê mir wetin
gotin wan... kesî li we sêr dikesa în kêne silav ken ser
qenehatim li Efrîn... silava vêra bişînin, în kêne bişînin.
May God be pleased with you, may God give good health. Do
you have anything to say to them... anyone watching you, let
them send greetings on my channel in Afrin... send greetings
to them, let them send.
Miletî li me sêr dike... xêra we be, em gîb hevda ne.
The people watching us... may it be your blessing, we are
all together.
Huru her yek li me sêr dike sa, sidqan hencam vî însanî...
gindim û teba'e kin...
Look, everyone who watches us, truly follow this person...
follow my village...
Te'lîqêt xweş ra bikin, weş terasê Alan da hatime. Ser
TikTok jî... ser YouTube jî...
Write nice comments, that "I came from Alan's side". On
TikTok too... on YouTube too...
Yanî... hevo... rindî ke. Teb'an ge...
I mean... that... do good. Naturally if...
Ge hin jime hez dikin sa, ge hin ji vê vîdyêt xweş û vê
besetê tet xweş a ser TikTok çêdikim...
If you love us, if you [like] these nice videos and this
nice simplicity I create on TikTok...
Û heryek li me sêr dike... etmenne dikim... hîn hen cem kekê
min.
And everyone watching us... I hope... you come to my brother
[referring to the host].
Filokê xwe xweş e, û vîdyê xwe xweş ne, teswîrî gind...
encet pir xweş e, pir ecban.
His folklore is nice, and his videos are nice, the filming
of the village... truly very nice, I liked it a lot.
Û silav û rêz ji giyara... û ehlen we sehlan ji kekê min
Xelîl ra.
And greetings and respect to everyone... and welcome to my
brother Khalil.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Kîbar û delal, em neha li nivandora gundê Selwa ne.
Precious and dear ones, we are now in the center of the
village of Selwa.
Me pirs kir, gû seyderet di vî gundî da tûne ye.
We asked, they said there is no pharmacy in this village.
Mekteb di vî gundî da yek, ibtidaî.
There is one school in this village, elementary.
Helaq di vî gundî da tûne ye. Dikanê seman yek tenê ye.
There is no barber in this village. There is only one
grocery store.
Cami' di vî gundî da heye. Bîra d'avê, sinane.
There is a mosque in this village. The water well is
separate/private.
Av halîyen na giştî veder e, miletî veder e... kehrebê gundê
gî ser taqa şemsiye ye.
The water currently is not public everywhere, the people are
separate... the electricity of the entire village is on
solar energy.
Saeta we xweş, û ka bi me ra bin, heta dawî vîdyo.
Health to you, and be with us, until the end of the video.
Geryam ez dû hemî waran...
I wandered through all the lands...
Min pirsî ji xûna zozan...
I asked the nature/lineage of the highlands...
Evîna te berda bû dil...
Your love had fallen into the heart...
Min ji bîr nekir te çaran...
I never forgot you at any time...
Evîna te berda bû dil...
Your love had fallen into the heart...
Min ji bîr nekir te çaran...
I never forgot you at any time...
Axaka te zêr û jiyan e...
Your soil is gold and life...
Deşt û merg û te cenet in...
Your plains and meadows are paradise...
Avate pak û kewser e...
Your water is pure and Kawthar [heavenly]...
Efrîna min... Efrîna min...
My Afrin... My Afrin...
Axaka te zêr û jiyan e...
Your soil is gold and life...
Deşt û merg û te cenet in...
Your plains and meadows are paradise...
Avate pak û kewser e...
Your water is pure and Kawthar [heavenly]...
Efrîna min... Efrîna min...
My Afrin... My Afrin...
Qurban bim ez rezê zeytûnê
I sacrifice myself for the olive orchard
Rengê çavê te ez kuştimê
The color of your eyes killed me
Çiyayê Hawar lûlê lûlê
Hawar Mountain, lulu lulu
Ti ji bîra... gorînê
You from memory... [unclear cut]
Keziya pora te meydan ke
Spread out the braids of your hair
Biskê va ra şû ger bike
Let the locks loose to wander
Eniya te Kela Seman e
Your forehead is the Citadel of Seman
Serî bilind ke...
Raise your head...
Miletê kîbar û delal, niha jî lehze tirba zê jê werê
muşareke kim.
Noble and dear people, now I will share the moment of the
tomb with you.
Me ra gotin tirbê gundî Selo herê, hinek li derkene.
They told us to go to the tomb of villager Selo, it is a bit
further out.
Bes êkît li vederê, ezê jê werê teswîr kim.
But there is one here, I will film it for you.
Xidir rehme Xwedê lê, miriyê waqiyakê.
Xidir, God's mercy upon him, a casualty of an incident.
Û saeta we xweş, bimerabin heta tûlî vîdyo.
And have a good time, stay with us for the duration of the
video.
Û niha jî ezê werê lehze tirba muşareke kim.
And now I will share the moment of the tomb with you.
Û bîrmeken me daem ken, emê bi daemî we serkevin.
And don't forget to support us, we will succeed with your
support.
Efrîna min, evîna min
My Afrin, my love
Jan û êşa vê dilî
The pain and ache of this heart
Xec û Zînî, tu şirînî
You are Xec and Zin, you are sweet
Hem derman û hem kulî
You are both the cure and the wound
Qurban bim ez bejn û bala
I sacrifice myself for your stature
Şimêr û mêrxas anîne
You brought forth lions and brave men
Bi yek û sed û hezara
By ones, hundreds, and thousands
Şîn qet neket tew canîne
Mourning never entered those souls
Min yarek dî li vê dinê
I saw a lover in this world
Ew qasî yar bike qurban
Make that many lovers a sacrifice
Bi mirna wan dil be şadî
With their death let the heart be joyful
Şûna şînê bike dîlan
Turn the place of mourning into a dance
Efrîna min, evîna min
My Afrin, my love
Jan û êşa vê dilî
The pain and ache of this heart
Xec û Zînî, tu şirînî
You are Xec and Zin, you are sweet
Hem derman û hem kulî
You are both the cure and the wound