Gelê me yê kîbar û delal, hewa xelqê pêncî ye, qenata "Hatim
Efrîn".
Our noble and dear people, this is the 50th episode, the "I
came to Afrin" channel.
Kanê emê li ku mêvan bin, bi dilekî xweş û geş, em derbasî
gundê Hec Cemala bin.
Let's see where we will be guests; with a happy and bright
heart, let's enter the village of Hec Cemal (Hajj Jamal).
Milletekî kîbar û delal, li xelqa gundê Hec Cemala.
A noble and dear nation, in the episode of the village of
Hec Cemal.
Kanê emê li ku mêvan bin, em hatin mêvandariya êla Mihîdîn.
Let's see where we will be guests, we have come to be guests
of the Mihîdîn clan.
Êla Mihîdîn Youtuber in, ne? Me'rûf in.
The Mihîdîn clan are YouTubers, aren't they? They are
famous.
Kanê emê li ku mêvan bin, emê derbasî cem bin.
Let's see where we will be guests, we will proceed to them.
E apê me noşkirin bidin.
Let our uncle give a greeting.
Ahlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Ahlen we sehlen, ser serê me.
Welcome, upon our heads (you are very welcome).
Milletekî kîbar û delal, li xelqa gundê Hec Cemala, kanê emê
li ku mêvan bin.
A noble and dear nation, in the episode of Hec Cemal
village, let's see where we will be guests.
Em hatin mêvandariya êla Mihîdîn. Êla Mihîdîn Youtuber in
ne? Me'rûf in.
We have come to be guests of the Mihîdîn clan. The Mihîdîn
clan are YouTubers, right? They are famous.
Kanê emê li ku mêvan bin, emê derbasî cem bin. Apê me
noşkirin bidin.
Let's see where we will be guests, let's go to them. Let our
uncle give a greeting.
Ahlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Ahlen we sehlen, ser serê me.
Welcome, upon our heads.
Navî te?
Your name?
Welîd Mihemed Hisên.
Walid Muhammad Hussein.
Xalê Welîd.
Uncle Walid.
Bêje.
Speak.
Xalê Welîd, tu çend salî ye?
Uncle Walid, how old are you?
Ez tewlîdê pêncî û şeşan me, ez niha şêst û heyşt im me.
I am born in '56, I am now sixty-eight years old.
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide, sihet û xweşiyê bide.
May God give you a long life, may He give health and
happiness.
Te sag bin, saetê we xweş.
May you be well, may your hours be happy.
Ez Xelîl ji qenata "Hatim Efrîn", ji gundî Badîna, ez hatim
mêvandariya gundê Hec Cemala me.
I am Khalil from the "I came to Afrin" channel, from the
village of Badina, I have come to be a guest in Hec Cemal
village.
Ser serê me.
You are welcome (Upon our heads).
Me xwest em biterra rûnên, tiştekî li ser tiştê te yê xweş,
dengê te yê berê.
We wanted to sit with you, [to hear] something about your
nice things, your voice from the past.
Ija ez zanim, ija nizanim wî, tu tiştê çap tînî li bosta me.
Well if I know, or if I don't know it... you are bringing up
printed things (recording/media) on us.
Zerer nake.
No harm done.
Tiştê di dilê te de heye, ji me ra vebêje.
Whatever is in your heart, tell us.
Bêje.
Say it.
Niha ez derbasî gundê Hec Cemala bûm.
Now I have entered the village of Hec Cemal.
Belê.
Yes.
Tişt... edet û teqalîdê Hec Cemala çawa ne?
Thing... how are the customs and traditions of Hec Cemal?
Û şîva di gundê Hec Cemala de meşhûr çiye?
And what is the famous dinner/dish in Hec Cemal village?
Û li ser Hec Cemala bi şiklekî giştî ji me ra deng ke. Kerem
ke.
And generally speak to us about Hec Cemal. Please go ahead.
Bi nisbet li eleqatê îctîmaîye, gundê me, em giş wekî malekê
ne.
Regarding social relations, our village, we are all like one
household.
Em rabin, sefereke me hebe, miriyek me hebe, nexweşek me
hebe, daweteke me hebe, şînek me hebe... Yanî tu hesasiyet
mabeyna me da tunne ye.
If we get up, if we have a trip, if we have a funeral, if we
have a sick person, if we have a wedding, if we have
mourning... Meaning, there is no sensitivity/conflict
between us.
Gundê me jî gundekî kevn e.
And our village is an old village.
Kevn e?
It is old?
Kevn e.
It is old.
Berê va tilî, pêşiya gundê me hîj divê gund bûn, bes ev
gundol wêran bûn.
Before this hill, in front of our village there used to be a
village, but these little villages were ruined.
Erê.
Yes.
Li ber ê li vir bû.
It was down here.
Erê.
Yes.
Dibe ew gundol... gundê sirt, hejdeh mal bûn.
Maybe that hamlet... the village on the ridge, was eighteen
households.
Gundê paşî jî nûr çar mal bûn.
The village behind was just four households.
Gundê paşî jî hejdeh mal bûn. Seyê neqloşîn bûn xirabe ye.
The village behind was also eighteen households. They were
[unintelligible - possibly "transported/moved"], it is
ruined.
Gundê Hec Cemala berê, hewldana li ser wî tilî bî, paşê
ra...
Hec Cemal village was formerly, an attempt on that hill, and
afterwards...
Na. Ne li wî tilî bûn.
No. They weren't on that hill.
Paşê ra hatin vir.
Afterwards they came here.
Erê.
Yes.
Wa dibîn.
It seems so.
Di Hec Cemala da Dêlîb heye?
Is there a "Dêlîb" (Madman/Place name) in Hec Cemal?
Heye Dêlîb.
Yes.
There is a Dêlîb.
Lê wexta nîga... Alet û hedîs tüne.
But in recent times... There are no tools/events [like
before].
Eybû mesel bide wîn... Bi delîbe, Bilxûrê Kitan.
It was a shame, for example... With Dêlîb, Bilxûrê Kitan
(Name/Nickname).
Hîn berê wî jî bi toxmaxa bûn.
Even before him, it was with mallets (wooden beetles).
Toxmaxa bî?
It was with mallets?
Bi du toxmaxa ra...
With two mallets...
Dêlev xalê Welîd bi toxmaxa bî?
Was Dêlev (Dêlîb), Uncle Walid, with mallets?
Bi du toxmaxa ra digotin Tîng.
With two mallets, they called it "Tîng" (the sound of
hitting).
Êwa.
Oh, I see.
Tîng e bî, darekî dirêj bû.
It was "Tîng", it was a long piece of wood.
Eybû mesela di paşiyê re qûrtiyek qulkirî bûn, dar kiribûnê,
û darekî qalind dîna bûn, paşiyê gundî kurt bî, li hafê jî
ban bidar xistibûn, bin darê dan bî.
For example, in the back, they had hollowed out a stump/log,
put wood in it, and put a thick wood... the back of the
village was short... they had built a roof with wood...
under the tree was "Dan" (wheat for pounding).
Em diçûn ser wî darî, hew kevirê ra dibî, ma destê xwe
didayê, û pê bilxûr dikutan.
We would go onto that wood, there was that stone, we would
put our hands to it, and beat the bulgur with it.
Belê.
Yes.
Berê wî jî toxmax bi desta bûn. Wextê Tîng çêbû, me pirr kêf
kir. Me gû qûlayî ye.
Before that, the mallets were handheld. When the "Tîng"
(mechanical/lever mallet) was made, we were very happy. We
said it was easy/luxury.
Ditî Tîngê rojê Dêlîb çêbû.
You saw the "Tîng" of the day, Dêlîb was made.
Dêlîb çêbû, wa hîn kêf kir.
Dêlîb was made, you were even happier.
Noka jî hazir dîtî ra dayne ciyê.
And now, you see it ready, put it in its place.
Belê.
Yes.
Heyat hîn xweş bî.
Life was better then.
Lew heqî dere, dinya rind dibe, xweş dibe, işta... wext
darê, emr jî darê.
Well, truthfully, the world gets good, gets nice, but...
time passes, and life passes too.
Êt berê me, ey zad pirr dîtin, cefo pirr dîtin, tima qumr
bî, ce bî, reht bîn bî, cefo bî.
Those before us saw lots of supplies, saw lots of hardship.
It was wheat, it was barley, it was comfortable (or
ruined?), it was hardship.
Yanî rehet bîn heta tu dibê bes.
Meaning, there was comfort until you say "enough".
Ê heqî dere, işta ev sivik dibe, sivik dibe, bes qesewat jî
pirr dibin.
The truth is, look, this gets lighter (easier), gets easier,
but the worries also increase.
Qesewatên berê ne wekî noka bûn.
The worries of the past were not like now.
Ê zengîn malê xwe dianî, zexîra xwe dianî, pezê xwe heba,
dimsê xwe dikelandin, rehet radiza. Hef bî heyata berê.
The rich man brought his goods, brought his supplies, if he
had his sheep, boiled his molasses, and slept comfortably.
That was the life of the past.
Wekî noka qesewat pirr tüne?
Like now, there aren't many worries?
Noka jî qesewat pirr bî ye.
Now worries have become many.
Qesewat... qûlayî bî lê qesewat pirr bûn.
Worries... it became easy (technologically), but worries
increased.
Xalê gundê Hec Cemala, niha cem me ba'dîna dibên donkê
ba'dîna.
Uncle, in Hec Cemal village... now with us in Badina they
say "the Donk (soup/dish) of Badina".
E.
Yes.
Cem we, şîva we meşhûr, geze hatin, mesela ekla gundê Hec
Cemala bixwin, çiye?
With you, your famous dinner, if guests came, for example to
eat the food of Hec Cemal village, what is it?
Wallahî noka... pirr qûlayî ye.
By God, now... it is very easy/varied.
Erê.
Yes.
Meselen, ferûc hatine, fexad hatine, diqelînin, patata
diqelînin, bacana reş diqelînin, va tiştina berra hene.
For example, chickens have come, thighs have come, they fry
them, fry potatoes, fry eggplants, these things are
available before us.
Hmm.
Şîva di berê... ê di berê jî, kuta bî.
The dinner of the past... the one of the past was "Kuta"
(beaten wheat with meat).
Kuta ye?
It is Kuta?
Hîn qurban dikirin, îda.
When they made sacrifices, during Eid.
Erê.
Yes.
Qûpil danîn, qûpil goşt bi goşt va, digûn 'em manê
kutaviye'.
They put the large pot, the pot with meat and more meat,
they said "we are making Kuta".
Pê kuta dikirin.
They made Kuta with it.
Nûk bûn, kuta jî, û dan bûn. Genim.
It was chickpeas, Kuta too, and it was "Dan" (wheat). Wheat.
Erê.
Yes.
Va tiştina bûn.
It was these things.
De hîn berê wî jî çawa bî, wallahî em negihîştinê ez
nizanim.
And how it was even before that, by God we didn't reach that
time, I don't know.
De noka jî, law doxermê dimis hebûn, me'mûniyê dimis hebûn,
digotin esîde, ev tişta hebûn.
And now... well, there was molasses Doxerma, molasses
Ma'mounia, they called it "Asida", these things existed.
Tiştê şîva di berê, pirr tiştê xweş bûn.
The dinner things of the past, they were very good things.
Bes tiştê nebatî tüne bûn. Zeytê nebatî tüne bûn, rûnê
nebatî li vir tüne bûn.
But there were no vegetable products. There was no vegetable
oil, no vegetable ghee here.
Ev tiştana giş rûnê eslî bûn.
All these things were original (animal/natural) fat/ghee.
Erê.
Yes.
Ti mal vê pez tüne bî, pezê dî hebî.
If a house didn't have sheep, another had sheep.
Lawîn sirkê hişk hebûn.
Oh boy, there were dried red peppers.
Daw dikelandin, ro diqetandin, dikirin parzinê, tûra, do
direvî, li ser tepsiya eşq dikirin.
They boiled the "Daw" (yogurt soda/whey), broke the sun
(dried in sun?), put it in the strainer, the bags... it
would clarify... they put it on the "Tray of Love".
Do xaze tebî ter, ser mîsap çêkirana.
[Unintelligible - describing preparation], making it
according to the standard.
Erê.
Yes.
Mexorin, yanî em gihîştinê.
We ate it, meaning we reached that time.
Hûn gihîştinê?
You reached that time?
Û ya jî hişk dikirin, zivistanê pîvaza, bi zeytê çê dikirin,
bîber dikirnê, merhem dikirin, noka...
And they also dried it, in winter with onions, made it with
oil, put peppers in it, made a paste/sauce, now...
Awa gi bîrbî.
That is all memory.
Îro ta gi tiştê hazir ew bî.
Today everything has become ready-made.
Law uşta noka giştek bî... patatê qewrandî ye, tiştê
qewrandî ye, işta şîva noka ferûc ne.
Well look, now everything is... fried potatoes, fried
things, look, the dinner now is chickens.
Ma goştê mirîşka ew ê eslî hinda kir.
It made the meat of the original chicken disappear/lost.
Hember.
Indeed.
Xalê Welîd, ekes sualekî şte pirskim. Berê jî meselen, bîn
mîsal, gînîvanek hat gundê Hec Cemala.
Uncle Walid, I will ask you a question in reverse. In the
past, for example, let's say, a stranger came to Hec Cemal
village.
Berê... yanî... tiştê de wane nî tawa, tawasulî ewê derba jî
çîkî kêm bî.
Before... meaning... things were not like this, the
communication back then was a bit less.
Dişî mesel gi mirîşkek bera jarjî kira, ê mala jarjî dikirn?
Would they, for example, slaughter a chicken for him? Did
the household slaughter [animals]?
Tabe'en, dîk bûn, mirîşk bûn, şerjê dikirin, mîvanî
dihatiyê.
Of course, there were roosters, there were chickens, they
slaughtered them when a guest came to them.
Dîk şerjê dikirin.
They slaughtered roosters.
E, ez biçûk bûm min dixwest tim mîvanê me werin, ma mirîşka
yan dîka şerjê kin.
Yes, when I was little I always wanted our guests to come,
so they would slaughter chickens or roosters.
Xweş e.
Good.
Xalê Welîd.
Uncle Walid.
Li gundê Hec Cemala, mekteb çend in?
In Hec Cemal village, how many schools are there?
Yek e.
One.
Yek e. Kevndar e lê nû avkirin?
One. Is it old or newly built?
Ecceb çêbû.
It was made "Ecceb" (Strange/Distinct - likely referring to
the style or period).
Ecceb girtin.
They took/built it "Ecceb".
E.
Yes.
Û meqbezî gundê Hec Cemala çend in?
And the cemeteries of Hec Cemal village, how many are there?
Yek bî.
There was one.
Yek bî?
There was one?
Kew jî kevn bî.
That one was also old.
I heye.
It exists.
Heye hewa.
It exists like that.
E.
Yes.
Em bên li gundê Hec Cemala, mekteb yek e û meqbez yek e.
Bîrê d'avê di gundê Hec Cemala de hene?
Let's come to Hec Cemal village, there is one school and one
cemetery. Are there water wells in Hec Cemal village?
Bîr yek û wî li deştê, cem merxa.
One well and it is in the plain, near the Merx (Juniper/Tree
or place name).
Wayl pozî jêr.
Down below the nose (hill/promontory).
E, û bîra jî qedîm e kes nizane kê çêkir, û kê kola, kesek
tarîxî gund nizane.
Yes, and the well is ancient, no one knows who made it, and
who dug it, no one knows the history of the village.
Digotin Bîra Hebîlan.
They called it the Well of the Habils.
Gundî me... çençalya pezî gundya... i çaxmaqê gundî hûlîl...
Our village... the bells of the village sheep... the
[unintelligible - specific term] of the village...
Hêa.
Yeah.
Awa, hîn jî 'el toyniya', berê noxirê diguhê bûn, dere bûn,
i mamola gil ser vê bîrê bûn.
That, even the "Ayn Toyniya" (spring name?), before they
used to [unintelligible verb] the spout... the whole
crowd/burden was on this well.
Gundê di dûr vê bîrê, ew gundê di dûr Hec Cemala, dihatin av
ji vederê dibirin.
The villages around this well, those villages around Hec
Cemal, used to come and take water from here.
Dihatin gij... vexwarinê ra dibirin...
They came all... they took it for drinking...
Law erê erê hîn teneketinê bûn.
Oh yes, yes, before there were tin cans.
Wextê qurban şerjê dikirin, mesela pezî reş xwedî sebesin
derbona, eyûrî gund çê dikirin, digotin kûn.
When they slaughtered a sacrifice, for example black sheep
[unintelligible], they made [containers] for the village,
they called them "Kûn" (waterskins).
Bi kûna dihatin av dibirin.
They came and carried water with waterskins.
Divir da, niha cem, li gundo giya diçûn av ji bîra tînan, bi
teneka tînan, hîn berî teneka jî...
From here, now with... in all the villages they went to
bring water from the wells, they brought it in tins, even
before tins...
Bi kûna bûn.
It was with waterskins.
Kûn jî, bixwe ji eyarî...
And the waterskin, itself from the hide of...
Pezî reş e.
It is black sheep.
Jî eyarî pezî reş kûn çê dikirin, dihatin pê av dibirin.
From the hide of black sheep they made waterskins, they came
and carried water with it.
Saetê te xweş xalê Welîd, te emirek tê da, te gotin tê hene
ji me ra bêje?
Bless your hours Uncle Walid, you gave it time, do you have
any words to say to us?
Emrê me... emrê Rebbê Alemê, emrê me tüne.
Our command... [is] the command of the Lord of the Worlds,
we have no command.
Wa xweşî giş milletî, saeta giya xweş.
Wishing happiness to the whole nation, happy hours to all.
I me'rîfê we xob me ra hene, tinene, gi alîkariya me jî
dikin.
This kindness you have for us, [unintelligible], you are all
helping us too.
Saeta genduya xweş, Xwedê teala tengiyê nede genduya.
Happy hours to you all, may God Almighty not give you
distress.
Xwedê ji te razî be, Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide.
May God be pleased with you, may God give a long life.
Her kesê li me seyr dike, tikaye vira silava bişîne.
Everyone watching us, please send greetings here.
Silav û hurmet û tehiyatim ji giyan ra ne, dûr û nîzîk.
My greetings and respect and salutations are to everyone,
far and near.
Û te qusûr ma hene te efû ke.
And if there are faults/shortcomings with us, forgive [us].
Walahi em qusûra li hevdû nabînin, em barin bar hev du.
By God, we don't see faults in each other, we are a load for
each other (we support each other).
Em mêvandarîya gundê Hec Cemala ne.
We are guests of Hec Cemal village.
Ser serê min.
Upon my head (Welcome).
Havadîk çûçik, tê ji me teqebûl ke, ji qenata "Hatim Efrîn".
This small gift, accept it from us, from the "I came to
Afrin" channel.
Heskerê me ji we ra pirr e, hîn mezinê me ne.
Our love for you is great, you are our elders.
Ê gidi mezinê xwe tune, mile rê mezin ki xwe, bi heqî xwedê.
He who has no elder, let him get an elder for himself, by
God's truth.
Tu serbest î.
You are free/welcome.
Na walah xalê Welîd.
No, by God, Uncle Walid.
Hadîk pirr biha tîne?
Does the gift bring much value/price? (Joking)
Saet xweş. Xwedê ji te razî be xalê Welîd.
Bless you. May God be pleased with you Uncle Walid.
Te emr te l'mihê ne, te gotin te kinê dengê.
You commanded, you [unintelligible], you said you'd make the
voice short.
Xwedê we bafiqîne, Xwedê Rabb el Alemîn.
May God grant you success, God the Lord of the Worlds.
Wekî gotî karî we bilind bike, û saeta vî milletî xweş,
bilindbûna vî karî jî li pişt milletî me ye.
As he said, may He elevate your work, and happy hours to
this nation, the elevation of this work is behind (supported
by) our nation.
Saeta giya xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Happy hours to all, may God be pleased with you.
Saet xweş xalê.
Bless you uncle.
Merhaba.
Hello.
Ahlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Allah yiselmik ya reb. Merhaba.
May God keep you safe. Hello.
Selamun, ahlen we sehlen.
Greetings, welcome.
Ez Xelîl ji qenata "Hatim Efrîn", ji gundî Badîna, hûra
mêvandariya gundê Hec Cemala me.
I am Khalil from the "I came to Afrin" channel, from Badina
village, here as a guest in Hec Cemal village.
Ser serê me.
You are welcome (Upon our heads).
Serî te sax be, hîn aîlet youtuber in?
May your head be safe, you are a YouTuber family?
Haa, emrê te.
Yes, at your service.
Roja meqabelak xweş û kîbar çêkin.
Today let's make a nice and noble interview.
Ahlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Navî te?
Your name?
Em kê solê çare, îşta paçan, sol ne... deh deh salî youtube
kir.
Dilşan.
Em kê solê çare, îşta paçan, sol ne... deh deh salî youtube
kir.
We put the fourteenth year, like this... no... ten, ten
years of YouTube.
Ewa solê çare.
It is the fourteenth year.
Ewa solê çare, youtuber... zewq dike.
That is the fourteenth year, YouTuber... he enjoys it.
Bê dayê, di destpêkê da, wextê te youtube... te kêş mir,
hewal dê kê teşcî kir?
Auntie, in the beginning, when you... started YouTube,
friend, who encouraged you?
Kê, wekî dibên, destek da te? Kî pişt da te? Te da'm...
teb'an.
Who, as they say, gave you support? Who backed you?
Supported you... of course.
Ê bergî Hemîd bî... ê niştî xawkê min.
The first one was Hamid... my nephew.
Wî pirr bi mera weke gotî, "Ella çêkin, çêkin," weleh eynî
tiştek pirr ta'bam bî, yanî pirr ta'bam bî.
He told us a lot, like "Come on, make it, make it," really,
it was something very tiring, I mean very tiring.
Lawkê min, Mihîdîn, zêde tima ser mobîlê çêkir, ew miheq bî.
My son, Muhyiddin, had a lot of desire for the mobile phone,
he was entitled/obsessed.
U xawkê min, Ayşê, ew jî wekî gotî, hew eynî tiştî xaw her
dikin.
And my nephew [niece], Ayşe, she also, as they say, they all
do the same thing.
U brakê min jî, wano giya, yanî... cîwazê xwe weke gotî, bi
televîzyonên xwe, giya mera, hawar kir, giya mera da'm
kirin.
And my brother too, they all went, I mean... with their
devices, as they say, with their televisions, they all
shouted out for us, they all supported us.
Yanî heta noka, giya mera hawar kirin.
I mean, until now, they all helped us.
Destpêkê wextê te qenat vekirî, însanê te da'm kirî, Hemîd û
xuçka te bî?
In the beginning when you opened the channel, the people who
supported you were Hamid and your sister?
Ayşe wa, erê.
It was Ayşe, yes.
Derbasbûn silav û tehîye ji wera diçînin.
Welcome, greetings and regards go out to them.
Saeta we xweş.
Thanks to you as well.
U tişkî pirr xweş e.
And it is a very nice thing.
U heta noka, heta noka... yanî çi vîdyo dakin, heta noka.
And until now, until now... I mean whatever video we upload,
until now [they support].
Di pişta wene.
They are behind you [supporting you].
Hedefê youtube, qenatî te ax... Mihîdîn, li qenatî youtube,
muşterikî te çiqas in?
The YouTube goal, your channel ah... Muhyiddin, on the
YouTube channel, how many subscribers do you have?
Dav pênc û şêst, heftê da.
Around sixty-five, seventy.
Dav pênc û heftê. Rind e, kîbar e.
Around seventy-five [sic]. That's good, that's grand.
Hedefê te di youtube da, win çi dikin? Win çi mihtewêj
didine pêş?
Your goal on YouTube, what do you do? What content do you
present?
Xwedê, emê sirf te'da rûtînî yewmî ye.
By God, ours is purely daily routine.
Yewmîyat.
Daily logs.
Yewmîyat in. Meselen em derkevin çuyînê, sirf te'da... yanî,
hono neha, pirr jî tinebîn tewê.
They are daily logs. For example, if we go out somewhere,
purely... I mean, like right now, there weren't many
[resources] with it.
Noka zêde pirr.
Now it's much more.
Em diçîne aza meselen, megat teswîr dikin. Xelkê li
Ewropayê, gund... meselen, ê gundê xwe dibîne, kêf dike.
We go to weddings for example, we film clips. People in
Europe, the village... for example, the one who sees their
village, enjoys it.
Diçîn daweta, me dawet teswîr dikir, xelkê kêf dikir.
We would go to weddings, we filmed the weddings, people
enjoyed it.
Îlam, bê, em kida çîn, yanî weke gotî, gava em kida çîn,
kemîre me li me ra bû, bisrahe.
Look, without [exceptions], wherever we went, as they say,
wherever we went, our camera was with us, honestly.
Wextê zehmetkê, teswîrê... tu Contî, pirr axiv dikî.
During the difficult times of filming... You, Janti [Can],
you talk a lot.
Ez belê, pirr qenatê wem sêr kir, min vîdyohat jî yekî...
hata paşê, gelek te'lîqet jî sêr kirin, tu axivî.
Yes, I watched your channel a lot, I [watched] the videos
one by one... until the end, I watched many comments too,
you are talkative.
Yanî hebûnekî te, kesayetî te li ser kemîre, pirr xurt e.
I mean your presence, your personality on camera, is very
strong.
Sipas ji te ra.
Thank you.
Heta dayka te ji te hez dike.
Even your mother loves you [for it].
Yanî wisa dixwazim, dayka te te hemêz bike, te maç bike.
I mean, I wish for your mother to hug you, to kiss you.
Hemêz dikim, maç dikim.
I do hug him, I do kiss him.
Ez kurbana te bim.
May I be your sacrifice [I love you].
Ez jî kurbana te bim.
May I be your sacrifice too.
Maşellah, Xwedê we ji hevdû nehêle.
Mashallah, may God not separate you from each other.
Em jî te, ji me ra nehêle, wî jî ji te ra bihêle.
[May God] not take you from us, and keep him [the host] for
you.
Elhek, tu xwedî qebûl û meqbûl î, li ser şaşe, wekî dibên,
qeybûlî ye te heye.
Truly, you are accepted and pleasing, on the screen, as they
say, you have acceptance.
Sipas dikim, spas.
I thank you, thanks.
Tu şerm nakî, tirs nakî, tu tîkî xweş î.
You aren't shy, you aren't afraid, you are very good.
Yanî, mirovekî serbest î, li ser şaşe.
I mean, you are a free/relaxed person on screen.
Him, him.
Yes, yes.
Ev tiştekî pirr baş e. Maşellah.
This is a very good thing. Mashallah.
Hemdilah şikir.
Praise be to God, thanks.
Hewa, mihebet e teb'an.
That is love [popularity], of course.
Teb'an.
Of course.
Hedefê wa yewmîyat in. Mihtewî wa, yewmîyatê têde qad dikin.
Their goal is daily logs. Their content, they present daily
logs in it.
Tiştekî xweş û kîbar. Tiştekî tebî'î. Win yewmîyatê da...
A nice and grand thing. A natural thing. In your daily
logs...
Noko meselen, wextê zeytûna û îna... koka sifte em diçûn
zeytûna, teb'an tinebû ezmê darana.
Now for example, during the time of olives and such...
originally at first when we went to the olives, of course
there wasn't the sorrow of the trees.
Rû bi rû, meselen, em çûn, diçûn zeytûna dara, ewa Ebu Contî
siahata xwe bera min sa'de dikir.
Face to face, for example, we went, we were going to the
olive trees, that Abu Janti [Father] would turn his
hour/time to help me.
Noko tişkî ta'ban bî ser wî ye zêde.
Now it has become something very tiring for him, too much.
Mara da'm dikir, wextî têde şol hewl didan, qeses hewl
didan, klamê d'alîtin çû.
He used to support us, giving work attempts in it, giving
stories, singing songs as we went.
Ê noko, bê am sa'de dikir.
And now, without [him], we helped [ourselves].
Yanî, m'kanî me yewmî yanî.
I mean, our place/content is daily, basically.
Wekî me çi kar kir, em spêde rabûn, heta meselen, em
firavîn, xwarin, şîvê, em çi karê xwe dikin, çi karê xwe mal
dikin meselen...
Like whatever work we did, we got up in the morning, until
for example, lunch, eating, dinner, whatever work we do,
whatever housework we do for example...
Digel giya, rojekî me çawa derbas dibe.
With everything, how our day passes.
Kemîre me ya tima marê l'mal e?
Is our camera always with us at home?
Kemîre me ya tima di destê me de ye.
Our camera is always in our hands.
Contî, li vî derê, tu dêkî xwe ro pirr harî dikî.
Janti, in this regard, you harass your mother a lot.
Ez belê, pirr qenatê wa min sêr kir, min vîdyohat... ez
jiyekî hatme, hata paşîn, gelek te'lîqet selbî bibînim, min
nedît, şikir ji Xwedê ra.
Yes, I watched their channel a lot, I [saw] videos... I came
from one, until the end, [expecting] to see many negative
comments, I didn't see any, thanks be to God.
Hewa mihebe ye teb'an.
That is love [from the fans], of course.
Hedefê wa, yewmîyat in, mihtewî wa yewmîyatê da qad dikin,
tiştekî xweş û kîbar.
Their goal is daily logs, their content presents daily logs,
a nice and grand thing.
Tiştekî tebî'î. Win yewmîyatê da...
A natural thing. In the daily logs...
Noko meselen, wextê zeytûna û îna...
Now for example, during the time of olives and such...
Wextê tu dakevî teswîrê. Wextê tu key bibelşî yewmîyatê tu
teswîrînî.
When you go down to film. When you start to film the daily
logs.
Tu jimarê tişkî xeber deynî, çû difikirîn, çû planekî
datînî, çû bernamekî datînî tu tekî xwe.
Do you prepare something beforehand, do you think about it,
do you set a plan, do you set a program by yourself?
Belkî meselen, a li malê ne, pêşda brokê em difikirin, em
biçin vîdyo çêkin, meselen.
Maybe for example, if we are at home, beforehand briefly we
think, let's go make a video, for example.
Yanî vîdyê me yewmîyat da dikave.
I mean our video falls under daily logs.
Meselen, bêjin, meselen... em îro rabin, me heye der teswîr
kin meselen.
For example, let's say, for example... today we get up, we
have to film outside for example.
Em radibin meselen, ka qehweka kûzora em sibê radibin
vedixwin, nanê xwe dixwin, teswîr dikin.
We get up for example, [have] a coffee... we get up in the
morning and drink it, eat our bread, we film.
Ma kîno xwedê dixwin? Em radibin û em hatê xwe teswîr dikin.
Who eats by themselves? We get up and we film ourselves [our
state].
Weha tişt, man...
Such things, I mean...
Awa ye merhele pê hevdira.
I mean...
That is the stage [we are at] together.
Wextê tu d'kî yewmîyat jî daxê, vîdyokî daxê, tu pêşda pê
difikirî?
When you also upload daily logs, upload a video, do you
think about it beforehand?
D'kî îro meselen çi vîdyo daxê?
Like, "what video should I upload today?"
Meselen tu kî çi şixwî bikî meselen, kî terîqê gendî ye, kî
ser êr e... tu çûyî t'bêra çayê çêdikî.
For example, whatever work you do, like a village road, or
on the ground... you went and made tea there.
Tu çûyî, ba'dê xeyr...
You went, afterwards...
Ê bisrahe rehet e, ez tişkî wekî d'vire xwe çêkim, î êr dera
pirr codî m'rehet e.
And honestly it's comfortable, I don't pretend/make things
up, and outside is very differently comfortable.
Tu me ê teswîr dikî, ga ezmê me birîtiya me, lingê xwe ana
ye dikênî.
Strange.
Tu me ê teswîr dikî, ga ezmê me birîtiya me, lingê xwe ana
ye dikênî.
You film us, while our pain/wound, we drag/place our legs
like this.
Tîbî wetî pekin, yanî hindek car-carê bikhame, ez dibêm.
[Unclear], I mean sometimes [he] pushes it, I say.
No deynî, em seqeta pirr pê nakin wekî bikhame ser tiştî
dera wîş na.
No wait, we don't care much about the disability like
pushing on things outside, not like that.
Can.
Aunt Dilşan...
Dear.
Xwudê bîne, ne bîne xweş bî, bê hasîn lê, ba'dê fetroke.
May God bring it, may it not bring [illness], may it be
well, may there be recovery, after a while.
Xwedê... wekî gotî, yanî doxtorê ji hewî xwe, cîhazê xwe, ji
hew hatibûne wekî gotî.
God... as they say, I mean doctors with their desire, their
equipment, came willingly as they say.
Ê rind bû.
It was good.
Hîn sivik tahda mera pê ve hasî yan.
Still slightly we felt it [improvement].
Î ne we ye, ê hedîs bî. Em pê nehesîn heta wextê wekî gotî,
a'yb me sêwilandî.
And it wasn't that, it was an event/accident. We didn't feel
it until the time as they say, the shame/disability struck
us.
Paşê wiladê şûnda tiştekê çûke.
Then after the birth, something happened.
Yanî hal heye?
I mean is there a solution?
No.
Derbazi bû.
It has passed.
Lê derbazi bû, wextê tişta derbazi bî jî...
But it passed, when things pass too...
Ê ştewwa bî. Xwedê, xezar wêtînî, xwedê ji we razî be.
And it was like that. God... [unclear blessing], may God be
pleased with you.
Xwedê jê... ser ser û çava.
God from... [you are welcome/on my head and eyes].
Xaltîka Dilşan, dil û can e.
Sir/My dear.
Aunt Dilşan, [you are] heart and soul.
Mihîdîn.
Janti?
Muhyiddin.
Contî mahze ne, lê...
Janti [nickname] strictly, but...
Belê.
Yes.
Bes teqena ser navî Mihîdîn veke.
Janti.
But he opened the channel under the name Muhyiddin.
Dê nava muhaq bî bisrahe.
That was the rightful name, honestly.
Î mexws tişkyon, ew jî pê kêf ke, yanî ser navî ye.
And special things, he should also enjoy it, I mean it's
under his name.
Tişkî xweş e.
It is a nice thing.
Eywa.
Yes.
Ser navî bî. Noko sibê da me Contî, Zehucan bixêr derbî,
qenat a Mihîdîn e.
It was under his name. Now since morning we [call him]
Janti, Zehucan came out well, the channel is Muhyiddin's.
Erê, ewa re, qenatê bofeke... nav taqanet e Mihîdîn e.
Yes, that's right, the channel... the channel name is
Muhyiddin.
Lê a Mihîdîn e. Lê, me'nîm sexbêlî wiyabe.
But it is Muhyiddin's. But, my meaning is let the care be
for him.
Xwedê star û belê, weşlî deweta her tiştî kefxweş, emê ji me
jî ba'd nînin, emê werin.
God protect and yes, ... weddings everything joyful, we will
not be far from it, we will come.
Înşallah, înşallah.
God willing, God willing.
Înşallah, xwedê ji te jî razî be, xwedê sehetê te bide.
God willing, may God be pleased with you too, may God give
you health.
Mihîdîn çend salî ye?
How old is Muhyiddin?
Hifdeh, hifdeh.
Seventeen, seventeen.
Dav hifdeh.
Around seventeen.
Xwedê 'emrê dirêj bide.
May God give him a long life.
Ê wa ye jî.
It is so.
Hemdilah.
Praise be to God.
Îşî te çawa ye?
How is your work?
Hemdilah îşî wacib, xalê te çawa ye?
Praise be to God, work is duty, how is your uncle/situation?
Hemdilah, sihetî te çawa ye? Te rehet e? Tu bi kêf e?
Praise be to God, how is your health? Are you comfortable?
Are you happy?
Wez rehetim, rind e, keçûbê, îşî me bi kêf nin.
I am comfortable, it's good, [unclear], our work is happy.
Hemdilah şikir ji Xwedê ra.
Praise be to God, thanks to God.
Silamkê kesî ra bişîne? Tu silav û başkê kesî ra bişîne?
Will you send a greeting to anyone? Will you send greetings
and goodness to anyone?
Ezê bişînim silavê...
I will send greetings...
Ez silav dikim mamê te pirr eşkera herim.
I greet your uncle very openly I go.
Silamê we jî ser ser û çava.
Your greetings are also welcome [on head and eyes].
Xaltîka Dilşan, naho di mihtewî ta da, em bivtilin ser
mihtewa, bîma eno hûn youtuber in, di gundê Hicamelê da.
Aunt Dilşan, now in your content, let's return to the
content, since you are YouTubers, in the village of
Hijamala.
Di vî darê, mobîlê xwe day cam wa tehedîyat kê me, û meqaleb
kê min.
In this place, you gave your phone... we will do challenges,
and we will do pranks.
Ava jî tişkiya, p'ketim ta'lîqata teb'an, tişkî daxwazim.
This is also something, I looked into the comments of
course, something I want.
Tu daxwazî.
You want.
Tişkî mera daînin ka.
Let's see them put something for us.
Ferda fosen, î noko tehedîyat û me pirr çêkirin, mobîlê
Contî û Mihîdîn.
I...
Ferda fosen, î noko tehedîyat û me pirr çêkirin, mobîlê
Contî û Mihîdîn.
Let it be, and now challenges and we made a lot [of videos],
[on] Janti and Muhyiddin's phone.
Î daxwazim mi ser mobîlê min û Ebu Contî, Ebu Contî jî tişkî
ewî xwe sart e bisrahe.
And I want [videos] on my phone and Abu Janti [Father], Abu
Janti is also someone with a cold/serious nature honestly.
Yane mesxerî û dera, ciddî ye.
I mean mockery and such, he is serious.
Ciddî ye.
He is serious.
Yane biyê mesxerî ke, yo tişkî vî tûnî, te 'emr nokî, cokî
nokî Contî, meqleb serî me çêkir, li şarê kûsê.
Yes.
Yane biyê mesxerî ke, yo tişkî vî tûnî, te 'emr nokî, cokî
nokî Contî, meqleb serî me çêkir, li şarê kûsê.
I mean if you make fun, or this thing isn't there, you don't
do this, you don't do that Janti, he made a prank on us, in
the city [unclear].
Ê mokî yedekal bikir.
Hey, don't interfere.
Yane şû nî, tûnî, em nokî kû.
I mean it's not proper, it's not there, we don't do
where/how.
Eywa.
Yes.
Meqaleb ser Ebu Contî nabe.
Pranks on Abu Janti don't work.
Meqaleb...
Pranks...
U tehedîyat o, cibûyî dakevê, qusîra xwa fêke, meselen wextî
tehedîyat da dikevin.
And challenges, when it happens/goes down, [unclear], for
example when they enter challenges.
Meselen, ya didin çor buçka da dikevin, dimbldiyo da
dikevin, meselen cimhûrî xwe ye...
For example, they fall into four [unclear], they fall into
[unclear], for example their audience...
Bi fihm qenatî xwe mekinin, dar bî, yen qqusîra xwa, ez dêkî
xwa ne.
Understand making their channel [unclear], outside was, or
their fault, me and my mother are [in it].
Ê meqleb o da, meselen...
And in pranks, for example...
Em serê birîkî xwe çêkirin, 'emrê birîkî me, biftîm bête
fekî...
We made [a prank] on our pocket/money, our pocket's life,
[unclear]...
Ê ti bêjî netî bêjî... nînco car car eh, bikeme, d'estê.
Whether you say it or don't say it... like sometimes uh, I
do it, [unclear].
No deynî, em seqeta pirr pê nake, bikhame ser teşnî dera,
wej nê.
No wait, we don't care much about the disability, putting it
on outside things, not that.
Wextê Ebu Contî, tu meqaleb kî pê bikî, tirs nakî?
When you do a prank on Abu Janti, aren't you afraid?
Bofkî min, 'asabî ye.
My father is short-tempered.
Mwa, ez tirs nakim, 'asabî ye.
[Unclear], I am not afraid, he is short-tempered.
Î pirr xalk, çû zêde bin, dê meselen, m'mokî ne, her biger,
meselen 'Efrîn e, g'Heleb e, g'e...
And many people, going too much, saying for example, don't
do this, go around, for example Afrin, or Aleppo, or...
Gundo ye, g'manaze re, g'dukandar gehî xwa pêgîn meselen,
mehalat, dukanê dera.
Villages, or scenery, or shopkeepers [unclear] reach
themselves, for example, shops, outside stores.
Noko, hedefê min gav tişto ye.
Now, my goal is all these things.
U dîsan bêjî, wa'de yîm millet diznî xwedê, yanî...
And say it again, I promise the people with God's
permission, I mean...
E bes îşî mokî ye bê meselen, yanî a helkim, ez berdewam
dikim, a derkevim, u hetto deqî hûrû dîsa, yanî mehalat o
jî.
But if the work isn't there for example, I mean I will
solve/handle it, I will continue, I will go out, and until
this minute again, I mean shops too.
U dewato jî, u we de 'eyfrîn jî, u gundo jî, g'bdes me keve,
em teswîr dikin.
And weddings too, and [unclear] Afrin too, and villages too,
if it falls in our hands, we will film.
Wek mobîlê xwe da yê, di mihtewî wa da, youtuber... ta'lîqê
wa ez gi dibînim, mig xwend, mig dîrase kir.
Like it is in your phone, in your content, YouTuber... I see
all your comments, I read them, I studied them.
Tehedîyat jî watên xwestin, u ma hinke ew bikin.
Challenges were also requested from you, and let us do that.
Gota tehedîyat da katin, dî bon mekin.
They said enter challenges, [unclear].
Bon mekin vê carê, ez dê barata bikemê.
Don't do [unclear] this time, I will do it for you.
Înşallah.
God willing.
Xaltîka Dilşan, em neha biftilin ser solê, çîçke, neha her
gundkî em derbas bîn, emkê pirs kin.
Aunt Dilşan, let's now turn to questions, a little bit, now
every village we pass, we will ask.
Nosbînê... gundê hec... bên l'... mobnî heccamolo û ba'dîna,
nosbîn heye lê tine?
Nostalgia... village of [unclear]... between... between
Hijamala and later [current place], is there nostalgia or
not?
Heye.
There is.
Xo gigtel ba'dîna mêr kirî.
You married [unclear] afterwards.
Xaltîka Dilşan ti bixwe ji Heccamolo yî lê?
No.
Aunt Dilşan, are you yourself from Hijamala or?
No, ewa ji Ma'serkê.
No, she is from Ma'sarka.
Ma'serkê, no hey gundê tnihey mobata.
Ma'sarka, no there is a village [unclear].
U j'vir jî tîp şû, j'vê derê jî ba'dîna mêr kirine.
Ma'sarka.
And from here too [unclear], from here too later they got
married.
Mêr kirine. Ma'netû nosbîn, mobîna gundê heccamolo û ba'dîna
da heye.
They got married. Meaning nostalgia, between the village of
Hijamala and later exists.
Wek wej mera gotî, me j'wera pirs kir, nosbîn jî heye.
As he told us, we asked you, nostalgia also exists.
Wextê Ebu Contî, nesîbê tel virve bî ye... çîçke mera ser wê
deng ke.
When Abu Janti, your destiny was here... tell us a little
about that.
Dibe kêmasî hebin, hûnê bibaxşînin, spas dikim.
There might be shortcomings, please forgive us, thank you.
Di derheqê mala qenata Xwefeke, qenata Xwefeke, qenata me
hemûyan e.
Regarding the home of the Khofeke channel, the Khofeke
channel is a channel for all of us.
Hêvîdar im hûn abone bin, şîroveyan jê re binivîsin, likean
ji bîr nekin.
I hope you subscribe, write comments for it, and don't
forget the likes.
Dayê te digot ez dixwazim tiştekî bibêjim.
Mother, you said "I want to say something."
Yanî tîp şû, behsa di qenata me de, ser te'lîqata dibînim ku
tefrîqê dikî.
Yes, specifically, discussing our channel, in the comments I
see [people saying] that you discriminate.
Nokê gistik zanan, caran mara tefrîqê têrê nabînin, xudê
şike xwa.
Now everyone knows, sometimes we don't see discrimination as
fitting for us, God forbid.
Xasma qîşî mara yek saqat be, mara tefrîqê têrê dike?
Especially if a child of ours were disabled, would
discrimination be fitting for us?
Yanî Mehdîn ne li qimşê nabin wekî karekî tişkî pê ve bike.
Meaning Mahdin is not at the level where he can do a job or
something like that.
Yê hew ez û wî man, ew can didin hem dikin.
It's just me and him [Janti] left, we give our soul and do
everything.
Dibê ha te tefrîqê dikî, tu Jantî li ser yê din digirî.
They say "Ha, you discriminate, you favor Janti over the
other."
Nokê rêk kê ve, der kê ve, teswîr e, dera ez û wî ne.
Now on the road, outside, filming, it's me and him.
Yanî kî dajo, hew dajo pare bibe?
Meaning who drives? Just because he drives, does he get a
share?
Jantî mokîna dajo.
Janti drives the car.
Ew jî teswîra dikişîne.
He also shoots the video.
Û teswîra... û ba'zê pir balê xwe didinê, hew teswîr dike û
hîn be'zê wan...
And the filming... and some pay a lot of attention to him,
just filming and some of them learn...
Ew ez û wî ne.
It is me and him.
Tiştekî pir xweş e, dewam kin, berdewam kin, guhê xwe nedine
gotinan.
It is a very nice thing, continue, keep going, don't listen
to gossip.
Milete we ji we hez dike, te'lîqat têne dîtin êyew.
Your people love you, comments are seen, yes.
Gyo razî ne, Xwedê se'ta xwaş bide te jî, bide wan gya jî.
We are pleased, God give you good health too, give them all
too.
Û de'mî gindiyo hem gîşta, bê mecal e.
And always the villagers and everyone, without means.
Teb'en mecala me jî gora yê xelkê ne tişt e yanî, hemdika.
Of course our means are nothing compared to others, thanks
to God.
Erê bes însan, her çiqas be hindik be, bes wextê tu sifirê
da belişî...
Yes, but a human, however little it is, but when you start
from zero...
Tu pê dihesî tişkî pir mezin e.
You feel it is a very big thing.
Ê ma sifir da ye, û em wekî ta'bî xwan e.
Well, it is from zero, and we are according to our nature.
Yanî wekî tu yek kerrê yê derkî ebeden, çi tama tiştinê hewa
ye.
Meaning like if you are mute/isolated you will never come
out, what sense is there in that.
Em ê ta'bî xwan e.
We are according to our nature.
Û umrê mi jî ma tu veyî te feykiri umrê min çend e?
And my age too, wait, have you guessed how old I am?
Umrê min pêncî ye.
My age is fifty.
Pêncî, Xwedê umrê te dirêj ke.
Fifty, God lengthen your life.
Dewalid 74, 74 pêncî ye, 2024 umrê min pêncî ye.
Born in 74, 74 is fifty, in 2024 my age is fifty.
Pêncî ye.
It is fifty.
Carê te caran, di qenatî te da, te afkar xeyala xelkê go
hana bikî, te afkar jê birin lê nebirin?
Once, did you ever, in your channel, imagine other people's
ideas to do like this, did you take ideas or not?
Ma birin, ma birin.
Of course.
We took, we took.
Afkar, hinekan dibin...
Ideas, some become...
Nokê meselan te'lîqat de dibêjin Jantî ezewa bike.
Now for example in comments they say Janti do this.
Ee.
Yes.
Ca di te'lîqata de, yê zmiş dikin meselan vîdyûyî sibe de
hana bikin.
Or in comments, they think/suggest for example do a video
tomorrow like this.
Ee.
Yes.
Yanî he, meselan filan gundî, yanî he... yanî hey Xwedê te
vî ew bê, tebe'en em pê dikin.
Meaning yes, for example such villager, meaning yes...
meaning hey God, whatever it is, of course we do it.
Ca mara cem xwa nizane, bes wextê xelk yê zmiş ke mara zane.
Or we ourselves don't know, but when people think/suggest we
know.
Hîn afkar ma ba'ze jî ji te'lîqata dibin.
Still ideas remain, some are from comments.
Tebe'en em ji milet dibin.
Of course we take from the people.
Ji milet dibin.
You take from the people.
Nokê meselan, ê min nefsa min şîvê xwestime ser ewê gindî,
ez ê dikim şîvê.
Now for example, mine, my self desired dinner on that
villager, I do the dinner.
Ee.
Yes.
Nokê meselan îro me, meselan teleb... tê bîra min meselan
yek Kebsê çêke.
Now for example today we, for example demand... it comes to
my mind for example someone make Kabsa.
Em ê meselan tê bîra min, erê, şî bikî heyat tê bikî, em
kîsê meselan rabin.
We for example it comes to my mind, yes, whatever you do
life you do, we for example stand up.
Meselan ma xwest, wî têke get û çêke.
For example we wanted, put it in the gut and make it.
Ez ê dikim, em ê kin nava nişta me çi tiştê get û wî me
çêkir, me teswîr kir, me daxist ser rûpelê.
I do, we do inside our things whatever thing we got and that
we made, we filmed, we downloaded to the page.
Yanî neqla siruştî ye wekî tu dibêjî, neqla zindî ye, zafitî
ye, ê tistê zafitî.
Meaning a natural transfer like you say, a live transfer,
spontaneity, that thing of spontaneity.
Ya şiş bu zafitî.
Yes exactly that spontaneity.
Ca me tiştekî xwaş dît, cema'etê.
Or we saw a nice thing, group.
Xelasîr til Kebsê, milkebsê dî pir xwaş bû, mil... şeklê
gindî tî bi şehî yekî dibên.
Finishing the Kabsa, the other Kabsa was very good, shape of
the villager you say with a desire.
Û ro ye sormê... sormê silkê takir ne.
And the day of the Sormê... Sormê Silkê [stuffed tripe with
chard] you made.
Ah.
Ê çiçkimro te tişî re'nkirin şandî amîn xwar û devê jî
şelixandin bûn.
What did I do today, you sent colors/kinds, Amin ate and his
mouth was torn/burned.
Ê te silametiya te.
Yes to your health.
Tu Jantî te rehet dikî.
You Janti, you relax.
Ah.
Sormê silkê, tişkî mera ser xeber de dên ke.
Sormê Silkê, put something for us on the word.
Sormê silkêyê noke, sîr û çîrî bûn noko mucerreb in.
Sormê Silkê now, garlic and things were now tested.
Ez zoni çûn jî pelê gindî tiştat xwas ma bicerbînim serhet.
I know going too leaves of the villager things nice let me
try on the line.
Min se kir pelê gindî pe'n in û rind in, min got welle sormê
xwa rind derketin.
I looked leaves of villager are wide and good, I said well
my Sormê came out good.
Min qut kirin, min çêkirin, min se kir Jantî û bavê wano jî
yê diperpir jê hez kirin.
I cut them, I made them, I saw Janti and his father also
very much liked them.
Çûne xwaş in, nerm kirine, ana mara jî hez dike meselan.
Are they good?
They are very good, softened, now we also like for example.
Are.
Yes.
Di vira da belkî mexlû hedîs kon, ma'lûmê îdafî ye.
Here maybe create a mixed story, additional information.
Sormiyê silkê bixo, însanî ku ta'liq rakirî...
Eat Sormê Silkê, a human who has lifted the uvula...
Sormiyê silkê vêra pirr rind in.
Sormê Silkê are very good for that.
Te rakirî, te'liq yê rakiribê însan, sormiyê silkê pir vêra
rind in.
Yes man who?
Te rakirî, te'liq yê rakiribê însan, sormiyê silkê pir vêra
rind in.
You lifted, if a human has lifted the uvula, Sormê Silkê are
very good for that.
Zoni xiştî û dehatî bînî.
I know brick and rural you bring.
Le'nû ew çilû tişkî serd o, çiqo bikelîne û ew germ sardo
be.
Yes.
Le'nû ew çilû tişkî serd o, çiqo bikelîne û ew germ sardo
be.
Because it is like a cold thing, however much you boil and
that heat be cold.
Rast e.
It is true.
Niha pirsê me xelas, ortix hinke tu gotina te, pirsê ji me
fers kî, çi cema heye em kêne bibên rûmî vêndarê wane?
Now our question finished, no more some your word, question
from us impose, what group is there we can say to their
viewers?
Xwedê qenata we jî bi ser xîne, û bi serhatî mişterek bê û
inşella hûn bi ser kevin.
God bring success to your channel too, and be a shared event
and God willing you succeed.
Û ya hana başbo jî bibin inşalla.
And God willing become good like that too.
Û Xwedê bi Yûtûberê gya ra bê, hemû milet, meselan eger bi
ser kevin...
And God be with all YouTubers, all nation, for example if
they succeed...
Û gelek bilind bibin.
And become very high.
Û Xwedê kesî feqîr neke, dê nexweşîyê lê, le'n efkaro jî ne
qûlayî ye teb'en, karekî pir çetin e.
And God not make anyone poor, give sickness, because
thoughts too are not easy of course, it is a very hard job.
Xwedê sebê... ma çavê xwe li ber kir hemgû perçavê hez dikim
em kî Yûtyûb vîdyû çêkeyn.
God patience... we closed our eyes before everything we like
we make YouTube videos.
Erê, ortix em qena 'alem dînê, em nîkirin.
Yes, no more we see the world, we did not.
Guş mera ma, ew xelas, te kê çêkî.
Ears stayed to us, that finished, you will make.
Xelas, ortix bes hinke tehediyata çêkin, ban mekin, serê
wana tehediyata çêkin.
Finished, no more just some challenges make, don't call us,
on their heads make challenges.
Bes ma qala bû serî min çêbikin.
Just don't make talk on my head.
Na na.
No no.
Ez jî hez nakim, ez jî hez nakim, bes ez pê dişêm.
I also don't like, I also don't like, but I am tired of it.
Yani gogîne wextê xala û jontî min çêdikir, muqabilî bizûrî
min serî kir.
Meaning sometimes when aunt and Janti made, against my
pleasure I looked.
Ah.
Çavê min tijî hêstir bûn, hêstir nehatin kînim.
My eyes filled with tears, tears did not come I pull.
Min balê xwa da te, min çwîna nekir xelas bê, le'nû eger pê
hesiyam, eger fedî bikim.
I paid attention to you, I didn't go finished, because if I
felt, if I be ashamed.
Êş welle me ne kîna.
Pain well we don't have malice.
Teb'en girî jî ne eyb e, însan şewata êşek bigya re heye.
Of course crying is not shame, human burning pain with
everyone exists.
Xelkê dûşan berî em niha cem te xelas dikin, em derin.
Everyone in yes.
Folks two moments before we now finish with you, we go.
Ez dixwazim tişkî tejmera hewal de, di heyta te ra derbas
bibe û te bîr nekiribe heta noko.
I want something to you about, in your life passed and you
have not forgotten until now.
Tê bîra min gellek got...
It comes to my mind many said...
Erê.
Yes.
Ez bêjim.
Let me say.
Deng ke.
Speak.
Tu nikanê, odî zura neke.
You can't, room don't force.
Tiştek ana derbas bî û...
Something now passed and...
Derbas bî... min...
Passed... I...
Seraha o.
Frankly oh.
Seraha teb'en.
Frankly of course.
Yanî wekî tî em li mişber bîm, min... wekî tî mêr kir û
qeçik anîn û milûkî xwaşî û xwaşî, û heta noko kela di dilê
min da...
Meaning when we were in forced [exile?], I... like you
married and brought kids and property joy and joy, and until
now boiling in my heart...
Ewa jî noko li Elmanya.
That one too now in Germany.
Te ra da înêkî.
You gave one Friday.
Hem da înêkî.
All gave one Friday.
Ê.
Yes.
Înşalla Xwedê dîtina gindî jî bide te jî ba dînim.
God willing God give seeing of the villager too to you too
so I see.
Pir rind e.
It is very good.
Amîn ya reb, î gyo berê digînê, hêşta qiçik şevê xwa bîne
pir çêtir e.
Amen oh Lord, of all before reaches, still little bring his
night is much better.
Şevê din.
The other night.
Hata noko çiqo xewna dibînim, ewî dibîm, curum ew na nayê
dînê.
Until now how much dreams I see, I see him, my crime he
doesn't come to sight.
[Crying]
Qisûra me nê ti efkê, û me kî bibê me derd kile ser te
vekir.
Don't look at our flaw, and we who say we opened a pain sore
on you.
Ê bes serî min, Xwedê inşalla qenatî te jî bi ser xîne.
Yes but my head, God willing bring success to your channel
too.
Saet xwaş.
Good health.
Te rehet bibe, tu cefê dibîne, û inşalla ê te, te bi
necihîne.
God willing.
Te rehet bibe, tu cefê dibîne, û inşalla ê te, te bi
necihîne.
You be comfortable, you see suffering, and God willing
yours, yours not leave place.
Inşalla.
God willing.
Jantî, se'a min te, ti gotina te dawî bi bîrokinî...
Amen oh Lord.
Janti, my hour you, your word end with remember...
Welle, bibî xatirê gyo razî be, û sa'ta we xwaş, û teb'en
vîdyoyekî pir xwaş in, û halqî we jî pir xwaş e.
Well, be goodbye all be pleased, and good health to you, and
of course a video very nice, and your episode also very
nice.
Û inşalla neqla tê jî, bîznê Xwedê, hemû bi hev re bin, emê
be'v re ji derkevin, emê be'v re jî bi hejêjin cem e,
te'arufê jî orik çêbibe.
And God willing your transfer too, with God's permission,
all be together, we together also go out, we together also
shake gathering, acquaintance also there happen.
Inşalla.
God willing.
Û xazim istimrar çêbibe, erê.
And I want continuation happen, yes.
Inşalla hemkî har li no warin, û inşalla dibê hîn gi tiştê
di muface'etê pêşiya da ji vê xwaştir.
God willing all who look at us come, and God willing be yet
things in surprises forward from this better.
Inşalla, inşalla, bi selametî.
God willing, God willing, with safety.
Mehdîn bira, kî min berê ez darim, tu dixwazî ti gotina
bikî, ti şîrove bikî.
Mahdin brother, who me before I go, you want to do some
words, do some comment.
Xwedêno sa'ta we xwaş, Xwedê ji te razî be.
Gods good health to you, God be pleased with you.
Jantî sa'ta we xwaş, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Yes health.
Janti good health to you, God be pleased with you.
Tu qusûra me hîn efkin, hûnerê mîhvandariya gundî hecce
malin û bi zat a mala hecce malê...
You forgive our flaws too, art of hosting of villager Hajj
home and by self of Hajj home...
Wa ji mera teqsîr nekir, û inşalla hata em kênin em ê bi hev
şa bibin.
They did not make shortcoming for us, and God willing until
we laugh we will be happy with each other.
Selamî, ehlen we sehlan.
Greetings, welcome.
Wele we baş nekir, we sormê xwa nexwar, hûn çûn.
Good health to you.
Well you didn't do good, you didn't eat your Sormê, you
went.
Ma, ma sormê mayî kelînîş, ew ketin jî mayî, heta noko sar
wekî nê kelîne jî mayî, nê kelîne.
But, but Sormê remained boiling, that fell also remained,
until now cold like not boiled also remained, not boiled.
Destê te sax be, Xwedê ji we razî be.
May your hand be healthy, God be pleased with you.
Sa't xwaş, Xwedê ji we jî razî be, û ehlen we sehlan.
Good health, God be pleased with you too, and welcome.
Herû mîvan nîmayî delal û şîrîno tina.
Always guest don't remain dear and sweet don't have.
Qenatê teb'en, ê em hatin Efrînê ye.
Channel of course, yes we came to Afrin.
Hatim bi Efrînê, erê.
I came to Afrin.
I came to Afrin, yes.
Me şaş kir.
Yes.
We confused.
Iwa, tu nece me zyara, ehlen we sehlan, ji wara jî.
Soul oh.
Yes, you don't go our visit, welcome, from the camps too.
Û her yekî wekî tu dixwazê werê cem me zyaretê, mala me opî
ye.
And everyone like you wants come to us visit, our house is
open.
Hê me ji gyara vekirî ye, ehlen we sehlan.
Still we open from camps, welcome.
Welle sa'ta we xwaş, ehla istiqbalê, û Xwedê ji we razî be.
Well good health to you, best reception, and God be pleased
with you.
Û mû ji xwast, yanî berê da dixwazin, we derbas cem we bûn.
And we wanted, meaning before wanted, we pass by you.
Teb'en, tona bi neqletî, tona hat bes neqletê...
Of course, not with transport, not came but transport...
Ê xwaş bî na?
Yes was good no?
Lê git cema'î bî.
But went collective was.
Arê.
Yes.
Inşalla, inşalla Xwedê...
God willing, God willing God...
[Music Playing]
[Mûzîk]
[Music]