Merheba, miletê kîbar û delal. Heva xelekê sêsiyê li qenatê
"Hatim li Efrîn". Ka naha merivan, bi dilkî xweş em derbas
gindê Dimîlya bin.
Hello, noble and dear people. This is the third episode on
the channel "Hatim in Afrin". Come along now folks, with a
happy heart, let us visit the village of Dimilya.
(Music plays)
Merheba Xaltîka Nazê.
Hello Auntie Naze.
Ehlen wa sehlen, erê li ser çavan, erê...
Welcome, you are welcome, yes upon my eyes, yes...
Sihet çawa ye?
How is the health?
Elhemdulillah şikir ji Xwedê re, baş e, elhemdulillah...
Praise be to God, thanks to God, it is good, praise be to
God...
Xaltîka Nazê, tu çend salî ye?
Auntie Naze, how old are you?
Ê welle emrê me... seşê sîk hatî.
Oh well, our age... sixty something has come.
Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike.
May God give you a long life.
Xwedê emrê we jî dirêj bike, saxî ya canê we be, şikir ji
Xwedê re.
May God give you a long life too, health to your souls,
thanks be to God.
Xaltîka Nazê, te çend qeçik mezin kirin?
Auntie Naze, how many children have you raised?
Qeçik? Sê... lawik in, çar jî qîzik in, heft maşellah dikin.
Children? Three... are boys, and four are girls, they make
seven, Mashallah.
Maşellah, Xwedê bihêle.
Mashallah, may God keep them.
Xwedê bihêle, saxî ya canê te, serata te.
May God keep them, health to your soul, and your head.
Xaltîka Nazê... berê, heyata berê pir xweş bû?
Auntie Naze... in the past, was life in the past very good?
Heyata berê xweş bû yarebî... kar hebû, bes xweş bû jî.
Life in the past was good, oh Lord... there was work, but it
was good too.
Cefa bû û xweş bû?
It was hardship and it was good?
Erê welle, xweş bû welle.
Yes really, it was good really.
Berê we nan çû dikir, we kunc şû dikir, we çaw dikir?
In the past, how did you make bread, how did you wash
clothes, how did you do it?
Wa nanî... sêlê dikir... cile, dire... me pa dikir, me ar
dikir, me nan dikir... erê welle yarebî, ma wa dikir.
That bread... we made it on the griddle... clothes,
harvest... we cleaned, we made flour, we made bread... yes
really oh Lord, we did it like that.
Û kunc... teşî, we teşî jî dirêst?
And clothes... the spindle, did you spin with the spindle
too?
Kunc me teşî... bi desta... hînî ewyî tûmaq jî dikita...
tûmêx...
Clothes we spun... by hand... back then the cotton beater
would also beat... the cotton beater...
Me'nî paqij bûn?
Intentions were pure?
Me'nî paqij bûn... wew kî noka dermana derd tunebûn...
pir... soda hebû dikirnê, başra hebû dişûşt, erê tûmêx.
Intentions were pure... not like now with medicines and
troubles... plenty... there was soda we put in, there was
'bashra' (soap type) we washed with, yes the cotton beater.
Berê... ber pêxwas bûn û diçûn û dihatin?
In the past... were you barefoot when going and coming?
Lê... erê... kû me ciqam eriban a... lingê xwe bas dana ber
sota ber sobê... ew berê... pixorê... Tine, pêlav tina... de
bes lingê me gandin, ne em ciwan bûn, pêra ne dihesiyan.
Oh... yes... where were our ragged patches... we just warmed
our feet by the fire, by the stove... that past... the
cold... None, there were no shoes... so our feet just froze,
no, we were young, we didn't feel it with that.
Heyata ciwanliqê xweş e.
The life of youth is good.
Erê, lê... rebbî xweş e welle yarebî.
Yes, oh... Lord it is good, really oh Lord.
Xaltîka Nazê... berê... wextê mesele gibîkik bot... mesele
diçûn daxwaztin...
Auntie Naze... in the past... when there was a betrothal...
for example they went to ask for a bride...
Hevdu nedidîtin heta roj dawetê?
They didn't see each other until the wedding day?
Erê welle yarebî... hişta hewa narnînî.
Yes really oh Lord... just like that, they didn't see.
Noka bi hev re didin, diçînin aqilê hev didin... yanê...
Now they talk together, they go and exchange thoughts... I
mean...
Sorê xwe dan ser hev da, ne dan ser hev da...
They put their secrets on each other, or don't put them on
each other...
Ê bes noka jî, dusa... dusa jî... hevdu berdidin û
derdikevin û xirwa dibe.
But even now, still... still... they divorce each other and
leave and it gets bad.
Berdan pir dibe, xirwa dibe, yanî noka.
Divorce happens a lot, it gets bad, I mean now.
Diçûn, bûkik didîtin, daxwaztin... û nedidîn hevdu, heta ku
roy dawetê.
They went, saw a bride, asked for her... and didn't see each
other, until the wedding day.
Heger roy dawetê ne'ecibanda?
What if on the wedding day he didn't like her?
Hew bû nesîbê xwe, ne... qebûl dikirin.
That was just his destiny, no... they accepted it.
Cwab nedidan?
They didn't answer back (refuse)?
Na. Dêkê, babê, bi kê dana... qebûl dikirin.
No. Mother, father, whoever gave her away... they accepted.
Nedigotin rind e, xirab e, dirêj e, zengîn e...?
They didn't say she is pretty, ugly, tall, rich...?
Na... tina bû heqqê... tina bû.
No... there was no right... none.
Heyata berê xweş bû.
Life in the past was good.
Xweş bû, cefabû, xweş bû.
It was good, it was hard, it was good.
We qeçik jî diçûn pişta tînan?
Did you carry children on your backs to bring them?
(Referring to work/fields)
Erê welle yarebî.
Yes really oh Lord.
Tu diçûyî...
You went...
Welle e, min nefsê min, serê xwe zênim... nêrî sêle, berî
royê... me xilas dikir teştk non...
Well yes, myself, I know my own head... looking at the
griddle, before the sun... we finished a basin of bread...
...û sibe zû, hindik destê me, baz didan ber mirîşka... ber
se, çay man bişûn... hema... beynî xwe û... dostê xwe û...
me dikir ber... çengî xwe û yalla banê. Em ê rabûn biçin
çogindî... dêwrîş... gû hezingê wana qalind... gîj me yê
banîna...
...and early morning, our little hands, ran to the
chickens... to the dog, washed the tea glasses... just...
between ourselves and... our friends and... we put it
under... our arms and let's go up [to the roof/mountain]. We
would get up to go for collecting kindling... dervish...
their thick wood... we brought it all...
...û em tûj bûn, em dabeziyan, kaşanekî, sûlkê me xwê ser û
berê qesd. Em ê botan û... cirîn derê me yê dîno, em ê
rûniştana, me xû da ber çîka bo man.
...and we were sharp (fast), we came down, up the hill, our
sweat all over us on purpose. We would be... [unclear] the
door we brought, we would sit, we gave ourselves to the
shade for us.
Bas e kînda, em çûn çitpiyo... me şelekê çitpiyo jî tîno.
It was good there, we went for brushwood... we brought a
load of brushwood too.
Silav... diçûn nêzîka... paşê ro jî çirpitî...
Greetings... going near... and later whispering...
Bes em royek... yekro diçû, yekro nediçû... ne ro ro.
But only one day for us... one day went, one day didn't
go... not every day.
Ê berê telefon tinebû, gûhê çûlê bû... û ar... doyê jî gûh
be êr bû... şîv şevîn gûh be xêzîngo bû?
Well in the past there were no phones, it was the ear of the
wilderness... and fire... even buttermilk was by the fire...
supper and night meals were by the firewood?
Erê welle nebû yarebî...
Yes really there wasn't oh Lord...
Roj cafo bû.
The day was hard.
Mesele berê... te hevs dikir? Çer çawa nêke ji me re hewal
de?
For example in the past... did you love [him]? How did it
happen, tell us the story?
Çend carak... Xaltîkê, got xaltîka mezinû... û ew jî ma ra
hewal didan, me guh lê dinda... em çûçik bûn, da nizanîn,
hişta fehm nedikirin... me buxwo nizani hawal da... wew jî
ma ra hewal dida.
A few times... Auntie, said the big auntie... and they told
us about it, we listened... we were small, didn't know yet,
didn't understand yet... we didn't know the story
ourselves... and she told us the story.
Te hevs kirî daxilî te damayî ye?
Did you love him so he has stayed in your heart?
Yê mirî kîme... navê wî Xelîl... mêrê min bi navê jinê... Wê
jî ma ra hewal didan, mesele... min qet çav ne lê dida...
heta roj dawetê.
The one who is dead... his name was Khalil... my husband in
the name of the wife... They told us about him, the issue...
I never laid eyes on him... until the wedding day.
Hîn roj dawetê... şev dawetê... te dît?
Then on the wedding day... the wedding night... you saw him?
Ber sibe... êr... ber pixorê... çavê min lê ket... roj
man... me ne diviya.
In the morning... fire... at dawn... my eyes fell upon
him... the day remained... we didn't want/love [at first].
Jê dil da bû?
Had you given your heart to him?
Lê... dil pak bûn!
Oh... hearts were pure!
Û fe'len jî yekî... ge şorik bikira... yanê hew şora hifz
dibû.
And actually if one... made a soup/meal... I mean that meal
was memorized/enough.
Diket aqilê...
It entered the mind...
Lawê birayê min... ewlî me... Şêx Xelîl bi navê xwe... Bû...
fitiq bû ra hebû... bûn nebû...
My brother's son [referring to host or relative]... our
first... Sheikh Khalil by his name... It was... he had a
hernia... it happened or didn't happen...
Welle sê çar mehaki bû... îke çûkin... texmîn meqder tine,
pir we nake... kêm bû.
Well it was three or four months [ago]... [or] one little
one... no estimate or amount, not much... it was little.
Gotekê min go, rehmetî... go ya rebbî... gulê... şîlanê
heye.
Not a word I said, the deceased... said oh Lord... the
rose... the eglantine is there.
Gulê min çû ye...
My rose is gone...
Ma tû gulê şîlanê... bes gulê qûçkayê... gulê xana eraviyê û
bi qorikî ye.
You are the eglantine rose... but the rose of the
rock/corner... the rose of the Arab house and with the stem.
Go yanê berî ruyê herin... şiqim bi qelşînin...
Said meaning before the faces go... let them split the
almond...
Wîneyê lewksê leqet heftêra derbas kin, dest hev didin...
Pass the picture of the Lux [lamp] to seventy places, they
give hands to each other...
Wîneyê bi heva girtin, paş xwe ne rûn warin... Wellel azîm
çêbû.
They took the picture together, didn't leave it behind
them... By God almighty it happened.
Çêbû.
It happened.
Û hîn lawikî heye, lawê birayê min hîne heye.
And there is still a boy, my brother's son is still there.
Heye welle.
He is there, really.
Heyata berê xweş bû.
Life in the past was good.
Heyata berê, wekî noka bû... xweşî em nate hebû yarebî... Te
biçûka... sîqet hebû... te biçûka qiseyek bikira, mezinê
qebûl nedikir.
Life in the past, was like now [in some ways]... we had
happiness among us oh Lord... You, the little one... there
was trust... if you, the little one, said a word, the elder
didn't accept [disrespect].
Hes kirin ji hebû?
Was there love too?
Haskirin temam bû... ê noka na, tiştek nemaye ji loyê me.
Love was complete... but now no, nothing remains from our
side.
Am gî me'rîyê hevdî, ozinê...
We were all relatives of each other, poets/singers...
Am xêrî hevdû naxwazin. Am na rincîn cem hevdu natên.
We don't wish good for each other [now]. We don't get upset,
we don't come to each other.
Ê îso merliqê biçî ye? Biçî tê neyê?
So now what is manhood? Going, coming or not coming?
Noka ez sibê, em te hebdim me, ka bes ez hebdim no sker.
Now I, tomorrow, we [unclear: adore?] you, but I [unclear]
no sugar.
Mesele... tu naşî mêr?
The issue... will you not marry [again]?
Na... qet qet... Mêrê min çû... ez dê rûnim...
No... never never... My husband is gone... I will sit
[remain single]...
Ez lawê te me.
I am your son.
Awa tû, min hûnî vane... 2000... ma derbas bî ne... hûn
xwedê ne... ez bi qurbana we bim.
That implies you, I [love] you all... 2000... passed... you
are [of] God... may I be a sacrifice for you.
Xaltîka Nazê, şîvê di Dimîlya da... ma'rûf çi ye?
Auntie Naze, in Dimilya, what is 'shiv' (dinner) known as?
Şîvê me'rûf?
Known dinner?
Noka cem me Behdîna dibên "Danokê Behdîna".
Now among us Bahdinis they say "The Wheat Soup of Bahdinis".
Divê danokê Behdîna... rast e?
They say the Wheat Soup of Bahdinis... is it true?
Belê... danok... şîrê me wanokî giran... hev nû bûn. Nan û
savar, tiştî wanokî giran... şîvê giran, sivik nebûn.
Yes... wheat soup... our milk was heavy like that... they
were new. Bread and bulgur, heavy things like that... heavy
suppers, they weren't light.
Berê genim... bi dasa?
In the past wheat... [harvested] with sickles?
Bi soqî diketan.
It fell by the stalks.
Me bi pişta dikişand...
We pulled/carried it on our backs...
Bi delîb...
With the threshing sled...
Bi delîb... bi canîkê, bi kerê... me gêre dikir. Erê canim
welle.
With the threshing sled... with the colt, with the donkey...
we threshed. Yes my soul, really.
Paşê me bê dikir... me dikire kîs û me bar dikir û yalla
banê.
Then we winnowed it... we put it in sacks and loaded it and
let's go up/home.
Hema... emrê te dirêj be.
Anyway... may your life be long.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Tişte berê xweş bû?
Things of the past were good?
Xweş bû... û ştê... xwarina xwe... gî sax bû xwarina xwe.
It was good... and thing... our food... our food was all
healthy.
Bi keşk, bi tûra... mîş... keşk... bastiq... sujiq... tişta
paşê ne dihat... hemû ji berê çêdikirin.
With kishk (dried yogurt), with bags... whey... kishk...
fruit leather... walnut sausage... things didn't come from
later... all were made from before/scratch.
Berê pir tişt çêdikirin.
In the past they made many things.
Erê welle, doxwurme.
Yes really, fried meat (qawirma).
Tiştê di berê xweş ne... mesele di berê xweş ne... heyata
berê xweş bû.
Things in the past were not... for example in the past were
not... life in the past was good.
Xweş bû welle yarebî.
It was good really oh Lord.
Demsî raza... hek kûçikê... teneke diçû... em li dêkê me
hebû. Sê kûçikê teşt jê dikirin.
The table cloth laid out... if a spoon... a tin went... we
had at our mother's. Three spoons from the basin/bowl we
ate/took.
Xilas dikirin. Gi dixwarin, va dixwarin... niha kîm dixwin.
Finished it. All ate, this ate... now few eat.
Berê pir tişt çêdikirin.
In the past they made many things.
Do... Do dixwarin ma... maselê di berê xweş ne. Heyata berê
xweş bû.
Yogurt drink... They drank yogurt drink... for example in
the past not good. Life in the past was good.
Jafabû, bes xweş bû.
It was hard, but it was good.
Te emrê te ne, tu gotinê te ne...
Your age, your words [are not enough/don't match?]...
Xwedê ji we razî be... saet xweş bû hatî.
God be pleased with you... it was a good hour that you came.
Emê qehwekê jî çêkin.
We will make a coffee too.
Hûn xwedê ne... ser sera û ser çava.
You are [guests of] God... upon heads and upon eyes.
Saheta we xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Have a good time, God be pleased with you.
Saheta we xweş.
Have a good time.
(Music plays)
Merheba Xalê Ehmed.
Hello Uncle Ahmed.
Ya mît ehlen wa sehlen.
Oh hundred welcomes.
Weysat çawa ye?
How is your condition?
Wele siheta me zeîf e.
Well our health is weak.
Çend salî ye Xalê Ehmed?
How old are you Uncle Ahmed?
Welle... li kaxezê heyştê û sê ye.
Well... on the paper [ID] it's eighty-three.
Heyştê û sê?
Eighty-three?
Belê.
Yes.
Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide te.
May God give you a long life.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Te çend qeçik gihandine? Te çend mezin kirine?
How many children have you raised? How many have you grown?
Welle min deh gihandine... yek berî vê... deh û yek... berî
vê bi sê salê yek waba bû... kêm deh mane.
Well I raised ten... one before this... ten and one...
before this by three years one passed away
[plague/illness?]... remaining ten left.
Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, yên mayî jî Xwedê bihêle.
God have mercy on him/her, and may God keep the remaining
ones.
Xwedê ji te razî be, emrê te dirêj ke.
God be pleased with you, may He lengthen your life.
Xalê Ehmed em ji qenatê Youtube "Hatim li Efrîn"...
Uncle Ahmed we are from the YouTube channel "Hatim in
Afrin"...
Erê...
Yes...
Lunek pir xweş e, derbas gindor dibe, cem mezinê me, gel
çîrçîrokê berê dîne, gel tiştê dîtûraz dîne.
It's a very nice vibe, passing through the villages, with
our elders, bringing stories of the past, bringing heritage
things.
Ka çi çîrokê miro... ser berê deng ke... çû xweş bû? Wi heya
çû derbas kir?
So what human stories... speak on the past... how was it
good? How did life pass?
Wellehî... berî giştî kîl vederê... daîg... bilet hatî
vederê... ewle mesela... ke hindik dihatin...
By God... before everything [goods] by weight/measure
here... mothers/animals... tickets/loads came here... that
issue... that little came...
Berî hingê... wekî goçberiyê bû.
Before then... it was like nomadic life.
Mer haldarî kê ne ma... bar dikirin derekî...
Man didn't stay in one condition... they loaded up to a
place...
Erê.
Yes.
Yanî aborî berê, berî hezar salî da...
I mean, the economy in the past, a thousand years ago...
Bi miletê Tirkî re kîr û mîr hootî.
Rulers and officials came and went with the Turkish nation.
Yanî ne ku bi evro hatina, bes hezar salî da li vir hatina
dîtin û em zêde bûne.
I mean, it's not that they just came today, but they have
been seen here for a thousand years, and we have increased.
Û îdî va... bi ra... hîmê vo kîmê tû gote?
And so... regarding... what was the foundation you
mentioned?
Gote baran hat û de... Gote tîşkî na pês ketî yanî zuncî ye.
They said if rain comes and... They said nothing develops,
meaning it is a chain.
Gote qaçikim... Gote çi digrin deynin, emê bijîn biçin.
He said, let me escape... He said whatever we plant, we will
live and go on.
Gote erdî pses in, êr ketî, tû yê vî qalincî, î pês av dikî.
He said the land is behind, fire fell on it, you irrigate
this thicket.
Yanî me'ne... Hirş... Kelam... Dîrok... Yanî bi ra... em
tina bûn.
Meaning... The forest... The talk... History... I mean,
really... we didn't exist [in that way].
Erê. Hêşînayî?
Yes. Greenery [crops]?
Belê em şa... Hirş e, çiya ye, kelam e... yanî pir pir yanî.
Yes we... It is forest, it is mountain, it is talk... I
mean, very much so.
Êj ji hezar salî vir da, ti da şixulîn.
From a thousand years ago until now, we worked in it.
Yavash yavas... Genim, Pîrê, me têda şixulîn.
Slowly, slowly... Wheat, Hay, we worked in it.
Dê... kirin erd.
Then... they turned it into [arable] land.
De emrê me da, vê qiraznê darik tinebûn.
In our lifetime, there were no trees in this landscape.
Erê.
Yes.
Yanî zeytûn tinebûn. Li deştê... zeytûn tinebûn, rez hebûn.
Meaning there were no olives. In the plain... there were no
olives, there were vineyards.
Kêm zêde bûna?
Were they somewhat abundant?
Kêm zeytûn hebûn, kêm.
There were few olives, few.
Ji emrê me da ha.
Since our lifetime, you see.
Rez hebûn. Û erdê boş hebûn, dikirin genim, dikirin garis,
garisê spî.
There were vineyards. And there was plenty of land, they
planted wheat, they planted millet, white millet.
Bendenê mirovan pê sarî xwa nava qolîç.
The sheaves of the people [were carried] on their heads in
the crooked places.
Heta dikirin pembû.
They even planted cotton.
Pembû?
Cotton?
Erê pajî.
Yes, my brother.
Yanî çi divî erdî da biçîn, dibê.
Meaning whatever you plant in this earth, it grows.
Vê qiraznê jî giştik... berê dikotin zîwan... zîwan
diçandin.
In this landscape as well, everything... before they called
it darnel... they planted darnel.
Sêfiye... meselan... bîstan diçandin li vê qiraznê.
Summer crops... for example... they planted vegetable
gardens in this landscape.
Erê.
Yes.
Bele em dore... axa ya kindirî mêş... berê xeyar tinebûn,
'acûr... 'acûr diçandin.
But around... the land of squash... before there were no
cucumbers, 'acûr (Armenian cucumber)... they planted 'acûr.
'Acûr?
'Acûr diçandin. Ê tiştî hinek vê qiraznê da diçandin,
patata... gi diçandin.
They planted 'acûr. And some things they planted in this
landscape, potatoes... they planted it all.
Erê.
Yes.
Paşê çêl... yanî heftê heştê salî vir da da, orta dorse da
peyda bûn.
Then forty... I mean since seventy or eighty years ago, it
appeared in the middle period.
Yavaş yavaş...
Slowly, slowly...
E... yavaş yavaş... paşê... yanî heqet tar û bibêm, darê vê
qiraznê heftê sal emrê xwe heye.
Eh... slowly, slowly... then... I mean if I truly define it,
the trees in this landscape are seventy years old.
Erê.
Yes.
E... Exlebiye heftê sal e.
Eh... The majority are seventy years old.
Wekî din çayê kirmîc... mesela, sêl pêş de îşo bûn.
Otherwise, the tea of the Kirmîc (river/region)... for
example, floods happened before tonight.
Ewwelî... li ser pêz de jî şivan, pezê xwe jî dikirin pezê
reş.
Firstly... regarding the sheep, the shepherd, they made
their sheep the black sheep.
Pezê reş?
Black sheep?
Mekîne... divê çano da, Dêmiş divê.
Machines... in this place, they call it Damascus [referring
to specific Damascus breeds/goods].
Dêmiş divê?
They call it Damascus?
Heta mîrê xwe bi qûç bûn, bizinê xwe bi qûç bûn. Te yek sor
di nav da nedidît, gi reş bûn.
Even their rams were horned, their goats were horned. You
wouldn't see a single red one among them, they were all
black.
Gi reş bûn?
They were all black?
Digotin pezê reş.
They called them black sheep.
Paşê noxir hebûn.
Then there were cattle herds.
Hm.
Çêl, golik, tana... şivanê xwe hebûn.
Cows, calves, heifers... they had their own shepherd.
Şivan jî gund bû.
The shepherd was also from the village.
Şivîn... salê sal, daw û dim he diçû ber vê noxirê...
serbêder o... heqê xwe dibir.
The shepherd... year after year, continuously went before
this herd... the head shepherd... he took his wage.
Erê.
Yes.
Pere tinebûn.
There was no money.
Pere tinebûn?
There was no money?
He?
Huh?
Pere dibir?
Did he take money?
Golik... bi kêlekê... çêl bi... bi golik nîv kêlê, çêl bi
kêlekê.
A calf... for a bushel... a cow for... for a calf [he got]
half a bushel, for a cow a [full] bushel.
Kêlê genim?
A bushel of wheat?
Kêlê ye.
It is a bushel.
Î diçû ber... e hef perê xwe wane dibir.
He who went before [herding]... eh, he took his payment like
that.
Şûnê tenê dibir?
Did he take grain instead?
Jinê çi dikir nav gund digerî...
What did the wife do? She walked through the village...
E... çêl e, serî çêlê nanek didanê. Serî golik nanek didanê.
Manê pê bijîn.
Eh... a cow, per cow they gave a bread. Per calf they gave a
bread. Meaning, so they could survive on it.
Saeta te xweş Xalê Mihemed. Bi îzna te emê hinekî derbasî ba
Xaltîkê bibin.
Bless you, Uncle Mohammed. With your permission, we will
move over to the Aunty for a bit.
Xaltîka Emîne.
Aunty Emine.
Erê, bi xêr hatin ser çava.
Yes, welcome, upon my eyes.
Ka ev çiye? Ji me ra li ser vê bêje.
What is this? Tell us about this.
Weleh, xortê min... Vêra dibên hekîb.
By God, my young man... They call this a saddlebag (hekîb).
Hekîb.
Saddlebag.
De hekîb.
So, a saddlebag.
Ev berê qernewî çêdikirin... tike miro tişkî berê...
They used to make this centuries ago... You know, people of
the past...
We bi destê çêdikir. Tevn... qenewîç... merş... çel...
They made it by hand. Looms... canvas... rugs... sacks...
Wa cil jî çêdikirin.
They made clothes too.
Wa cil jî çêdikirin?
They made clothes too?
Lê em diçûn qişka me şel û tînan yorim... ma çoyê gundî
dewrîş da tînan.
But we went to the looms, we brought shalwar pants... we
brought cloth from the Dervish village.
E deşta me nan dikir, dewar hebû me xizmet dewar dikir.
Eh, our plain made bread, there were livestock, we served
the livestock.
De, ev berê hişta gija bûn. Qçik jî me gî bi cefo mezin
kirin.
So, these used to be plentiful. And we raised the children
entirely with hardship.
Bi cefayê?
With hardship?
Ê bi qişko, gî bi dewer, gî bi çûle...
Yes, with looms, all with livestock, all with sacks...
Xwedê Rebbûl 'alemîn saeta xweş bide jî, canikî sax bide.
May the Lord of the Worlds grant a good hour (health) and a
healthy body.
De hişta yorim korê me hebûn.
So, back then, my son, we had work.
Ê berê me dikir, em kê çi korî bikin?
Eh, we did it before, what work should we do [now]?
Çûl bûn, mal bûn, qçik bûn, cefo bûn.
There were sacks, there was home, there were children, there
was hardship.
De hişta me wan otê va dida.
So, back then we gave them to those [people].
Elhemdila, divê ro da ro derket.
Praise be to God, from this day, the sun came out.
Û şikir ji Xwedê ra, gî bî fereleqê jî ketin.
And thanks to God, they all fell into abundance.
Tu Xwedê saeta xweş bide jî, bide me jî înşala.
May God grant them good times, and grant us too, God
willing.
Xwedê wejbelom afaz bike.
May God protect you from misfortune.
De yanî, ev tişta bi xwe dibûn?
So, I mean, did these things happen naturally (were they
made at home)?
Lê gî bi cefo bûn, gî bi destan bûn yorim wele.
But it was all with hardship, all by hand, my son, really.
Xaltîka Emîne, bi kê tişkî şte pirsk im. Berê... dibêj
zêvero, kîmî sipî çêdikirin?
Aunty Emine, let me ask you something. Before... they say
jewelry, did they make white truffles (beads/ornaments)?
E kîmê sipî... te gîştê lê te negîştê.
Eh, white truffles... you reached it, or you didn't reach it
[understand].
Na negîştimê, bes berê me wabû.
No, I didn't reach it, but our past was like that.
Kimê... ji zêvero çêdikirin.
Truffles... they made them from jewelry (adornments).
Erê, bofkê mûkûj miro çêkirin.
Yes, people made silk covers.
Hm. Kîmê zêveran?
Hm. Truffles of jewelry?
Erê, kîmê sipî deko me çêdikirin.
Yes, we made white truffle tattoos/adornments.
Çêdikirin?
They made them?
Hm.
Û dibê berê, wextî gî biçûna, yek mesel gwa qîzik ji mêrk ra
bixwastana...
And they say before, when they went, for example if they
asked for a girl for a man...
Ne didî hata rûyê dewa tê.
He wouldn't give her until the face of the claim comes.
E wele, hebû hebû. Çû tinebû.
Eh really, it existed, it existed. It wasn't absent.
Çimwa givern e, no wele hebû.
Because they were prevalent, no really, it existed.
Hebû, me hebû me ji heqê û...
It existed, we had it, we... from the right of...
Hey na, di wextê dûr da.
No, no, in the distant time.
Na na webû, dogrî bî.
No no, it was so, it was true.
Diçûn dixwastin, û hefdaûna dikirin?
Did they go ask for her, and did they make a feud/dowry
claim?
Ê nok no, darin cem hev, tên bav ra deyn dikin. Bav ra
didin, distînin, di'ecibînin, na'ecibînin.
Eh look no, they go together, they come to give the debt to
the father. They give to the father, they take, they like
it, they don't like it.
Berê ew tinebû yorim, wele webû dogrê.
Before that didn't exist my son, really it was true.
Noko tine, noko urza kiş kûçik.
Now it doesn't exist, now the respect is gone (lit. line is
distinct like a dog).
Berê çê dikirin urzak.
Before they made a respect/line.
Urzak?
A line/respect?
Dandoqî çi tînan?
What did they bring for the dowry chest?
Dandoq... wekî teno gilûk bûn.
Chests... they were like round balls.
Wekî noko tînan?
Did they bring them like now?
Wekî noko ye, bizrî xwe heye.
Like now, it has its own seed (origin).
Tînan çêdikirin.
They brought them and made them.
Me gî, derzê, bizê pêva dikir, me poçik dikirin, nav me
taxtek dikir...
We all, needles, awls, we used on it, we made tassels, we
put a board inside...
Orte gî bi benîka me çêdikirin, bi dor dixistin. Va no
çêdibî.
We made the middle all with threads, we put it around. This
is how it was made.
Û wa çêdikir, wa bi minzer bi daro dixist.
And she made it, she hung it neatly on the wood.
Hinek jî dibên me'nê çe'vo.
But...
Some also say it means eyes (evil eye protection).
Ê çe'vo... be'z liber qiçko dişewitînin. Me teno jê dikir
ber piko dişewitandin.
Yes eyes... some burn it for the children. We cut it like
that and burned it before the flames.
Rin bû.
It was beautiful.
Heye tê berê xweş bû?
Was your past good?
Îda yorim malê xweş bû.
Indeed my son, the home was good.
Cafo bî, bes xweş bî, ne?
It was hardship, but it was good, right?
Xweş bî, wele xweş bî. Û em biva hevdra diçûn, am dot...
It was good, really good. And we went together like this, we
milked...
Noko cîranê kerr ê cîrê.
Now the neighbor is deaf to the neighbor.
Erê.
Yes.
Berê hem cema... we, wawa, em na, em qçik bûn, di nav hev da
mezin bûn, malê mel, malê...
Before, all together... you, like that, we, no, we were
children, we grew up amongst each other, house to house...
Saeta te xweş Xaltîka Emîne. Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike.
Bless you Aunty Emine. May God prolong your life.
Û emr tana te, tu gotin tana.
And your life too, may you not see bad words.
Bi saeta we xweş, Xwedê wa rizî be, û Xwedê havalê wa be, û
Xwedê tu talyol wa nemîne inşalla.
Bless you, may God be satisfied with you, and may God be
your companion, and may God not let any bitterness remain
for you, God willing.
Wele wa selamet, wele mal.
Really, safety to you, really home.
Xwedê rehma xwe li te bike.
May God have mercy on you.
Xwedê Rebbûl 'alemîn saeta xweş bide we, û tima hebin, û ser
lingê xwe bin.
May the Lord of the Worlds grant you good times, and may you
exist, and be on your feet.
Û Rebbûl 'alemîn wefeyê bide ne dên... yanî hûn bikêmin
saeta xwe ma.
And may the Lord of the Worlds grant loyalty... I mean, may
you not decrease our good time.
Amîn.
Amen.
Eva bi munasibê Eîd el-Hub, nêzîk bûye, hîn jî wek dêkê me
ne, hezkirina me ji we ra pirre.
This is for the occasion of Valentine's Day (Eid al-Hub), it
is near, you are like our mother, our love for you is great.
Eva tişkî pir besît e, hedîye ji me da.
This is something very simple, a gift from us.
Ji qenatê "Hatim li Efrîn", teqdim dikê, hezkirin ji we ra.
From the channel "Hatim li Efrîn", presenting it, love to
you.
Ê bixatira me rabin.
Eh, stand up for our goodbye.
Ê ew a tişkî aqil min wacib e.
Eh, this is something my mind considers a duty.
Ellah selem.
God give peace.
Em jî ey Xalê Ehmed, Xwedê şîfa bide Xaltîkê. Qisûrê me hene
hûnê efû bikin.
And us too, oh Uncle Ahmed, may God grant healing to Aunty.
If we have faults, you will forgive us.
Ê wekî we zêde bike inşalla.
Eh, may He increase people like you, God willing.
Saet xweş. Xwedê ji we razî be, Xwedê emrê kî dirêj bide we.
Bless you. May God be satisfied with you, may God grant you
a long life.
Xwedê şeva we xweş bike.
May God make your night pleasant.
Înşalla em silavên germ ji gundê Dûmila dişînin.
God willing, we send warm greetings from the village of
Dumila.
Esselamu Eleykum we rehmetullahî we berekatuhu.
Peace be upon you and God's mercy and blessings.
Ez hatim gundê Dûmila teswîrê, li qenatê "Hatim li Efrîn",
ser qenatê Youtube.
I came to the village of Dumila for filming, on the channel
"Hatim li Efrîn", on the Youtube channel.
Me dîtî zirqê dikê, me got em derbaz jê em tebîn, em tişkê
pirsk in, ka...
We saw he is making baskets/wicker, we said let's pass by so
we can see, let's ask something, so...
Ma pênasînekê bide?
Will you give us an introduction?
Ehlen we sehlen. Şe'ban Bavê Ehmed.
Welcome. Shaban, Father of Ahmed.
Şe'ban Bavê Ehmed?
Shaban, Father of Ahmed?
Hotina we ser serî me, ser çavê me ye.
Your coming is upon our heads, upon our eyes.
Bi qewma ra dibêjin Şe'ban Bavê Ehmed.
The people call me Shaban Bavê Ahmed.
Ez xwe zirqê dikim.
I make baskets/wicker myself.
Teqrîben textî mecilî bîst salî ye.
Approximately, the experience in this field is twenty years.
Bîst salî?
Twenty years?
Bîst salî ye.
Twenty years.
Awa zen'etê min e.
This is my craft.
Karê me hav e. Em şta... ku dere şixulek ber min nayê tîn
dîtin.
Our work is this. We just... since no job comes before me
[is available] to be found.
Û merî nî fukare ne. Em kê îşta ser şixulî xwe bin, û ser
karî xwe bin.
And we are poor people. We just want to be on our own work,
and on our own job.
Û elhemdilla ji Xwedê ra.
And praise be to God.
Elhemdilla.
Praise be to God.
Te bîst sal ne vê korî dikê?
Have you been doing this work for twenty years?
Te p'oş ji dêmilo ye?
[Asking off camera] Are you waiting for a moment?
Xweş dêmilo ye, na.
[Responding] A pleasant moment, no.
Ji dêmilo ye, te vê korî dikê zîrqê.
Since that time, you have been doing this basket work.
Temam, ewa ji dêmilo ye ez zîrqê dikim.
Okay, since that time I have been making baskets.
E ya pî ye jî dikim.
Eh, I do the footwork too.
Yo pî ye, zîrqê ye, ez çêdikim.
The footwork?
The foot one, the basket one, I make them.
Korê min a.
It is my work.
Xwedê rizqê ta bişîne.
May God send your sustenance.
Saxbe, saeta we xweş.
Be healthy, bless you.
Me hot lexta birin, me xwest ez dere we deyn kim û der
bikim.
We came to take a shot, we wanted to put you in it and bring
it out.
No ez dixwazim. Yanî pêşketina nû kî hene di nav me da,
gerek em bahra me se'dê bikin.
No, I want it. I mean, whatever new developments exist among
us, we must help our share.
Em bahra xalkin. Milo dengî me bigihî hemu aleme.
We should create a share. So our voice reaches the whole
world.
Giştikî, e no mentiqa Efrîn, çi şixul têda heye, çi ştê tê
têkirin, zen'et çî têda hene.
Everything, eh this region of Afrin, what work is in it,
what things are done in it, what crafts are in it.
Meslehet, xudan meslehet hene, xudan şixul hene.
Professions, there are business owners, there are workers.
Milo xalk me bibîne e no... ma'lmiqê me jî heye di şixul da.
So people see us in this... we also have mastery in the
work.
Ekîd.
Certainly.
Û bi xwe gundê Efrîn pir xweş in.
And principally the villages of Afrin are very beautiful.
Gundê Efrîn emê derbaz giyo bin inşalla.
We will pass through all the villages of Afrin, God willing.
Bi xwe qenatî me hatim li Efrîn, lûnikê tûras dıqedmîne.
Principally our channel "Hatim li Efrîn", presents the
heritage colors.
Tiştê di gund da meşhûr, adet û teqalîdê di gund da, bi dilî
xweş em derbazî gundê giyo dibin.
Things famous in the village, customs and traditions in the
village, with a happy heart we pass through all the
villages.
Saeta we xweş, û Xwedê saeta xweş we de.
Bless you, and may God grant you good times.
Û hev tişta tişkî pir rinda.
And this thing is something very good.
Ez dixwazim her însanek, kî dengî me digre bi wara muşareke
kê, û dengî we b'gizaro gînê.
I want every human, whoever catches our voice to share it,
and spread your voice around.
Û aleme'k zanibe ku vê mentiqo jî mentiqo pir xweş e.
And for a world to know that this region is also a very
beautiful region.
Bi tebîetê xwe xweş e, bi şixulî xwe xweş e.
It is beautiful in its nature, it is beautiful in its work.
Û Xwedê ebînê we zêde bike, saeta we xweş.
And may God increase your viewers, bless you.
Xwedê ji te ra razî be, Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide, rastî min
xwest ez bişînim, derbasbûm, an na go ez miletê xwe aciz
bikim, tiştekî ser şixulê, bes min şixulê tew na dî, min dî
hûn rûniştine...
May God be pleased with you, may God grant you a long life.
Honestly, I wanted to send [greetings], I was passing by, I
didn't want to bother my people while working, but I didn't
see any work, I saw you were sitting...
Saet xweş...
Thanks...
Te emr tenê, te gotin tenê, te kîşmê ra bike.
It's just your command, just your word, whatever you ask
for.
Bi Xwedê ez bêm, Xwedê saetê xweş bide, û Xwedê wekî we pir
bike, dengê me bigihîne dera...
By God, I say, may God grant a good hour, and may God
increase people like you, may our voice reach places...
Music
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Xwedê we silamet ke. Navê te?
May God keep you safe. What is your name?
Cemîl Mistefa Ebdo.
Jemil Mustafa Abdo.
Xalê Cemîl, ehlen we sehlen.
Uncle Jemil, welcome.
Ehlen.
Welcome.
Merheba xaltîk?
Hello auntie?
Ehlen we sehlen, ehlen.
Welcome, hello.
Navê te?
What is your name?
Navê min Mehbet e.
My name is Mehbet.
Xaltîka Mehbet.
Auntie Mehbet.
Em dam xalo, çend salî ye xalê Cemîl?
Tell us uncle, how old are you, uncle Jemil?
Eger temam heftî... Eger 40 naha me.
If complete [I'm] seventy... If [born in] 40, I am now [that
age].
Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide.
May God grant you a long life.
Saxbî, spas dikim.
Be healthy, thank you.
Te çend qîz û kur mezin kirin?
How many daughters and sons did you raise?
Xwedê yên we bihêle, yekî min mir... yên din hene, heft heb
hene.
May God spare yours, one of mine died... the others are
here, there are seven.
Xwedê ji te ra bihêle û Xwedê emrê dirêj bide.
May God spare them for you and may God grant a long life.
Û daxwaza karê me jî... îşta karê gundaye me... dîşî cûda
cûda, merd kir, wer kir...
And regarding our work... well, it's our village work...
separate things, acted bravely, did this...
Karê cefa.
Hard work.
Karê cefa, me... înn şixilê me, betûn û zeytûn û dar û qut
dikirin.
Hard work, we... look our work was concrete, olives, and
cutting trees.
Te vedan dikir?
Did you do construction [plastering/stone work]?
Min vedan dikir.
I did construction.
Heyata berê xweş bû?
Was the life of the past good?
Oooo... em pir noka kêfê dikin, fehm?
Oooo... we are having a lot of fun now, understand?
[Sarcastic]
Berê xweş bû?
Was the past good?
Ê rê, wela el-ezîm.
Yes, by God Almighty.
Berê nanê firnê tunebû, noka...
Before there was no bakery bread, now...
Meselen... nanê genimî bixwe dikir me.
For example... we made wheat bread ourselves.
Ê vê nanê... vê firneha derketin, em nişkê hemû noka jî... o
noka meselen... firne heye.
And this bread... these bakeries came out, suddenly all of
us now... oh now for example... there is a bakery.
Nanê genimî malê kes nake.
No one makes wheat bread at home.
Ke firnê. Nanê genimî berê dikir ser sêlê.
Only the bakery. They made wheat bread before on the
griddle.
Berê ser sêlê me dikir.
Before, we made it on the griddle.
Pûşîn têkir?
Did you feed it kindling?
Pûşîn têkir.
Fed it kindling.
Saet xweş xalê Cemîl, Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide.
Thanks Uncle Jemil, may God grant you a long life.
Xwedê ji te razî be, ser serî, bi xêr hatî.
May God be pleased with you, on my head [welcome], you are
welcome.
Xaltîka Mehbet?
Auntie Mehbet?
Erê.
Yes.
Mana sî navê te çî ye?
What is the meaning of your name?
Dem... mihbet îşta... hezkirin lo, dinê giha...
Time... love well... it is love, the world has ended...
Hezkirin heye?
Is there love?
Hezkirin... Hezkirin tune me zortir qa?
Love... Is there no love greater than ours?
Sal wext derbasbûn.
Years and time passed.
Hezkirina berê yan ya noka?
The love of the past or the one now?
Ya berê... ya noka... hezkirin... o dinê giha.
The one of the past... the one now... love... oh the world
has ended.
Dinê bê hezkirin nabe.
The world cannot exist without love.
Erê.
Yes.
Çend salî ye xaltîk?
How old are you, auntie?
Wele gerek... şêst... şêst û heftan.
Well probably... sixty... sixty-seven.
Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide.
May God grant you a long life.
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God spare you.
Te çend qîz û kur mezin kirin?
How many daughters and sons did you raise?
Neh lawik min hene. Du qîzik min hene. Ê mirî rehma Xwedê lê
be.
I have nine sons. I have two daughters. The dead one, God's
mercy be on him.
Em manê... Îşta rehma Xwedê li mirîyê we hemûya be.
Amen... Well, God's mercy on all your dead.
Û metê Mihemed gisp...
And aunt of Muhammad...
Kote kiçkê ji mira ser berê dengê heyatê berê çiqas xweş bû,
we çawa derbas dikir?
Tell me a little about the past, how good the life of the
past was, how did you pass it?
Wele qijik tûtî nan?
Well [unintelligible] bread?
We nanê genimî çawa dikir?
How did you make wheat bread?
Berê dêmilû li ko xwedî dikir.
Before, early morning we raised [livestock].
We dileqlem kî biçûnim paşê benî çûye gundî hewîş.
[Unintelligible description of village life/work].
Sibê îê zingo... nîvro hîç... îê kindê... îê çirpîyo.
In the morning the 'zingo' [sound of churning]... noon
nothing... the 'kind' [sound]... the 'chirp' [butter
splashing].
Silav li vî dûçûna zingo, paşê rindî şîn çirpîyo.
Greetings to this tail of 'zing', then the good blue/fresh
'chirp'.
Çirpi.
Chirp.
O tam rahet dibin.
And the taste became pleasant.
Meke sibê rabû teştî hevîr bikira.
Mother got up in the morning to make a basin of dough.
Meke rabû dew bikiya.
Mother got up to make yogurt drink.
Meke pez bidoşta.
Mother milked the sheep.
Meke şîr germ bikira, şivîn xêra lê çê...
Mother boiled milk, supper was good...
Em kêlçî jî boriya zingo dinimol...
We [unintelligible] the churn 'zingo'...
Em kê wena teq req... dîsa peskê wera danê.
We did 'clack clack'... again threw it back.
Dîsa halê me... halê berê...
Again our situation... situation of the past...
Û biftin... orta heba pehle...
And sleep... in the middle was labor...
Heba zêtûnê... heba car cara... heba bêdera... îşta...
There were olives... there was sometimes... there was the
threshing floor... well...
Kokişandin... bê darba kirin...
Gathering... without threshing...
Ser danê me bê îşo gidiya...
[Unintelligible] given on us went...
Fiştik.
Peanuts!
Î ro noka xwe tûnin ne.
Today now they are not there.
Xwe tûnî... Ma çavê reş nikan?
Not there... do black eyes not do?
Çiqas sebabyî meke dihet heneke...
How much cause mother came joke...
Gamoş hewşê poş kirin o bigeh li kûlke gundo.
Covered the buffalo in the yard and reach the hut of the
village.
Berê poş dikirin.
Before they covered [them].
Me çend qicik hunîn, hefadê tunebûn.
I had a few small ones, no grandchildren.
Me gidişûşt.
We washed.
Gip poç bû?
Was it crop-eared [small/worthless]?
Gip poç... û desto...
Crop-eared... and hands...
Ax dikirim o...
I sigh oh...
Îşta heyata berê hebiya, em kêf dikir.
If only the life of the past existed, we would have fun.
Çetin bî ne?
It was hard, wasn't it?
War... war heba nanê me...
Place... if there was a place for our bread...
Te vê jî hez dikir?
Did you love him too?
Ya jê hez dikir... Ewa jimer min tirkî nizanibû.
I loved him... He didn't know counting/money from me.
Îşta ew heqî berê min... em kê binçim...
Well that right of mine before... we who go...
Me cilda dikirin... Me ergan grêdidan...
We made bedding... We tied quilts...
Îşta me teşî dirsta... me şadî şkinîn...
Well we spun spindles... we broke [happiness?]...
Korê berê hebiya.
If only the son of the past existed.
Ekê pirsekî şta pirs kim.
I will ask a question.
Berê... kim... cezabora kim çê dikirin? Kime sipî? Te gîştê
lê ne gîştê?
Before... who... whose trousseau did they make? Who is
white? Did you reach it or not?
No... no kim nedî.
No... no didn't see who.
No kim nedî.
No didn't see who.
Û berê qelengê jinan mêra wextê qid dikirin... Bi pere bî lê
bi çi qid dikirin?
And before, when men set the bride price for women... Was it
with money or what did they set it with?
O qelengê te çiqas kirin?
And how much was your bride price made?
Qelengê min... kuro...
My bride price... boy...
Qelengê min bi çar hezarî bî.
My bride price was four thousand.
Nav da, deng da, go Mistefê Ûqizê xwo...
It made a name, made a noise, they said Mustafa Uqize [her
father] his...
Qeleng bi çar hezarî birrina.
Cut the bride price at four thousand.
Û yorganek didan qîza, ya bûkînek...
And they gave a quilt to the girl, or a doll...
Bofkê min destek pert dida me...
My father gave me a handful of rags...
Nav da, deng da, go Mistefê Û... wele go...
It made a name, made a noise, they said Mustafa U... well
said...
Destek pert da ye qîza xwe.
Gave a handful of rags to his daughter.
Û ji vê ve birdan, qelengê qîza... meselen...
And from here they took, the bride price of the girl... for
example...
Bî çar, bî heft, bî dehe didî... îşta pîrê dergî û disidî.
It was four, was seven, was ten given... well old engagement
and [unintelligible].
Disidî fir de jî em nizanin. Biçî orta milyonek.
[Unintelligible] we don't know. Goes to the middle of a
million.
Qelengê yanê... berê... wextê qelengê qîza qid dikirin...
Bride price ie... before... when they set the bride price of
girls...
Bûka min da bi çar hezarî bî. Qelengê min bi çara bî.
My bride given was four thousand. My bride price was four.
E te bi çara qid kir.
Ah you set it at four.
Îşta... jimar çikirin.
Well... counting made.
Saeta te xweş, Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide.
Thanks to you, may God grant a long life.
Xwedê te bihêle, Xwedê...
May God spare you, God...
Ez pir kêf xweş bûm, ez Xelîlê Şehdîna qenetê hatim le hefi,
ser Youtube.
I was very happy, I am Khalil Shehdina [channel name] came
to visit, on Youtube.
Ehlen we sehlen...
Welcome...
Hêvîdarim xelkê me jî...
I hope our people too...
Te jî qenete... ger...
You too channel... wander...
Havo jî bi minesebet eyd el-hub nizîk bûye, te daîka me
ye... hezkirin jî heye.
This is also on the occasion of Valentine's Day being near,
you are our mother... there is love too.
Hezkirin... Hezkirina dinê me giber vê...
Love... love of the world is big...
Havo jî hedye te ye n, hadîk pir basîd û pir çîçik e...
This is also your gift, very simple and very small...
Saet xweş...
Thanks...
Tib xatira me rabî...
For our sake...
Wela nizanim dînkim, dest korê...
Well I don't know [how to use/wear], hand of son...
Dîna me da, urmonîkî bî.
In our custom, it was a harmonica [small thing].
Îşta em pehle cî bûn, em şixle cî bûn, em îşta z... zêtûn cî
bûn.
Well we were laborers, we were workers, we were well o...
olive [pickers].
Me îşta bidevêr bar dikir, pîxo do pî mêra, me kisî çatkî
ser dêvir.
We loaded [animals], feet with men's feet, we pulled sacks
on [animals].
Î noka maşallah mokîne...
Today mashallah machines...
Hemû lingê xwe jî ji qêyîpê derbas nakin...
All don't even pass their legs from the mud...
Eyn me sîn herekî kerîkî me bî, qilqîlq do fêl dikir...
Like we had a donkey, did tricks...
Ekê pirsekî şta pirskim.
I will ask you a question.
Te û xalê Cemîl we... hevdû dît, we heskir we bir, lê... û
indan hevdû.
You and uncle Jemil... did you see each other, loved and
took, or... gave to each other [arranged].
Bi xwedê dîna orf û edetê me, şerm bî.
By God, in our religion custom and tradition, it was shame.
Şerm bî.
It was shame.
Me hevdû nedît.
We didn't see each other.
Bixwedê kî dinê yorim nebî ya, dî min negîndî dî.
By God if [someone] didn't interpret/help, I wouldn't have
seen him.
Hesker bî.
It was loved [destiny].
Cemîl esker bî.
Jemil was a soldier.
Xalê me û pîrê me bûn dotmam û pismam.
Our uncle and our grandmother were cousins.
Bûkê me sehkir, birakê Cemîl me zingo lê...
Our bride heard, Jemil's brother 'zingo' on...
Em ştara çûne, liyo peya... deq qîçke, û pî heften pismamê
hef ne.
We went to shelter, on foot... [unintelligible], and cousins
of each other.
Û da bofkê me jî hem dan kêm ne wî hisê xwe bikira.
And gave our father also [unintelligible].
Erê no no.
Yes no no.
Me wîrî erzanî bî.
We found cheapness.
Dêk bofkê noka jî kikum nav dozî sîr ne.
Look father now also [unintelligible].
Hemû di gûna me da arzanî bî.
All in our village was cheapness.
Me ne wîrî...
We didn't see...
Em sê salan dergîstî bûn, me rohekî ser çavê hevdû nedî.
We were engaged for three years, we didn't see one eye on
each other's face.
Heta em hatin ba hev.
Until we came together.
Xalê Cemîl?
Uncle Jemil?
Belê.
Yes.
Berê erzanî bî?
Was the past cheap?
Erzanî bî.
It was cheap.
Donimê erdê bi çiqas bî?
How much was a dunam of land?
Donimê erdê... bi pênc werqa.
A dunam of land... for five notes.
Bi çar werqa.
For four notes.
Bi sê werqa.
For three notes.
Deh werqa.
Ten notes.
Heta bîst û pênc werqa.
Up to twenty-five notes.
Wiha erzan bî?
That cheap?
Wiha erzan bî.
That cheap.
Î ro?
Today?
Î ro donimê erdê bi milyona ye.
Today a dunam of land is for millions.
Milyonek, du milyon.
One million, two million.
Deh milyon.
Ten million.
Deh milyon, bîst milyon, sed milyon.
Ten million, twenty million, hundred million.
Li gor ciyê xwe.
According to its place.
Berê zehmet bî, erzanî bî, noka biha ye...
Before it was hard, it was cheap, now it is expensive...
Berê pere tunebûn, erzan bî.
Before there was no money, it was cheap.
Noka pere hene, biha ye.
Now there is money, it is expensive.
Noka pere hene?
Is there money now?
Noka pere hene.
Now there is money.
Pere kanî?
Where is the money?
Kî şixul bike pere hene.
Who works, has money.
Em şixul nakin.
We don't work.
Miletê me têr naxwe xalê Cemîl.
Our people don't eat their fill, uncle Jemil.
Wele naxwin.
By God they don't eat.
Teneka rûn bûye çiqas?
How much has a tin of oil become?
Teneka rûn bûye sed milyon... sed hezar.
A tin of oil has become 100 million... 100 thousand.
Kîloya şekir bûye çiqas?
How much has a kilo of sugar become?
Kîloya şekir bûye... çar hezar... pênc hezar...
A kilo of sugar has become... four thousand... five
thousand...
Noka bûye heft hezar.
Now it's seven thousand.
Nanê şil?
Fresh bread?
Nanê şil bûye du hezar.
Fresh bread has become two thousand.
Lîtreya mazotê?
Liter of diesel?
Mazotê... bûye hezar, hezar û pênc sed.
Diesel... has become a thousand, a thousand and five
hundred.
Ê karker rojekî çiqasî dixebite?
And a worker, how much does he work for a day?
Karker rojekî bi deh hezara, donzdeh hezara dixebite.
A worker works for ten thousand, twelve thousand a day.
Têra wî nake.
It's not enough for him.
Têra wî nake, îdare nake.
Not enough, doesn't manage.
Gaza wî, şekirê wî, çayê wî, rûnê wî...
His gas, sugar, tea, oil...
Goştê wî.
His meat.
Goştê wî... goşt em nastînin.
His meat... we don't buy meat.
Hûn nastînin?
You don't buy?
Em nastînin.
We don't buy.
We goşt berdaye?
Have you given up meat?
Me goşt berdaye.
We gave up meat.
Saeta te xweş xalê Cemîl. Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide.
Thanks Uncle Jemil. May God grant you a long life.
Ez pir kêfxweş bûm.
I was very happy.
Û bişkî derbasbûm cem xaltîkê bîn.
And I passed by the auntie a little.
Ehlen.
Welcome.
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God spare you.
Kekê liva rûne.
Brother sit here.
Kekê me hboy?
Our brother [unintelligible]?
Min nasî? Navê te çî ye?
Did you know me? What is your name?
Xelîl.
Khalil.
Kekê Xelîl.
Brother Khalil.
Kekê Mistefa.
Brother Mustafa.
Merheba.
Hello.
Kekê Xelîl, çend salî ye?
Brother Khalil, how old are you?
Wele gerek 35...
Well about 35...
Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide.
May God grant a long life.
Saxbî.
Be healthy.
Tu xelkê kîderê yî?
Where are you from?
Gundê Dimilya.
Dimilya village.
Erê.
Yes.
Nêzîkî Meydankê?
Near Meydanke?
Nêzîkî Meydankê.
Near Meydanke.
Ser seran.
Welcome.
Tu ser seran hatî.
You are welcome.
Eşîra we heye?
Do you have a tribe?
Eşîra me... Reşî.
Our tribe... Reshi.
Eşîra Reşwan.
Reshwan tribe.
Ez 15 salî me.
I am 15 years old.
Hemû kasetên min mecalê Efrîn, hemû yên daran, dawetên
Efrîn, stranên Efrîn.
All my tapes are in the Afrin style, all regarding the
trees, Afrin weddings, Afrin songs.
Efrînkî ne, beht, teb’an, em dibêjin dawetan.
They are purely Afrinian, naturally, as we call them
weddings.
Ê vê karê, yanî, bi xwe bidayeten, yanî wek dibên, gelek
pîşê me rû dane, me rû nekiribû di mecalê kevn da.
Regarding this work, frankly, in the beginning, as they say,
many professions faced us, but we hadn't faced the old field
yet.
Got, dwan duwan, Allah rehme, Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, xulqetî
min nî heq bû.
He said, one by one, God have mercy, may God have mercy on
him, it was not my nature/right [to be sad forever].
Feqet, min çûçik dît, em vêrra dimeşîn. Em vêrra diçin
dawetan, em dikelikin, diketin.
However, I saw a little bit [of hope], and we walked along
with it. We went to weddings with it, we laughed, we joined
in.
Tiştek mirin riya me ye, tu bêje kîjan rê ye, em ê ser
mesrehê herin û werin, em ê bikin, ser mesrehê bikin û
werin.
Death is on our path anyway, whatever path you say, we will
go on stage and come back, we will do it, perform on stage
and come back.
Li kafre wekî bêjin, mesela sora nucûm bê, sora diyar bê, em
tim bi kelakê diketin.
In the unbelief [hard times], let's say, whether it
represents the stars or the land, we always engaged with
laughter.
Feqet ew tişto jî wekî çûçik hindik meraq dikir.
But regarding that thing, I also had a little bit of
interest/passion.
Min tim lê dinerî, meraq, meraq, meraq, meraq... min
nizanîbû ez ê vê karî bikim.
I always looked at it, interest, interest, interest... I
didn't know I would do this work.
Roj bi rojê, roj bi rojê, bidaye, muqedem hefletan li
Dimiiliya derketim.
Day by day, day by day, initially, I came out as a party
presenter in Dimiliya.
Ziad Can, o, ezbenî, orgê, Allah iske bi xêr...
Ziad Jan, oh, sir, the organ [player], may God remember him
with goodness...
Li bra dawetê rast hat...
He coincided with the wedding...
Gundî pişt dan min.
The villagers supported me.
Bi min ra got, ez ê te da’im kim, Apê Behdar ra bişixulin.
Yanî neşrêkê, Ziad Can û neşrêkê Apê Behdar bû, ez vê karî
niha dikim.
He said to me, I will support you, work with Uncle Behdar.
So, it was a partnership, Ziad Jan and a partnership with
Uncle Behdar, I am doing this work now.
Bû teqrîben du sal û nîv e hema ez vê karî dikim.
It has been approximately two and a half years now that I am
doing this work.
Du sal û nîv e, heye kekê cîger, klaman didê, mamos... zer
de dikeve dawetan, milet dawetan jî pir dibînin, dawetên
Efrîn, li vî derê dikeve.
Two and a half years, yes dear brother, you sing songs,
teache... gold is poured into weddings, the people see many
weddings too, Afrin weddings, it happens here.
Li vî derê yekê sorkî ji te pirskim, kekê cîger. Wextê ku
însan, mesele, tu wextê te pê hesî dikî bi klaman dê?
Here I will ask you a question, dear brother. When a person,
for example, when do you feel it with the songs?
Meraq ber dilê te da hebû? Lê meraq paşê çêbû? Lê ba’dî te
da klaman, te pê hesî, hesî te xweş û daxwaz kir?
Was the passion already in your heart? Or did the passion
develop later? Or after you sang, did you feel it, feel good
and desire it?
Na, siftah meraq min ra nebû. Yanî dawet û meraq min nebû.
Meraq min nekir mirabî. Wekî min dar gotî.
No, at first, I didn't have the passion. Meaning, weddings
and passion, I didn't have it. I didn't have passion for
being a singer. As I told you.
Yanî tim li xulqeta xwe dinêrîm, min digot, ekî kî ça kî bî,
ez ê ser mesrehê bikim.
Meaning, I always looked at my nature/situation, and I said,
whoever it may be, however it may be, I will perform on
stage.
Pa çûyî me dawra orgê ber bayê vî dayê me, çiqa ‘alemî me
sehkir, meraqa min ser klaman jî orgê bêhtir e.
Then I went around the organ, faced with this mother
[situation], as much as people listened to me, my passion
for songs became greater than for the organ.
Fe mecal xeyirandin, û Ziad Can jî rast hat.
So the field changed, and Ziad Jan appeared/coincided.
Da’im da min û ano, yavaş yavaş, dawet dawet, û meriyê merra
rû nekin, xelk merra rû nekin, barê gundî, gundîta.
He supported me and like that, slowly slowly, wedding by
wedding, and [hoping] people don't frown at us, the public
doesn't frown at us, for the sake of the village, the
villager-hood.
Gundîta merra rû nekin, xelkê dî ke tarû ke.
[If] the villagers don't frown at us, other people will
accept/look at us.
Gundî me, Allah ji we razî be, Xwedê saeta xweş bi giya de,
dawet dawet, teqrîben ehû silme.
Our village, may God be pleased with you all, may God give
everyone a happy hour, wedding by wedding, approximately [we
reached] peace/success.
Î gundî me barê gundî kî.
This village of ours is a village burden/responsibility.
Saeta te xweş, em pir kêfxweş bûn bi bra Xelîl, te jî û
qenata te jî ya Reb.
Bless your time/voice, we were very happy with Brother
Khalil, you too and your channel too, oh Lord.
Saet xweş, qenata Hatim li Efrîn, hûrva nîvanê dimîla me, bi
dilkî xweş derbas gundî dimîla bim, û me xwest feqerê
klaman, tiyê me reşstran ke bêje teb’an.
Bless you, Hatim's channel in Afrin, looking at our Dimila
[village], may I pass through the Dimila village with a
happy heart, and we wanted a segment of songs, our things,
let him sing black/folk songs naturally.
Ser serî min, te jî û qenata te jî, înşallah alf mebrûk ji
qenata te ra o.
Upon my head [my pleasure], you and your channel too, God
willing, a thousand congratulations for your channel.
Ser serî min dilê min.
Upon my head, my heart.
Allah yibarîk fî umrek. Em cêm kekê Mistefa. Kekê Mistefa tu
ji kîjan gundî yî?
God bless your life. We are with Brother Mustafa. Brother
Mustafa, which village are you from?
Ji Kerkê Şêran im.
I am from Kerkeşêr [Qerqîna Şêran].
Ji Kerkê Şêran î?
You are from Kerkeşêr?
Te tembûrê te ni belşî ye, lê çend sal ne te ew dikî?
Yes.
Did you start your tembûr [saz] now, or how many years have
you been doing it?
No, tembûr bi xwe pênc sal hene.
No, the tembûr itself, it has been five years.
Pênc sal hene?
It has been five years?
Erê.
Yes.
Û tu yavaş yavaş dawam dikî?
And you are continuing slowly slowly?
Erê yavaş em dawam dikin, em dixwazin heryê ne, pîşê kêm e.
Em li mesreha û der û derê bigrin.
Yes, slowly we continue, we want [to reach] everywhere, the
profession is small. We want to take the stages and places
all over.
Erê.
Yes.
Yavaş yavaş, înşallah, wekî dibên, însan bes hedef kir dilê
xwe û bi dilkî xweş û tewekul kir, giya vêrê dimeşî.
Slowly slowly, God willing, as they say, if a person just
sets a goal in their heart and trusts with a happy heart,
everything walks [works out] with it.
Erê, înşallah.
Yes, God willing.
Noha, ez rica dikim ji te û kekê cîger, hinkê ji me ra stran
ke bêjin.
Now, I request from you and the dear brother, sing some
songs for us.
Û mila her kes me bibîne, guhdarî mîne.
And let everyone see us, remaining as listeners.
Ser serî min, tikram xwoş. Saeta we xweş be.
Upon my head, you're welcome. May your hours be happy.
[Music starts playing]
Ez heşîna gundî me.
I am the greenery of the village.
Ez sêwiyê ketî me.
I am the fallen orphan.
Navê xwe li ser rakin.
Remove your name from it.
Xwedanê xetî me.
I am the owner of the script [destiny].
Ez heşîna gundî me.
I am the greenery of the village.
Ez sêwiyê ketî me.
I am the fallen orphan.
Navê xwe li ser rakin.
Remove your name from it.
Xwedanê xetî me.
I am the owner of the script [destiny].
Ha wî canê, ez girtî me, ez dilbirîn darim.
Oh my soul, I am a prisoner, I am wounded in the heart.
Ez dilbirîn darim.
I am wounded in the heart.
Ez heşîna gundî me.
I am the greenery of the village.
Ez sêwiyê ketî me.
I am the fallen orphan.
Ez heşîna gundî me.
I am the greenery of the village.
Ez sêwiyê ketî me.
I am the fallen orphan.
Ha wî canê, ez girtî me, ez dilbirîn darim.
Oh my soul, I am a prisoner, I am wounded in the heart.
Ez bawiskekî şev û roj dixwînim.
I am a breeze singing night and day.
Aşiqê helbestan, le ye Cigerxwîn im.
A lover of poems, indeed I am Cigerxwîn.
Ez bawiskekî şev û roj dixwînim.
I am a breeze singing night and day.
Aşiqê helbestan, le ye Cigerxwîn im.
A lover of poems, indeed I am Cigerxwîn.
Ha wî canê, ez girtî me, ez dilbirîn darim.
Oh my soul, I am a prisoner, I am wounded in the heart.
Kekê Boro delal, helqê gundê Dimîla, li ser qenata Hatim li
Efrîn, helqê sisyê.
Dear Brother Boro, the episode of the Dimila village, on
Hatim's channel in Afrin, the third episode.
Kanim ji me re yazmîş kin, gundî çûreyin, daxwazên em derbas
kijan gundî bin. Teb’an gundî Dimîla mezin e.
Can you write to us, what kind of villages, requests for
which village we should visit. Naturally, the Dimila village
is large.
Heta gukî nî me derxist, me ciwaran derxist, me çerxek ta
xweş ciwaran birin. Saeta we xweş.
Until we brought out a flower, we brought out the
neighborhoods, we took a nice tour of the neighborhoods.
Bless your hours.
Û tî qisûr me hene, hûnî efû kin, û ji me re yazmîş kin,
gundî çûreyin, daxwazên em derbas kijan gundî bin.
And if we have any shortcomings, please forgive us, and
write to us, what kind of villages, requests for which
village we should visit.
Dê dê dê gulê, lê lê lê gulê.
Come come come Rose, oh oh oh Rose.
Sirme mîna zîv û tîn e.
The mascara is like silver and luster.
Va dilê min forî goşt e.
This heart of mine has become [tender like] boiled meat.
Ne polat e û ne kevir e.
It is not steel and it is not stone.
Va dilê min forî goşt e.
This heart of mine has become [tender like] boiled meat.
Ne polat e û ne kevir e, way.
It is not steel and it is not stone, oh my.
Va dilê min forî goşt e.
This heart of mine has become [tender like] boiled meat.
Ne polat e û ne kevir e.
It is not steel and it is not stone.
Va dilê min forî goşt e.
This heart of mine has become [tender like] boiled meat.
Ne polat e û ne kevir e, way.
It is not steel and it is not stone, oh my.
Seba me bê, min nizanî, ne min zanî, ne te zanî.
Because of us, I didn't know, neither I knew, nor you knew.
Seba me bê, min nizanî, ne te kanî, ne min kanî.
Because of us, I didn't know, neither you could, nor I
could.
Va dilê min forî goşt e, ne polat e û ne kevir e.
This heart of mine has become [tender like] boiled meat, it
is not steel and it is not stone.
Va dilê min forî goşt e, ne polat e û ne kevir e, way.
This heart of mine has become [tender like] boiled meat, it
is not steel and it is not stone, oh my.
Hey! Lê lê zalim, lê lê xayîn
Hey! Oh cruel one, oh traitor
Te ez kuştim, te ez helandim
You killed me, you melted me away