Merheba miletê kîbar û delal, heva xeleka didyayê li qenata
Hatim li Efrîn.
Hello noble and dear nation, this is the second episode on
the channel Hatim in Afrin.
Ka bi me ra bin, bi dilkî xweş, em derbasî gundê Be'dîna
bin.
So stay with us, with a happy heart, let's enter the village
of Ba'dina.
Ka niha bi me ra bin, li xeleqê, li gundê Be'dîna, li ser
qenata Hatim li Efrîn.
So stay with us now, in the episode, in the village of
Ba'dina, on the channel Hatim in Afrin.
Ka em herin cem xalê Hecî Ehmed, elekê me ra çi gotinên wî
hene.
Let's go to Uncle Hecî Ehmed, let's see what words he has
for us.
Selamun Aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleykum Selam, ehlen wa sehlen.
Peace be upon you too, welcome.
Tu çawa yî?
How are you?
Ez baş im.
I am good.
Xalê Hecî Ehmed, tu yê ji me ra çîkê meseleya kevin ewil de.
Uncle Hecî Ehmed, you will tell us a bit about the old
issues first.
Berê heyat çawa derbas dibû? We çawa dikir?
How did life pass before? What did you do?
Heyat... berê giwa... şûl çêdikirin...
Life... before... they did work...
Heta wextê şêst û çar...
Until the year sixty-four...
Eeee paşê... cot xelas bû, daxê resas bû...
Eeee then... plowing ended, the branding became lead
[difficult]...
Eeee paşê... luks xelas bûn... daxê resas çêbûn... em çûn
nobê resas...
Eeee then... Lux lamps finished... lead branding happened...
we went to lead guard duty...
Me ew luks çêdikirin.
We used to fix those Lux lamps.
Luks, me pêdixist. Luks min daşitê...
Lux lamps, we lit them. I hung the Lux...
Ew fitîl dertin evî... Luks me dadixistê...
Those wicks came out of it... We hung the Lux...
Paşê mişext... mişext çêbûn.
Then exile... exile happened.
Baran lê dikir, wê zemanî pir bû.
It rained, in that time it was plenty.
Nînika tiştek nayê. Baran tune, dar tune.
Nowadays nothing comes. No rain, no trees.
Însan helak bûn. Me'nê çi ye? Me'nê vê baranê, rehma Xwedê
têne ser me.
People are exhausted. What is the reason? The reason is this
rain, God's mercy doesn't come upon us.
Xelqê berê... paşê... wê zemanî...
The people of the past... then... in that time...
Me dexl û dan... dexlekî... pir hebû.
We had crops and grain... crops... there was plenty.
Nan kêm bû.
Bread was scarce.
Em diçûn nav şêx Hese Seydî. Me ard dianî.
We went to Sheikh Hese Seydi. We brought flour.
Bi meşê em diçûn.
We went by walking.
Bi meşê diçûn, û doza Hese Seydî... me ard dianî... bi şev
em diçûn, bi şev dihatin.
We went by walking, and the case of Hese Seydi... we brought
flour... we went at night, we came back at night.
Helak bûn wê zemanî de.
They were exhausted in that time.
Eeee de elhemdu lîlah noka rind e.
Eeee so praise be to God, now it is good.
Noka rind e, kerebe heye, av heye.
Now it is good, there is electricity, there is water.
Seyare tunebûn?
Were there no cars?
Booo! Kerebe? Tunebûn!
Booo! Cars? There were none!
Me go babo bi kera dikişand.
I said, man, we hauled with donkeys.
Bi kera çêdibû. Kerebe... kerebe çû?
It was done with donkeys. Cars... what cars?
Me bi kereba tiştek nedianî, hekî bi cindordan, bi malatan.
We didn't bring anything by cars, unless by tractors, by
goods transports.
Eeee... rê rind, rê... te bextê rê rind e.
Eeee... the road is good, road... you rely on the road, it's
good.
Apê Hecî Ehmed, emrê te çend e?
Uncle Hecî Ehmed, how old are you?
Emrê min? Heştê û pênc sal.
My age? Eighty-five years.
Nîvê salê bi serda çûne.
Half a year has passed on top of it.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Elhemdu lîlah noka rind e îşta jî.
Praise be to God, now it is good, even now.
Ya'nî bereket heye.
I mean there is abundance.
Nan heye, der heye.
There is bread, there is a place.
Însan vê meselê de helak bûn. Rehet bûn.
People were exhausted in that matter. They became
comfortable.
Fer bûn. Ya'nî fer helak bûn. Ne helak bûn hindik.
They became many. I mean they were very exhausted. Not
exhausted a little.
Ee ya la elhemdu lîlah, dîsa ela kul hal...
Ee oh praise be to God, again in any case...
Em dimeşin, rind e.
We are walking/living, it is good.
Zarokên me jî rind derketin.
Our children also turned out good.
Zarokên me çûne Alamanya derketin.
Our children went to Germany, they left.
Yek li vir e, yek li wir e, didu jî li vî derê ne.
One is here, one is there, and two are in this place.
Eeee de rind e. Cîranê me jî rind in, ehwal jî rind in.
Eeee so it is good. Our neighbors are also good, the
conditions are also good.
Em ji miriya hew ne... bi derê... wexta tu...
We are not anymore from the dead... outside... when you...
Xêr nav lê kirin "Qûre Hefarê"?
Why did they name it "Qure Hefare" (Excavator's Hole)?
Qûra weşê, çê nav lê kirin Qûre Hefarê?
That beautiful hole, why did they name it Qure Hefare?
Hefarê... kolan... av derket.
The excavator... dug... water came out.
Me li wê derê çûna hefare kirî...
We went there and rented an excavator...
Erd... sed û bîst metre me kirî... noka me kir hefarê.
Ground... we dug one hundred and twenty meters... now we
made it an excavator [well].
Însan bîra bînin ji cî tana bûn.
People used to bring [water] from wells, from places far
away.
Bes hew hefar hebû... qûl... bîrek hebû.
Only there was just the excavator... hole... there was a
well.
Bes bîrek hebû.
There was only one well.
Eeee kur noka tune bûn.
Eeee deep [wells] were not there now [back then].
Li wê derê jî çend mal hebûn.
In that place there were also a few houses.
Eeee gotin... wextek hate... îşta... Qûre Hefarê ye ew.
Eeee they said... a time came... now... that is Qure Hefare.
Wê me'neyê nav lê kirin Qûre Hefarê.
For that reason they named it Qure Hefare.
Ee wa.
Ee yes.
Nav lê kirin Qûre Hefarê?
They named it Qure Hefare?
Nav lê danîn Qûre Hefarê. Hefar hate jêrê.
They gave it the name Qure Hefare. The excavator came down.
Wê menê nav lê kirin Qûre Hefarê.
For that reason they named it Qure Hefare.
Hewar hate jêrê.
The cry/excavator came down.
Xalê Hecî Ehmed, heyata berê pir cefa bû.
Uncle Hecî Ehmed, life before was very hard.
Î noka ne we ye?
Is this now not like that?
Na we ye, noka rind e.
No it is like that, now it is good.
Î noka jî cefa ye.
This now is also hardship [in a way].
Noka rind e.
Now it is good.
Berê av diçû ji kî derê dihat...
Before water went, from where did it come...
Av diçû ji kû da dihat, me nediçû tana ka, av tê kirinê, bi
hor bi ata.
Water went, from where it came, we didn't go until where,
water was put in, with sacks, with horses.
Mal... de kî me pê... kindir, tişt, şte perçe şkandin.
Home... so who of us... ropes, things, things broke into
pieces.
Eeee... berê peşê me camiyê jor, av gol bû.
Eeee... before behind our upper mosque, water was a
lake/pond.
Gol bû, me dawrî xwar, gola avê dida.
It was a pond, we went around, the water pond gave [water].
Wa av nema, me diçû kî derê av tîne dan.
That water ran out, we went to where to bring water.
Nav kî çi jî bîrik heye.
In the middle of whatever there is a small well.
Me diçû ji wê derê av hanî, bi hewî, xwedê rehma xwe lê ke,
bi hewî hatin...
We went to bring water from there, with aid, may God have
mercy on him, they came with aid...
Av hanîn...
They brought water...
De kî me dawi xwar e, ew der xwaş kitiq deran tînan.
So whoever of us went around, that place was good, bringing
[water] from places.
Av...
Water...
Xwedê te bihêle, Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike xalê Hecî Ehmed.
May God keep you, may God prolong your life Uncle Hecî
Ehmed.
Ez ji te pir memnûn im.
I am very grateful to you.
Ez jî memnûn im.
I am also grateful.
Xwedê qewetê bide te, sehata xweş bide te.
May God give you strength, give you good health.
Tu emrê te li me hene, tu kê ne bibê.
Do you have any command for us, whatever you say.
Ne şaş im, rê şaş...
I am not mistaken, wrong way...
Xêr hatin, ser çava hatin.
Welcome, you came upon [our] eyes.
Saeta we xweş, niha jî bi me ra bin, em derbasî gundê
Be'dîno bin, li pîreke jor.
Good times to you, now also be with us, let's enter the
village of Ba'dina, to an old woman up there.
Ka niha li xeleqê, gundê Be'dîna, ka bi me ra bin, em
derbasî cem xaltîka Fir bin.
So now in the episode, village of Ba'dina, so be with us,
let's go to Aunt Fir.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen wa sehlen yaro.
Welcome dear.
Çi text e? Çawa yî?
What's up? How are you?
Elhemdu lîlah, yekî çûbe yaro, em ê rûniştin e, em ê şukir
o.
Praise be to God, one has gone dear, we are sitting, we are
thankful.
Têkêy, çîçkê, miro, ser meseleya... çend salî xaltîka Fir?
You will [tell], a little, human, on the issue of... how old
are you Aunt Fir?
Heştê û çar im.
I am eighty-four.
Xwedê emrê te dirêj bike.
May God prolong your life.
Xwedê sehetê xweş bide te.
May God give you good health.
Bû we jî yade, Xwedê rû xweş bû we giya de yaro.
To you too mother [dear], may God give a happy face to all
of you dear.
Saeta we giya xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be, Xwedê hewalê we be.
Good times to all of you, may God be pleased with you, may
God be your companion.
Saet xweş.
Good times.
Xaltîka Fir, heyata berê pir bi cefa bû ne?
Aunt Fir, life before was very hard, right?
Lêêê yaro...
Ooooh dear...
Haşa me cefa didî...
God forbid, we suffered...
Me êmo dikişand...
We carried fodder/wood...
Me bar dikir...
We carried loads...
Me gî dida...
We gave grass...
Tehl bû.
It was bitter/hard.
Heyata berê, noka wek Xatûnekê ez rûniştî me.
Life before, now like a Lady I am sitting.
Berê...
Before...
Wek dêkê mişî miro weledê... dê wek edebê sim... fir çetin
bû.
Like a mother ewe, man, the child... mother like polite...
it was very hard.
Fir çetin bû gilen.
It was very hard indeed.
Pezê Bota...
The Botan sheep...
Pêzê me hebû, malê me sê sed gulê bî.
We had sheep, our household was three hundred heads.
Deryê gulê, malê melî bî. Pezê Bota, done.
At the door of the flock, the house was full. Botan sheep,
gave [milk].
Ê min ê pez bidoşta.
And I would milk the sheep.
Min ê şîr germ bikira.
I would heat the milk.
Min ê nan dikir.
I would make bread.
Jinin bar dikira.
Women would carry loads.
Mignê kar bikira.
We would do work.
Û pezê biçûk... tekra şînî pêskeve... hew çûçik bî...
And the small sheep... again let the fire light up... it was
just small...
Tekra şînî pêsposkro.
Again lit up the fire/work.
Û sergo raş ê, wekî malê Hecî Bekir walê bî.
And the ash pile is black, like the house of Hecî Bekir it
was like that.
Û çar teşt...
And four basins...
Wê wextê ekindî ye... me sibê çêkirî.
That time is afternoon... we made it in the morning.
Ekindiye... ekindî wane... me kê wexta... zar çar teşt
çêkran.
It's afternoon... their afternoon... we when... just made
four basins [of food/work].
Û kinc jî wa bides... tişta...
And clothes also by hand... things...
Lê kinc boralî şûştin bî.
Oh, clothes were washed over there.
Ne wek hano noka.
Not like here now.
Na hano noka.
Not here now.
Hem nûn dikir, cîranik ve hebûye, Bota, qurbanî, vê destê
nîçûyê wîr bistre.
I also made [bread], there was a neighbor, Botan, sacrifice,
this hand [of hers] went there to knead.
Oho qewet hebû.
Oho there was strength.
Wa nan dikir, wa kinc destê dihiştin.
Like that she made bread, like that they left clothes
[washed] by hand.
Û tekra, "Ey Bota", minî ez jî dikim, mir tixiloz kirî bexs
min.
And again, "Oh Botan", I also do it, to me [she said] you
scrubbed/twisted [the clothes] for me.
Nîsa wota, maşallah...
Women like that, mashallah...
O yaro, ta çû anoka...
Oh dear, until now...
Û pên e...
And they are...
Da zici çûn koro, me pên e elmalî...
Since they went to work, we are like apples
[useless/sitting?]...
Û xelkê berê hind diçûn av jî ji deştê dianîn ne?
And people before went and brought water from the plain too,
right?
Av... ew wextê em ne gihîştinê.
Water... that time we didn't reach it.
Wextê avê... berê pênak av bî, dêka min zê, keta min diçû
bîrê av tîna.
The time of water... before there was a little water, my
mother, I know, my daughter went to the well to bring water.
Diçûn bîrê tînan.
They went to the well and brought it.
Bi pişta xwe dikir tînan don.
She put it on her back and brought it down.
Wê wextê gisek teneke, çar teneke av, eke wê wextê bonyona.
That time a sack/tin, four tins of water, only that time for
their bath.
Heyata berê pir çetin bî.
Life before was very hard.
Wele dîsa yaro, noka qelwbûn îtir bî.
By God again dear, now fakeness/heart-issues are more.
Nexweşî îtir bûn.
Sicknesses increased.
Em têr nan naxwin.
We don't eat bread to satisfaction [no appetite].
Me wextê kar dikir, wextê me kêf jî dikişand.
When we worked, that time we also had fun.
Me wexta kar dikir, wexta jî em bi kêf şîşta dikir.
When we worked, that time we also did things with joy.
Lê...
But...
Xaltîka Fir, berê...
Aunt Fir, before...
Sehne, zevyê berê gî onabî?
Look, were the fields before full of grass?
Fere, berê gî onabî.
Plenty, before there was grass.
E me dîsa, noka pirşê me gî boqirî.
Eh we again, now our manger has the grass mowed/eaten.
Fere me gî boqirî, tiştî me heya.
Plenty we have grass mowed, we have things.
Fere em tînin.
We bring plenty.
Hêda, onoka misol ev noka qelo kir.
Slowly, now for example this one finished it now.
Bi hezar... sê sed wara meqelo kir.
With a thousand... three hundred times we finished it.
Buroş çor.
Four pots.
E mesele... ebe... seet... kefçe... laê la gene... wey hano.
Eh the issue... father... hour... ladle... no no look...
like here.
Xêrê şinî berê hew şinî no, nîvon kî tabata, ta kişîf têkro,
di no pîşinyê.
The good of the past, just that past, half of the nature,
until it was discovered, give it to the past.
Le, hew na tina bû no, molo eybîr.
No, that wasn't brought anymore, it was a shame for the
family.
Eybîr.
It was a shame.
Însanê berê rind bî?
Were people of the past good?
Xoş bî, berê. Xoş bî. Na, xoş bî.
It was good, before. It was good. No, it was good.
Em bi kêf bîn, em rehet bîn.
We were happy, we were comfortable.
Em ne te bîn, em ne nexweş bîn.
We weren't feverish, we weren't sick.
Sehbê min... xoş bî.
My husband [owner]... was good.
Mero di cûlqê xo da heyat xoş e.
A person in their own clothes/skin, life is good.
Nê konê.
Not tents/nomads.
Caniqê jî... Xwedê emrê kî dirêj bide.
The young girl too... may God give long life.
Wa dê jî sehet û we xoş, Xwedê ji we razî be, Xwedê hewalê
we be, û Xwedê rû xweş bû we mîniye yaro.
To that one too health and good times, may God be pleased
with you, may God be your companion, and may God give a
happy face to you all dear.
Rû xweş bû we mîniye.
A happy face to you remains.
Li wan mîniye, em ne te hewê.
To those remaining, we don't have breath/patience.
Îşallah.
God willing.
Te çîrokê berê hifz kirine, ti kê yekê ji me ra wîl de lê
ne?
You have memorized the stories of the past, won't you tell
one for us?
Wele nikanim. Wala nikanim.
By God I can't. By God I can't.
Xwedê sehet û we xoş bide, xwedê tenekê.
May God give you good health, God give you [blessings].
Ez bextê we me, me nexin eybê noka yaro.
I am at your mercy, don't put us in shame now dear.
Eywa, na baş e.
Okay, no it is good.
Xwedê sehet û we xoş bide, xwedê tenekê bide destu.
May God give you good health, may God give a tin/gold in
your hands.
Amîn, amîn, xwedê me pîs neke, xwedê me neke darba xelkê.
Amen, amen, may God not make us dirty, may God not make us
the struck/mockery of people.
Wa kî.
Like that.
Te emr ten, te gotin ten.
Your command, your words.
Seet xoş, gule gule, û îşallah milletê me jî gi be fitilê
warê malê xo.
Good times, bye bye, and God willing our nation will all
return to the place of their homes.
Îşallah, hana gi bi heftir xêrê bên.
God willing, may they all come with sevenfold goodness.
Wa rin, ga rin, gi wa rin, ha.
That way, this way, all that way, ha.
Warin, em muhtacê wa nin, wa rin.
Come, we are in need of them, come.
Em wargey gûrtirîn, wa din ir rin.
We are the place of wolves, they are giving [pain].
Xwedê emrê kî dirêj bide te, dika qisûra me hene te efû ke.
May God give you a long life, mother if we have faults
forgive us.
Û vê vîdyo em ê daxin ser qenatê Yotubê, hûn ê lê sêr kin û
gel lê sêr kin.
And this video we will upload to the Youtube channel, you
will watch it and people will watch it.
Saeta te xoş.
Good times to you.
Îşallah, ta jî xoş û xwedê ji we razî be.
God willing, to you also good [times] and may God be pleased
with you.
Eywa, bila bila, saeta we xoş.
Okay, sure sure, good times to you.
Xelkê gundê Baadrê ne, îro emê mêvanê mala Xalê Mistefa bin.
Mêvanê çîçikê ser meselê berê me ra hewal de, û hela berê
çawa sincix dikirin û heyata berê çiqas xweş bû.
They are people of Baadre village, today we will be guests
at Uncle Mustafa's house. We will be guests for a little bit
[to talk] about the stories of the past, how they used to
gather sincix (oleaster/hackberry) and how beautiful life
was in the past.
Merheba Xaltîka Fatma.
Hello Aunt Fatma.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Merheba Xalê Mistefa.
Hello Uncle Mustafa.
Êê, ser çava.
Yes, upon my eyes (You are welcome).
Aqil birrîne?
Is the mind still sharp?
Belê, belgî, belgî, belgî...
Yes, yes, yes, yes...
Na, na, na, jî marinde (ma rinde), rûne. Îşellah tu çawa yî
Xalê Mistefa?
No, no, no, stay comfortable, sit down. God willing, how are
you Uncle Mustafa?
Elhemdillah, şikir ji Xwedê ra, elhemdillah.
Praise be to God, thanks to God, praise be to God.
Tu çend salî yî Xalê Mistefa?
How old are you, Uncle Mustafa?
Ez? Ji heştê û hefte... heşt...
Me? From eighty-seven... eight...
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te apê.
May God give you a long life, uncle.
Te jî, te jî elhemdillah.
You too, you too, praise be to God.
Hinekî çîçikê me ra berê, we sincix çawa dikir, tîkê me ra
bêje?
Tell us a little bit about the past, how did you gather
sincix, tell us a little bit?
Wele wekê berê, sincix... yanî wextê ewqas nebî, feqîrî jî
hebî, qerza (qehra) jî dikir.
Well, like in the past, sincix... I mean, back then there
wasn't much, there was poverty, and we suffered hardship.
Û yanî em diçûn nehiyê, ew dibîn, mijûl dibûn.
And, I mean, we would go to the sub-district, that would
happen, we were busy.
Mesela meha hefta da, me ê biçû qirşik-mirşikê xwe kom kira
anîba, darê xwe anîba. Yanî meras dikirin.
For example, in the seventh month, we would go and gather
our brushwood and kindling and bring it, bring our wood. I
mean, we were preparing [for winter].
Qirşik-mirşik me ê kom kira anîba, darê xwe kira anîba.
We would gather brushwood and kindling and bring it, gather
our wood and bring it.
Û meha heştê jî... me ê hemî... belamî (belkî) sincix
baniya.
And in the eighth month... we would all... maybe bring
sincix.
Me ê biçû heta nîşê xwe (bişê xwe), mesela gûzê xwe, tiştê
xwe me ê baniya vata (wê derê).
We would go as far as our forest/grove, for example, bring
our walnuts, our things there.
Me teştekê xwe tijî kir, me ê aniha orta belamî (belkî)
sincix baniya.
We would fill our basin, we would bring it to the middle,
maybe bring sincix.
Orta belamî.
To the middle, maybe.
Haa... tiriyê xwe di cewlan...
Haa... our grapes in the baskets...
Û ma şerbetê xwe... yanî di kelan... me tekru (têk da)
sincix mîş dikir.
And our syrup... I mean boiling it... we mixed it, harvested
the sincix.
Me tekru ew dikir...
We mixed it and did that...
Me dikelan, me nîşê (bişê) xwe pêar (pê re) dikir.
We boiled it, we processed our harvest with it.
Û ma dorkê (dwarê) xwe girê didan... me dorkê sincix...
benîk benîk... gûz-mûz pêva dar (daleqandî) dikir.
And we tied our mounts (donkeys)... we tied the sincix...
string by string... we hung walnuts and things on it.
Pê dorkê xwe girê didan dar dikir, ma haa, yanî cihê xwe,
xeznê.
We tied it to our mounts and hung it up, haa, I mean, in its
place, the pantry.
Erê.
Yes.
Tekro (têk da) jî welle... ma sincixê xwe dikir. "De wa, de
wa."
We mixed it as well, by God... we made our sincix. "Come on,
come on."
Yanî pênc roj, şeş roj me sincixê xwe dibir heleb
(Heleb/Bajar).
I mean for five days, six days, we took our sincix to Aleppo
(or the city/market).
Erê.
Yes.
Em diçûn heleb (bajar), me xonê (xanî), me difroşt.
We went to the city, we [went to] the building, and we sold
it.
Heger niha Sincix hazir bikir, wa bibir xonê difrot, hîn
(hûn) ê biçun?
If sincix was ready now, and if you took it to the building
to sell, would you go?
Bi mokîne.
[Even] crawling.
Bi mokîne?
Crawling?
Bi mokîne, xelîfatkê (xîlafetkê)... hebiya berê...
Crawling, I swear... if it was like the past...
Berê malê begê (begî) hebiya, berê hemû tişt çolax (çolag)
hebiya.
In the past, if there was the Bey's house, if everything was
open country in the past.
Em mokîne, em no (ne) hebiya?
Even crawling, wouldn't we exist?
Hîn pê diçûn û sincixê xwe difrot?
You went on foot and sold your sincix?
Me çû, pê dibir... û me niş-mişê (tişt-miştê) xwe jî...
tiştê xwe jî di dogendin (dagirtin).
We went, carried it on foot... and our stuff... we filled
our things up.
Û me li wê derê diman, me sincixê xwe dirfrot.
And we stayed there, we sold our sincix.
Wa dirfrot.
It sold.
Heyata berê pir cefo (cefa) bî.
Life in the past was full of hardship.
Pir cefo, pir bî.
Lots of hardship, lots of it.
Cefo û pir bî?
Hardship and lots of it?
Yanî cefo hebî.
I mean, there was hardship.
Ê de... cefo jî tunebî, nan tuneyî.
And well... if there was no hardship, there was no bread.
Yanî tişt tuneyî, bera (bela) ow (ew) hebî.
I mean there was nothing, but that existed [the struggle].
Dibên destê rast... şeş de destê rast...
They say the right hand... six in the right hand... [Idiom
or localized saying].
Erê.
Yes.
Dê Xaltîka Fatma, te, hela çîçikê me ra deng bike, dûre te,
te... hela wa heyata berê, wa çû kinc dişûştin, wa vî qicik
no gip (gup) mezin kirin?
Okay Aunt Fatma, you, tell us a little bit, your turn,
you... how was life in the past, how you washed clothes, how
you raised these kids so big?
Ee, ma dikir.
Oh, we did it.
Qicikê me hûrik bîn.
Our kids were tiny.
Mura (bira) çîçik yanî deng ke ser berê.
Please, speak a little about the past.
Haa, qicikê me hûrik bîn.
Haa, our kids were tiny.
Ê ma, em diçûn zeytûna.
And well, we went for olives.
Ma qicik li pişta xwe dikirin.
We carried the kids on our backs.
Me zeytûnê da dişandin, em hêwarê dihatin.
We shook down the olives, we came back in the evening.
Ma bera (bela) nanî xwe dikir...
We made our bread...
Hêwarê me nanê xwe dikir. Qicikê me jî pişta me.
In the evening we made our bread. And our kids were on our
backs.
Wextê sibe em diçûn zeytûna, me dadîşandin, hêwarê em
dihatin.
In the morning we went for olives, we shook them down, in
the evening we came back.
Û em diçûn şelekan...
And we went for Şelek (collecting wild greens or thin bread
work)...
Şelekan?
Şelek?
Ha... em diçûn reqa ko (kû)... xonîk (xanîk) kû ye...
Ha... we went to the rocky place where... where the hut
is...
Ê reqa xonîk kû ye, em diçûn xonîk hebî.
Where the rocky hut is, we went, there was a hut.
Yo ximî (xemê) celda, cel (cal) hebî.
Or the sorrow of the clothes/skins, there was a pit.
Yo ximî dada.
Or the sorrow of the mother/nanny.
Û bîrî (bêrî) piling hebî.
And there was the striped bêrî (milking apron/bag).
Hebî.
There was.
Em dihatin.
We used to come back.
Ê em ka, kî şelekan...
And us, who [gathered] Şelek...
Em ka toqê zêro...
And us, the golden necklace...
Wa li pişta xwe dikir tîna?
Did you carry him [husband/child] on your back or not?
Ê, em diçûn toqê zêro, qicikê kewir (kebir)... çakironê
(çêkirana)...
Eh, we went for the golden necklace, the big kids... making
them...
Ê, bigota, ewa toqê zêro ye, î mrozo (miraza) ye.
Eh, if one said, this is the golden necklace, this is the
wish.
Kewir (kebir) wa bêtinê?
Was the big one alone?
Kewir wa bêtinê.
The big one was alone.
Te jî hewêt (hiz kir), lê ne hewêt?
Did you love him, or did you not love him?
Min ne hewêtiyo.
I didn't love him.
Te ne hewêtiyo?
You didn't love him?
Ez biçûk bûm.
I was small (young).
Ê...
Yeah...
Me biçû şelekê xwe ba yno (anî)... bota mol (anîbûya mal).
We would go bring our şelek... brought it home.
Emê bota no mol...
We brought it home...
Ê bîrî (bêrî) piling jî hebî.
And the striped bêrî (milking bag) was there too.
Erê.
Yes.
Emê bota no... ma sûnciqê (sincixê) xwe bikira.
We brought it... we processed our sincix.
Emê biçûna daşta boliyo (Baliyan?).
We would go to the plain of Baliyan.
Ma sûnciq dikirin.
We made sincix.
Em diçûn... ma dikir, em dihatin, em diçûn mal bûn.
We went... we did it, we came back, we went home.
Em lo (li) mal... ez o (ya) zivistan bîm, ma şelekê xwe...
qişkê (qirşikê) xwe... cafo (cefa) bî.
We at home... I was of the winter [meaning worked in
winter], our şelek... our brushwood... it was hardship.
Xasale tunebî.
There was no washing machine.
Buxarê bî.
It was steam [boiling water].
Ma nan dikir.
We made bread.
Ma şîv dikir.
We made dinner.
Ma qajikê (kincê) e... çavî (kê) ma... xeta o ye...
(nediyar).
Our clothes... whose were they... the line is... (unclear).
Erê.
Yes.
Û... onê (ewên) derwa... vî xişlimo (xuşlema) bişîne?
And... those abroad... should I send this greeting?
Bişîne. Heryê (her yek) kî te ser dike, tikanî vê re silamo
bişîne, tikanî qiciko (qicika) giş silom key (kî).
Send it. Everyone who is watching you, you can send
greetings to them, you can greet all the kids.
Mihemed, Ebruyîm (Ebru)... li meydan kê... li...
Mohammed, Ebru... in the square... in...
Alemaniya (Almanya) silomê jer (jê re) bişînim.
[In] Germany, I send greetings to him.
Silomê ji wan ra hene.
Greetings to them.
Zekî ra hene.
To Zeki as well.
Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide te jîn (jin).
May God give you a long life, wife/woman.
Amîn, amîn.
Amen, amen.
Biristal (Pistal?) ma ra hene.
To Pistal (name) as well.
Û li... Alemaniya (Almanya)... Fîrîda (Ferîde) ra hene.
And in... Germany... to Feride as well.
Xatîniya (Xatûna) gind (gund) ra hene.
To the lady of the village as well.
Ol (Mal/Ailê) Tirkiyem.
My family in Turkey.
Mehmedîm ra hene.
To my Mehmed as well.
Ailê gind (gund) ra hene.
To the family in the village as well.
Qijikê (qicikê) giyê (gihayê/giş) ra hene.
To all the kids as well.
Malî...
The house of...
Gindî (gundê) Baadrê, giş gundê Baadrê ra hene, Îsmaîl.
The village of Baadre, to all of Baadre village, Ismail.
Baadrê... Baadrê giş giyê (giş) ra hene.
Baadre... to all of Baadre as well.
Gih (giş) xalkê (xelkê) bera (berê) kêmabûn (kêm man)... em
gin (giş) nava (li vira) daban...
All the people of the past remain few... we were all here...
Em nazim (nizanim) bînin...
I don't know [if] we bring...
Û ma (me) digot we neçit.
And we said don't go.
Ma digot mokîne...
We said crawling...
Bofkê (bavkê) min digot timbêl e, timbêl.
My father used to say [he/she] is lazy, lazy.
Min digot na, na, mokîneyî, babe.
I said no, no, crawling/slowly, father.
Na... ey warem (ew yara min?) timbêl.
No... [is] that love of mine lazy?
Belê (berê) wa digot, yane.
Yes, they used to say that, I mean.
Ê, ma şûnjê (sincixê) xa (xwe) bir... hişta (eşte)...
Eh, we took our sincix... look...
Ma boto (bota/anî) kurê xwe... kincê xwe deşto (deştê)
bişton (bişûştana).
We brought my son... washed our clothes in the plain.
Xasale tune bî.
There was no washing machine.
Papûra (pampora/babûra) tune bî.
There was no primus stove/steamer.
Or (agir) tune bî.
There was no fire [gas/modern heat].
A kurê xwe dikir.
She did her son [took care of him].
Wa dikir. Saeta te xweş Xaltîka Fatma.
You did. Health to you, Aunt Fatma.
Amîn yane Xwedê...
Amen, I mean God...
Û wek manika (mîna nika) galê (gelê) me yê Xalê Mistefa,
heyata berê pir cefo (cefa) bî.
And as our Uncle Mustafa mentioned now, life in the past was
full of hardship.
Sincix bagig (belkî) korik (karik) jî te bikira, bi cefo bî.
Even sincix, maybe if you did a job, it was with hardship.
Cefo derbas bî.
The hardship passed.
Salekê...
One year...
Baranê lê ne dikir.
The rain wouldn't stop.
Baranê... yanî rehmet (baran) ne diborî.
The rain... I mean the mercy (rain) wouldn't pass.
Hemê (emê) bidere (biderkeve)... ker (kerr) hebîn, ker...
berê ker.
We would go out... there were deaf [people/donkeys]... in
the past donkeys.
Ker e... şoxir (rûller)...
It's a donkey... a roof roller [stone cylinder to compact
mud roofs]...
Tenekê (denikê?)... teneka... me l'kerê pêşta (piştê) dan.
Tin cans/rollers... we put them on the donkey's back.
Emê biçûna kithix (kewtix/kela?)...
We would go to the citadel/ruin...
Şkanî (şkefta) berbana (berbaniyê/banî).
The cave of the roof/upper area.
Biçûna kithix... me yê av lêq (lêkir)... banî yo (banî ya).
Would go to the citadel... we put water... on the roof.
Me ye... em lêq tînin... me yê av baniyo.
We... we bring mud... we put water on the roof.
Rûyê neqlê ke (kî), din (du) neqlê, me yê baniyo.
One trip, two trips, we brought it to the roof.
Êj (êdî) bere (berê) cefo pir bî.
So, in the past, hardship was plentiful.
Pir bî.
It was plentiful.
Emê biçara (biçûna)...
We would go...
Kuderê... ya marikê (meregê)... ya berpezkî (berpezê)... ya
berberxikê (berberxê)... ya...
Where... to the haystack... or to the sheep... or to the
lambs... or...
Navdê (nava) tûna... ya...
Among the mulberry trees... or...
Yanî cefo... cefo temam bî, temam bî.
I mean hardship... hardship was complete, it was complete.
Xwandin jî kêm bî ne, apê?
Education/Reading was also scarce, wasn't it uncle?
Xwandiniya me tunebî.
We had no education.
Tunebî.
There was none.
Ê em sêv bûn?
But were we "apples" (healthy)?
Em sêv bûn.
We were apples (healthy).
Em sêv bûn. We daxê (wê demê) jî mekteb kêm bûn (me teb kêm
bûn).
We were apples. At that time schools were few (or: our
health/strength decreased).
Kêm bûn.
They were few.
Ê bofkê (bavkê) me jî... helo (hela) saeta xwe bî (sax
bî)...
And our father too... may his hour/health be good (alive)...
Yanî ewq (ewqas) ne dikir.
I mean he didn't do that much.
Em sêwî (sêvî) de ko ma... mi de ko (didanê) xwe ne dî
(nedît).
We apples... [regarding] that, I didn't see my teeth [fall
out].
Didanê xwe ne dî.
I didn't see my teeth [fall out].
Ê emkê (emê) bi vê cîyê (ciyê) weş (xweş)...
Eh, we in this nice place...
Eda (ev da)... virdo (vir de) wî do (wê de), virdo wî do,
virdo wî do... ma ewq (ewqas) xoda (xwa da) firandin.
Here... here and there, here and there, here and there... we
flew ourselves [rushed around] that much.
Disa elhemdillah şikir ji Xwedê ra, hîn gihîştin vê emrî,
hîn jî wa dîtin.
Again, praise be to God, thanks to God, you reached this
age, you saw this too.
Saeta geş, ko xweş... helbet...
Bright hour, nice [mood]... of course...
Yanî ji derba... saeta geş xweş.
I mean from the blow/time... bright and nice hour.
Silamê me jî ji gundê ra hene.
Our greetings to the village as well.
Heçî (her çî) kî gund maş (temaşe) dikin...
Everyone in the village who is watching...
Yanî li mala dinirin (dinêrin), li me dinirin...
I mean looking at the house, looking at us...
Xizkê (xizmekê) me... lavkê (lawikê) me, derê (dêra) me,
çiqas dê...
Our relatives... our son, our church/place, however much...
Saeta xweş, bigihê dê (bigihêje).
Happy hour, may it reach [them].
Xwedê emrekî zêde bide wede (we de).
May God give you (plural) a long life.
Bi ta de jî, bi wî de jî, bi gih (giş) de.
To you (singular), to him, to everyone.
Lê maro (ma ro) qicik mezin kirin, işti (êdî/aştî) di vê
emrî da kî (hinekî) li maro (ma ra) barna (bana?).
But you raised kids, now in this age, call out to us a
little bit.
E wuri (ew wir)... qicikê... yê heye...
That one there... the kids... who are here...
Yê heye binrê (binêre)... yê heye non (nan) nirê (nanêre)...
Who is here looking... who is here not looking...
Na...
No...
Wa no ye...
It is not like that...
Gotin wa hene, inke (hineke/hinek) bikin berî am (em) hene
dar...
There are sayings like that, some do it before we are
trees... [Unclear phrase, possibly referring to
death/burial].
Na, na, na.
No, no, no.
Salê me her (hezar)... salê me ware (were) xêr libe (lê be),
gule gule, mehê me her (hezar)...
May our year be a thousand... may our year come with
blessings, smiling/rose (gule gule), may our months be a
thousand...
Salê acer (ecêb/nû) gule, rehmê Xwedê li be, rehmê Xwedê li
be yane.
The new year smiling, may God's mercy be on it, may God's
mercy be on it, I mean.
La îlahe îllalah, la îlahe îllalah.
God is Great.
There is no god but God, there is no god but God.
Xwedê we bihêle.
May God keep you.
Xweş Xalê Mistefa, Xwedê te razî be.
Good Uncle Mustafa, may God be pleased with you.
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bi ta de.
May God give you a long life.
Ta de jî, ta de jî, ta de jî.
You too, you too, you too.
Berî em nika ji cam wa derkevin...
Before we leave the glass (screen) now...
Bîlak (belkî) bîlak (belkî)...
Maybe, maybe...
Xwedê...
God...
Xwedê... Xwedê...
God... God...
Xwedê emrekî zêde bi wa de.
May God give them a long life.
Berê keraba (xerebe?) tunebî, na bî?
In the past there was no ruin/destruction, was there?
No.
Haa baş e.
Haa, that's good.
Na wesa (wusa).
Not like that.
Na wusa.
Haa.
Havo (ev a) bixwe menzer e.
This itself is a view/scene.
Bes ê berê mezin dihatin.
But the ones in the past used to come big/great.
Ê, no ha, heba (hewa) bixwe menzer e.
Eh, not like that, the air itself is a view.
Û ortê (orta) da vê dixist.
And in the middle, this would fall/strike.
Havojî (ev a jî) wî dike... de wî de de wî dike...
This one also does it... come on do it, come on do it...
Hebî.
There was.
We se (wusa).
Like that.
Ax de (xwedê) rehmê... rehmê xwedê li miriyê me gişko
(gişka) be.
Yes, by God.
Ax de (xwedê) rehmê... rehmê xwedê li miriyê me gişko
(gişka) be.
Ah God's mercy... may God's mercy be on all our dead.
Amin yane xwedê.
Amen, oh God.
Havo (ev a) çend sal e emrê vê?
How many years is the age of this [item/person]?
Ya sise (sê) sal heye.
It's about three years.
Sise (sê) sal heye.
It's three years.
Sise (sê) sal e.
Mm.
It is three years.
Saeta wa xweş, Xalê Mistefa, Xwedê te bihêle.
Health to you, Uncle Mustafa, may God keep you.
Te jî bihele, te jî bihele, te jî bihele.
Keep you too, keep you too, keep you too.
Qisûrek me heye, tê efû ke.
If we have a fault, forgive it.
No, no... no Gule, Gule, Xwedê te bişê (bihêle) wa ve...
No, no... no Rose, Rose (Smile, Smile), may God keep you
with that...
Merheba xûşkê.
Hello sister.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Tu çend salî ye xûşkê?
How old are you, sister?
Pênc û pênc (bîst û pênc).
Five and five (Twenty-five).
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te.
May God give you a long life.
Ez hatim, wek ez zanim di gundê Baadrê da berê... noho
(niha)... wextê bîkûz (bêrîkûz/qûz) dikirin...
I came, as I know in Baadre village in the past... now...
when they were bending over [weaving/working]...
Hene dikirin.
They did henna [or songs].
Çend stran kevin digotin.
They sang some old songs.
Eh hewall (heval) bîn...
Eh, they were friends...
Berê digotin.
They used to sing in the past.
Tiştê folklorî bi hewe re...
The folkloric things with you...
Te kî ne, marhatî, bi dê û dengê te xweş e.
Who are you, welcome, with your pleasant mother and voice.
Em zanin yekî kanê wextê...
We know that one, when...
Ya ehlen we sehlen, ew roj bas...
Oh, welcome, that day is enough...
Baş tîştekî, ez ê wera yekî di bêjim, bila kefxweş bin
tîştekî.
Okay something, I will sing one for you, let you be happy
with something.
Bi xêr hatin, bi xêr hatin.
Welcome, welcome.
Ehlen we sehlen, tîjî û êlî sîrkêjî, û ê gilinê jî, saetê
giyan xweş, ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome, the sharp ones and the vinegar clan, and the
complainers too, good health to your souls, welcome.
Yekê jê bêje.
Sing one of them.
Destxweş.
Thanks.
Çiya germ e, li ber gedûkê...
The mountain is hot, by the mountain pass...
Me çinîbû kefnê nûkê...
We had woven new shrouds...
Keça xêra zêva bûkê...
The good daughter of the shrine is the bride...
Kesk û sor û zer li rûkê...
Green and red and yellow upon her cheeks...
Qidme wa, qidme wa tirkî...
Her step, her step is like a Turk...
Bûkê çi kîşmar anî da girê...
What snake/serpent has the bride brought to the hill...
Tîşkê, tîşkê jimar anî da girê...
The ray, the ray of numbers she brought to the hill...
Emê têne ji bilbilê...
We are coming from the nightingale...
Beslê xwe gire dor bi gulê...
She tied her head around with flowers...
Zava nalê ro li mehlê...
The groom groans, the sun is in the neighborhood...
Ji madê xazê yek çapik lê...
From the grief of the ghazi, struck one clap...
Saeta te xweş.
Health to your voice (Well sung).
Ya te jî xweş, xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide te.
Yours as well, may God give you a long life.
Bi sihetî xweş bide te.
May He give you good health.
Dengê te pir xweş e. Hawa berê wextê bûk û zava hinda
dikirin...
Your voice is very beautiful. Was this how they used to do
it for the bride and groom back then?
Hawa bû, wextê bûk û zava hana dikirin, tiştê folklorî me lê
dikir.
It was like this, when they took the bride and groom, we
performed folkloric traditions for them.
Tiştê folklorî me tîna, û me bûkê xwe zavê xwe hana dikirin.
We brought folkloric things, and we celebrated our bride and
groom like that.
Bes noka, zemanî noka hemû tû da, miç miç dikin û da xurê
diçin kualfêrê.
But now, in this current time, it's all different, they
kiss-kiss and go down to the hairdresser.
Bes yê me, berê hana, me dida hevala, me hana dikir.
But ours, back then like that, we gave her to friends, we
did it like that.
Tiştê folklorî me lê dikir, tiştê folklorî me tîna.
We performed folkloric traditions, we brought folkloric
things.
Û me bûkê xwe, zavê xwe hana dikirin.
And we celebrated our bride and our groom like that.
Saeta te xweş.
Health to your voice.
Saeta te jî xweş, xwedê te bihêle.
Health to you too, may God keep you.
Tu dihanî, tu kêf dikî, xwedê ji te razî be.
You bring [joy], you make fun, may God be pleased with you.
Vê vîdyokê dikeve ser qenatê Youtube.
This video will go onto the YouTube channel.
Tu mişkela ji cem te hene?
Do you have any problem with that?
Na, tiştek tune, ser çava, saeta we xweş.
No, nothing at all, with pleasure (upon my eyes), health to
you.
Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide te.
May God give you a long life.
Xwedê rebbil alemîn we biparêze ya rebî.
May God, the Lord of the worlds, protect you, oh Lord.
Merheba kekê Hemze.
Hello, brother Hamza.
Ser serî û ser çava.
You are very welcome (Upon my head and eyes).
Halê te çawa ye?
How are you?
Spas, xwedê ji te razî be.
Thanks, may God be pleased with you.
Kekê Hemze tu çend salî yî?
Brother Hamza, how old are you?
Bîst û neh salî me.
I am twenty-nine years old.
Bîst û neh e.
Twenty-nine.
Te bi xweşî badînayî.
You are happily from Bahdinan.
Belê.
Yes.
Em wek dibînin, em pir taldahata dibînin.
As we see, we see a lot of talent.
Û me xwest em werin cem te, ji me ra dawe lêxî.
And we wanted to come to you, so you can play a tune for us.
Ku çiçikê li ser xwe xeber dimiro deng kir.
[Asking] to speak a little about yourself and the sound
[music].
Te çû ka te û te kîjan emrî da te belişî, te dest pê kir?
How did you [learn], and at what age did you begin, did you
start?
Wele yanî, seke, emrê min diwanzdeh salî min dest pê kir.
Well, look, at the age of twelve I started.
Yanî teqrîben musîqî neye û derna me ber.
Meaning, practically there was no music [school] and nowhere
for us to go.
Wa êdî min dest pê kir, cehdê xwe kîme tehmîrê.
And so I started, I made my own effort with the instrument.
Paşê ez serxweşxolîm der, wana mumarise û dera, heta
gihîştim vê ruyê.
Then I busied my head with it, practicing and such, until I
reached this level.
Heta gihîştim vê ruyê.
Until I reached this level.
Tu noka mecalê dewatê najmêjî? Yanî bes bo xwe?
Do you not play in the wedding field now? Meaning just for
yourself?
Na mecalê dewatê naşixulim.
No, I don't work in the wedding field.
Bes wane bo berê, min cah xolê de xelaskir û çi me hecî
nexwand.
But for those, before, I finished my time [studying] and I
didn't study the Hajj [referring to formal study].
Me hecîrî nûte musîqî nîzamî, du sala min xwand.
I didn't study musical notes formally, I studied for two
years.
Û zêdetir noka mecalê dewara vêk ne, em dibên xweşkok.
And mostly now not in the field of [professional] turns, we
call it for hobby/pleasure.
Tu dewrekî jî didê?
Will you give us a turn [play a song] too?
Belê.
Yes.
Sual Kekê Hemze, ez ji te bipirsim Kekê Hemze.
A question Brother Hamza, let me ask you Brother Hamza.
Wekî dibên tenbîr ta pir meraq kir.
As they say, you had a lot of passion for the Tembûr [Saz].
Meraq berê dilê te da hebû lê ji malbatê kesek hebû?
Did you have the passion in your heart before, or was there
someone in the family?
Yan tu bi xwe wisa çêbû, meraq te li ser çêbû û te xwest te
lêxî û te elimî?
Or did it just happen by yourself, you got the passion for
it and wanted to play and learned?
Xwedê meraq tenê nabe.
By God, passion alone is not enough.
Mereq tenê nabe.
Passion alone is not enough.
Na, min dî millet... yanî hebû mereq bî, min noka seke
miletê xelkêm la.
No, I saw people... meaning there was passion, I look at the
people around now.
Wele ji vê ruyê dibî meraq, yanî wî cihê dest pê kirî we
heta wiha ro nakîşîne.
By God, from this perspective, it becomes passion, meaning
from where you start, it doesn't drag on like this.
Yanî bi me'ne tu ku wextê însanekî tiştekî bike...
Meaning, in the sense that when a human does something...
Dikeve hnoke, ger tenbîr be ger çi be.
Falls into the vibe, whether it's Tembûr or whatever.
Na mereq be, heta ceribîne.
No, if it's passion, until he tries.
Gerek silef biceribîne paşê meraq dilî xwe ke.
He has to try the fretboard first, then put the passion in
his heart.
Seke, tu werda tiştek e, mesela însan be tiştekî, yanî meraq
ke.
Look, you come to something, for example, a human regarding
something, meaning he has passion.
Ebb, bo serxwe bişixule, ê pêk tîne.
Ugh, if he works on himself, he accomplishes it.
Bes heno, mereq hebe û serê xwe pê neêşîne, wele tu mereq
bî...
But there are those, who have passion but don't
bother/struggle with it, by God even if you are
passionate...
Xelas, meraq e, be alemîne, paşê be alemîne.
That's it, it's passion, without learning, then without
learning.
Û ku meraq tunebî, nabe.
And if there is no passion, it won't happen.
Naka qolê te tiştekî te dirist neke...
If your arm doesn't make something correct [if you don't
have the talent]...
Saeta te xweş.
Health to you.
Noka qolê te tiştekî te dirist neke, tu nikarî lêxî.
If your arm doesn't make something correct, you can't play.
Belê, ne tu tiştekî ser nahî, xelas, meraq e, be alemîne,
paşê be alemîne.
Yes, if you don't put anything into it, that's it, it's
passion, without learning, then without learning.
Û ku meraq tunebî, nabe.
And if there is no passion, it won't happen.
Ku.
If.
Saeta te xweş.
Health to you.
Ê tiştê, yanî tiştê pêşerojê da, tiştê, tu dixwazî xwe lê bi
pêş bixî?
Uh things, meaning in the future, things, do you want to
advance yourself in it?
Yanî, weletî me û kirmanc û xastî badînan jî ya daxwazî
mûhîn û hîn pêşkevin di vî şî da.
Meaning, our country and Kurds and especially Bahdinan too,
the request is important and to advance more in this thing.
Yanî, bi taybet di warê cemahîrî de, vîdyo klîp û tiştî,
yanî pir rind be vî şî.
Meaning, especially in the public sphere, video clips and
things, meaning it would be very good this thing.
Bi xweşî tiştekî ji me re lêxe.
With pleasure, play something for us.
[Muzîk dileyize]
[Music playing]
Miletê kîbar û delal, xeleqa me ya îro heta mekanê me jê
wêre...
Noble and dear people, our episode today, as far as our
location allowed us...
Heta mekanê me şûre bisawirandin, da me sawirandin.
As far as our location allowed filming, we filmed.
Û hîn jî tequsûr me hene, hûnê efû kin.
And we still have shortcomings, you will forgive us.
Heta mekanê derxist û lexta me ji wara derxistin.
Until the location brought it out and we brought out the
segments for you.
Ê ku kêmasî ban derketana me ji wara derxistin.
Whatever deficiencies appeared, we brought them out for you.
Tebe'an gundî me yên kevn, yên berê, wekî hûn zanin mezin e.
Of course, our old villages, the ones from before, as you
know, are great.
Heta mekanê me rê da, xizî wara.
As far as our location permitted, for you.
Û înşalla xelekek din li ser gundê me yê din emê daxin.
And God willing, we will drop another episode about another
one of our villages.
Û tequsûr me hene hûnê efû kin, û kaş mera şta'lîqê de
binivîsin, gundî sisyê hîn daxwazin em têkevin kîjan gundî.
And we have shortcomings, you will forgive us, and I wish
you write for us in the comments, the people of Sîsê [likely
village name], which village you want us to enter next.
[Muzîka dawiyê dileyize]
[Outro music playing]
[Dawiya vîdyoyê]
[End of video]
[Mûzîka Enstrûmental]
[Instrumental Music]