Merheba miletê me yê Efrîn, miletê me yê delal.
Hello to our people of Afrin, our dear people.
Eva ewle vîdyo em wara hatin li gundê Sewiya.
This is the first video [where] we came here to the village
of Sewiya.
Emê nehateka van gundê Sewiya.
We haven't come to these Sewiya villages before.
Emê gel kal û pîran in.
We are with the elders [old men and women].
Eva ewle vîdyo dakete ser qanat, ez hatim li Efrînê.
This is the first video uploaded to the channel "I Came to
Afrin".
Hatim li Efrînê, qenatê Youtube.
"Came to Afrin", the YouTube channel.
Eva ewle vîdyo li gundê Sewiya.
This is the first video in the village of Sewiya.
Emê herin têkevin gundê Sewiya.
We will go and enter the village of Sewiya.
Emê gel kal û pîran in hela.
We are with the elders now.
Ji me ra bêjin çi.
Tell us what [you want].
Û emê tiştkê gel kal û pîran in.
And we will be a bit with the elders.
Le'anû binîhayet kal û pîr bereketê me ye.
Because ultimately, the elders are our blessing.
Mezinê me ne.
They are our seniors.
Em sekin hela heyatek çawa jîn.
Let's see how they lived a life.
Û çawa darbaskirin.
And how they passed [the time/life].
Û bi me ra bin.
And stay with us.
Û di vîdyo da yazi mîşkin, hela gundî...
And write in the video [comments], which village...
Di dêhîn dixwazin, kîjan gunda be.
You want us to come to, whichever village it may be.
Û em herin têkevin kîjan gundî.
And we will go enter whichever village.
Niha bi me ra bin, emê hem têkevin gundê Sewiya.
Now stay with us, we will also enter the village of Sewiya.
Bi me ra hazir bin.
Be ready with us.
Û me ra yazi mîşkin gundî, didiyêhin ji kîjan gundî daxwazin
em têkevin.
And write to us the village, say which village you want us
to enter.
Em hatin wek me gotî em ketin gundê Sewiya.
We came as we said, we entered the village of Sewiya.
Mala hevsila va em hatin, mala Xalê Cemîl.
We came to this household here, the house of Uncle Cemil.
Wara em cem Xalê Cemîl tişkê rûnên û mla çend gotina ji me
ra bike.
Come, let's sit a bit with Uncle Cemil and let him say a few
words to us.
Merheba Xalê Cemîl.
Hello Uncle Cemil.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser dil û çava ra.
Welcome, upon [my] heart and eyes [with pleasure].
Çî şdax Xalê Cemîl?
How are you Uncle Cemil?
Weleh elhemdillah, hûn çawa ne? Ehlen we sehlen.
By God, praise be to God, how are you? Welcome.
Bavî te Xalê Cemîl e?
Your father [name] is Uncle Cemil?
Çend salî ye Xalê Cemîl?
Huh?
How old is Uncle Cemil?
De bimen, hezoyê, nêzîkî hefte ye.
Well, let's suppose, approximately, close to seventy.
Ser hefte ket?
Passed seventy?
De 'emrekî dirêj bide.
May [God] give a long life.
Bi Xwedê.
By God.
Tu sax bî baba de.
May you be healthy, dear.
Tu bixwa ji Sewiya ye?
Are you yourself from Sewiya?
Ez Sewî me.
I am from Sewiya.
Kê mera çend mesela kevin hewal dê.
Who will tell us a few old stories, friend.
Li gunda... noke berê digotin mesela li Ba'dîna bi meşê
diçûn avê.
In the village... now, back then they said, for example,
they walked to Baadina to get water.
Diçûn av tînan.
They went to fetch water.
Camêrê Sewiya jî diçûn.
The men of Sewiya also went.
Gundî me berêj, vana diçûn Ba'dîna.
Our villagers back then, they went to Baadina.
Bi teneka.
With tin cans.
Tenekê me jî gihi qul bûn.
Our cans were all full of holes.
Me'nê bizda bûn.
Meaning they were battered.
Heta em diçûn dihatin, nîvê rê diçûn.
By the time we went and came back, half [the water] was gone
on the way.
E gi bi kerabû, gi bi dêwêrbû, qatir bûn.
It was all with donkeys, with beasts of burden, mules.
E nuh nuh elhemdillah gihi kêrê avê hene.
Uh, now, now praise be to God, there are all water taps.
Gi şebah hene.
There are all networks [plumbing].
Milet nuh nuh kêf e.
The people now, now are in comfort.
Kêm bîna me çiye?
What is our shortcoming?
Bes...
Just...
Keşkê ma, şebabê me gi çûne derve.
Our wish... our youth have all gone abroad.
Em daxwazen werin.
We want them to come back.
Daxwazen biftilin.
Want them to return.
Hemdillah.
Yes, return.
Praise God.
Hine ji ber destê xu çûn, ne bi dilê xu çûn.
Some went because of their circumstances [forced], not by
their own heart's desire.
We nokî caw bigir.
And now take the place/situation [as it is].
Xalê Cemîl.
Uncle Cemil.
Çend salî Xalê Cemîl?
Huh?
How old is Uncle Cemil?
Tu dêmîn heftê û neset û pênc û yek in.
You say seventy and... fifty one [birth year 1951].
E nêzîkî hefte.
Yes, close to seventy.
Ser hefte ket.
Passed seventy.
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide.
God give a long life.
Bigo yê dê.
Say, yes father [friend].
Tu sahbaba dê.
You are healthy father.
Te bi xweşî ji Sewiya ye.
You are happily from Sewiya.
Ez Sewî me.
I am from Sewiya.
Têkê mera çend mesela kevin hewal dê.
You will tell us a few old stories, friend.
Li gunda... noke berê digotin mesela li Ba'dîna bi meşê
diçûn avê.
In the villages... now back then they said, for example,
they walked to Baadina to get water.
Diçûn av tînan.
They went to fetch water.
Camêrê Sewiya jî diçûn.
The men of Sewiya also went.
Gelo mesela berê digotin mesela li Ba'dîna diçûn avê.
Whether the story back then, they said, for example, they
went to Baadina for water.
Şebabê Sewiya da diketin avê, şebabê Ba'dîna ve diderxistin?
Did the youth of Sewiya jump into the water, and the youth
of Baadina chase them out?
Gundê me yek e, masiyê tê bikî ber nade.
Our village is one [united], if you put a fish in it, it
won't let it go.
Me'ne bizda bit.
Meaning it was strong/fast.
Heta em diçûn dihatin, nîvê rê diçûn.
By the time we went and came back, half [the water] was gone
on the way.
E gi bi kerabû, gi bi dêwêrbû, qatir bûn.
It was all with donkeys, with beasts of burden, mules.
E nav nav elhemdillah gisi kêrê avê hene.
Uh, now now praise be to God, there are all water taps.
Gi şebah hene.
There are all networks.
Milet nav nav kêf e.
The people now now are in comfort.
Kêm bîna me çiye?
What is our shortcoming?
Bes...
Just...
Keşkê ma, şebabê me gi çûne derve.
Our wish... our youth have all gone abroad.
Em daxwazen werin.
We want them to come back.
Daxwazen biftilin.
Want them to return.
E biftilin.
Yes, return.
Hemdillah.
Praise God.
Hine ji ber destê xu çûn, ne bi dilê xu çûn.
Some went because of their circumstances, not by their own
heart's desire.
We nokî caw bigir.
And now take the place/situation.
Bê.
Yes.
Xalê Cemîl.
Uncle Cemil.
Kê do herem.
Let me go [ask].
Dibê axî walêt şirîn e.
They say the soil of the homeland is sweet.
Tişt wek axî walêt tne.
There is nothing like the soil of the homeland.
Li dero hene, milet heye.
There are people abroad.
Pirr zengîn e, milyonder e.
Very rich, millionaire.
Pirr zengîn e.
Very rich.
Dibê xol û av û eskê herim.
He says [I want] the soil and water and... let me go.
Wela cem bav û cem anê, ma tişgerekê tey.
By God, to father and to mother, we have a thing
[connection].
Yarim dibê tu kênêj be 'amkêlî me pênc qirûş axwîna.
My friend says if you are... our uncle... five kurus...
[unclear dialect phrase about money/value].
Çiqas pere pirr ne.
No matter how much money there is.
Tiştî jê axê baştir qet tenê tne.
There is absolutely nothing better than the soil.
Ax serake giya.
Soil is above all.
Û werin werin, kîjan rê bimeşin werin.
And come back, come back, whatever road you walk, come back.
Rind werin, şixulê pîs çêtir e.
Come back good, better than bad work.
Şînahî rind e yarim.
Greenery [home] is good my friend.
Buhar, bi kulîlkê çê nabê.
Spring doesn't happen with [one] flower.
Bi şînahî şîn dibê.
It becomes green with greenery [vegetation/people].
Bixêr werin... hûn ê bibînin...
Welcome... you will see...
Elhemdulillah qîzkê kurmancî gi bekeleriya, gi camî'a, gi
doxtor in.
Praise God, Kurdish girls are all bachelors [degrees], all
universities, all doctors.
Jê hez dikin ko şer navê nav miletê kurmanc da navê.
They love that there is no war, among the Kurdish people
there is no [war].
Berê... canê xwedê de xist... navê nav giş hevdû ra bira
kin.
In the past... God put soul [in us]... name all brothers to
each other.
Gî seqafet in, gî kîf in.
All culture, all joy.
Tişt û mişt wano wano tne nemo.
Things and stuff like that don't exist anymore [bad things].
Neha cem me Ba'dîna.
Now with us [in] Baadina.
Dibe dongê Ba'dîna meşhûr e.
They say the voice/song of Baadina is famous.
Gi pê deng dikin.
Everyone talks about it.
Dibê donkê Ba'dîna.
They say the "donk" [song/tune] of Baadina.
Li cem wa Sewiya, wek mabîstî dibê kîto ye.
With you Sewiya people, as we heard, they say it is "kîto"
[a type of song/story].
Meselê kîtoyê bes kêşkim.
The story of "kîto", let me just pull/ask.
Kîto çê dikirin, berê dewar dikirin.
They made "kîto", back then they kept livestock.
Li îdamê hî 'aşûra.
At the time of Ashura.
Singel tînan.
They brought "singel" [wheat/grain].
Ew singya hel tînan dikirin îçî kîtoyê.
They brought that "singel" and put it inside the "kîto".
Û pirr dikirin.
And they filled it up.
Di he panzdeh mala bela dikirin gya dixwar.
They distributed it to fifteen houses, everyone ate.
Bilfî'il hîn halyo jî naxna kîtoyê bike.
Actually, even now if someone makes "kîto".
Xêrî şîvê dengî ya.
It is better than the sound of dinner [meaning it's a very
good meal].
Ne ferq çi ye û filan çi ye.
No matter what difference or whatever.
Li gundê Sewiya kîtoya xweş e.
In the village of Sewiya, the "kîto" is good/delicious.
E xweş e.
Yes, it is delicious.
Xweş e.
Delicious.
E.
Yes.
Xalê Cemîl, xê nav lêkirin.
Uncle Cemil, who named it?
Gundê Sewiya, xê nav lêkirin.
The village of Sewiya, who named it?
Hawa zemanda ye, pirr e.
This is from ancient times, very [old].
Belkî mde hezar sal a ye.
Maybe for a thousand years.
Û însan jî pirr hindik bûn.
And people were very few.
Însan pirr hindik bûn.
People were very few.
Yanî gundê Ba'dîna tne bî wextê gundê ma çêbûn.
Meaning the village of Baadina didn't exist when our village
was formed.
Çend gund hene kokanê, Sewiya darê hewnan pirr kam bûn.
There are a few villages rooted... Sewiya had many 'hewn'
trees [unclear tree type, possibly 'hêwir' or 'hewneb'].
Deştê kedaşk hatin zemanda malek tenê dînok.
From the plain... came in ancient times, only one house saw
it.
Sewî bû.
It was an orphan ['sêwî' means orphan].
Û mamo, sêwî yo, paşê şûnê rê.
And uncle, the orphan, then the place of the road.
Ki çêbû mala 'Imikê.
Which became the house of Imik.
'Imikê kal hemna zemanda pirr, pirr kevne ne.
Old Imik, from ancient times, very, very old.
Hawa pirr kevne ne liv derê sekinîn.
These are very old, they stood here.
Û heta liv derê jiyana xwe kirin.
And until here/now they made their life.
Gundê me mezin bû, fireh bû, zêde bûn.
Our village grew big, expanded, increased.
E heya niha jî ma, mala 'Imikê, mala Nasirler a, mala...
And until now it remained, the house of Imik, the house of
Nasirler, the house of...
Jêrî ma.
Below us.
Mala Nesirler a liv derê hebûn.
The house of Nesirler was here.
Nesirler a her hîn xirabiyên xwe hene.
Nesirler still have their ruins [old houses].
Evna girîfiyê gundê me bûn.
These were the core/elders of our village.
Sazik dikirin, tiştekî dibanê dikirin, digu wej me re sinê.
They made arrangements, they did things, they said this is
for us... [unclear].
Saetê te xweş Xalê Cemîl.
Health to you Uncle Cemil [Thank you].
Ser 'eynî.
Upon my eye [You're welcome].
Û heva gundê te silav.
And this, greetings to your village.
Ez hatim.
I came.
Migo eger em Sewiya, lê no pêdhesim Sewiya gundê me didiya
ye.
I said if we are Sewiya... but now I feel Sewiya is my
second village.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser dil û çava.
Welcome, upon heart and eyes.
Bovkê min dot Sewiya û ez jî dihatim.
My father gave [a daughter?] to Sewiya and I also came.
Û Sewiya gundek pirr xweş e.
And Sewiya is a very nice village.
Bilindî ye.
It is high/elevated.
Zivistanê bayê xwe pîk e, l'avînê wane ye.
In winter its wind is sharp, in summer it is like that
[pleasant].
Berî noka em derên.
Before now we leave.
Ez dixwazim te Xalê Cemîl te gîş vê 'emrî.
I want you Uncle Cemil, you [with] all this age.
Te dinesîhat o bicî lî noka digînê.
You give advice to the generation reaching now.
Te di şoro bike.
You make a speech/talk.
Meselen rindiyê da herin.
For example, let them go in goodness.
Dina rindiyê dixwazim, te dine siha bime dê.
I want goodness in the world, you give us advice.
Wela nesîhatê xo bikim.
By God, let me give my advice.
Elhemdulillah cîlê berê welleh ji me baqiltir e.
Praise God, the generation of the past, by God, is smarter
than us.
Hol biderê ketin tengosiyê, hemdila çûn dinge Ewrûpa.
They fell into difficulties here, praise God they went to
Europe.
Bara kolê xo man, wela gi jê ro pere şandin.
Their burdens/families remained, by God they all sent money
to them.
Kê mase ne gîşt kesî.
No one reached anyone [in need?].
De zirûfkî walî hat poş milet.
Then a circumstance like this came upon the nation.
Maşela şebabê me jin...
Mashallah our youth... [unclear].
Me çêtir in ne.
They are better than us.
Gi da'mon din, minasibok bê, mirîk bê, tiştek bê.
They all support, if there is an occasion, a funeral,
something.
Gi pero dişînin, kes li 'ardê namîne.
They all send money, no one is left on the ground
[helpless].
Te tengosê namîne.
You don't remain in difficulty.
Yeke dawata xo bike, maşela cumhûrê me pirr e.
If one makes his wedding, mashallah our crowd is large.
Heta g rê hebe seke dawetên me her dawetek dibê.
As long as there is a way, look, our weddings, every wedding
happens.
Hije wanê didin hene, dawet dibin.
Those who give [support] are there, weddings happen.
Deha mereqim naben.
They don't worry anymore.
Maşela cema'e misa'ede pirr e.
Mashallah the community's help is abundant.
Cema'e pê hesim e.
The community is feeling [empathetic].
Yanî miletê me bi şekil 'am, miletê Efrîn.
Meaning our people in general, the people of Afrin.
Qasî kîbor e li mirya û li dawata pirr lez ginde.
They are very noble/great in funerals and in weddings, very
quick [to help].
Teqsîrê nakin.
They don't fall short.
Teqsîr nakin e.
They don't fall short, yes.
Ebeden.
Never.
Her bî hesûb.
Always calculated/accountable.
Û haryekî darva te nesîhet dikî.
And anyone abroad you advise.
Li dê bavkê xo birne.
To take care of their father [parents].
Van havno mezin kirin.
They raised these [children].
Dibê bi cefo wekî dibên heyatî berê.
It says with hardship, as they say, the life of the past.
Cefo têda pirr bî.
There was much hardship in it.
Li ser êr bî, şîv bê meselen.
It was on fire [cooking], dinner for example.
Gi av bo diçûn deştê tînan.
All water, they went to the plain to bring it.
Vê qicikno mezin dikirin.
They raised these little ones.
Yanî nesîhetê te.
Meaning your advice.
No te dibê mila li dê bavkê xo birnin.
Now you say let them take care of their parents.
Wala nesîhetê xo.
By God, my advice.
Em bêr derketin.
We came out before.
Bê em bêr no derketin, me gû çqas tişkî rind e.
Before we didn't come out [abroad], we said how good
something is.
Qişkê me, nefs êl min.
Our kids, my own self.
Me do ke seker, deh heb hindir xistin, me nezanî deh heb
çine.
We gave... put ten inside, we didn't know what ten are
[unclear context].
Bê lewhê taqê...
Without a plate/board of... [unclear].
Ewê...
That...
Û naş mirroş mu'alemê roş ho tin.
And... [unclear dialect] teachers came.
Maşela jinkê me, hemokê te kevesînin.
Mashallah our women, they compete with you all.
Av heye.
There is water.
Xazan heye.
There are cisterns/tanks.
Xazanê di avê germ hene.
There are hot water tanks.
Û li molo giş hene, ne l'cem min û ne l'cem te.
And in all houses they exist, not [just] at mine and not at
yours.
Cem 'alemê hene maşela şebab tî teqsîrê nakin.
At everyone's place they exist, mashallah the youth do not
fall short.
Na wala.
No by God.
Û ey mi sa'adê tele fîn ke bi çiqasî dişîne.
And whatever help [is needed]... how much he sends.
Û bi xol û daye sindûq şê kirine.
And with soil and mother... they prepared a box/chest.
Minasibek... digu na gundî me, gundo giyo.
An occasion... he said not our village, the village of
everyone.
Çi minasibe heye.
Whatever occasion there is.
J'vê ro sake giştin û dibê herin.
From this way look, they reached and say go.
Her çêkin.
Always make/do.
Biderê ji wekîl hene.
Out there, there are representatives.
Elhemdulillah gundo giyo.
Praise God, the village of everyone.
Ma wela rind in, tû teqsîro nakin.
They are good, they don't fall short.
Bes ez selam dikim.
I just greet them.
Êv çûne derve.
Those who went abroad.
Qeder îmkaniyet virda werin.
As much as possible come back here.
Virda werin.
Come back here.
Qeder îmkan l'viderê werin mla hevo îsist namîne.
As much as possible come here so this [place] doesn't remain
weak/empty.
Mla xîdî me ne tin lê rûnan e.
So that our land is not without people sitting on it.
Em bê hacê gindone.
We are in need of the villages/people.
Û bes elhemdulillah zirûf fikir fere bû.
And enough, praise God, the situation [mindset] became
open/better.
Û çê bû.
And it became good.
Ne wekê berê.
Not like before.
Berê îcbarî çûn, ne b'kîfê xo çûn.
Before they went by force [necessity], they didn't go by
their own pleasure.
Usa to gya ye xweş, xweş xweş baş. Ehlen we sehlen.
Like that... good, good good fine. Welcome.
Saetê te xweş Xalê Cemîl.
Health to you Uncle Cemil.
Wakî dibên ez pirr kêf xweş bûm.
As they say, I was very pleased.
Hatim genda û ewil şexs dahatim cem Xalê Cemîl.
I came to the village and the first person I came to was
Uncle Cemil.
Ehlen we sehlen şol te ne werre.
Welcome... [unclear].
Û Xwedê 'emrekî dirêj bide.
And may God give a long life.
Bavî mi wacê dê.
My father... [unclear].
Dû sehba.
[Unclear].
Qisîr nama hene te kêf kê.
There is no shortcoming... you made us happy.
Te gotin te hene.
You have your words.
Te kênê bê.
You will [say]...
Kê tne.
Who isn't [happy].
Elhemdillah serê te b'xêr be.
Praise God, may your head be well [bless you].
Û Xwedê ji te razî be.
And may God be pleased with you.
Ser çava. Ehlen we sehlen.
Upon eyes. Welcome.
Saetê te xweş Xalê Cemîl.
Health to you Uncle Cemil.
Wek me wara gotî li gundê Sewiya, em hatin cem Xalê Hanan.
As we told you in the village of Sewiya, we came to Uncle
Hanan.
Ka emê nehan cem Xalê Hanan hela pirskin.
Let's now ask Uncle Hanan a bit.
Yekî çi meselê wî ji mera hewol dê.
What story of his he will tell us, friend.
Merheba Xalê Hanan.
Hello Uncle Hanan.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser sera ser çava.
Welcome, upon heads upon eyes.
Îş te çûne?
How are your affairs?
Elhemdulillah, tu çawa yî?
Praise God, how are you?
Îş te razi be.
May your affairs be pleasing.
Ez ji Badîna Xelîl.
I am Xelîl from Baadina.
Li ser Youtube qenatî 'Ez Hatim li Efrînê'.
On YouTube, the channel "I Came to Afrin".
Ez bi xo gerîm fitilîme hatim li Efrînê.
I myself wandered and returned, came to Afrin.
Û wek mibîstî meselê xweş pirr cem te hene.
And as I heard, you have many nice stories.
Tikî noka mera meselokê.
You will tell us a story now.
Hewol dê.
Tell us/Friend.
Di fikrê ta da.
In your mind.
Ey ehlen we sehlen.
Ey, welcome.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Dibê rojekê yekî, kelek stebîlê gundek heye.
He says one day someone, there is a village [called] Kelek
Stebîlê [or similar name].
Û hemerr, bajêr, temînatê xo în warin.
And always, [to] the city, they bring their provisions back.
Û temînatê xo.
And their provisions.
Hemerr, î, me îno warin.
Always, yes, we brought them back.
Dabeşî dab kera diçûn.
They went by sharing donkeys [riding donkeys].
Bi kera diçûn.
They went by donkeys.
Ew jina xwa.
That wife of his.
Darin, jinek li kerê rûniştî, mêrek li pê dimeşe.
They go, a woman sitting on the donkey, a man walking
behind.
Kekê, dibê; Ya Rebî, xelkê te hemûyan nesîbê wan heye.
And when he reached the middle of the road.
Wisakî yekî gûr.
Like a big one [dog/wolf].
Bi benî rê.
On the side of the road.
Kekê, dibê; Ya Rebî, xelkê te hemûyan nesîbê wan heye.
Man, he says; Oh Lord, all your people have their
destiny/share.
Çavê min nabînin, kûr im. Wê, bide rêka te me, bere
şûşkilî... xelkê, kasek tirlê me ne serekî ye.
My eyes cannot see, I am blind. Well, put me on your path,
let it be... people, a bowl of grapes is not a leader/head
[folk expression].
Wella, mêrekî; jinekê gotî: "Wella, jinika esker, wî merî
nabe."
Well, a man; a woman said: "Well, the soldier's wife, that
man won't do."
Xerîk... Dibê, jinekê gotî: "Tu ji Xwedê çêtir nizanî. Were,
bela emê rêka xwe darin."
Strange... He says, a woman said: "You don't know better
than God. Come, let us go on our way."
Lê gotî: "Heram e, da here, em herin waran."
She told him: "It is forbidden (haram), come on, let's go to
the places."
Kuro, mêrek çiya nîvhat?
Boy, didn't a man from the mountain come halfway?
Bi mêrê çiya nîvhat sarrê...
With the man from the mountain coming halfway to the head
[of the path]...
De jinekê gotî: "Xêr e kuro? Were, de em li kerê nêçîra xwe,
bere em lê binihêrin."
So the woman said: "Is it good, boy? Come, let's look at our
hunting donkey, let us look at it."
Em xêr e kuro, da kûr e, çûle bibîne jî?
We are good, boy, but he is blind, how will he see the open
field?
Kuro, bi ilkare dan, birin çûn...
Boy, they hit it with the tool/stick, they took it and
went...
Bi ilkare dan, birin çûn, gîhaştin...
They hit it with the tool, took it and went, they arrived...
Bajêr...
The city...
Got: "De mantiqan li bajêr dikare daye."
He said: "Give the logic [speech] in the city."
Kere şilû bû.
The donkey was hairless/bald.
Got: "Bi kero min e..."
He said: "By my donkey..."
"Dibe, nabe, ker hêlek, go hem jineka min e û kerê ji min
e..."
"It happens, it doesn't happen, the donkey aside, he said
both my wife and the donkey are mine..."
"Baba, meriya gişka min bistîne."
"Father, take all my people [family]."
"Û çavê min nabînin."
"And my eyes do not see."
"Go: 'Bavo meriya ji te zulme, heke jina min û kerê min
bistîne.'"
"He said: 'Father, the people are oppressive to you, if you
take my wife and my donkey.'"
Haa, rogaran li ev heyirîn. Gîhaştin ber reîsê mexferê.
Haa, the days were confused by this. They arrived before the
Chief of the Police Station.
Mexferê... Reîsê mexferê îfade rakir...
The station... The Chief of the station took the
statement...
Go: "Bavo, de kûrik û bî, ma bi xorê anîhat, û tiştan me
anîhat..."
He said: "Father, the boy and the... well, by eating it
came, and things came to us..."
Wana go çipkir? Wana harekî ba dondorkê kir.
What did they do? They applied some sort of ice cream
[cream/ointment].
Jinikê... û mêrê jinikê, û wî kûrî... got: "Bi harekî
dondorkê kin."
The woman... and the woman's husband, and that blind man...
he said: "Apply some cream to them."
"Û harek berqê hebin, gulê min e."
"And have some lightning [electricity/shock], it is my
flower."
"Û seh kin, mêrekî dibê, mêrê jinikê dibê: De migul jinika
xwe kiriba..."
"And look, a man says, the woman's husband says: If I had
done [it] to my wife..."
"Ez nadiketen."
"I wouldn't have fallen."
"Ez nadiketen, va bela li min ra çênebûya, û ez bûra
regîniya sofî."
"I wouldn't have fallen, this trouble wouldn't have happened
to me, and I would have become the color of a Sufi."
Û jinikê dibê... min gotî: "Mêrko, te ji Xwedê nabo,
qetirek, di derê min tere, wî biger, were em berê xwe
darin."
And the woman says... I said: "Man, you didn't get it from
God, a mule, go through my door, look for him, come let's go
on our way."
Û ewî jî dibê çi? Dibê: "De ji kerê û jinikê çûbûya, de
şert... na... Reîsê mexferê yekî me de."
And what does he say? He says: "If only the donkey and the
woman had gone, on the condition... no... give us one Chief
of the station."
"Ya kerê..."
"Or the donkey..."
"Ez dê korê bikime."
"I will make him blind."
Û hêlek berqê biskinî çûn cem Reîsê mexferê...
And they stopped a bit of lightning [electricity] and went
to the Chief of the station...
Wella, go: "Mêrek..."
Well, he said: "A man..."
"Dibê, kî migul jinika xwe kiriba sa..."
"Says, whoever would have done [it] with his wife then..."
"Ewê nexweşiya min nadî."
"Wouldn't have seen my illness."
Jinik jî dibê: "Min bitara gotî: 'Te ji Xwedê nader,
rehmetîra...'"
The woman also says: "I told him clearly: 'You won't get it
from God, for mercy's sake...'"
"Were jê veger, emê rêya xwe darin."
"Come turn back from it, let us go on our way."
Û mêrê jî dibê...
And the man also says...
"De, wî kûr... dibê ji kerê jinikê çûbûya, ya key destê min
kevî."
"So, that blind man... says if the woman's donkey had gone,
or if it falls into my hand."
"Go dê her bol-bol hokerê werin."
"He said plenty of 'hokers' [donkeys/people] will come."
[Laughs]
Mêre jinikê ro? Go: "Her du jinikê heva herin, û çok de gul
jinê xwe ke."
The woman's husband, right? He said: "Let both women go
together, and kneel and do [it] to your wife."
"Woy jî penî kergî kûne xist, û go tê biqeherîne, çok da
hera."
"He also put a penny in the donkey's behind, and said 'you
will annoy it', and kneeled there."
Û saeta we xweş, û Xwedê ji we razî be.
And have a good time/hour, and may God be pleased with you.
Geşta we jî razî be. Yanî demek... wext nîne, gerek mara gel
hev bike.
May your trip be pleasing too. Meaning a time... there is no
time, a man needs to do it with each other.
Ê lê?
Oh really?
Gel jin be, gel mêr be, gerek mara...
Whether with a woman, with a man, a man needs to...
Bêje: "Min go, tiştî gul jinê xwe ke."
Say: "I said, do the thing to your wife."
"Heke nedikir, nediket hemdê."
"If he didn't do it, he wouldn't fall into grief."
Saeta te xweş xalê Henan. Kekî dibê ez pir kêfxweş bim. Me
hatim Sêvya û bere jî ez darim û têm. Inşallah emê hîn
werin.
Have a good time, Uncle Henan. Brother says I am very happy.
I came to Sêvya and I go and come back again. God willing,
we will come again.
[Inaudible] ... ser seran û ser çavan.
[Inaudible] ... you are welcome (on heads and on eyes).
Tu bi xêr hatî, ser çava.
You are welcome, upon my eyes.
De, işta razî be û Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide te.
So, may [God] be pleased with the work, and may God give you
a long life.
Û wekî dibêjin, te emr... te hene, te gotin, te hene te kê
bikî...
And as they say, you have... age... you have sayings, you
have things you do...
Vê vîdeo kê here ser Youtube, tu mişkîla cem te hene?
If this video goes on Youtube, do you have any problem?
Milletê derva li te sêr ke, kêfxweş bibe. Xwedê emrêkî dirêj
bide te, xalê Henan. Xwedê ji te razî be.
The people abroad will watch you, they will be happy. May
God give you a long life, Uncle Henan. May God be pleased
with you.
Li xeleqa sêyem, lextê poşin... Em kê niha biçike ser
Ziyareta Sêvya.
In the third episode, dressed nicely... We will now go up a
bit to the Shrine of Sêvya.
Deng kin, û bime ra... Kekê Reşîd, Selamû Aleykûm.
Make noise [speak up], and with us... Brother Reşîd, Peace
be upon you.
Selam û ehlen.
Peace and welcome.
Tu çend salî ye?
How old are you?
Walayî şêst û sê.
By God, sixty-three.
Şêst û sê, Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide te.
Sixty-three, may God give you a long life.
Saxlem be.
Be healthy.
Ava xeleqa tef sêlef e, ser Youtube.
This is an episode of "Tef Sêlef" [program name], on
Youtube.
Ez hatim li Efrînê, hatim li Efrînê.
I am "Hatim in Afrin" [channel name], Hatim in Afrin.
Ava xeleqa tef sêlef, me dixwast em li Sêvya bisewirînin.
This episode of "Tef Sêlef", we wanted to film in Sêvya.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Û Sêvya gundê me didiya ye.
And Sêvya is our father's/grandfather's village.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Tu kê mera ko çişkî xeber de... ser Ziyaretê.
You will give us a little talk... about the Shrine.
Bese verikî em silava lê bidin. Merheba.
Just wait a bit so we can greet him. Hello.
Navî te?
Your name?
Ma'mûş.
Ma'mûş? Wer Ma'mûş.
Ma'mûş? Come, Ma'mûş.
Dibe tu kilama xweş didiyê?
They say you sing beautiful songs?
Êh.
Yeah.
Tu kê nika mera kilama pê dê.
You will give us a song now.
Kekê Reşîd, vê Ziyaretê pir kevin e?
Brother Reşîd, is this Shrine very old?
Ziyaret pir kevin e, emrê xwe... teqrîben dibe hazar sal
heye.
The Shrine is very old, its age... it is approximately a
thousand years old.
Em negiştine.
We didn't reach [that time].
Emrê xwe hazar sal ne. Pir kevin e, dar û niştan.
Its age is a thousand years. Very old, the trees and
surroundings.
Bêro, Ziyaretê çîk dibên?
Brother, what do they call the Shrine?
Ziyaret Hac Yûsif e.
It is the Shrine of Hac Yûsif.
Hac Yûsif e?
Hac Yûsif?
Erê, Ziyareta Hac Yûsif e.
Yes, the Shrine of Hac Yûsif.
Tirbî vê gundî, de run nav vê Ziyaretê?
The graves of this village, do they go [are they buried]
inside this Shrine?
Teb'en, tirbe... nê tînin vêderê, erê.
Of course, graves... no, they bring them here, yes.
Tirbî vê gundî de run nav vê Ziyaretê.
The graves of this village go inside this Shrine.
Vê Ziyaretê, bes milletê Sêvya tên nav Ziyaretê, le ji derva
yî Sêvya jî tên?
This Shrine, do only the people of Sêvya come into the
Shrine, or do those from outside Sêvya also come?
Na, bes milletê gund. Î vir û Efrîn, Heleb, Elmanya, kû bin,
cenazê xwe tînin biro.
No, only the people of the village. Those here and Afrin,
Aleppo, Germany, wherever they are, they bring their
funerals here.
Cenazî gundê Sêvya tên viderê, teba şandin.
The funerals of the village of Sêvya come here, sent to
rest.
Millet... wextî tê ba Ziyaretê, ji dervayî Sêvya jî tê, le
bes le Sêvya derin ber vê Ziyaretê?
The people... when they come to the Shrine, do they come
from outside Sêvya too, or do only those from Sêvya go
before this Shrine?
Ji gi daro tênê.
They come from everywhere.
Mentîqa Efrîn, ek... ek mero tênê.
The Afrin region, ev... every man comes.
Ewa... niho li mista cem li ba'dîno, Ziyareta Şêx Reşîd
heye.
So... now right next to us in Ba'dîno, there is the Shrine
of Şêx Reşîd.
Teb'en, erê.
Of course, yes.
Şêx Reşîd, Ziyareta cem e ba'dîno, mesela ji dervayî ba'dîno
jî tên, ne bes ba'dîno tenê.
Şêx Reşîd, the Shrine near Ba'dîno, for example, they come
from outside Ba'dîno too, not just Ba'dîno alone.
Havo jî şikeftil... gundê Efrîn tên. Tên, erê, gi daro tên.
This one too... [from] the villages of Afrin they come. They
come, yes, they come from everywhere.
Wara em çişkê herin, mera xeber de...
Come let's go a bit, talk to us...
Nav gund de ta got Tirbe hene, na we?
In the village you said there are graves, right?
Tirbe hene. Îşta û ocaq e.
There are graves. Here is a hearth (holy spot).
Ê qurbanan lê bardikin, darda bardikin, işta wane.
They slaughter sacrifices there, hang them on the tree,
things like that.
Û ocaq e.
And it is a hearth.
Em giştin niho nav Ziyareta Kekê Reşîd, viderê Ziyareta
Sêvya.
We have now arrived inside Brother Reşîd's Shrine, here is
the Shrine of Sêvya.
Vêro dibên Ziyareta Hac...
Here they call the Shrine of Hac...
Ziyaret Hac Yûsif.
Shrine of Hac Yûsif.
Hac Yûsif.
Ziyaret Hac Yûsif, erê.
Shrine of Hac Yûsif, yes.
Ziyaret bi xwe pir kevin e.
The Shrine itself is very old.
Em negiştine, Ziyaret pir kevin e.
We didn't reach [its beginning], the Shrine is very old.
Dê çido û ocaq heye.
There is a place and a hearth.
Nêtik xwe dikin, qurbanan lê bardikin, berê de hatin, sar
salê, me'nê baranê. Qurbanan lê vir dikirin, dar dikirin.
They make intentions/wishes, they slaughter sacrifices, they
used to come, at the head of the year, for rain. They would
slaughter sacrifices here, hang them up.
Û Ziyaret jî pir kevin e.
And the Shrine is very old.
Kekê Reşîd, wek apolê xwe didimê, yanî Ziyaret, a halo ye?
Yanî kes...
Brother Reşîd, as I see with my eyes, meaning the Shrine, is
it untouched? Meaning no one...
Newêre nêzîkî bibe, teb'en.
No one dares get close to it, of course.
Newêre.
They don't dare.
Ma hewala kirin, dar kirin, kesî nekarî tiştek bikira daro.
They tried, to do something to the tree, no one could do
anything to the tree.
Apolê xwe didimê, pir kîbar e, bilindî ye. Cî xwe...
I see with my eyes, it is very grand, it is high up. Its
place...
In polîto jê jêdikin, lê jê nakin.
These [people] remove from it, but they don't remove
[properly/completely - referring to branches].
Teb'en.
Of course.
Jê dikin.
They remove [branches].
Na, na, na, îna jê dikin. Jê dikin, debreşînin biro, dar
dikin, biav dikin.
No, no, no, they remove these. They remove them, sprinkle
them here, hang them, water them.
Na, na, z... 'ûd e ye. Îşta nêtik te hebe, darek te hebe.
No, no, it is a... stick/incense. If you have an intention,
if you have a tree [wish].
Û wek em dibînin, niho li viderê, li Ziyareta Sêvya, û tirbe
jî hene.
And as we see, now here, at the Shrine of Sêvya, there are
graves too.
Û çido jî pir dirêj e, cewî xwe jî pir xweş e. Yanî însan
kênê darkevê seyranê jî viderê, vedahesê.
And the place is very long/spacious, its weather is very
nice. Meaning if a person comes out for a picnic here, they
can rest.
Teb'en, teb'en.
Of course, of course.
Bi şeklê 'am, gundê Sêvya, gundek pir bilindî ye.
Generally speaking, the village of Sêvya is a very high
village.
Teb'en, wekî bil'ade, meselên havînê denê pir germ dibe.
Of course, as usual, for example in the summer the plains
get very hot.
Em dibên biro, biro jî pir hênik e.
We say here, here is very cool.
Kîbar e.
It is elegant/nice.
Lê de havînê pir hênik e.
But in the summer it is very cool.
Hav te xweş bavê minê, dar deke. Îj Efrîn tî, erê de ne
mesela tiştinî xwe tînin li berî didin, daxwan, vedixwin,
darin.
Have a good summer my father, hang [wishes]. They come from
Afrin, yes, they bring their things before it, they ask,
they drink, they go.
Pir têne, pir têne.
Many come, many come.
Kîbar e.
It is grand.
Ji guncîş dervayî guncî.
From the village and outside the village.
Xwedê emrêkî dirêj bi we de. Xwedê vê gundî xweş.
May God give you a long life. God [keep] this village
pleasant.
Sax be.
Be healthy.
Û te 'eltîjal we nebîne, gundê Sêvya bi şeklê 'am, gundê me
didiya ye.
And don't be stranger, the village of Sêvya generally
speaking, is our father's/grandfather's village.
Hava ewvil xelqe, ser qenetî Youtube, ez hatim li Efrînê.
This is the first episode, on the Youtube channel, "Hatim in
Afrin".
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Ma'mûş, kî tkê mera... stranî...
Ma'mûş, who will [sing] for us... a song...
Eş...
Ash...
Tkê bi navê Mûhemmed, pir şîrîn e tkê hawo. De.
You will do "In the name of Muhammad", it is very sweet, you
will do that one. Come on.
De.
Come on.
[Sings] Navê Mûhemmed, pir şîrîn e.
[Sings] The name of Muhammad is very sweet.
[Sings] Bejna bûhiştê... şîno şerîn e.
[Sings] The stature of paradise... is green and sweet.
[Sings] Navê Mûhemmed, pir şîrîn e.
[Sings] The name of Muhammad is very sweet.
[Sings] Bejna bûhiştê... şîno şerîn e.
[Sings] The stature of paradise... is green and sweet.
Saeta te xweş.
Well done (Health to your hour).
Kekê Reşîd çend salî ye, mamû?
How old is Brother Reşîd, uncle?
Nok û du salî me. Xwedê da, nod û du salî ye.
I am ninety-two years old. God gave, ninety-two years old.
Bî nebîn, pî hesin dê?
May the evil eye not see, is the foot iron [strong]?
Erê, pîrapsal pêda, pî hesin, îşta çike.
Yes, old age on foot, foot is iron, just like that.
Aw e.
That's it.
Nimûh kêm e.
Growth is little [getting shorter/shrinking].
Ê, nimûh e.
Yeah, growth.
Te mûhawela kir te bibê textera daro?
Did you try to become a doctor of trees [herbalist/healer]?
Welle me geran, qederê em kir, me geran, tişta... şatre.
Well we walked, as much as we could, we walked, things...
skillful.
Îşaretî xwe dimol da çû, tebî'î ye.
His sign went to the mall [modernity?], it is natural.
Tebî'î, cidden, cidden, zekî ye, pir tebî'î, cidden, îşta
çişke, nimûyî xwe kêm e.
Natural, really, really, he is smart, very natural, really,
just a bit, his growth is small.
Xwedê rehetîyê pê dê, û Xwedê emrêkî dirêj pê dê.
May God give him comfort, and may God give him a long life.
Sax be.
Be healthy.
Xwedê te'altî ji gundê... sax be.
God [bless] the High... of the village... be healthy.
Milletî me her kes li Efrîn, li dîtûnî dinyayê.
Our people, everyone in Afrin, in the view of the world.
Ava xeleqa tef sêlef, wek ma gotî, li gundê Sêvya.
This episode of "Tef Sêlef", as we said, in the village of
Sêvya.
Û inşallah emê... gundên jimaraden... û jimra hîn yazmîş
kin, hîn gundî didiyê dixwazin, le kî darê be?
And God willing we will... [visit] the villages you count...
and write to us more, which other villages you want, where
should it be?
Êh şê, le bedaren, ne gundek dûr be, kî tê. Ne ho gund, le
berê ve gundî ye?
Yeah okay, but close by, let it not be a far village, who
comes. Now villages, what is in front of this village?
Êh, kemî li berê ve gundê Goliya...
Yeah, a bit in front is the village of Goliya...
Goliya jûr, Berbenê, Gundê Xofê, Ba'dîno, Gundê Dêrwiş, vê
çono giş beravê sîwarin ne.
Upper Goliya, Berbenê, Gundê Xofê, Ba'dîno, Gundê Dêrwiş,
all these directions are mounted on the riverbank [slope].
Min bolek xwedê, Kekê Reşîd. Em li wê pozî sekinîn, cem Xolê
Cemîl, min bola xo dayê, pir kîbar e, tiletî gund pir xweş
e.
I gave a look to myself, Brother Reşîd. We stood at that
peak, near Uncle Cemîl, I looked at it, it is very grand,
the view of the village is very nice.
Yanî însan, bes vîdigînê viderê, vedahesê.
Meaning a person, just seeing here, rests.
Teb'en. Neha li viderê, teqîben, bîst, pênc gundê sî gundî
hano dihazirî.
Of course. Now here, approximately, twenty, five villages,
thirty villages are present here.
Ji mûbat o do, Ereb, û gundê Hisên, Qurqo, gundê Xelîl,
Me'melo... temamî ya Ba'dîno, vê gund, na giş, avo pêyî ke.
From Mûbata (Maabatli), Arabs, and the village of Hisên,
Qurqo, village of Xelîl, Me'melo... all of Ba'dîno, this
village, all of them, follow that.
Mentîqa îtlalê xo pir bilind e.
Its viewing region is very high.
Pir xweş e.
Very nice.
E sêkkanê vê gundî çiqo ye? Teqrîben.
And what is the population of this village? Approximately.
Sêkkanê vê gundî, şêst mal e.
The population of this village is sixty houses.
Şêst mal e?
Sixty houses?
Şêst mal, gi sekan e.
Sixty houses, all inhabited.
Gi ehli gund in.
All are people of the village.
Emê şî saeta te xweş, Kekê Reşîd, qisî dikim hey te ef ke.
We also say have a good time, Brother Reşîd, I say if you
forgive/pardon.
Û tu mişkîla cem te tûne ye, vê xelqê... barê de ser
Youtube, qenetî, Hatim li Efrînê.
And you have no problem, this episode... will go on Youtube,
the channel, "Hatim in Afrin".
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Û jimra yazmîş kin, tu qusûr hene ser yazmîş kin, bîma înno
heva ewil xelqe da dikeve ser qenetî Hatim li Efrînê.
And write to us, if there are any faults write them down,
since this is the first episode being uploaded to the
channel "Hatim in Afrin".
Wek melwayî gundî Ziyaretê, gundê Sêvya, Hac... Hac Yûsif.
Like the gathering of the village of the Shrine, village of
Sêvya, Hac... Hac Yûsif.
Ziyaretkî pir xweş e, în her kes kênin werin.
It is a very nice Shrine, everyone can come.
Û jimra yazmîş kin, ko gundê dîdîyêyîn kî dixwazin, û aman
kî derê?
And write to us, which other/grandfather's villages you
want, and where should we go?
Û gi xelkê we hay ser mera yazmîş kin, aman cem. Em herin li
wa bibînin.
And all your people, write to us about them, near us. Let us
go and see them.
Saeta we xweş.
Have a good time.