Ka em bi hevra sêl kin, tev bilind û mezim bikin.
Let us elevate it together, make it all high and great.
Cilûberg adet û urfan, şûro herf û şa binêkin.
Clothes, customs and traditions, sword, letters and make
them happy.
Cilûberg adet û urfan, şûro herf û şa binêkin.
Clothes, customs and traditions, sword, letters and make
them happy.
Gund bi gund war bi war, dîtina her kesê navdar.
Village by village, place by place, seeing every famous
person.
Gund bi gund war bi war, dîtina her kesê navdar.
Village by village, place by place, seeing every famous
person.
Ka rûnin stran û lorîkan, biçêrûkin sêr û hengan.
Let's sit for songs and lullabies, graze in sights and
tunes.
Kanal a me yî xweş e... Kanal a Hatim li Efrîn.
Our channel is good... The channel of Hatim in Afrin.
Dembaş hevalên hêja, hevalên dûr û ezîz, ez hatim bi
vîdyoyekî xweş û vîdyoyekî ecêb.
Good day dear friends, distant and dear friends, I came with
a nice video and a wonderful video.
Vîdyoya min îro, ortê gundê Kêlibiyê, ta di sewran da, silav
û rêz ji şêniyê gundê Kêlibiyê ra.
My video today, inside the village of Kelibiye, in the
orchards, greetings and respect to the residents of Kelibiye
village.
Silavên me ji wa ra hene, yên bi xêr hatin, ser û çava,
kanala Hatim li Efrîn.
Our greetings to them, those who came are welcome, upon our
head and eyes, Hatim in Afrin channel.
Em îro nivandarê gundê Kêlibiyê ne, li cem bavê Zuhêr, xalê
Şêxo.
Today we are guests of Kelibiye village, at the place of
Bavê Zuhêr, uncle Şêxo.
Nasbîn jî mabeyna me da heye, nuhom hûrbîsmê hejîra ye, em ê
sozekî xweş bidin we.
There is acquaintanceship between us, now it is the fig
season, we will give you a nice promise.
Em ê bi hevra destpêkin, em ê derbasî nav baxçe bin, em ê bi
hevra hejîra berhev kin.
We will start together, we will enter the orchard, we will
harvest figs together.
Piştî em gundê Kêlibiyê jî me silavek da û me tiştek ji wa
ra sewrandin, em ê derbasî kuta bin, li wê dere jî hejîr
hene, em ê ji wa ra bisewrînin.
After we gave a greeting to Kelibiye village and filmed
something for them, we will pass to the end, there are figs
there too, we will film for them.
Berî em dest vîdyoya xwe dekin, em dibêjin silav û rêz ji
kekê Sadiq, bavê Şahan, mamosteyê me, tembîrvanê me,
dengbêjê me.
Before we start our video, we say greetings and respect to
brother Sadiq, Bavê Şahan, our teacher, our tanbur player,
our bard.
Silavên me jê ra hene, ji ortê gundê Kêlibiyê da, heta li
Cindirêsê.
Our greetings to him, from the middle of Kelibiye village,
all the way to Jinderes.
Silavên me ji kekê Behrî ra hene, ji kekê Rustem ra, ji
şêniyê gundê Kêlibiyê giya ra heye, saetên we xweş, Xwedê ji
we razî be.
Our greetings to brother Behrî, to brother Rustem, to all
the residents of Kelibiye village, have a good time, may God
be pleased with you.
Saeta hemû milletê Kurd xweş, li kî derê bin, kanala Hatim
li Efrînê, destekî bidine, destekî bi îştîrakê be, destekî
bi de'mekî be.
Good times to all the Kurdish nation, wherever they are,
give a hand to Hatim in Afrin channel, a hand with
subscription, a hand with support.
Ban dikim ban we dikim, silavê dila rêz dikim.
I call out, I call out to you, I line up heartfelt
greetings.
Ban we dikim, silavê dila rêz dikim.
I call out to you, I line up heartfelt greetings.
Dengbêj û xandavan zana, karker û cotkar hozan e.
Singers and readers are wise, workers and farmers are poets.
Hela hela, bi xêr hatin, saeta we xweş, Xwedê ji we razî be.
Hello hello, welcome, have a good time, may God be pleased
with you.
Şêxê yî bê, apê Şêxî bê, gundê Kêlibiyê, cîran û cînar mişê
bûn.
Come my Sheikh, come uncle Sheikh, Kelibiye village,
neighbors and folks were many.
Cîranê Kêlibiyê, ez dilêmame.
Neighbors of Kelibiye, I am [dilêmame].
Ebû Zuhêr, Ebû Zuhêr.
Abu Zuhêr, Abu Zuhêr.
Bavê Zuhêr, weleh me bîra te kir.
Bavê Zuhêr, by God we missed you.
Weleh me jî bîra we kiribû.
By God, we missed you too.
Ez hatim min go emê silavekê bidin.
I came, I said let's give a greeting.
Weleh min jî bîra we kiribû, weleh bîra we dikir.
By God I missed you too, by God [I] missed you.
Magot em herin cem xalê Şêxo, qehwekî vexwin, cem bavê
Zuhêr, em key hejîr naxwin jî, em ê bi hevra bibin.
We said let's go to uncle Şêxo, drink a coffee, at Bavê
Zuhêr's, even if we don't eat figs, we will be together.
Xaltîka Meyrem jî derkeve?
Should Aunt Meyrem come out too?
Belkî Meyrem vê carê çîniyê dakirî? Vê carê girîtir e.
Maybe Meyrem loaded the magazine [got angry] this time? This
time she is heavier [more serious].
Vê carê keniya me, weleh kêfa me ro...
This time our laughter, by God our joy...
Qîzika min da min, qîzika min da min.
She gave me my little girl, she gave me my little girl.
Ez nexweş bûm, ez qurban, giya maştek kirime.
I was sick, my dear, the grass gave me an allergy.
Avî giya maştek kirime, ez qurban kirim.
This grass gave me an allergy, I sacrifice myself [for you].
De werin ba min, emê bi sekinin, qehwe... emê ronin bîhna
xwe vedin, xalê xwevdana xwe kin, nû hejîra berhev kin.
Come to me, we will stand, coffee... we will sit and rest,
take our nap, then harvest figs.
Bêbê, Şêxê yî bê.
Come, my Sheikh come.
Gundê Kêlibiyê, şeş sed sal berê gundê çêbûye.
Kelibiye village, the village was built six hundred years
ago.
Şeş sed sal vê gundê betal e. Mêr e, xedar e, camêr e.
For six hundred years this village has been standing. [They
are] brave, fierce, noble.
Li pêşiya axa sekinîne, li pêşiya Fransa sekinî, herb bi
Fransa ra kirin.
They stood against the Aghas, stood against France, they
fought with France.
Em mêr in, em ne neyar in. Em heta nuka...
We are men [brave], we are not enemies. We, until now...
Em li pey mêra, û camêra, û xedara dimeşin. Em yê xirab ra
nameşin.
We follow brave men, and noble men, and fierce men. We do
not follow the bad.
Em honikî hene zanin.
We know such things.
Xwedê û yê alek, daxwaza min lê razî bin, daxwaz lê ne razî
bin.
God and the people, my wish is they be pleased, or they be
not pleased.
Tamam e.
It is done/Okay.
De we de ha, nuka çûye we de ha, çûye we de ha, nuka sebebê
germî çûye?
So the time has gone like this, gone like this... has the
cause of the heat gone now?
Weleh germ bûn... we'dê dinyayê tehet el-foq bûye.
By God it was hot... the world's time has turned upside
down.
Havîn gerek havîn be.
Summer must be summer.
Zivistan zivistan be, bihar bihar be. Têkda nemane.
Winter be winter, spring be spring. They are not distinct
anymore.
Bihar teva havînê bûye, havîn teva payîzê bûye, payîz teva
zivistanê bûye.
Spring has mixed with summer, summer has mixed with autumn,
autumn has mixed with winter.
Wextê dinyayê tehet el-foq bûye. Binî hatiye ser, ser çûye
binî.
The world's time has turned upside down. The bottom came to
the top, the top went to the bottom.
Heta çav nemezbûta, dinya hemû nemezbût e.
Until the eye is not right, the whole world is not right.
Dibê 'tarham fîl erd, yerhemkum fî sema'.
It says 'Have mercy on earth, [He] will have mercy on you in
heaven'.
Li erdê rehm tune, li asîman rehm tune.
There is no mercy on earth, there is no mercy in the sky.
Em li erdê li hevdu rehmê nakin, heta baran di wextê xwe da
barî.
We do not have mercy on each other on earth, so that rain
would fall in its time.
Germ di wextê xwe da bû, bihar di wextê xwe da bû.
Heat was in its time, spring was in its time.
Umrê min heştê û şeş sal in.
My age is eighty-six years.
Me zivistan dîtiye, me bihar dîtiye, me havîn dîtiye, me
payîz dîtiye, em berf dîtiye, me dîtî.
We have seen winter, we have seen spring, we have seen
summer, we have seen autumn, we have seen snow, we saw.
Me dîtiye çel roj berf li erdê xelas nebûye.
We have seen forty days where snow did not finish [melt] on
the ground.
Me dîtiye deh-pênc roj baran ser hev da bariye, orta mala me
digeriya.
We have seen ten-fifteen days rain poured continuously, it
was circulating in the middle of our house.
Em kanî kora bûn, baranê bisekinî.
We became blind [from waiting], for the rain to stop.
Asîmanê gewr bû, le ne ewê reş dihat ne.
The sky was grey, but the dark/black clouds were not coming.
Galegalê ne welê, le kuteq çêdibûn, masî şeş solî dihatin,
gî masiyê mezin, me dîtîye, digot nuka xêr û kerem û mişka
dera dikitix tînin.
The thunder was not like that, but banging happened, fish of
six soles came, all big fish, we saw it, saying now
blessings and grace and mice are brought out [by floods].
Av jî bila min naçe.
Water doesn't go down my throat [I can't swallow/accept this
situation].
Ne tûzik, ne mendik, ne av, ne bîr, tiştek nemaye.
No cress, no dropwort, no water, no well, nothing remains.
Weleh na wane.
By God it is not like that.
Lê?
Then?
Me kutîye, heştê sal nebes xêre, me heştê sal derbas kirin.
We finished it, eighty years is not enough good, we passed
eighty years.
Pêr rojî diyer, me xirab dîtî, me pîs dîtî, me pak jî dîtî,
me belengaz jî dîtî, me olçaq jî dîtî.
The day before yesterday was visible, we saw bad, we saw
dirty, we saw clean too, we saw poor too, we saw low too.
Heta ha valê merî mêr im, heta ha valê merî xirab im.
Until here [I am] a brave man's friend, until here [I am] a
bad man's friend.
Em nistîr û sox im.
We are [expression: thorns and weeds?].
Xwedê, eger ez sox bimirim, ez xirab namirim.
God, if I die [sox?], I won't die bad.
Li vê dinyayê, ezê herim cinetê.
In this world [afterlife], I will go to heaven.
Bi îzna Xwedê.
With God's permission.
Te nîyet pak e, tu yê herî cinetê.
Your intention is pure, you will go to heaven.
Cinet a te be, min derbas kir, cinet a te nebe, gav û gulikê
min li te kele ne.
Let heaven be yours, I passed it, if heaven is not yours, my
steps and [gulik?] are boiling for you.
Dilê no pak e.
Your heart is pure.
Ê şikir ya Rebî, hemdê te, şikir ji te ra, malê xwedê ava
be.
Oh thanks oh Lord, praise to You, thanks to You, may God's
house be prosperous.
Mala xwedê ava be, ewê kî me nîşan didin.
May God's house be prosperous, those who show us.
Rebeno.
Poor things [term of endearment].
Rebeno Xwedêyo.
Poor things, Oh God.
Ca ew piro, nexweş bî, hewldan nîne.
Oh that old one, if he is sick, there is no effort [he can't
do much].
Hewl tune. Ba'dîno, ba'dîno.
No effort?
No effort. Parsley, parsley.
Bas werin, Ebdilkerîm wî basûtê.
Just come, Abdulkarim from Basouta.
Ebdilkerîm, moyî Basûtê?
Abdulkarim, from Basouta?
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Tê nas bikî?
Do you know him?
Awa zer, zer cewher e, cewher.
This yellow, yellow is a jewel, a jewel.
Awa taze ye, taze ye, cewher e.
This is fresh, fresh, it is a jewel.
Ev zer e, ev cewher e.
This is yellow, this is a jewel.
De boye kê ca... de bu we bîta, gu a jê têr nabim.
For who... for you [bîta?], she said I can't get enough of
her.
Te go 'ez jê têr nabim'.
You said 'I can't get enough of her'.
Lo ew kûçik e.
Oh she is a [playful insult, lit: dog].
Awa na, na.
No, no.
Awa, hû, şer şerî wî je, û çûyî heyran maş kirî.
That one, oh, evil evil [?], and went my dear [mash?] done.
Wî! Efrîn bixêr û... wî Efrîn bixêr û...
Oh! Afrin is good and... oh Afrin is good and...
E rê kî sal bi xêr hatî namo.
Hey the one who came for the year welcome [namo?].
Le min go kûa te tik tokê dîtîye?
But I said where have you seen TikTok?
Awa bes seet tik tokê diseurîne.
That one just watches TikTok for hours.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Ê xaltîk, da qîzika te, te, e rûkê şil bû şil bû, bibînin e
sîretê te rabûye.
Hey auntie, give your girl, you, oh the face got wet got
wet, see your face has risen.
Mî û mî ye, û xweş...
Sheep and sheep, and nice...
Ey xelk, bes hema din, min dike û didinê...
Oh people, just give... I do and give...
Mastê mî ye.
It is sheep yogurt.
Bi rebenê reş, bi rebenê şûr, î î î î î î.
With black [reben?], with salty [reben?], ee ee ee.
Xweş e ro?
Is it good [ro?]?
Xweş e ro ortê berî bibe.
It is good in the middle before it takes.
Em tînin mast... şîr jî berdidinê.
We bring yogurt... we add milk to it too.
Şirîn dibe, m’a tehm nake.
It becomes sweet, doesn't it taste [good]?.
Hîn paşê ra tînin savarê, simeaqê, îsota tûj, îsota şîrîn,
îsota reş.
Then afterwards they bring bulgur, sumac, hot pepper, sweet
pepper, black pepper.
Heta şirîn dibe paşê.
Until it becomes sweet afterwards.
Rast e, mela canê te sax be.
True, Mullah, may your soul be healthy.
Heta ro şorbe hewal didim, dîsa bamiya hewal didim...
Until the sun... I give soup, I give okra again...
Awa ta rû şorbe hewal didim, dîsa bamyê hewal didim yare.
That one until face I give soup, I give okra again my
friend.
Erê, erê, erê.
Yes, yes, yes.
E nîsk nîne?
Are there no lentils?
Nîsk hene.
There are lentils.
Kevçî me nînin?
Don't we have spoons?
Kevçî hene.
There are spoons.
Kevçî hene?
There are spoons?
Kevçî hene.
There are spoons.
Nanê genim heye.
There is wheat bread.
Nanê genim heye, nanê ceh heye.
There is wheat bread, there is barley bread.
Hemû hene.
Everything is there.
...û hînda dîwarê xaniyê me de... çawa lo...
...and there in the wall of our house... how is it man...
Rostem, eşa emê xelqê dinyayê teva tarif kin.
Rostem, now we will describe all the people of the world.
Saetê xweş li hemûya dixe, serserê lo xalê me...
Good times befall everyone, upon the head of our uncle...
Emê xizmetê ji milet re bikin...
We will serve the nation...
Rostem re nagû... Rostem gundî Kêlîbû me... bo vîdyo bikim.
Em gundî Kêlîbû... gundê silav kim.
Don't say to Rostem... I am Rostem from Kelibu village... to
make a video. I am from Kelibu village... I greet the
village.
Rostem Behrî... ba vê Şahan...
Rostem Bahri... with this Shah (King)...
Erê... Sidqî... silavê me ji gişki ra hene...
Yes... Sidqi... our greetings to everyone...
Êmê ji qîzikê Ewropa... qîzik çiqas pirbin... ma çavê min li
qîzika ne...
For the girls of Europe... however many girls there are...
my eyes are on the girls...
Meriyê min na, meriyê min in... silavê me ji giştka ra hene.
Not my relatives, (but) they are my people... our greetings
to everyone.
Gundî Kêlîbû Şêxê...
The Sheikh of Kelibu village...
Ez çavê Ewropa, qîzik... çiqas pirbin, ez çavê gişka
radimûsim... ji bîra min naçin.
I kiss the eyes of Europe, the girls... however many they
are, I kiss all their eyes... they don't leave my mind.
Tu pîr bûye, pîr bûye...
You have become old, you have become old...
Ê min jî dilê min jî... laşê min jî, xwestiya min jî... law
milletê min jî... kurmancê gişka... tewu kurmancê gişka...
em destê gişka radimûsin.
My heart too... my body too, my desire too... oh my nation
too... all Kurds... indeed all Kurds... we kiss everyone's
hands.
Mana vîdyo...
Meaning the video...
Yalla. Hawa bîberî vîr dikim... şandina teneka da... evna
xişî em ji malê radihêlin tînin... em duxun, mîvan duxun...
şû...
Yalla. I put this pepper (?) here... sending it in the
tin... these things we bring from home... we eat, guests
eat... wash...
De pîra were. Heva hevsar e... nê pî cûte dajot.
Come on old woman. This is a headstall... used for ploughing
with a pair.
Oy havoooo... heta sêrê lê bigre.
Oh my... until hold the head of it.
Heva lûqê xanîyan e... berê xanî ax bûn...
This is a roof roller for houses... in the past houses were
made of earth...
Pê xanî wexta dilop dikirin... pê lûq dikirin... îf diketin
hevdû... heva ma'nê baran neket hundur... dilop neke.
With this, when houses were leaking... they rolled them...
they became packed together... this means rain wouldn't
enter inside... wouldn't leak.
Heva jî heva. Heva jî destar e.
This is also this. This is also a hand mill.
Heva destar e... pê nîsk, nok, genim, ceh... hindeşek (?)
kime sê... du pê dihêrin.
This is a hand mill... with it lentils, chickpeas, wheat,
barley... a handful (?)... two people grind with it.
Heva destar e... berê bvî tiştî dihêran.
This is a hand mill... in the past they ground with this
thing.
Heva jî cercer e.
This is also a threshing sled.
Wextê cercerê lê... pê sap dikutan.
At the time of the threshing sled... they crushed the straw
with it.
Heva jî çingil e... heger satilek te bikeve bîrê... tu
çengil dikî berdî bîrê... pê dikişînin. Heva jî şîş e...
This is also a hook... if your bucket falls into the well...
you hook it and drop it in the well... they pull it out.
This is also a metal rod...
Vê lûqê me sê qulê... radibirin tînin... ma'nê dilopê neke.
This roller of ours has three holes... they used to bring
it... meaning so it wouldn't leak.
Eywaaa... Miletê me yê delal, em neha jî cem Xalê Şêxo
rûniştin, me qehwa jî vexwar...
Eywaaa... Our dear nation, we are now sitting with Uncle
Shexo, we drank coffee too...
Em xwest ne sotin cem Xalê Şêxo... em silav bikin ji gundî
Kêlîbû...
We didn't want to burn (waste time?) with Uncle Shexo... we
send greetings from Kelibu village...
Xalê Şêxo ne xerîb e, nasîn jî me bi hevûdu heye... emê nika
hejîran jî berev kin.
Uncle Shexo is not a stranger, we know each other... we will
now pick figs too.
Erê erê erê erê...
Yes yes yes yes...
Bes ma'nê em pişt wakin... neha hejîr çûbûne... wekî têt li
dar da heye... emê hinekî berhev bikin.
But meaning let's clarify... now the figs are gone (season
is ending)... like what is left on the tree... we will pick
some.
Bila bîra hejîra jî kirî...
Let him remember the figs too...
Erê erê erê... Werin... Hejîr jî bîn e, em kê neha hejîra
biçinin.
Yes yes yes... Come... It's the smell of figs too, we will
pick figs now.
Erê erê erê... yalla bimeşin... De were.
Yes yes yes... let's walk... Come on.
Meyro were, Meyro were, Meyro were...
Meyro come, Meyro come, Meyro come...
Yalla... Em kê noka hejîra biçinin.
Yalla... We will pick figs now.
Aaaaay... Em naqim naqim... li şîşê... û satilê... dest xwe
dikin.
Aaaaay... We use the neq (picking tool)... on the stick...
and the bucket... we do it with our hands.
Em da em hejîra diçinin...
Here we are picking figs...
Yew weşandî ye...
That is a fallen one...
Wer babo, wer, wer, wer, wer, wer, wer, nobeq...
Come father (dear), come, come, come, come, come, come,
look...
Erê, erê, erê, erê, erê... Pê ra were.
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes... Come with him.
Were, were, were, were, heva hincas e heva.
Come, come, come, come, this is a Hincas (Pear) fig.
Hincas e?
Is it Hincas?
Erê erê erê... Emê niha çawa bikin? De de...
Yes yes yes... How will we do it now? Here here...
De de, de, de, de, de, were...
Here here, here, here, here, here, come...
De wan dayîn.
Give those.
De emke bikin vî seltikê... tiştî bikşîne.
So let's put them in this bucket... film the thing.
Noka Xalê Şêxo hejîrê tef rind mar a biçîne, kijan noqarin
da?
Now Uncle Shexo, pick the Tef (early/best?) figs for us,
which ones are the Noqar (late/hard?) ones?
Hejîrê zerik... wekî vê mûdêlê... vê mûdêlê rindtir tê hejîr
tinenin.
The yellow figs... like this model... like this model, they
don't bring better figs.
Evna dibilin leçer ji ne xalkê me ra?
Do they call these Leçer for our people?
Nebê leçerî... law dibê... didibê qişta...
Don't say Leçerî... oh he says... he says Qişta (Cream)...
Evna leçer û pir nûber bûn.
These were Leçer and very early.
Wekî vê tinen, qûrisilk (?) heva zû dibe?
They bring like this, does the Qûrisilk (?) ripen early?
Erê erê erê... Heke mirov jî mejbûr ke... û bikşîne... em
hejîra dikin.
Yes yes yes... If one forces... and pulls... we make figs.
Heva zû dibe... qûrisilk zû dibe... û diji dibe.
This one ripens early... the Qûrisilk ripens early... and it
also happens.
Erê erê erê...
Yes yes yes...
Wanoyê leçer o nîro...
Those Leçer ones today...
De... yirim (?) ez ketim çûkê xanê... her sal pirr in bûn...
So... I fell into the corner of the house... every year
there were many...
Ê ne baran neketî, telbîs tenê... wena bûn...
Since rain didn't fall, only the covering... they became
like that...
Çî çî tiştê...
What what thing...
Wa şîne erdê gune ye...
Those blue ones on the ground, it's a sin...
Em bûş nabin yûrim, em bûş nabin.
We don't become empty (useless/exhausted) dear, we don't
become empty.
Heke sê roj berî vê me kiribûna... te bibîra çirîgê ketina
erdê.
If we had done it three days before this... you would have
seen the heavy rain (?) fallen on the ground.
Xwextena... hemû jî me avêtine rehet...
Those times... we threw them all comfortably...
De mi şerm ji heyrî...
So I was ashamed of the other...
Na mere bûş bibe, were koro bike.
No, if the man becomes empty, come make him blind (?).
Hejîr, hejîr... emê hejîra dikin.
Figs, figs... we are making figs.
Haaa... Vê heva... Meriyê me heva neyê bixwara neyûrim...
Haaa... Look at this... Our people, let this not come down
dear...
Qet çito ye, xweş e?
How is it at all, is it good?
Hejîrê zereke havo... ahsen mûdêl çînî... û dibê leçer... û
dibê mîvan jî duxun.
It's the yellow fig, friend... the best model to pick... and
it's called Leçer... and guests eat it too.
Eha...
Erê, erê...
Yes, yes...
Erê tu jî vê devî xokê bixwe ha...
Yes, you eat from this mouth of the plum (?) too ha...
Hele... Heva jî... Zêrê me jî tera dişînim...
Look... This too... I send our gold/greetings to you too...
Kê bixwe... Selîm ra dişînim... Rustem ra dişînim...
Whoever eats... I send to Selim... I send to Rustem...
Necah Eynê-Twal Heleb e ne... Rêzan Heleb e... Mehremê
Heleb...
Najah Ainet-Twal is in Aleppo... Rezan is in Aleppo...
Mehrem in Aleppo...
Qîzkê xwe li Heleb e ne...
My girls are in Aleppo...
Heke satilek hejîr berhev kin...
If they pick a bucket of figs...
Bişîne Heleb.
Send it to Aleppo.
Bişînim Heleb.
I will send it to Aleppo.
Lê lê lê... Emê solînê din bişînin Heleb.
Le le le... We will send the other Solîn (vegetable
patch/greenery) to Aleppo.
Heke çû bişîne wera.
If it goes, send it there.
Haaa...
Erê, erê...
Yes, yes...
Hela yûrim erê...
Hello dear yes...
Emê biçinin, tu jî pa ra bikşîn.
We will pick, you film from behind.
Erê.
Yes.
Erê, erê, erê, erê, erê, erê...
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, yes...
Haaa...
Bibe ser mehersekî... ser bopkî xwaşî... ser mijî... ser
meyrû jî...
Take it on a Mehersek... on a good Bopik... on us... on
Meyro too...
Ku dere em le'bitîn bes bide bikşîne.
Wherever we played/worked, just give and film.
Meyro satilê hûn e...
Meyro, the bucket is yours...
Ki pa ra hûn e... em bikşînin.
That back is yours... let us film.
Hê...
He...
Erê, erê, erê, erê, erê...
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes...
Em karê dikin û ew karê dişînin... em hena hiş dikin... em
heneko... zevrezê bistanê dixun...
We do the work and they send the work... we do hiş like
this... we are like this... we eat the vegetables of the
garden...
Sekin mla were...
Wait man, come...
Mele tew re?
Man, are you confused?
Ê rind e... Hamûda Ebas fantaziyê bikirin... hamûdê tenê...
It's good... Hamuda Abbas bought a fantasy (fancy thing)...
Hamud alone...
Le le le...
Erê, erê...
Yes, yes...
Erê, erê... Meyrû ko bir dibînim.
Yes, yes... Meyro, I see some there.
Meyro ney pey şiqam daqîne.
Meyro, don't drop it after the slap (?).
Erê.
Yes.
Lê, lê, lê... Vê şîşê çiqas şeqirîkî bilind be... ez pê
tînim xwarê...
Le, le, le... However high this branch fork is... I bring it
down with this rod...
Ha bzêr sor bi sor pê zê dikê... em zê dikin... em ber hev
dikin.
Ha, look, red by red, he adds to it... we add... we gather.
Çiqas şeqim bilind be...
However high the branch is...
Şîş tîrêj e...
The rod is long...
Hawa zibistanê nîvş on tên... em jî zê dikin... çê dikin...
dixun...
This winter half of them come... we also add... make...
eat...
Em tî çê dikin... zê mîvan o... zibistanê...
We make things... for guests... in winter...
Ber êvarî şû be...
Let it be before evening...
Emê leçer o çêkin...
We will make Leçer...
Erê.
Yes.
Hejîrê hişkê bixun...
Eat dried figs...
Lê, lê, lê... Şîşê me dirêj e...
Le, le, le... Our rod is long...
Em dînib... em bi xwe tînin... Êd bilind...
We see... we bring it ourselves... The high ones...
Em zê dikin.
We add (gather) them.
Haaaaa...
Lê...
Le...
Emkê vîdyokî çêkin mela Ewropa...
We will make a video for Europe...
O Amerîka... Latînî... Şerq û Xerb... giştkî li ma binerin.
And America... Latin [America]... East and West... let
everyone watch us.
Mla gî bibîne.
Let everyone see.
Emê hejîr... hejîrê bînin... emê hejîra biçinin.
We will figs... bring figs... we will pick figs.
Dê...
So...
Hawa geş... gişka rindtir derê.
This bright one... comes out better than all.
Hetka teyîn hebe bişewitîne hela...
If there is a sun, let it burn, hey...
Bixwe bixwe...
Eat eat...
Emê hejîra biçinin.
We are picking figs.
Êbî me hejîr nexwar.
Oh my, we didn't eat figs.
Erê, erê, erê...
Yes, yes, yes...
Hela Sadiq...
Hey Sadiq...
Erê, erê, erê, erê, erê... Giştk dibin.
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes... They all ripen.
Evlo... êk me netîn e... vî zestî da man e kevn e xwarin.
Evlo... the one we didn't bring... stayed in this zest (?),
it's old food.
Êkê zûr destî me ne... tiştî dkevin...
The one under our hand... things fall...
Hamûda heba... noka meya bişanda... ser mla... rol ser...
If Hamuda was here... now we would have sent... on the
man... role on...
Kû av duxuriya.
Where water was drunk.
Weysetî nate.
It doesn't come to his will.
Wer vêş avêt... o wî ye...
Yes.
Come throw this too... and it is his...
Wa la ma'sîmî jarkî yûti boş nobê.
Oh man, the innocent one once... let him not be empty.
Erê... lo bixun, bixun, bixun, bixun.
Yes... man eat, eat, eat, eat.
Vê hejîrê... te ra dîn e... ma ra noxwe.
This fig... I saw for you... don't eat for us.
Bxwe we...
Eat it man...
Hawa tiştê şêxî yî be... xoş, helal be... kî bixwe... li wî
helal.
This is a Sheikh's thing... good, be halal... whoever
eats... halal to him.
Kî dixwe mla bixwe.
Whoever eats, let him eat.
Tiştî mijiye qopîm... jar o çeqa.
A thing of mine... (unclear)... poor and (unclear).
Kî tiştî min...
Who my thing...
De jeleke.
So hurry.
Hela vê hejîrê devî xokê... vê hejîrê devî xokê hela
derdikeve, hewa ye şîrîn e.
Look at this fig of the plum's mouth... this fig of the
plum's mouth is coming out, this is the sweet one.
He...
Ah...
Lê...
Le...
Erê, erê, erê, erê, erê...
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes...
Tiştekî em ora dikin... ew karê dişînin... em hena hiş
dikin... em heneko...
Something we do there... they send that work... we do hiş
like this... we are like this...
Zevrezê bistanê dixun.
We eat the vegetables of the garden.
Erê, erê, erê.
Yes, yes, yes.
Wa bidê hevalo.
Oh give it friend.
Afikrim, afikrim, afikrim.
Bravo, bravo, bravo.
Ewa...
Ewa, hincas ew ay ewa.
Ewa, that is Hincas (pear) fig, ay that one.
Tekû vê, vê hejîrê, hewa wekî vayoljîr e.
Look at this, this fig, this is like a Vayol (?) fig.
Wana binî bera bigre, wana binî bera... wana...
Catch those bottom ones, those bottom ones... those...
Wer, wer, rind bikşîn.
Come, come, film well.
Êwa...
Afikrim.
Bravo.
Afikrim, afikrim, afikrim.
Bravo, bravo, bravo.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
De bes bikşîn.
Okay enough filming.
Maşînê bîb... sêrin bîb... serincê hey rî mir mir...
The machine... (unclear) look... (unclear).
Îşê xu bar mede.
Don't give up your work.
Xeta we berê aw naçe, ew noga nema.
Your line didn't go that way before, that turn is gone.
Erê, erê, erê.
Yes, yes, yes.
Lê haydê.
Come on then.
Erdê kul e nobe, erdê kul e nobe.
The land is full of holes, wait, the land is full of holes,
wait.
Li erdê zad têra. Bêy av o zad têra.
Crops grow on the land. Crops grow without water.
Ha bo zad têra, wî çibikim şêrî.
See, crops grow, what should I do with the lion (brave one).
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Yo zad têra, bêy av em qet nake.
Crops grow, without water we don't do it at all.
Av mezin naha her sal tijî tijî dimîne, ke xelkê telbîs
dikin.
The big water stays full every year now, that people cover
up.
Heke nebe zad, wê çawa be?
If there are no crops, how will it be?
Haş in.
Peace.
Haş in û belaș in.
Peace and free of trouble.
Rehet bin.
Be comfortable.
Were, were, were. Bavo, bavo, bavo, were, bixun.
Come, come, come. Father, father, father, come, calm down.
Ne, ne, ne.
No, no, no.
Tu mezinê gundî, ne l'ser sînoran, ne l'ser tiştan, rêkî wa,
elîkî wa.
You are the elder of the village, not over borders, not over
things, your way, your side.
Erê.
Yes.
Haş û belaș in.
Peace and free of trouble.
Xalî Şêxo, tu nawaye...
Uncle Shekho, you are not like that...
Cima ra qopîkê xoyî şîrin, tu feqîrî, hikûmetî me kirmancî
wye, ne bes Xalî Şêxo kuta hara, hemî kirmancî, yanî dilê me
pê ve.
For the community, your sweet cap, you are poor, our
government is Kurdish like that, not just Uncle Shekho going
anywhere, all Kurds, meaning our hearts are with it.
Doğrî ye, doğrî ye, doğrî ye...
It's true, it's true, it's true...
Hopîk gyo zehwra çiqe.
Hopik went to the oleander (poison) branch.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Qurban ke zehwra qurban te.
Sacrifice to the oleander, I sacrifice for you.
Erê keko, erê.
Yes brother, yes.
Oy, yabo yabo.
Oh, father father.
Oy yabo yabo.
Oh father father.
Wey nînê, wey nînê.
Oh mother, oh mother.
De were, de were.
Come on, come on.
Roj gelek eşk bî, yorem tiş namîne, mo guneh.
The day was very painful, my dear nothing remains, it's a
sin.
Baran têne.
Rain is coming.
Vê telbîs dikinê.
They are covering it up.
Canik merivê Hecî Xaşo ne, pîrek a Hecî Xaşo ne...
The lady is Haji Khasho's relative, Haji Khasho's wife...
Heke mofik a, wer bê min ji te na xwum, na, na.
If it's a joint (bone), come say I won't eat from you, no,
no.
Cem'a, Xalî Şêxo yê bi nav û deng e, mirovê gelekî qenc e.
Community, Uncle Shekho is famous, a very good man.
Xalî Şêxo tu kirmanc î.
Uncle Shekho, you are a Kurd.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Cem'a, Hecî Rehan, Hecî Rehan jina Xalî Şêxo ye.
Community, Haji Rehan, Haji Rehan is Uncle Shekho's wife.
Cem'a bibînin, bes bibînin kanî çi dibêje me.
Community look, just see what he tells us.
Bêje, neynik tenê na xwin.
Say it, they don't eat only lentils.
Bibînin hejîrêt wan, di wextê hejîran da ne.
See their figs, they are in the time of figs.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Hejîr me çinîn. Emê îro ta danê sersê, emkê vexwin.
We picked figs. Today until the afternoon, we will consume
them.
Emê ava hênik vexwin, ava bîra, şerab e.
We will drink cool water, well water, it is wine.
De, de, de, de.
Come, come, come, come.
Ax, ax.
Oh, oh.
Hadar we hat, w'e bixwe pişo.
Your relief has come, eat it cat.
Du sal te Xalî Şêxo maye, bes milet bigihîne.
Two years Uncle Shekho remained, just to reach the people.
Erê.
Yes.
Du ha sene melê niri...
Two years...
Hîç aqilê xo yê rehet zekî ne.
His mind is not comfortable/clear at all.
Wele baqil, dibê bibî cind û, dibê cind û, dibê tir e.
By God smart, he says be a jinn (crazy), he says jinn, he
says it's a fart.
Dibê cin û cin û, dibê tir û tir û, şorr û tir û, kûk menî
noyî we, tir û tir û dibê.
He says jinn and jinn, he says fart and fart, salty and
fart, root means nothing like that, fart and fart he says.
Tir û tir û dibê.
Fart and fart he says.
Hîç aqilê wî ne li gogê ye.
His mind is not in place at all.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Ne.
No.
Na, mela heben, mela.
No, let the mullahs have it, mullahs.
Bes mela heben, mela çavî rik bin.
Just let the mullahs have it, let the mullahs be envious.
Eyno li me şêr ke...
Eyno look at us...
...hela li me şêr ke, yabo.
...hey look at us, father.
Eyno li me şêr ke, cindî kîfş e, şêxê îbe.
Eyno look at us, the jinn is visible, Sheikh Ibe.
...Najoh, Belantîn, Zekî, Qicik, Cûcik, Mezin, Mehrem...
...Najoh, Valentine, Zeki, Small, Tiny, Big, Mahram...
Pismam, ehlen we sehlen...
Cousin, welcome...
Heta we giya xoş.
May all your time be happy.
Ehlen we sehlen, se'eta we giya xoş.
Welcome, may all your hours be happy.
Wer qîza xû, apê xû.
Come my daughter, my uncle.
Wer, wer apê me.
Come, come our uncle.
Ya na nanê te me, sar nebû.
Oh no, I am your bread, it didn't get cold.
Erê yabo.
Yes father.
Nizam xawra bî we bîyo.
I don't know if the dream was like that.
Xawra bî we.
The dream was that.
Ewa, ewa jî we mîrtir e, ewa, ewa, ha.
That one, that one is more emir-like (noble), that one, that
one, ha.
Ka, ka.
Where, where.
Ewa vî avê, ba'dîno xwarî, wîj sê şa'bî...
That one this water, ate the Badini (dialect/people?), he
too three Shabis...
Lê babo.
Oh father.
Ma vî ba'dîno xwarî, bîj tê şa'bî ma.
Did he eat this Badini, say you are our Shabi.
Ha, ha.
Hildo girêde, cerê kelomê hildo girêde...
Lift and tie, lift and tie the jar of words/songs...
Mezinê herî qemca.
The elder of the best ones.
Lê lê lê lê...
Le le le le...
Hop, hop, hop, hop, lê lê lê...
Hop, hop, hop, hop, le le le...
E lê lê, lê lê lê, lê lê lê, lê lê lê...
E le le, le le le, le le le, le le le...
Wele kefxweş bûn, hûn pir hatin sefayê.
By God we were happy, you came with great pleasure.
Ne, de kefxweş bin.
No, be happy.
Ne kefxweş bî, bila dilê te xweş bî.
If not happy, let your heart be happy.
Gelo biftale mala xwe, xwedê deste xwe ser gora bigre.
Let him return to his home, may God hold his hand over the
grave.
Ar zê, keze bînî jî cûcik jî mezin şîrîn tire.
Ar Ze, guys look, the small one is also sweeter than the big
one.
Xêr e welle.
It is good, by God.
Ewa keze wî keze we ye.
That guy is your guy.
Hinek dibêjin hela ew qaşîrê, ew pîs ka şîrîn e.
Some say hey that peel, that dirty one is sweet.
Dibêjin, keze wî keze be şîrîn e, keze wî keze be şîrîn e.
They say, that guy that guy is sweet, that guy that guy is
sweet.
Erê.
Yes.
Her kes ewladê xwe pê şîrîn e.
Everyone finds their own child sweet.
Erê.
Yes.
Am baba, ba ba ba ba ba.
My father, fa fa fa fa fa.
Ha.
Babo ma.
Our father.
Wer babo were.
Come father come.
No vî cûcik mera pêbiniye, xwedê kî zar mera pê tessela
dibê, xem xeyalê xo mera di revîne.
Now this small one appears to us, God who makes the child a
comfort for us, chases away our worries and dreams.
Me hesabê kîr ve dike, can çûke.
He settles accounts with us, life is small.
Eeeee...
Xwedê sa'eta we xoş ket, xwedê ji we razî ket.
May God make your hour happy, may God be pleased with you.
Xwedê sa'eta xweş da de, xwedê canikî sağ da de.
God gave a happy hour, God gave a healthy life.
Alê baba, alê, xwedê wa bêlê.
Go father, go, may God leave/keep you.
Em no sikan, silavê me li gora ne.
We don't stop, our greetings to the graves.
Em tim hisê wa bikin.
We always feel/hear them.
Sa'eta we giya xoş, bay bay, gula gula, oxir be.
May all your hours be happy, bye bye, roses roses, farewell.
Xwedê we bihêle, xwedê temen dirêj bike.
May God keep you, may God give you long life.
Qurban sa'eta we.
Sacrifice for your hour.
Oxir be, oxir be.
Farewell, farewell.
Oxir be.
Farewell.
Oxir be, bixatin.
Farewell, welcome.
Oxir be, oxir be, oxir be, oxir be, xatirê we.
Farewell, farewell, farewell, farewell, goodbye.
Xwedê we bihêle.
May God keep you.
Kerem kin, kerem kin.
Welcome, welcome (Please come in).
Xwedê we bihêle.
May God keep you.
Em pir kêfxweş bûn, hun hatin...
We were very happy, you came...
Hûn pir kêfxweş bûn.
You were very happy.
Em pir kêfxweş bûn.
We were very happy.
[Music]
Roj baş.
Good day.
Hela we sehlen, birê xalî.
Welcome, dear brother.
Tu çawayî?
How are you?
Îşê te çawaye?
How is your work?
Welle elhemdulîlah, tu çawayî?
By God praise be to God, how are you?
Welle elhemdulîlah, îşê te çawaye?
By God praise be to God, how is your work?
Xwedê quwetê bide te, xwedê sihetê xweş bide te, hem dîsa
hatin cem te.
May God give you strength, may God give you good health, we
came to you again.
Hela û sehlen, ser ser û ser çava.
Welcome, upon the head and upon the eyes.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Îbo îjarê çin te selqên me darket? Em dibêjin sa'eta te xoş,
pir xelqê xoş bî te lîstikê kirî.
Ibo, this time what baskets did we get? We say may your hour
be happy, the people were very happy with the game you
played.
Em jî mîna xelkê ne, em nativîne li ser xelqê, xelkê mîna me
ye.
We are also like the people, we don't put ourselves above
the people, the people are like us.
Welle, dîtina şerefa kî mezin e.
By God, seeing is a great honor.
Welleh, şeref ya me ye, gelekî şeref in, jimarê jî gelekî...
By God, the honor is ours, very honorable, the number is
also very...
Xurtê dima ewlemrê xo milo.
Young men always put their life on the shoulder.
Belê, em naha hatin, şoxul na eyb e, pir karekî rind e, em
hûr û nîvandorê gundî kêlû bibîn, me hejîr cêkirin.
Yes, we came now, work is not shameful, it's a very good
job, we see the small and middling ones of the Kelu village,
we prepared figs.
Lê belê em ne hatin e, em sekin, hela maşallah meydiyet te
hejîr gîre xist.
But we didn't come, let's stop, wow Mashallah the
materiality/amount of figs you got.
Kêş mera xeber de, tu kîlo tu di kirê, li te jê dikê, li
dare duhene...
Tell us a bit, the kilo you buy, you pick, on the tree...
Welle bi xû dare me tinen, em giyê di dorme da ne, ew jî
tiştek yek fuqara tê de heye, yek hejîrê xo berrekî dixwe.
Well we don't have trees ourselves, we are all in the
surrounding area, there is also something for the poor in
it, one eats their fig for a blessing.
Xwedê vanan de suqlal bike.
May God make these prosperous.
Îbo tukîlî van bi çi dikirê?
Ibo, how much do you buy a kilo of these for?
Welle ji deh û pêncî da hene heta bîstî.
Well, there are from 10.50 up to 20.
Deh û pênc, bîst, heta sî werexist, ji sûqê lo dikirê, tînî
rê dixê.
10.5, 20, up to 30 spread out, buying from the market,
bringing and putting on the way.
Piştî hişk bîn te kîlo bi çi difroşe?
After they dry, how much do you sell a kilo for?
Xwedê neke haliyan, terbiyem nabêlê, heştê da heye heta sed
û bîst û pênc.
God forbid the situation, my manners don't allow, from 80 up
to 125.
Ê rind sed û bîst û pênc, sed û sî, teybet rind davan e.
The good ones 125, 130, the special good ones go.
Hesebe.
Calculated.
A balê xwe didimê, tu yê berbistê ra jî te hêjîra te raxistî
te hişk dikî.
I see you laid out the figs in the open space too, you are
drying them.
Hemî bi destê xwe dikim, xwedê qewet ke, xwedê qewet ke badî
jî.
I do it all by hand, may God give strength, may God give
strength after this too.
Xwedê ji te razî be, xwedê sihetê xweş bide te, rizqê te
bişîne.
May God be pleased with you, may God give you good health,
send your sustenance.
Îbo derveyî hêjîra jî, zorî çîna hatin bîstan, pir bûn îsal?
Ibo, besides figs, did much trouble come to the orchards,
were they many this year?
Yanê wek 2020 bîstan veçandirna dine gihandin bi zirara
bîstênkî.
Meaning like 2020, did the orchards reach a different
transplanting with orchard damage?
Welle pir zirar pê ket, pir, me tuxtir dar îna mendiz,
nobedarê xiyanet bî go fêke mesel.
By God lots of damage happened, lots, we brought doctor
medicine, the guard was treacherous regarding the fruit for
example.
Ba ser da hat û me qe tesîr pê nekir ku gih şewitand.
Wind came upon it and we had no effect on it that it burned
all.
Ez balê xwe didimê, cewê bacanên sor, giya te'sîra bayê ye.
I see, the row of red tomatoes, it's all the effect of the
wind.
Te'sîra bayê ye.
It's the effect of the wind.
Xwedê rizqê we bişîne.
May God send your sustenance.
Dîsa kî dibên emrê xwedê l'ser ser û ser çava.
Again we say God's command is upon the head and upon the
eyes.
Nika li ser piştî te hêjîr jî, te sikalor te dikirî û te
tînî te hişk dikî.
Now regarding the figs, you buy 'sikalor' (fresh figs) and
bring and dry them.
Belê.
Yes.
Piştî te hişk kir jî, kîlo te go ji heştê heta sed û bîst û
pênc derê.
After you dry them, you said the kilo goes from 80 to 125.
Îbo nehwî tev rind, me'na hişkkirinê, kîjan nehwî rind e?
Ibo, the best type, meaning for drying, which type is good?
Bi xwa yên kundirkî av ne. Wanê di nav rind dibin.
The 'kundirki' ones are juicy. They become good inside.
Sêke wanê zern in jî, vanê kundirkî çêtr in.
Look the yellow ones too, these 'kundirki' are better.
Wanê zern in jî, vanê kundirkî çêtr in.
The yellow ones too, these 'kundirki' are better.
Baş e, piştî te sikalor anî te kirî, kar dikeviyê şolê?
Okay, after you bring and buy sikalor, is there profit in
the work?
Welle elhemdulilah tiştek kar jî heye. Ê karê neke zirarê jî
nake.
By God praise God there is some profit. If it doesn't
profit, it doesn't harm.
Ege zirarê jî neke, karê jî nake.
If it doesn't harm, it doesn't profit (meaning it's
balanced).
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê rizqê we bide.
God give you sustenance.
Xwedê zirarê nede kesî, hînî rehet bibin.
God give harm to no one, may you be comfortable.
Xwedê berê bîstên ra, hînî hejîra jî hawdikin, hişk dikin,
xwedê sa'eta xweş bide.
God grant to the orchards, you treat the figs too, dry them,
God give a happy hour.
Bide jî.
Give it too.
Hûn çawa hişk dikin?
How do you dry them?
Xwedê ewa ro, am radixin.
God, that sun, we lay them out.
Tênî ro, duxa nîro da, l'ser serî kenda am giya di
qulipînin.
Sun comes, until noon, on top of the slope we turn them all
over.
Ew jî teqrîben heta pênc roja dajo.
That also takes approximately up to five days.
Pênc ro geh heta hişk bibin.
Five days until they get dry.
Ab ro dikin, ya em sehara didinîn.
We put them in the sun, or we put them on crates.
Xer em dermanax difroşin, em banîka nakin.
But we sell without medicine, we don't do the roof/storage
method (with chemicals).
Hinek dibên banîka ro dikin, hinek dibên bes dikin sehara.
Some say they do the roof method, some say they just put on
crates.
Waxtê dikin sehara, em dikepsinin lê.
When they put on crates, we press them then.
Na em tey em dikepsinin.
No we specifically press them.
Piştî wa kir sehara, hin nayênin, na em far dikin.
After doing on crates, some don't bring, no we package/sort
them.
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê rizqê we bide.
God give you sustenance.
Xwedê sa'eta xweş bide.
God give a happy hour.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
God be pleased with you.
Xwedê te jî bişîne, ya rebî.
God send to you too, oh Lord.
Em pir kêfxweş bûn, hun hatin, me silavek jî da te, em piçik
hejîra jî bişidînin.
We were very happy, you came, we gave you a greeting too,
let's tighten/pack a few figs too.
Neha mewsimê hejîra ye, xelk hejîrê xwe radike.
Now is the season of figs, people are harvesting their figs.
Me got em miletê xwe re muşarek kin.
We said let's share with our people.
...û me çil gundî xelîl, w maşdara çêkir.
...and we emptied forty villages, and made the drying racks.
Lê niha, ema tefedelî jê, em pîç xelkê kin bila bibînin,
hino ehwal yan divê tiştek em rabidibin.
But now, please go ahead, let us show the people a bit so
they can see, some situations or if something is needed we
raise it.
Ya gûz bin, gibeiv bin, em karê xwe dikin.
Whether walnuts or almonds, we do our work.
Ewa şerefe kîj me ra, xêre, ewa şuxlî me ra ye.
That is an honor for us, it is good, this is our work.
Walê merî şuxul neke, merî malê çepelxiyê bike, ewa ne
tiştek e.
By God, if one doesn't work, if one does dirty things to
property, that is worth nothing.
Elhemdulilah em giyê dikin, bîstan e, ef ejîr e.
Praise God we do it all, orchard, these figs.
Weke te re derjiye elhemdulilah gişt e.
As it has appeared to you, praise God it is everything.
Sewran!
Sewran! [Greeting]
Sewran.
Ti çawa yî?
How are you?
Tiştê hewa dimsî me ye, he, amade boşter vir dikin.
This thing is our molasses, yes, we serve it better/more
ready here.
Ştewî hewa me ci, ma bixwe çêkirî vê ciyê?
Is this your production, did you make it yourself in this
place?
Elhemdulilah jî em vî îşî kêfxweş in ha teyiban, weke ona em
xizmet miletê xwe dikin.
Praise God we are happy with this work, good ones, like this
we serve our people.
Miletê me jî elhemdulilah teqsîrî ji me ra nakin e, xwedê
pêxember jî wa razî be.
Our people also, praise God, do not fall short with us, may
God and the Prophet be pleased with them.
Tiştê ev ne ejîrê te hişk kin?
Are these not the figs you are drying?
Ba'dê wa ji vir rakirin hîn tînin vir kûm dikin?
After removing them from here, do you bring them here and
pile them?
Belê, em vir kûm dikin şev şev van ber... ne bivore...
bivore kûrtin e bivore.
Yes, we pile them here night by night... with a cover...
covering them with a cover.
Tiştê em ejîrê xor tesfiye dikin heta yekê dudya, tiştê em
kurê xwe no derbas dikin way me hana derbas nekin.
We filter/sort our figs one by one or two by two, we don't
pass anything to our sons that we wouldn't pass [for
ourselves].
Û pişî niha we hana kirin sehare î bû hîn bi kîlo te go dorê
heştê heta sedî difroşin.
And after you did this like this, it became a crate, you
said you sell it by kilo around eighty to a hundred.
Heta sedî, sedî sîst.
Up to a hundred, a hundred and sixty.
Û min bala xwe dayê, berê hînî dim jî çêdikin.
And I noticed, before you were making molasses too.
Dimis neyî kelandî ye hewa î be'cona.
Molasses is not boiled, this is of tomatoes.
Î kelandî ye?
Is it boiled?
Na î kelandî ye, ê berû ye.
It is not boiled, it is sun-dried.
Ê berû ye?
It is sun-dried?
Ê berû ye ji wele ez pê fahm nakim, tîrê ma pê fahm dike
wele.
It is sun-dried, honestly I don't understand it, our old
woman [wife/mother] understands it honestly.
Ewna jinik karê jinê ye.
Those are women, it's women's work.
Îbo... ba'cona hîn ji ê wa jê dikin?
Ibo... tomatoes, do you remove [skin/seeds] from them?
Û bi desta av dikin û rê dixin w darê...
And with hands they make juice and put it on the wood...
Na bi desta, ew hay makîneyê gind e.
No not with hands, that is their machine.
Em makîneyê dixin?
Do we put it in the machine?
Paşî çûpî ginde bi desta ê ştewî avê gije didin dirvê?
Then their pulp with hands... giving the juice outside?
Avê ginde em didin ber wa.
Their juice we put before them [in the sun].
Û berû ye?
And sun-dried?
Û berû ye.
And sun-dried.
Çend ro li berû ye dimîne?
How many days does it stay in the sun?
Wele heta heft roke, deh ro wele berû ye dimîne, bes tayib
eva kemiye ye o.
Honestly up to seven days, ten days honestly it stays in the
sun, but okay this is 'kemiye' [quantity/bulk].
Kemiye?
Quantity?
Kemiye.
Quantity.
Û piştî wê jî hînî têkin qatremîza w a ji bo firotinê.
And after that you put it in jars for selling.
Qatremîza erê.
Jars yes.
Xwedê rizqê we bide.
May God give you sustenance.
Sax be, ser ser û ser çava.
Thanks, on my head and eyes [You're welcome].
Wekî dibêjin hînî radibin li ser karê xwe l nav milkê xwe.
As they say you stand over your work inside your property.
Ser serî min in.
You are on my head [Welcome].
Xwedê ji we razî be, û em pir kêfxweş bûn em îro mêvan bûn
li cem te, berê em carkê hatin.
May God be pleased with you, and we were very happy we were
guests today at your place, before we came once.
Û inşalla emê tim herin werin, û çi emirta, çi gotina te
heye, dîsa xwestî te ji kebîrê gund re, ji babê re?
And God willing we will always come and go, and whatever
command, whatever word you have, again your request to the
village elder, to the father?
Vê silavê ji Xelîl re ye.
This greeting is to Khalil.
Xelîl.
Khalil.
Qanata şebab gan iştîrak kin, eyb e ji we re o.
Subscribe to the guys' channel, it's a shame for you [if you
don't].
Em kêp çixwe soyîn noka...
We want to raise our cap [subs] now...
Noka em pêncû... pênc sed û hinek in e.
Now we are fifty... five hundred and some.
Ecele kin, em kêp bîst hezarî kin şebab.
Hurry up, let's make the cap twenty thousand guys.
Em bi bes bîst a gînin, em kê...
If we just reach twenty, we will...
Salek şingil, heflek çêkim ji miletê xwe re.
A shingil hall [party], I will make a party for my people.
Ekîd, ekîd.
Sure, sure.
Yekî derketî ser qenatê Hotim El Efrîn gî me'zûm ne, kal û
pîrek gî me'zûm ne inşalla.
Anyone who appeared on the channel Hatim Al-Afrin is
invited, old men and old women are all invited God willing.
Bes emî bighên bîst hezarî.
Just let us reach twenty thousand.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Miletî ma wey Efrîn... iştîrak kin miletî ma warapo! Iştîrak
kin.
Our people of Afrin... subscribe our people come on!
Subscribe.
Xwedê ji te razî be, Îbo em pir kêfxweş bûn, xwedê ji te
razî be brakê min.
God be pleased with you, Ibo we were very happy, God be
pleased with you my brother.
Xwedê rizqê we bideşîne û hînî li ser milkê xwe radibin û em
pir kêfxweş bûn.
May God send your sustenance and you stand over your
property and we were very happy.
Hûrû em derbasî gundê Kêlîbûyî pişî we tma' silavek ji do
wa.
Today we passed to the village of Kelibuyi after you... a
greeting to them.
Ya selaam.
Oh peace [Great].
Le'no me dît î hejîra jî hişk dike.
Because we saw he dries figs too.
Tebe'n eva karê me ye.
Of course this is our work.
Xwedê ji te razî be û niha jî me xatirê xwe ji te xwest.
God be pleased with you and now we asked for your leave
[said goodbye].
Sax be, oxir be.
Thanks, farewell.
Miletê kibar û delal saeta we xweş, hîn bi me re bûn heta
tûlî vîdyom herû vîdyokê xwe... ona derbaskir, em çûn
derbasî gundê Kêlîbû bûn.
Noble and dear people, have a good time, you were with us
until the length of the video today... passed like that, we
went and passed to the village of Kelibuyi.
Xalê Şêxo ji me re hejîr kirin, saeta ginde xweş, destê
ginde sax be, xwedê emrêkî dirêj bide.
Uncle Sheikho made figs for us, may their time be good, may
their hands be healthy, may God give a long life.
Û piştî wê jî em jam derbasî jam Kekê Îbo bûn me... ji we
re... sewran çû hejîra hişk dikê.
And after that we passed to Brother Ibo's place... for
you... sawran went drying figs.
Niho l cem ginde kemiye pirre xêre le'no ginde ji sûqlor
dikire tînê.
Now at their place the quantity is a lot, it is good because
they buy from the markets and bring.
Ne wekî darek tedidit hebin te hişk bike, kemiye pir dikire
tînê hişk dike wek wadiye.
Not like you have one or two trees you dry, he buys a lot of
quantity brings and dries like a valley.
Saeta we xweş, xwedê ji we razî be, û bîr mekin qenatê Hotim
El Efrîn da'm kin.
Have a good time, God be pleased with you, and don't forget
to support the channel Hatim Al-Afrin.
Me da'm kin me la bîst hezarî gîna nîzîk da inşalla ezê
heflek turasiye, dawetî Efrînda ji we re çêkim.
Support us, we are near reaching twenty thousand God willing
I will make a traditional party, an Afrin wedding for you.
Saeta we xweş û xwedê ji we razî be, û hîn bimînin xêr û
xweşiyê de.
Have a good time and God be pleased with you, and remain in
goodness and happiness.