[Music starts]
[Mûzîk dest pê dike]
Yek li vê derê wan nîzik e, ay. Û bîrek li derê hanê, ava wê
derê bîra avzê ye.
One of them is close to here, yes. And there is a well over
there, the water of that well is swamp water.
Got meta Aslan e? Kekê Aslan şêr e, silav dikim.
Did they say it's Aunt Aslan? Brother Aslan is a lion, I
greet him.
Lê bes vî qisletî, xirûqonetî gerek, mistaqbel gerek...
[bêfêmkirin] kulfet xedar dike. Hêvî û hesreta min ew e ez
nabînim. Axbarê gundê...
But this nature, strange things are needed, a future is
needed... [unintelligible] the family acts cruelly. My hope
and longing is that I won't see... The news of the
village...
E pîr bûn, bêdengî xweska min deke. Xweşî... Emlet...
They got old, silence makes my wish. Happiness... Life...
[Song] Hêvya te bûn, temen...
[Song] They were your hope, age...
[Song] Bûye bîranîn... Tu xweyî li min...
[Song] Has become a memory... You are my owner...
Merheba miletê kîbar û delal. Ez hatim bi vîdyoyekî xweş û
vîdyoyekî ecêb. Dîdîk min hûrû li gundê Kutanê ye. Em
mîvandarê gundê Kutanê ne.
Hello noble and dear people. I have come with a nice video
and a wonderful video. My meeting today is in the village of
Kutan. We are guests of the village of Kutan.
Em cem Kekê Hemûdê mistaqbal kirin, Bavê Cebel. Xwedê jê
razî be û silav û rêz ji şêniyê gundê Kutanê re. Hûn bi
dilekî xweş û geş, hemî derbasî gundê Kutanê bin.
We were welcomed by Brother Hamud, Father of Cebel. May God
be pleased with him, and greetings and respect to the
inhabitants of Kutan village. With a happy and bright heart,
may you all enter the village of Kutan.
[Song] Ne kul û derdên te...
[Song] Neither your wounds and troubles...
[Song] Ne naz û xemên te... Na na ez nakşînim...
[Song] Nor your coquetry and griefs... No, no I won't bear
them...
[Song] Ne tas û şaba te... Ne nan û... Wele ez naxwazim...
[Song] Neither your bowl and dinner... Nor bread and... I
swear I don't want...
[Song] Ne kul û derdên te... Ne naz û xemên te... Na na ez
nakşînim...
[Song] Neither your wounds and troubles... Nor your coquetry
and griefs... No, no I won't bear them...
[Song] Ne tas û şaba te... Ne nan û... Wele ez naxwazim...
[Song] Neither your bowl and dinner... Nor bread and... I
swear I don't want...
Ehlên û sehlên.
Welcome.
Ehlên û sehlên, merheba.
Welcome, hello.
Navê te bi xêr?
Your name, please?
Abdulhemîd Şêxo.
Abdulhamid Shekho.
Abdulhemîd Şêxo. Bavê...?
Abdulhamid Shekho. Father of...?
Şêxo ye. Bavê Şêxo.
Is Shekho. Father of Shekho.
Tu xweşî gundê Kutanê ye?
Are you a native of Kutan village?
Eywa.
Yes.
Çend salî ye?
How old are you?
Wele heştê û sê salim e. Tewalîdê çil û du yim e.
Well, I am eighty-three years old. I am the birth year of
forty-two.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bide û siheta xweş bide.
May God give long life and good health.
Serata te xweş be, spas.
May your head be well, thanks.
Ez Xelîl ji gundê Baedîna, ji qenatê hatim, îro em mîvandarê
gundê Kutanê ne.
I am Xelîl from the village of Baedîna, from the channel I
came, today we are guests of Kutan village.
Ehlên û sehlên. Em jî bi şêwe kêfxweş bûn. Qismetî we bûye
hûn hatine.
Welcome. We are also happy in a way. It was your destiny
that you came.
Xwedê ji te razî be. Ez dixwazim tiştekî ser gundê Kutanê ji
me ra deng key. Berê we çi kar pir dikir? Yan çawa radibûn?
We rojê xwe çawa derbas dikir?
May God be pleased with you. I want you to tell us something
about the village of Kutan. What work did you do most in the
past? Or how did you live? How did you pass your day?
Eştera xeber dim, berê we, ekanim bibêm bi pêncî salî...
I will speak plainly, in the past, I can say fifty years
ago...
Emrê min heşt salî bû, çend bû, me çi dîye û çûnê me şîne...
My age was eight years, or whatever, what we saw and how we
went...
Li vê derê weçaxê makîna pir tune bûn, ga dewar bûn.
In this place at that time there weren't many machines,
there were oxen and cattle.
Pa'le, zeytûn pir tune bûn, hindik bûn.
Laborers, olives weren't many, they were few.
Pa'le meselen cût bi dêwêr bû.
Laborers, for example, plowing was with cattle.
Diftilin, diçinin bi desta.
They would go around, harvest by hand.
Dişon, dîsa bi dêwêr, bi şixrê...
Threshing, again with cattle, with the threshing sled...
Kûm dikirin. Vê derê gund, bira, mal tune bûn.
They piled it up. Here in the village, brother, there were
no houses.
Li vê derê diftilîn bi hevdira g.. kûm dibû...
Here they went around together... it piled up...
Û carcar dikutan. Carcar.
And they threshed with the threshing machine [carcar].
Carcar.
Dehwan dikutan... û diftilîn ji wê û şûnda...
They threshed grain... and went around from then on...
Ba'dî kutan şûnda, kûm hev dikirin, û hûrî hev dikirin.
After threshing, they gathered the pile, and piled the chaff
together.
Eger însan, yanê raker, ya ser, rasen yekî biçûk hûrî cîranê
xwe.
If a person, meaning the lifter, or the head, straight away
[gave] one little [portion] to his neighbor.
Heskerinek bêrde zêde hebû, di vî gundî da. Elhemdulila.
There was an extraordinary love in this village. Praise be
to God.
Heqo emr, yanê medî, ma ellemê ji hefde heskirin dî.
Truth of life, meaning we saw, we saw love from each other
absolutely.
Hûn tim dixwazin em dengê Bavê Kalo guh lê bin.
You always want us to listen to the voice of Bavê Kalo.
Dengê Bavê Kalo bi heyeta berê we çû derbas dikir?
The voice of Bavê Kalo, with the life of the past, how did
he pass it?
Wek te xeber daye, ga palîk ba, ga karek ba, we dest dikir
yek cîranî.
As you spoke, whether it was labor, or work, you gave a hand
to a neighbor.
Seh, cûret e, rast e. Ene heyata berê dimeşî, bi serikî xweş
bû.
Yes, it's courage, it's true. That life of the past went on,
with a happy head.
Û bi serikî jî rehetî hebû.
And with the head there was comfort too.
Yanê meselen teke biçû Efrîn, teke bimeşya herra Efrîn.
Meaning for example if one went to Afrin, one would walk all
the way to Afrin.
Nexweşî te bû, tekeyan li kerê da bibra, heta opikî min
nexweş bû kerê birin Entabê re.
If you had sickness, they would take you on a donkey, even
when my little child was sick they took him to Antep on a
donkey.
Yanê wa heyata hebû. Û xwarin jî, bi şiklê na... xwarin kêm
bû, û bi şiklê na jî xwarin zêde bû.
Meaning that was the life. And food too, in the shape of...
food was scarce, and in the shape of [now] food is
plentiful.
Çi, yanê kêm bû? Wekî noka xudra û filan û bêvan û bacan
tune bûn.
What, meaning it was scarce? Like now vegetables and so on
and peppers and eggplants didn't exist.
Lê li meqabîlî wî, rez pir bûn.
But in exchange for that, vineyards were many.
Behir tûnakî tir hebû cema.
There were many figs with us.
Ê me çar rez me hebûn.
We had four vineyards.
Û me dixwar bi qufka tînan, hî cîrana jî dixwar.
And we ate baskets of figs, the neighbors ate too.
Û diftilî her tiştek hebû.
And it went around, everything existed.
Û cîrana jî, elhemdulila, yî gi tune ba jî, wî jî dixwar. Ew
jî xudan dî dibû.
And the neighbors too, praise God, even the one who didn't
have, he ate too. He also saw abundance.
Li paşê jî mehsere digerîn. Ma'sere, dimis, sê mehsere di vî
gundî hebûn.
Later they operated presses. Presses, molasses, there were
three presses in this village.
Yek li vir e, yek li wir e... sê ma'sere.
One here, one there... three presses.
Yekî jî qetrî... hemû jî diket ma'serê.
One also [unclear]... all went into the press.
Wî jî tenekê zêtiyê xwe dibirin, û xelkê didayê.
He also took his tins of oil, and gave to the people.
Û hemba hevdura şa dibûn.
And they were happy together.
Bavê Şêxo, li her gundekî berê, daweta xwe li ser bêdera
dikirin.
Father of Shekho, in every village in the past, they held
their weddings on the threshing floors.
Diçûn av ji kaniya, di bîra tînan.
They went to bring water from the springs, from the wells.
Gundê Kutanê we diçû ava xwe ji ku tînan?
Village of Kutan, where did you go to bring your water?
Gundê Kutanê, eslen gundê me ne li vir bû.
Village of Kutan, actually our village was not here.
Em, gû dised û pêncî sal in ê li vir e.
We, they say it's 150 years here.
Gundê me li vira Qişle hay. Li wira rûniştine.
Our village is here at Qishla. They settled there.
Paşê çûne wê derê. Sebebê hatina vira çiye?
Then they went over there. What is the reason for coming
here?
We çaxê mehkûm bûn e. Hikûmetî Osmanîş... hikûmet kêm bû.
At that time they were sentenced [outlaws]. The Ottoman
government too... government was weak.
Mal basmiş dikirin. Vana go em werin cem hevdu, serê vî
tilî.
They raided houses. These said let us come together, on top
of this hill.
Çar xanî hatine girtin. Çar xanî.
Four houses were built. Four houses.
Her çar xanî, yek in ê... li ser du qentirman e xanî.
All four houses, are one... the houses are on two arches.
Dudu devî xwe bi quble ne, dudu jî bi şimal dan e.
Two face the Qibla [South], two face the North.
Wa ortê, sirta jûr û dûr, kirin ji hewşa giya.
That middle, the upper and lower ridge, they made into a
courtyard for hay.
Û sê rêk têda, me'neyê dewarê xwe were wê ortê.
And three paths in it, meaning bring their cattle to that
middle.
Û li sê cîyê jî xew dikirin. Me'neyê giddiz û mehkûm, malê
gundiyan basmiş nedikirin.
And in three places they slept. Meaning thieves and outlaws
didn't raid the villagers' wealth.
Hewa yek.
That's one thing.
Yê dîkê heskirinek zêde hebû.
The other thing, there was a great affection.
Heskerinek zêde hebû liser dawata.
There was a great affection regarding weddings.
Yanê welew tişt kêm bû, dewar pir bû, mesref dibû, û qîmetî
însana hebû.
Meaning even if things [money] were scarce, cattle were
many, expense was made, and people had value.
Em hênin ser bavkê vî. Havalê Reşoyê Henî Şimê ye.
Let's come to this one's father. He is a friend of Resho of
Hani Shime.
Li bavkê xwe yekî bi tenê bû. Ra bû yekî dawetê jêra bike.
Of his father, he was an only child. He got up to make a
wedding for him.
Gund wekî çel malî, zêde tune ye.
The village was like forty households, not more.
Go ekê dawetê bikim. Bêra gotin xeyo tu dawetê bike, û emkê
jî mesrefê bikşînin.
He said I will make a wedding. They said to him, nephew, you
make the wedding, and we will bear the expense.
Yanê teke bibê çiqo dewar şarje kiribê? Sid dewar.
Meaning if you say how many cattle were slaughtered? A
hundred cattle.
Noka em kanin sid dewarî şarje kin? Sid dewar şarje kirin.
Now can we slaughter a hundred cattle? They slaughtered a
hundred cattle.
Her gundekî, si gundatî dawerek.
Every village, three villages one cattle.
Haw gundokê, herî ser sifre xwe, serekî hebê.
That village, everyone on his tablecloth, had a main dish.
Ser gulvî tiştî ne. Ê de nexweşî heba.
On the [unclear] of the thing. Then if there was sickness.
Yanê însan diçû ser wî nexweşî. Welew tişt bidesnexistî ji
hez dikir.
Meaning a person went to that sick person. Even if he didn't
obtain anything, he loved him.
Vêra radibû, li ber dilê gundê diçû... înşelle hewa nabe,
înşelle hana bibe... heskirinek hebû.
He would get up, go to comfort the village... Inshallah it
won't be like that, inshallah it will be like this... there
was affection.
Heskerinek zêde hebû.
There was great affection.
Dawet dibû, tey seke ro yekî tiştkê qewatle têrê çêkir ser
piyê xwe, li nav gund digerî.
A wedding would happen, you would see someone made a tray of
food on his feet, walking in the village.
Wê malê fer e na, wê malê kefç e na, wê malê ne tiştin e,
her kesî jî tiştê xwe belav dikir.
That house has no dishes, that house has no spoons, that
house has no things, everyone distributed their things.
Wê mala pê nedehesiya tasedikir. Ferêt gund û derê gund, ji
gya pir tir bû.
That house wouldn't feel the lack. The dishes of the village
and outside the village were more plentiful than hay.
Û lê mehfeze dikirin, wê dawetê. Dore radiftilîn.
And they protected it, that wedding. They danced around in a
circle.
Qiçkî hûrik ber nedadan. Dawet gumrah dibû yanê.
They didn't let small kids in. The wedding was
lively/crowded meaning.
Bêrda xweş dibû. Heskerin çê dibû.
It was extraordinarily good. Love was created.
Dest dikirin yek.
They joined hands as one.
Erê dest dikirin yek û heskirin heye.
Yes, they joined hands as one and there is love.
Tiştikî dî eştera xeber dim, roê eydê.
Another thing I will speak plainly, the day of Eid.
Roê eydê, qurban dikirin.
The day of Eid, they made sacrifices.
Qurban gyo dikirin. Xêr e, yanê îgi tune sed dewarê xwe
hebû.
They made many sacrifices. It's charity, meaning the one who
had nothing had a hundred cattle.
Belkî çel kerî pez û mîh ji vî gundî derdiket.
Maybe forty flocks of sheep and ewes went out of this
village.
Vira golek heye, noka em dibênin gol, tu gol wana mezin tune
bûn. Li Kurdagê tavda.
There is a lake here, now we see the lake, there were no
such big lakes. In all of Kurdagh.
Û av ji kû va dihat? Ji çar ciyava... ji bil va diçû...
And water came from where? From four places... from
[unclear] it went...
Hav gola...
That lake...
Têra hata mezinahî guncî dikir.
Until it grew large, they would make it a kneading trough
[or stone mortar].
Wê gunciyê... pezê xwe, dewarê xwe têra av dikir.
That trough... they would water their sheep and cattle in
it.
Ee hezkirinek berê da qewet li ba hebû. Yekî bigota "Se'ê
anê teke", bibê "Naka ez dimeşim, fere divê ez matora
derim".
Uh, there was a strong love/affection in the past. If
someone said, "Come in an hour," he would say, "No, I'm
walking now, I have to take the motorcycle." [Comparing
patience/pace].
Xeyo, emkê bimeşin her 'erfîn şa dibûn.
Brother, we would walk, everyone knew [the customs], they
were happy.
Heta 'erf... 'azaze, ken, mesxere şor...
Until the customs... the dignity, laughter, mocking talk...
Bi hevdura dikirin, mesxere... û yanî şorê kirêt jî ra e's
bû.
They would joke with each other, mocking... and, meaning,
ugly talk was difficult/rebellious for them [they avoided
it].
Ne wekî naka, pêşta şûnda tine bû.
Not like now, back then there was none of that [disrespect].
Yanî her tiştek hebû. Tiştinê berê dakî war bû.
Meaning, there was everything. There were things established
in the past.
Însan bi wê heyatê naka dişewite. Yanî dibê, "Xwezî ew ne
wena ye."
A person burns [with longing] for that life now. Meaning, he
says, "I wish it wasn't like this."
Yekî yanî qusûrê semeka nebîngiya.
Someone, meaning, wouldn't see the fault of a
[neighbor/friend].
Yekî yanî meselen, qîçkê xwan e, û tîmar kirî, û mezin kirî,
û gihande dereca mezin...
Someone, meaning, for example, has his kids, and cared for
them, and raised them, and brought them to a high level...
Naka jî bas dibîn dinê çiye. Yanî ew giştin 'emirê me kêm lê
dinêrin.
And now we just see what the world is. Meaning, all of them
look down upon our age/generation.
Xêr e? Law dinê çiye?
Is it good? Oh man, what is the world?
Yanî dibêkûn wa însana xêra mezin hene.
Meaning, it used to be that people had great goodness.
Berê qîmetê mezinan hebû. Naka lawikê deh salî li ber bavê
xwe radiweste.
In the past, elders had value. Now, a ten-year-old boy
stands up [argues] against his father.
Ew li berê qîçikê xwe, deriyê xwe, deriyê mirî...
He, in front of his child, his door [family], the door of
the dead...
Deh sal diçûn, axre dawa dikir, digot, "Lawêm li filan derê
mirî."
Ten years would pass, the afterlife would claim [someone],
he would say, "My son died in such and such place."
Naka ne wena ye. Hef tiştina, hef tiştinê naka hene, gihayî.
Now it's not like that. These things, these things that
exist now, are [like dry] grass [worthless/temporary].
Tiştê hana tine bû. Naka em dinêrin... yanî dinya çite.
Things like this didn't exist. Now we look... meaning, where
the world is going.
Li kura erdê haye, tebgîra deng dike, û guh haye... "Lawêm
li Firansa ye."
Wherever on the globe he is, he makes a voice recording, and
the ear hears... "My son is in France."
Kanî? Rû rû li ber e.
Where? He is face-to-face [via video].
Şevqa îvarî, yekşemê haye, ekê mara deng ke.
Wait for the evening light, it's Sunday, he will call us.
Û elhemdu lillah, yanî destê me jî kêm nake.
And praise be to God, meaning, he doesn't leave us in need
either.
Yanî "Bavo, çi gereke?" Em bidin.
Meaning, "Father, what is needed?" We will give.
Îşta mesele vê dinyê, vê naka, vê wextê, hew ferqa tê da
hebû.
So, the issue of this world, this "now", this time, there is
that difference in it.
Wê carê yekî ji Xweda û mize yekî, te zanî sa'î ye. Hewlî
xwe tê yarkiro.
That time [in the past], one from God and the effort of one,
you knew it was genuine effort. He helped his family/group.
Te naka ne wena ye.
But now, it is not like that.
Meselen hilîn, malê xwe têbibe, egî bibî merî dim, hebibî
filî dim...
For example, take it, he takes his wealth, if he becomes a
brave man [or rich], if he becomes a certain person...
Waxtê ku te ket, dibêjin, "Law erê te çi kirî?"
The moment you fall, they say, "Oh man, yeah, what have you
done?"
Berê ta her bimir, yekî bibê teqenamerû bû. Ne wena ye
heyran?
Before, even if you died, someone would say it was
fate/decree. Isn't it like that, my dear?
Ne wena ye bêguman.
It isn't like that, undoubtedly.
Apê Hemîd, em dixwazin hinekî derbas bin... xêr nav lê kirin
gundê Kûtana?
Uncle Hamid, we want to move on a bit... why was the name
"Kûtana" given to the village?
Me'neya gund e?
The meaning of the village [name]?
Me'neya gund... ji mera xeberdanê gotine, berê muxtar hebû.
The meaning of the village... from what they told us in
conversation, formerly there was a Mukhtar [village head].
Û hukmatê "Ûsmilî" bû. Ûsmilî çar sed sal li vira hukum kir.
And it was the "Osmanli" [Ottoman] government. The Ottomans
ruled here for four hundred years.
Li vira. Û hukmat "Ûsmolî" bû.
Here. And the government was Ottoman.
'Esker dihatin malê mixtêr, zêde. Naka pir li malê muxtar û
jinaskin daherin.
Soldiers used to come to the Mukhtar's house, often. Now
they go mostly to the Mukhtar's or the Gendarmerie.
Ee muxtarê me, gundê me, deqê xwe hebû, kût bû.
Uh, our Mukhtar, of our village, had his distinct look, he
was short [kût].
Bi Tirkî... dibû "Kûtê ana".
In Turkish... it was [said as] "Bring the short one" [Kût
ana].
Yanî "Deqê min kût". 'Esker digot "Kûtê ana, Kûtê ana", te
çû yanî "Deqê min ê kût" çû naye.
Meaning "My short guy". The soldier would say "Kûtê ana,
Kûtê ana" [Bring the short one], you went, meaning "My short
guy" went and didn't come back.
Lê bû "Kûtana". Te fehm kir?
Yes.
So it became "Kûtana". Did you understand?
Navê gundê me ji pîrikê da hatiye. "Kûtê ana".
The name of our village came from the old times. "Kûtê ana"
[Bring the short one].
Bi Tirkî yanî... deqê min kût.
In Turkish meaning... my short guy.
Erê xalê min.
Yes, my uncle.
"Kûtê ana".
"Bring the short one".
Bêguman di gund da şikestek heye, berê şikeftê xa bû?
Undoubtedly, there is a cave in the village, was it formerly
a cave used by you?
Şikeftî gundê Kûtana li kuderê heye û berê hebûn û...
Where is the cave of Kûtana village, and did they exist
before and...
Jê çira...
For what purpose...
Şikeft hebûn, yek li vira nîzik e heye. Û bîrek li berê
wana, berê wana bîra avzê ye.
There were caves, there is one near here. And a well in
front of them, in front of them is a water source well.
Ew jî di nav 'ardê me da ye.
That is also within our land.
Nav 'ardê me da ye.
It is in our land.
Gundî, wextê gi av kêm dibû, ji wê bîrê vedixwarin.
The villagers, when the water was scarce, would drink from
that well.
Bîr jî kûr dibû. Havînê av dadiket, zivistanê av radibû.
The well was deep. In summer the water went down, in winter
the water rose.
Pezê gund, kincê gund, îşê gund, teva li ser wê bîrê bû.
The village sheep, village clothes [washing], village work,
all of it was at that well.
Yanî av mecbûr vedixwar.
Meaning, they had to drink the water.
Paşê jî sahrînc pir kûlan e. Sahrînc, heta li çiyê jî kûlan
e. Naka gundê me sahrînc li çiyê kûlan e.
Afterwards, cisterns were dug often. Cisterns, they are even
dug in the mountain. Now our village has dug cisterns in the
mountain.
Tamam şuxlê xwa li çiyê bûn.
All their work was in the mountain.
Li berê hana, li berê hana, sahrînc hebû. Paşê li gund jî
pir kûlan e.
In front of here, in front of here, there was a cistern.
Later they dug many in the village too.
Îşta heyata avê hana dimeşiya.
So, the life of water [water situation] went on like this.
Ee berî çel û heştan bita ra bibêjim... makîna, ewwel
makîna, ji 'efrîn taksîk sibahekê hat me got eva çiye.
Uh, before '48, let me tell you... the car, the first car, a
taxi came from Afrin one morning, we said "What is this?"
Ermeniyan dajot. Kurmanca digot, Kurmanca ne dikarîbajo ta.
Armenians were driving it. Kurds said, Kurds couldn't drive
it then.
Erê.
Yes.
Li vira deşê fêr hebûn, ji çelî û çel û heşt û şûnda du
fustak çêbûn.
Here outside there were [drivers/mechanics], from '40 and
'48 onwards, two "fustaks" [type of vehicle/bus] were made.
Yek li Bilbilê, yek li gundê me.
One in Bulbul, one in our village.
Digolo, "Îslam nekarin makînê bajon."
They used to say, "Muslims cannot drive machines."
Yekî Ermenî li ser bû, divêra digotin "Curc".
An Armenian was on it [driving], they called him "George".
Yanî te'xir pir hebû.
Meaning, there was a lot of backwardness.
Û yanî ji wê, rohilatê tav da, ew makîna, ew fustakê hare
Heleb.
And meaning, from the sunrise, that machine, that vehicle
would go to Aleppo.
Te sibê jê ma? Ma ro ava da.
Did you miss it in the morning? It remained until sunset.
Erê.
Yes.
Wê gavê ew ker diçû, wera hat.
At that time, that donkey [transport] went, and came back
like that.
Û teke biftile, meselen tişt dida... tiştê wekî bida'ê xwe
teke çû bibê û tşitê xwe bibê Heleb.
And for it to return, for example, giving things... things
like merchandise, if one went to take his goods to Aleppo.
Bi awe dibirin, bi dewêr, zêt ji ma'sera dibirin. Em
gihîştinê.
They took it by that, by beasts of burden, they took oil
from the press. We reached [witnessed] that time.
Dikat hîza... xiyara.
It was cucumbers... cucumbers.
Erê.
Yes.
Xiyarê te de nezanin? Ewarê qaling in e.
You don't know your cucumbers [snake cucumbers]? The thick
ones.
Her qatirekê sêsêle didan. Her yekê du teneke nîv diçûnê.
They put panniers on every mule. Each one [side] took two
and a half tins.
Heft teneke nîv diçûn, wê qatirê... çar qatir diçûn ji vê
ma'serê ewe dibirin Helebê.
Seven and a half tins went, that mule... four mules went
from this oil press taking that to Aleppo.
Ma tê re.
It remained on the road [took a long time].
Tê re bi şiklekî... wekî silik sela Heleb kesî nedi... gi
dikirin mûj.
The road was in such a shape... like baskets [?] to Aleppo
no one... they made it all into raisins.
Mûj te zanî çûna ne? Zibîb.
Do you know how raisins are? Zibib [Arabic for raisins].
Erê ez zanim, erê zibîb.
Yes I know, yes Zibib.
Ee rezê bapîrê me, li vî derê havoyê honaye, rezekî berda
gumrah bû. Berda. Meşhûr bû.
Uh, our grandfather's vineyard, over here in this air/place,
was a very lush vineyard. Very. It was famous.
Ee perdeya tiriyê xwe pir e... diçûn nav rêz hilnadihat,
diçîn vî 'ardê ssor, li wir radixist.
Uh, the covering of grapes was plentiful... you couldn't
walk in the vineyard, they went to this red earth, and
spread them out there.
Çend qentar dihatin? Heta heft qentara dihat.
How many qantars [unit of weight] came? Up to seven qantars
came.
Her qentarek sê sed kîlo ye.
Each qantar is three hundred kilos.
Eke sê sed kîlo mûj, li vî gundî î ro, eke çûke, difirotin
Helebê.
If three hundred kilos of raisins, in this village today, if
one went, they sold them to Aleppo.
Ee gundekî "Ağalar" li wira heye, li vê derê cil birê.
Uh, there is a village "Ağalar" [Agjalar] over there, over
here he bought clothes/fabric.
Cil birê heye ji cem nebilê.
He bought clothes from near Nebol [Nubl].
Erê.
Yes.
Li wê derê dibir wira... û heta pênc şeş ro jî li odê, oda
wana heye.
Over there he took it there... and for even five or six days
in the room, they have a guest room.
Lê rûdinişt, wa gundina, wa mûjina dikirîn.
He sat there, buying those village goods, those raisins.
Bi çi dikirîn? Bi heryê diguherîn.
With what did they buy? They exchanged for wool.
Bi heryê.
Wool?
With wool.
Ee 'emle tine bû.
Uh, there was no currency.
Heşt... şeş zêr bi şeş rûbwaraqa bû. Digot Mecidî.
Eight... six gold pieces were for six notes/papers. They
called it Mejidi.
Zêrek bi şeş hewa bû.
One gold piece was worth six of those.
Ee wek herya danî, li vê derê îşta wa herya...
Uh, like putting down wool, over here so that wool...
Û îdî jî, îşta dims, mûj, me her yekî yanî aqel şî çar telîs
didanom.
And then also, so molasses, raisins, we, each one, meaning
at least, put away four sacks.
Û berfek li vira barî, di hezar û neh sed û çil da.
And a snow fell here, in nineteen hundred and forty.
Çil rojî berf li xwa da.
The snow stayed for forty days.
Çil rojî berf lê kir.
It snowed for forty days.
Bi şev û bi ro.
By night and by day.
Bi ro te nizanî berf ji kû va dibare, ji 'ardê va diçû.
By day you didn't know where the snow was falling from, it
went from the ground up [blizzard].
Û malê bapîrê min jî malekî berî vê sed û çil salî li vir e,
malê bapîrê min.
And my grandfather's house is a house from before one
hundred and forty years ago here, my grandfather's house.
Wa der dikeven, qapî girtî ye. Qapiyê berê qeyna, huna bêtûn
bûn.
They go out, the door is blocked. The old arched doors, they
were like concrete [solid].
Yanî ge... ew bûn. Bîdîraka bûn, dera bûn, ocax bûn, me'lebê
bibrat... heta qîçkê xwe daren, derkevin derva.
Meaning... they were that. They were [thick walled], had
doors, hearths, [waiting] for it to stop... so they could
take their children out.
Ne dewar ma, û ne nan ma, û ne tişt ard nema.
No cattle remained, and no bread remained, and no flour
remained.
Destarek hebû bi kevir a.
There was a hand-mill made of stone.
E gîştimê. Huna digerrandin.
I reached [remember] it. They turned it like this.
Îşta wê malê hilgirta sê çar mehriya bibra mal.
So that house would pick up three or four ewes to take home.
Du sê kîloya genimê xwe, deriyê xwe dianîn û ê berdan û, eke
çi qawîr bibe.
They brought two or three kilos of their wheat, their grain,
and released it [ground it], whatever huge [meal] it would
be.
Ê bizilme kirana, bixwarana. Çêl rojî.
They would make bread/paste, and eat it. Forty days.
Bavê Şêxo, wextê nebîne dî wekî dî, te ji me ra xeber da, we
pirre şag dî.
Father of Sheikho, may time not see another like it, you
told us, you saw many things.
Derbas bî, jiyan xweş bî.
It passed, life was good.
Pêşket.
It progressed.
Nihan ez dixwazim, 'emirê vê gundî, kûtana, çiqas sal e? Wek
te zanî, teqrîben tikanî ji me ra xeber de?
Now I want [to ask], the age of this village, Kûtana, how
many years is it? As you know, approximately can you tell
us?
Zêde yanî teqrîben ho... em dibên yanî du sed pêncî sal li
vira gunda...
More, meaning approximately so... we say meaning two hundred
and fifty years here in the village...
Vê derê çar xwanî lê hatine girtin.
Four houses were established here.
De sê sed sal, du sed û pêncî sal.
So three hundred years, two hundred and fifty years.
Nîzîkê du sed û pêncî sal, sê sed sal, gundî Kûtana heye.
Near two hundred and fifty years, three hundred years,
Kûtana village has existed.
Xalê Hemîd, saeta te xweş, Xwedê ji te razî be. Ez pir
kêfxweş bûm, dengkirina te xweş û kîbar û delal.
Uncle Hamid, bless your time/health, may God be pleased with
you. I was very happy, your voice/storytelling was good and
gentle and lovely.
Û çîrokê berê, ez pir hez dikim.
And the stories of the past, I love them very much.
Însanê ku di wextê mezin, cîyê xwa li ser serî min e.
The person who is from the time of elders, his place is on
my head [high respect].
Serî te sax be.
May your head be healthy [Thank you].
Û însanê ku di mezinê xwe tines, hew jî tine.
And the person who doesn't have his elder, he is nothing
either.
Ez te ra şoreş bibêjim. Dibê, merî kefnê xwe tinenin, 'acerî
xwe jî tinenay.
Let me tell you a revolution [wisdom]. It says, if a man
doesn't have his old ones, he doesn't have his new ones
either.
Yanî kefnê te tinenin, 'acerî te jî tinenin. Wekî kincê te
kefn tine, te yê 'acer li xwe nekir.
Meaning if you don't have your old ones, you don't have your
new ones. Like if you don't have old clothes, you didn't put
on new ones.
Rast e, selamê min.
It is true, my greetings.
Û ji gundî Kûtana, giyarê heye.
And from the village of Kûtana, there is respect [?].
Û gi jî ser serî min, ser çavê min. Û ez giya jî hez dikim.
And all are on my head, on my eye. And I love them all too.
Û elhemdu lillah gi jî ji min hez dikin.
And praise be to God, they all love me too.
Û ji qîçkê min ra, û ji qîzê min ra...
And for my children, and for my daughters...
Û ji lawê min ra, ji giyara selamê me heye.
And for my son, for all of them we have greetings.
Û saeta giya xweş. Û ez ji giya jî razî me.
And may everyone's time be good. And I am pleased with
everyone too.
Û her kes înşallah, êkê li ser îmanê ê bimre û cîyê xwe jî
cennet be.
And everyone, God willing, will die upon faith and their
place will be paradise.
Saeta te xweş.
Bless your time/health.
[Music Playing]
Merhaba, bi xêr hatin.
Hello, welcome.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome [Arabic greeting].
Navê te bi xêr?
Your name please?
Navê min Mihemed e. Ji gundê Ehmedê Mistê me.
My name is Muhammad. I am from the village of Ahmed Miste.
Kekê Mihemed, çend salî ye?
Brother Muhammad, how old are you?
Çîl û dida.
Forty-two.
Xwedê 'emrê dirêj bide te.
May God give you a long life.
Bi Xwedê, ez derbas gundî Kûtana bûm. Ez derbas bûm min seh
kir te karê sînkar dikî, heddad xer dikî.
By God, I was passing through Kûtana village. I passed by
and realized you do welding work, you do blacksmithing well.
Saeta te sax be.
Bless your time/hands.
Em nihan derbas çayê bin, gel te istiqbal bikin.
We will now move to tea, welcome you.
Kerem kin, ehlen wa sehlen.
Please come in, welcome.
Kekê Mihemed, çend sal in tu vê karî dikî?
Brother Muhammad, how many years have you been doing this
work?
Welle, de bêje ez mîrata bavê xwe heft sal li berê, bavê min
rehmetî, heddad dişuxilî, û abyar dişuxilî.
Well, let's say I inherited from my father seven years ago,
my late father worked as a blacksmith, and worked on wells.
Bîst sal zêde hene. Em divê karî da ne, qapiya, û pencerra,
û dera, û derebizûna...
It's been more than twenty years. We are in this work,
[making] gates, and windows, and doors, and railings...
Her îşê... em dişuxilin.
Every job... we work on it.
Te zehmet ji bavê xwe dît?
Did you see [learn] the hardship [trade] from your father?
Bavê min ê rehmetî meberê... Bavê kîta jî...
My late father formerly... your ancestors too...
Bavê kîta jî, le alemî lê... Bavê min qedîm û kevn di
mantiqê de tenê bûn.
Your ancestors too, in the world... My father was old and
ancient, the only one in the region.
Ji awareyî, vegeriyan hatin ser gundê xwe, li ser zanaeta
xwe rûniştin.
From displacement, they returned to their village, and
settled into their trade.
Kekê Mihemed, te go karê heddad ez dikim, û tu ji bavê xwe
hîn bûyî, yanî tu perlekê xweş î?
Brother Mohammed, you said I do blacksmithing, and you
learned from your father, meaning are you satisfied?
Xwedê quwetê bide te. Rixqê te bişîne. Şixul çawa ye?
May God give you strength. May He send your sustenance. How
is the work?
Xwedê elhemdulillah, niha zberê pir çêtir e.
God be praised, now it is much better than before.
Milet diftile malê xwe, xopiyan çêdikin, teslîhatê çêdikin,
şuxul elhemdulillah.
The nation is returning to their homes, repairing ruins,
doing maintenance, work is thank God.
Û em bi hêvî ne milet gişt biftile malê xwe û meznûbê
zanaetê xwe rakin.
And we hope the whole nation returns to their homes and
uplifts the status of their trade.
Inşallah rojên pêş da gi biftilin.
God willing, in the coming days everyone will return.
Berî ez derêm, te gotin te, tiştek bu te gotin tel bî
hinekî...
Before I leave, you said, you had something to say...
Saheta we xweş. Em bi hêvî ne miletê me û Efrînê gişt
vegerin malê xwe.
Health to you. We hope our nation and all of Afrin return to
their homes.
Û serî îşê xwe, û milkê xwe, û saheta te xweş, wejî
kêfxweşim têt ser çava.
And to their jobs, and their property, and health to you, I
am happy you came, welcome.
Xwedê ji te razî be. Xwedê ez derbas bim, mala we ava, silav
kêfketim.
May God be pleased with you. I will pass, may your house be
prosperous, greetings, I was happy.
Ser serî min, ehlen wa sehlen, dikan dikana we ye, mehel
mehela we ye, kîngî werin ser seran.
On my head, welcome, the shop is your shop, the place is
your place, whenever you come, you are welcome.
Ya ji xwarziyê min re, gerek noker mektebê, ba bixwînin, lê
zorûf li ser me ra derbas bûn, çetin e.
For my nephews, they must follow school, let them study, but
conditions passed over us, it is hard.
Zanaet jî rind e, lê bes xwendin e, berî her tiştî ye.
Xwendin e paşeroj e, xwendin e musteqbel e.
Trade is also good, but reading is before everything.
Reading is the future, reading is the prospect.
Ma ne xwendî, em poşman bûn. Em dixwazin her qîz û kurkê,
her mektebê bixwîne.
We didn't study, we regretted. We want every girl and boy to
study at school.
Miletê kîbar û delal, em nîvandarê gundê Kutanê bin. Bi
erebî dibêjin "Mudellele", bi rastî gundek delal û kîbar e.
Noble and dear people, we are guests in the village of
Kutana. In Arabic they call it "Mudallala", truly a
beautiful and classy village.
Gundê Kutanê ji naxiya xwe du kîlometre dûr dikevin, naxiya
Bilbilê. Emrê vê gundî, dorê dused û pêncî sal e.
The village of Kutana falls two kilometers far from its
district, Bulbul district. The age of this village is around
250 years.
Malbatê vê gundî, dorê sêsed mal e. Mekbes di vê gundî da
çar ne, bes haliyen yek heye.
The families of this village are around 300 households.
There were four presses in this village, but currently one
exists.
Camî di vê gundî da heye, hellaq hene, met'em di vêr da
heye, mel'eb di vê gundî da heye, bîrên avê heye, saydele
didin.
There is a mosque in this village, barbers exist, a
restaurant exists here, a playground exists in this village,
water wells exist, pharmacies serve.
Mekteb ibtidayî û î'dadî û sanawî jî heye. Û niha emê berê
bidin dev fananê kal...
School primary, middle, and secondary also exist. And now we
will turn towards the old artist...
Reşîd Mehmiçan, rehmetî Reşîd Mehmiçan hebû, pêra Zekeriya
Gulcan, ew jî nava bajarê derve, silav û rêz ji Zekeriya ra.
Reşîd Mehmiçan, there was the late Reşîd Mehmiçan, then
Zekeriya Gulcan, he is also out of town, greetings and
respect to Zekeriya.
Û Ehmed Efrînî heye, evna derbên nîşan menan heye, Abdo
Brahîm heye, Şiyar Brahîm heye, evna bajarê derva ne.
And Ehmed Efrînî exists, these are famous marks, Abdo Brahîm
exists, Şiyar Brahîm exists, these are outside the town.
Û eger em gun lê xeber didin li Efrînê, fîlan, eslen şêr li
vir e. Em silav û rêz ji kekê me Aslan dişînin.
And if we talk about [bravery] in Afrin, so-and-so,
originally the lion is here. We send greetings and respect
to our brother Aslan.
Sehet a te xweş, xwedê ji te razî be, serê me pê rakiriye, û
inşallah rojên pêş da emê wel ciyê bilind bibînin.
Health to you, God be pleased with you, you raised our
heads, and God willing in coming days we will see you in
high places.
Sehet a we xweş û bi me ra bin heta dawiya vîdeoyê.
Health to you and be with us until the end of the video.
Merheba xalê min.
Hello my uncle.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Navê te bi xêr xalê min?
Your name please, my uncle?
Navê min Arif, me'rûf bi Arifê Ebdirehman e, bi erebî yanî,
bes bi nas dikin bi navê Arifê Cewherî.
My name is Arif, known as Arif of Abdulrahman in Arabic, but
they know me by the name Arifê Cewherî.
Bavkê me navê xwe Cewherî bû, em ser navê bavkê xwe, nas
dikin bi navê Arifê Cewherî.
Our father's name was Cewherî, we are on our father's name,
they know us by the name Arifê Cewherî.
Bes bi Arif mehmûm kir, me nas nekir.
But just with Arif [mehmûm?], we didn't recognize.
Xalê Arif, tu çend salî ye?
Uncle Arif, how old are you?
Bi xwedê yûrim ez şêst û yek im. Şêst û yek.
By God, my son, I am sixty-one. Sixty-one.
Ê tu kêfxweş î?
So are you happy?
Ezbenî, ez ne xweş im ma ro çi bibêjim derdê giran û hemê...
Sir, I am not happy, what can I say today, heavy pain and
grief...
Ez bê jin û mal û... ez ne kêfxweş im yanî.
I am without wife and home... I am not happy, meaning.
Xwedê emrê dirêj te de û siheta xweş te de.
God give you long life and good health.
Xwedê we jî bihêle û wekî we jî dûr biki, inşallah.
God keep you too and keep [trouble] far from you, God
willing.
Ez derbas bim cem xaltîkê bim. Merheba xaltî.
Let me pass to the aunt. Hello aunt.
Navê te bi xêr?
Your name please?
Sore.
Sore. Çend salî ye?
Sore. How old?
Pêncî.
Fifty.
Xwedê emrê dirêj te de û siheta xweş te de.
God give you long life and good health.
Tu bi xweş vê gundî yî?
Are you happy with this village?
Na, ez bi xweş gundî... qesem e... bes kulvetî me
şikitandin.
No, I like the village... it is destiny... but my poverty
broke us.
Niha tu kê ji me ra xeber de, le xalê Arif, wa çû hevdû dît,
wa tiş gundî qesim e...
Now who will speak to us, Uncle Arif, how you met each
other, how the village is destiny...
Xalê Arif ji kutanê ye, xalê Arif ji kutanê ye. Keremke xalê
Arif, ka niha me ra xeber de.
Uncle Arif is from Kutana, Uncle Arif is from Kutana. Please
Uncle Arif, speak to us now.
Erz dikim, me çû hevdû dît, zemanê... em biçûk bûn,
wellehî... em ne ji vî jilî ne.
I state, we went and met each other, time... we were small,
by God... we are not of this generation.
Em jilî 'urfe bûn... me di hezkirin tina bû. Yanî hebûyî,
kîjanî re hebûyî...
We were the generation of tradition... we had love among us.
Meaning there was, whoever had...
Ciwanî, halê xwe xweş ra, hewayî kaniyê hezkir û zû çêkira
perê xwe yanî hezkirin çêkir, ne pere hebû.
Youth, good condition, loved the air of the spring and
quickly made his money, meaning made love, there was no
money.
Bes em bi fuqara bûn, xwedê dizane. Em bi meîşet û derbariyê
ketin, em di hezkirinê ne diheyîn.
But we were poor, God knows. We fell into livelihood and
making ends meet, we didn't reach love.
Tim... li korê cefa... Tab'an, tab'an... le ya ibnî em bi
ştê şuxulî...
Always... in the blind struggle... Of course, of course...
my son, we worked at things...
Em fetrokê... bavkê me deyn dikirin, av dikirin, em diçûne
mektebê, em be'lem in.
We... period... our father borrowed debt, watered, we went
to school, we know.
Me heta sefî nehiyê xwend. Me orta temam kir, bukolera
hûrikir. Orta emkîjî bi kolera hûrikir.
We studied until ninth grade. We finished middle school,
chipped at Baccalaureate. We chipped the middle with
[Baccalaureate?].
Me ne elimîn xwendinê, û muhawle kir heba elimîn xwendinê.
Bavê min ne elimî... îfe ma, em bi şuxulîn.
We didn't learn reading, and tried if we could learn
reading. My father didn't learn... so it remained, we
worked.
Em çûn li Helebê şuxulîn. Wêşta me kar kir. Paşê me çû
eskeriya xwe kir.
We went to Aleppo and worked. There we worked. Then we went
and did our military service.
Doxê me çû eskerî kir, berokî jinkê me welê mektebê bû. Em
sofî şamê raste hev du hatin li mantiqa 'Esbîn.
When we went to do military service, a woman [relative] was
at school. We met each other in the Damascus line in the
Asbin area.
Li wan rast hev du hatin. Go Arif, te zewicî ye, te ne
zewicî ye, çûbî me selî te?
We met there. She said Arif, are you married, are you not
married, what happened to you?
Welle min go em ne zewicî ne, wada çike, ma ro hal noke. De
hîn em bizewicîn, me nekirî serê xwe, em pênokirin.
Well I said we are not married, situation is such, today
condition is thus. So we would marry, I didn't take it to
head, we didn't do it.
Piştî wî ro, wellehî go xokik min heye, te kanî arê seke. Te
arê seke.
After that day, by God she said I have a sister, you can
look. You look.
Min xwest. Welle em hatin, wext çû, penc şeş meh çûn.
I asked. Well we came, time passed, five six months passed.
Em hatin mal... bavê min xwest, me bizewicî ne. Bes wera
yardim... hal çîkê te'ban bû.
We came home... my father asked, let's marry. But help...
condition was a bit tired.
Ne em bêjin, tebeqe bilind bûn, fuqara bûn. Lê kurekî... em
bêjin... kurekî acele bûn.
Not to say we were high class, we were poor. But a boy...
let's say... I was a hurried boy.
Ne em, yanî tebeqe berde me, ne fuqara bûn. Em bizewic, me
nekiribû, yanî xwedê... korekî... acele bûn.
Not us, meaning leave the class aside, we weren't poor. We
marry, we hadn't done it, meaning God... a boy... hurried.
Paşê me ro têkiliyên min... pismamê min... di firnê de
şuxulî xwedê heye... Noko li Tirkiyê haliyan.
Then my relations... my cousin... worked in the bakery, God
exists... Now currently in Turkey.
Welle go xîzek, pîrek heye, te kêrê seke, seke... Welle min
go, birokî gundî ji min ra hema ser o gotin.
Well he said there is a girl, a woman, you look at her,
look... Well I said, little brother, the villager told me
just regarding that.
Rabû em çûn wî derê, û nesîb bû, elhemdulillah. Lê bes bêdûn
hezkirin. Bêdûn hezkirin.
So we went there, and it was destiny, thank God. But without
love. Without love.
Tab'an, xaltîka te jî maşallah rindike... Hezkirin paşê
çêbû. Paşê jê hezkirin çêbû, bê hezkirin.
Of course, your aunt is also mashallah beautiful... Love
happened afterwards. Then love happened from it, without
love.
Hezkirin het noke, min dilê xwe kirim.
Love until now, I made my heart.
Eşq, min go kulvetî me, toblî mirat o, me ne dil vekir...
Dilê mi ra serbest û herikî.
Love, I said my poverty, crippled legacy, we didn't open
heart... Free and flowing to my heart.
Elhemdulillah, rehet im, û waş kulvetî xwe razî me. Heta
noke jî... li cem min rûniştî ye.
Thank God, I am comfortable, and satisfied with my poverty.
Until now too... she is sitting with me.
Ji min ra heqqa çikanîn... Maşallah, xizmeta me jî rind e, û
hefsê serî xwe ra dikim.
For me doing right... Mashallah, our service is good too,
and I keep her on my head.
Doxê heta sê qîzik in, sê qîzik in û... û kur law in. Qîzik
yek rehmetî bû, emrê 20 salî rehmetî bû.
Now up to three girls, three girls and... and a boy. One
girl was deceased, died at 20.
Şebabî, evvel emrê xwe bû, can talê xizmet... Elhemdulillah,
berî vê jî du sal, nas jê çêbûn ji xast.
Youth, was in prime of life, dear soul service... Thank God,
before this too two years, people happened from asking.
Elhemdulillah qismetî me jî kir. Eyb e bes, bi xwedê berda
jî... û xizmeta me jî kir.
Thank God made our destiny too. It's shame but, by God
before too... and did our service.
Em jî jê razî ne, xwedê jê razî be. Û berokî gundê me çîkî
rehmetî bû çû ser dilovaniya xwedê.
We are also satisfied with her, God be pleased with her. And
a villager of ours a bit deceased went to God's mercy.
Em jê ra dua dikin, xwedê rehma xwe lê ke.
We pray for him, God have mercy on him.
Kutana bajar e. Gurfa gundê me, mesela Qizilbaş heye, gundê
Bêlê heye, gundê Ehmedê Mistê heye...
Kutana is a city. The chamber of our village, for example
Qizilbaş exists, village of Bêlê exists, village of Ehmedê
Mistê exists...
Qorugul heye, heta Xelîlako, gundê Qeysem, Meydanleg,
weratin. Hatin merkez, li vir dixwendin.
Qorugul exists, until Xelîlako, village of Qeysem,
Meydanleg, they used to come. Came to the center, studied
here.
Mekteba me, ya ewil, sala 58an da mekteb li mantiqa Efrîn...
Heta ji gundê Qeysem dihatin li gundê me dixwendin.
Our school, the first, in year 58 school in Afrin region...
Even from Qeysem village they came and studied in our
village.
Ji alem digerin. Û elhemdulillah, em hûr bûn, cihê serbilind
in. Bi xwedê, her yekî... derhatî vê mektebê...
Searching from people. And thank God, we were..., we are a
place of pride. By God, everyone... who came out of this
school...
Bûn doktor, bûn mihendîs, bûn mirebbî el-ecyal... Bûn...
fêmkir? Yane gundekî pêşketî bû, hadarî bû.
Became doctors, engineers, educators of generations...
Became... understood? Meaning it was a developed, civilized
village.
Em bi gundê xwe razî ne. Em silav dikin... xwendewanên me jî
hebûn. Navê Kutanê di mantiqa Efrînê de jî heye.
We are satisfied with our village. We greet... we also had
students. The name of Kutana exists in the Afrin region.
Bi serbilindin, bi şebabên xwe, bi xwendewan... Bi toxtorên
xwe, bi muhendisên xwe, bi saydeleyên xwe...
We are proud, with our youth, with students... With our
doctors, engineers, pharmacists...
Yane gî me heye, elhemdulillah. Em zivî işî da zengîn in.
Meaning we have it all, thank God. We are rich in this work.
Mekteba me belkî sala 58an da mekteb li mantiqa Efrîn... Zor
me tune bûn, le heta ji gundê Qeysem dihatin li gundê me
dixwendin.
Our school, maybe in the year 58 school in Afrin region...
We didn't have many, but even from Qeysem village they came
and studied in our village.
Ji alem digerin. Û elhemdulillah, em hûr bûn, cihê serbilind
in. Bi xwedê, her yekî... derhatî vê mektebê...
People gathering. And thank God, we were..., we are a place
of pride. By God, everyone... who came out of this school...
Bûn doktor, bûn mihendîs, bûn mirebbî el-ecyal... Bûn...
fêmkir? Yane gundekî pêşketî bû, hadarî bû.
Became doctors, engineers, educators of generations...
Became... understood? Meaning it was a developed, civilized
village.
Em bi gundê xwe razî ne. Em silav dikin... xwendewanên me jî
hebûn.
We are satisfied with our village. We greet... we also had
students.
Navê Kutanê di mantiqa Efrînê de jî heye. Bi serbilindin, bi
şebabên xwe, bi xwendewan...
The name of Kutana exists in the Afrin region. We are proud,
with our youth, with students...
Bi toxtorên xwe, bi muhendisên xwe, bi saydeleyên xwe...
Yane gî me heye, elhemdulillah.
With our doctors, engineers, pharmacists... Meaning we have
it all, thank God.
Em zivî işî da zengîn in.
We are rich in this work.
Mekteba me belkî sala 58an da mekteb li mantiqa Efrîn... Zor
me tune bûn, le heta ji gundê Qeysem dihatin li gundê me
dixwendin.
Our school, maybe in the year 58 school in Afrin region...
We didn't have many, but even from Qeysem village they came
and studied in our village.
Ji alem digerin. Û elhemdulillah, em hûr bûn, cihê serbilind
in. Bi xwedê, her yekî... derhatî vê mektebê...
People gathering. And thank God, we were..., we are a place
of pride. By God, everyone... who came out of this school...
Bûn doktor, bûn mihendîs, bûn mirebbî el-ecyal... Bûn...
fêmkir? Yane gundekî pêşketî bû, hadarî bû.
Became doctors, engineers, educators of generations...
Became... understood? Meaning it was a developed, civilized
village.
Em bi gundê xwe razî ne. Em silav dikin... xwendewanên me jî
hebûn.
We are satisfied with our village. We greet... we also had
students.
Navê Kutanê di mantiqa Efrînê de jî heye. Bi serbilindin, bi
şebabên xwe, bi xwendewan...
The name of Kutana exists in the Afrin region. We are proud,
with our youth, with students...
Bi toxtorên xwe, bi muhendisên xwe, bi saydeleyên xwe...
Yane gî me heye, elhemdulillah.
With our doctors, engineers, pharmacists... Meaning we have
it all, thank God.
Em zivî işî da zengîn in.
We are rich in this work.
Mekteba me belkî sala 58an da mekteb li mantiqa Efrîn... Zor
me tune bûn, le heta ji gundê Qeysem dihatin li gundê me
dixwendin.
Our school, maybe in the year 58 school in Afrin region...
We didn't have many, but even from Qeysem village they came
and studied in our village.
Ji alem digerin. Û elhemdulillah, em hûr bûn, cihê serbilind
in. Bi xwedê, her yekî... derhatî vê mektebê...
People gathering. And thank God, we were..., we are a place
of pride. By God, everyone... who came out of this school...
Bûn doktor, bûn mihendîs, bûn mirebbî el-ecyal... Bûn...
fêmkir? Yane gundekî pêşketî bû, hadarî bû.
Became doctors, engineers, educators of generations...
Became... understood? Meaning it was a developed, civilized
village.
Em bi gundê xwe razî ne. Em silav dikin... xwendewanên me jî
hebûn.
We are satisfied with our village. We greet... we also had
students.
Navê Kutanê di mantiqa Efrînê de jî heye. Bi serbilindin, bi
şebabên xwe...
The name of Kutana exists in the Afrin region. We are proud,
with our youth...
De ji xelkê ta...
So, from your people...
Gotin ji kû tê, na yê? Man'a tu... hebe ji 'asî me.
Where does the talk come from, or not come? Meaning you...
even if... I am stubborn/content.
Ee, de noka berê vê... tewadekû...
Yes, so now before this... somehow...
Bes meylê bidê wek Şêx Mesûd e.
Just pay attention like [it is] Sheikh Masud.
Qeyzik mubaşer razî dibim.
I get satisfied immediately/directly.
Razî dibî?
You get satisfied?
Qeyzik mubaşer razî dibim. Bes hewldana Şêx Mesûd ha.
I get satisfied immediately. Just the effort of Sheikh
Masud, okay.
Hebû te lew wek li ecelê Şêx Mesûd e, derbikê razî dibim.
If you have it... like for the sake of Sheikh Masud, play
it, I will be satisfied.
Ez dioxim çiqas xelkê te xweş îsa.
I want your people to be just as happy.
Bi miraz gûzê...
With the wish of the dowry...
Ji kû tê na yê? Xweş teqîzek jî çêbe, xizmetkarê wek şexsî,
rind û sultana ye.
Where does it come from? Even if a good restriction happens,
a servant like a person, is beautiful and a sultan.
Î da bike, yekê pî meke to.
So do it, do not neglect anyone.
Yekê pî meke to.
Do not neglect anyone.
Elhemdulilah, qeder meşî û em ji qederê xwe razî ne.
Praise be to God, destiny has marched on, and we are
satisfied with our destiny.
Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God.
Saeta te xweş be, spir kîf xweş mim.
May your hour be happy (bless you), I am very happy.
Ê tu gidin îsane di me'zin dibînim.
I see you are a deeply understanding/wise human being.
Ez dixwazim her demê ki ez gel te bim.
I wish that I could be with you all the time.
Weleh elhemdulilah jî, em bi hevdû ra gihîştine vê rûyê.
By God, praise be to God too, we have reached this day
together.
Emrê min şêst yek e, emrê wê ketiye pêncî sa.
My age is sixty-one, her age has entered fifty.
De yek sal jî kêmasî tê da.
Give or take one year less in that.
De yek sal kêmasî tê da.
Give or take one year less.
Û me emr xweş derbas kir.
And we passed our lives happily.
Û me qişte jî mezin kirin.
And we raised the children.
Û wî jî qişte li me sêwî kirin, elhemdulilah.
And he [God/Fate] made the children orphans to us [separated
them from us], praise be to God.
Elhemdulilah şukur yê rebim.
Praise be to God, thanks oh Lord.
Xwedê bîne.
May God bring them back.
Weleh em baş qederê xwe razî me.
By God, we are well satisfied with our destiny.
Wa ji bê emrê jî bêra derbas kir, ez jî razî me.
Even if he spent his life [away] from me, I am satisfied.
Wa dibêm, mirina min tê hebe, bila we re ye min.
I say, if my death comes, let it come to me.
Na, weleh, xwedê... heqîqeten...
No, by God, God... truly...
Gumerî na... merî av vira heye, zengîn kevê, kulfet xisar
dike.
It's not about gambling... a man is here, if he becomes
rich, he damages the wife/family.
Kulfetê, îşî kulfetê kê kes nake yoro.
The wife, a wife's work, no one else can do, my friend.
Nake.
They cannot.
Merivê gûr binivîsîne feqîr ket, merivê cefî bîne, kulfetî
heynî kar nake.
Even if a man writes volumes [has knowledge] but becomes
poor, or a man brings suffering, the wife does work like no
other.
Ne te fehm kir?
Did you understand?
Bi mira... yanî... pirs...
With desire... meaning... ask...
Pirs, pir zikini...
Ask, ask deeply...
Heta go niha vê rûyê, ez îro heftê û sê salî me.
Until this very day, today I am seventy-three years old.
Ji heftê û sê salî, em ji xelkê xwe, ji cîranê xwe razî ne.
At seventy-three years old, we are satisfied with our
people, with our neighbors.
Min cîranê xwe neêşandiye, min kes neêşandiye.
I haven't hurt my neighbor, I haven't hurt anyone.
Ê go ez bi şev bimeşim, ez ji ewle me.
If I walk at night, I am safe.
Heta go ez ji vir rûnim, sibe heta êvarê kes min naêşîne.
Even if I sit here from morning till evening, no one hurts
me.
Bavê min, te ji cahîltiya xwe da, te bi evînî zewicî yan bi
dîtbarî?
My father, in your youth, did you marry for love or arranged
(by sight)?
De biner...
Look now...
Hertişt bi cahîltiya xwe xweş e.
Everything is nice in its youth.
Bi meraqa xwe xweş e.
It is nice with its own desire.
Weleh min ji meraqa xwe anî.
By God, I brought [her] out of my own desire.
Min bi meraqa xwe anî.
I brought [her] out of my own desire.
Wê çaxê cahîltî hebû, aqil tune bû.
Back then there was youth/ignorance, there was no wisdom.
Çaxê cahîltî hebû, mehabî jî dît.
When there was youth, we also saw affection.
Ê de wextê te qîz ke, ji qîz ke, hez ke, tu kiçûlan jî hez
ke.
So when you [choose] a girl, from a girl, love her, love the
little ones too.
Tu ke bi dandina pir, serê xwe biwînî, tişta, tu ke xwe
venî, tu ke xwe derbikî.
If you give a lot, confuse your head with things, if you
hide yourself, if you expose yourself.
Bes wara fi'el ne wane ye.
But the actual deed is not like that.
Yek îşê xwe bimeşîne heta tebiyeta xwedê jê bistîne.
One should manage their affairs until nature/God takes it
from them.
Îşê çiberdan pir biyar im.
I am very tired of the business of divorce [separation].
Îşê çiberdan pir biye.
The business of divorce has become frequent.
Em jî dixwazin...
We also want...
Yanî... bila şebab jî netirsin.
Meaning... let the youth not be afraid.
Û qîzik jî netirsin.
And let the girls not be afraid.
Teb'en ne dijminê hevdu dibin.
Naturally, they don't become enemies of each other.
Em dibin hevdu, heyata xwe bi hevdu ra derbas kin.
We belong to each other, to pass our lives together.
Bextewar bin.
To be happy.
Bila emrê dirêj û şewq û şayî.
May there be long life, joy and happiness.
Bila bi emrê wek hevdu pîr û kal bibin.
May they grow old and gray together like each other.
Bila emrê wek hevdu kal û pîr bin, bi şayî, bi şênayî.
May they grow old and gray like each other, in joy, in
happiness.
Tab'en ew jinikê, yekê jê ta hez bike, bi mûkine ta, bi
teyare ta...
Naturally that woman, if one loves you, with your machine,
with your airplane [wealth/status]...
Ew ne jiyan e.
That is not life.
Jiyan ewe ko tu bi dil û can jê hez bikî.
Life is that you love her with heart and soul.
Dil û can jê hez bikî.
Love her with heart and soul.
Me mûkine jî kirî.
We also bought a machine.
Û qişkê xwe jî me mezin kirin, mektabê jî.
And we raised our small children, school too.
Ya elhemdulilah, yanî ez noka teqrîben nefsê xwe hatime, ez
nîvîko zengîn tirm, ne zengîn tirm.
Oh praise be to God, meaning I have now roughly come to my
soul [myself], I am somewhat richer, or not richer.
Ê heyat diguhêrim, diguhêrim. Bes metirsin, hevdu ban. Welew
bê hezkirinê hevdu ban.
So life changes, it changes. But don't be afraid, have each
other. Even if without [romantic] love, have each other.
Xaltîka min, tu çawayî? Baş î?
My aunt, how are you? Are you well?
Ez baş im, tu çawayî?
I am well, how are you?
Saxbê te xweş e, sihetê te baş e?
Is your health good, are you feeling well?
Welahî em baş in.
By God, we are well.
Tu ji halê xwe razî yî?
Are you satisfied with your situation?
Ee, em razî ne.
Yes, we are satisfied.
Apê min go zarokê me li derveyî welat in, li Almanya ne.
My uncle said our children are outside the country, in
Germany.
Ee, li Almanya ne, li Ukrayna ne.
Yes, they are in Germany, in Ukraine.
Ee, em ji wan dûr ketine, em noka tenê mane.
Yes, we have fallen far from them, we are left alone now.
Em noka tenê mane li malê.
We are left alone in the house now.
Ne bûk heye, ne zava heye, ne neviyê min hene.
There is no daughter-in-law, no son-in-law, no grandchildren
of mine.
Em mane tenê, hew em herdû ne.
We are left alone, it's just the two of us.
Xwedê wan bihêle, Xwedê wan biparêze.
May God keep them, May God protect them.
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God keep you.
Hûn çiqas, çend sal in zewicî ne, xaltîka min?
How long, how many years have you been married, my aunt?
Welehî bîst û pênc, sîh salî heye em zewicî ne.
By God, twenty-five, thirty years we have been married.
Sîh salî heye, zêdetir e jî.
It's been thirty years, even more.
Zarokê we çend hene?
How many children do you have?
Sê hebê min kur in, pênc hebê min qîz in.
Three of mine are sons, five of mine are daughters.
Du heb li ba min in, yên din hemû derketine.
Two are with me, the others have all gone out [abroad].
Hemû çûne.
They all left.
Xwedê wan biparêze, Xwedê emrê wan dirêj bike.
May God protect them, may God prolong their lives.
Xwedê te bihêle, sax bî.
May God keep you, be healthy.
Tu dixwazî tiştekî bibêjî wan?
Do you want to say something to them?
Ez dixwazim silavê xwe li wan dikim.
I want to send my greetings to them.
Ez pir bêriya wan dikim.
I miss them very much.
Ee, ez pir bêriya wan dikim.
Yes, I miss them very much.
Ez dixwazim dengê wan bibihîzim, wan bibînim.
I want to hear their voices, to see them.
Înşela, înşela.
God willing, God willing.
Înşela.
God willing.
Apê min, tu dixwazî tiştekî bibêjî wan?
My uncle, do you want to say something to them?
Weleh ez dixwazim bibêjim wan.
By God, I want to tell them.
Wekî ez jî hej zarokê xwe dikim.
That I also love my children.
Ez hej miletê xwe dikim.
I love my people.
Ez hej te dikim.
I love you.
Û ez hej miletê xwe yê dervayî welat jî dikim.
And I love my people who are outside the country too.
Miletê me yê dervayî welat, miletê me yê Efrînê, yê Kobanê.
Our people outside the country, our people of Afrin, of
Kobani.
Miletê me yê Kurd.
Our Kurdish people.
Em dixwazin, yanî...
We want, meaning...
Emrê te, te gotiye min, ji Malatya me.
Your age [life]... you told me, I am from Malatya.
Malatya, gundê mezin bûye, wilo we hêsan dîtine.
Malatya, it was a big village, you saw it as easy like that.
Gavê romêzin bûm, rojekê bi hesreta min...
When I was... [unclear], one day with my longing...
Ê niha bibînim, axbarê gundê hanê bibîzim.
So now to see, to hear the news of that village.
E pa her ro, dengê wan dibihîzim, bes ez... dengê wan
nabihîzim.
And so every day, I hear their voices, but I... I don't hear
their voices [in person].
Milet gi silav dikim.
I greet all the people.
Milet gi silav dikim, ez destê giyan maç dikim.
I greet all the people, I kiss everyone's hands.
Ez serê giyan maç dikim, eyînê giyan maç dikim.
I kiss everyone's heads, I kiss everyone's foreheads.
Em heft sal in li vir dane rûniştin.
We have been settled here for seven years.
Em xerîbê ketine miletê me... gî xerîbî yê.
We have fallen into exile, our people... all are in exile.
Xerîbî, te fehm kir?
Exile, did you understand?
Ê min gî hevdû ji bîr kiriye.
And I have forgotten everyone [due to separation].
Tabaen telefonê em daîn dikim bi hevdû ra.
Naturally, we talk on the phone with each other.
Lê ne wekî ti bi hevdû ra mezin bî, ti nav cîkî bê, ti nav
hewşekê bê.
But it's not like when you grow up together, when you are in
one place, when you are in one courtyard.
Ti ser sifrekê bê.
When you are at one table.
Na wane ye.
No, it is not like that.
Bes de zor û ziyan, qeydî sebir kirine.
But despite force and harm, we have been patient.
Elhemdulilah şukur.
Praise be to God, thanks.
Wa qenata hoca min hûrû...
And the channel of my teacher here...
Wa ez bi xêr hatina te dikim.
And I welcome you.
Û silavê min ji eyî milet heye, ani ez kar nakim.
And my greetings to any people there are, now I don't work.
Ez nexweş im, lingê min diêşe, qiloçê min diêşe.
I am sick, my leg hurts, my hip hurts.
Zengînoskê min, hûrû milet jî giş pişiya min hinda bûn.
My throat... and here all the people have disappeared from
behind me.
Wê nexweşiya ez girtim nexweşiya... Elhemdulilah xerçqê min
temam e.
That sickness took me, the sickness of... Praise be to God
my expenses are complete [covered].
Perê min hene, kulfetî min loqilî min in, qişkê min loqilî
min in.
I have money, my wife takes care of me, my children take
care of me.
Bes miletê min ji min dûr e.
But my people are far from me.
Wê hêşt ez celqilmixê û nexweş bûm.
That let me to be shaken and I became sick.
Û hûrû jî bi qenata te, ez kefxweş bim.
And here too, with your channel, I became happy.
Û ez miletê xwe giş silav dikim.
And I greet all my people.
Miletê min, çiqa heval hene giş silav dikim.
My people, however many friends there are, I greet them all.
Ferdan we ferdan, çûçik, mezin, ser seri min, ser çavê min.
Individually and individually, small, big, on my head, on my
eyes [you are welcome].
Saeta te xweş be, Xwedê te bihêle.
Bless you, may God keep you.
Derdê min giran e...
My pain is heavy...
Tu dermanê canê min î.
You are the cure of my soul.
Bawer ke canê min.
Believe it, my soul.
Bawer ke.
Believe it.
Bawer ke derdê min giran e.
Believe it, my pain is heavy.
Ez qurbana min.
I am a sacrifice [for you].
I am a sacrifice.
Bawer ke bîna te, bîna gul e.
Believe it, your scent is the scent of a rose.
Tu gul î...
You are a rose...
Diya min, diya min, diya min î...
My mother, my mother, you are my mother...
Tu roniya çavê min, diya min î.
You are the light of my eyes, you are my mother.
Diya min, diya min, diya min î...
My mother, my mother, you are my mother...
Tu roniya çavê min, diya min î.
You are the light of my eyes, you are my mother.
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Navê te bi xêr?
Your name, please?
Hanîfe.
Hanifa.
Xaltîka Hanîfe tu çend salî ye?
Aunt Hanifa.
Aunt Hanifa, how old are you?
Şêst û sê.
Sixty-three.
Maşala.
Mashallah [God willing].
Te wêlî nake?
You don't look it?
Çi wêlî nake?
What don't I look like?
Gidibên gid kûrî Cefo bikin, rast e lê?
They say, ask the Khori Jafa [clan/family], is it true?
Weleh da kûrî Cefo me pir kirî.
By God, the Khori Jafa we did a lot.
Paşê piştî kûrî Cefo em çûn li Heleb rûniştin.
Then after the Khori Jafa, we went and settled in Aleppo.
Yanî em emrê me bîst û pênc bî, em çûn Heleb.
Meaning our age was twenty-five, we went to Aleppo.
Û qiçik jî hûr bûn, işta de îsa be kore bî.
And the kids were small, look so it was blind [difficult].
Ne wekî kûrî gundo bî.
Not like it was with the Khori Gundo [village clan].
Kûrî gundo jî me pir kirî.
We also did a lot of Khori Gundo [interacted/lived with
them].
Saxbê te, saeta te xweş be de û emrê dirêj be de.
Your health, may you be blessed and have a long life.
Spas.
Thanks.
Bixudê ez derbas gundî Kutanê bûm.
By God, I was passing through the village of Kutana.
Ez derbas vê malê dikim û kîbar bîm.
I pass by this house and was honored/impressed.
Te çiçekê da xemilandî.
You have decorated it with flowers.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Te çiçeka, te giş destê xwe şandî?
The flowers, did you plant them all with your own hands?
Walah mi bi destê xwe şandiyê.
By God, I planted them with my own hands.
Hekel di destê xulî za te tenê me.
Look at the dirt on my hands, you just caught me.
Kes cem min tine ye. Ez û lawkê me wî sewî ye.
No one is with me. Me and my son, he is an orphan
[fatherless/alone].
Xwedê hişta ra bihêle.
May God keep him for you.
Xwedê we jî bihêle.
God keep you too.
Got kekê Aslan e. Kekê Aslan şêr e, silam dikin.
They said it's Brother Aslan. Brother Aslan is a lion, they
greet him.
Erê.
Yes.
Ma reyî mi jî silam dikin genda, ehlen we sehlen.
My husband also greets them [the people], welcome.
Ez dixwazim Xaltîka Hanîfe, ez tiştekî ser genda pirs kim,
wextê çûçik.
I want, Aunt Hanifa, to ask something about the
past/village, when you were small.
Meraqa kilama dil dihebî lê tune?
Did you have a passion for songs in your heart or not?
Erê.
Yes.
Meraqa kilama jî, tembûrê jî.
A passion for songs too, and for the tambur [lute] too.
Pir meraq bî, te sehkerî şi...
It was a great passion, you listened to...
Kilamê berê yan kilamê niha?
The songs of the past or the songs of now?
Na, kilamê berê xweş tir bûn.
No, the songs of the past were better.
Kilamê gundê me xweş tir bûn.
The songs of our village were better.
Henê tu tistîkê xwe, çûkê xwe çê dikir.
When you did your chores, your small tasks.
Paşê te yê kîje rê tembîrek çûçik kirî.
Then you bought a small tambur somewhere.
Û hena meraq bî, kilam û tembîre pir meraq bî.
And there was passion, songs and tambur were a great
passion.
Pir.
Very much.
Û piştî mezin bî û dest...
And after you grew up and hand... [stopped?]
Dest berdanê kir.
Given up on it.
Stranê gundê niha tev poşin, pir xweş heye?
The village songs now are all... are they very good?
Em îdafe xelqê xwe dikin.
We are adding to our people [audience].
Xweş e. Kilamê estîn şê ge xweş in. Ge xweş in.
Good. The songs of [unclear, possibly a name or type] are
very good. Very good.
Yekî yanî tibî top siz tune. Yekî yanî t... ew bike tine, ge
xweş in maşela kilamê xwe.
One, meaning, without a ball/drum isn't there. One
meaning... they are very good, mashallah, their songs.
Û dengê genda jî û yanî hissê genda jî pir xweş e.
And their voices too and meaning their feelings too are very
good.
Yanî ge me dewat kir em hînin.
Meaning if we make a wedding, we will bring them.
Hînin lê!
Bring them, indeed!
Lê mitrib xêrî wî hene livir?
Are there singers other than him here?
Welehî dengê gen pir xweş e.
By God, their voices are very good.
Min vêra deng kir, mi digot hew jî hazir be.
I called him here, I said let him also be ready.
Ez derbas gundî Kutanê bûm.
I was passing through the village of Kutana.
Cem genda dewat jî heye, hew jî meşxûl e.
They have a wedding nearby, he is also busy.
Û ez derbas vê malê xweş û kîbar de lebim.
And I passed by this nice and elegant house.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Te jî û hew jî û giştek cimat gişta ehlen we sehlen.
You too and him too and everyone, the whole gathering,
welcome.
Xweş ta ra bêlê.
Pleased to meet you.
Xaltîka Hanîfe, tu bixoş gundî Kutanê yî lê?
Aunt Hanifa, you are originally from the village of Kutana,
right?
No, aş Hecmoq im.
No, I am from Hajmoq [likely village name].
Te li vder mêr kirî?
You married here?
Mm.
Çend sal in tu li vî gundî ye?
How many years have you been in this village?
Weleh çil û hef sal in.
By God, forty-seven years.
Çil û hef sal in.
Forty-seven years.
Ee.
Yes.
Maşala.
Mashallah.
Tu kanî ji mera xeber de tiştê tafrind vê gundî da çi ye?
Can you tell us, what are the distinct things in this
village?
Le weleh gund bixo girindî, yanî te...
Well, by God, the village itself is grand [elevated],
meaning you...
Çû te tistîkî lixo nihêrî wek bojoro ye.
When you go, look at it, it is like a city.
Hemdilah, yanî cîran liqî xo jî rind in, yanî însanetî xo jî
rind e.
Praise God, meaning the neighbors among themselves are good,
meaning their humanity is good.
Û cewî xo jî rind e.
And its atmosphere [weather/vibe] is also good.
Û çûyê yanî te ne wek mesela gundekî li ûrto çê telxo
behayrê.
And going, meaning not like, for example, a village in the
middle [lowland] that suffocates you.
Her mîvanekî tewarê tilxo nahayrê, har cam cîranekî, gi
biz'arî xweş in ne, gi kêf xweş in ne, rind e. Cewî xo pir
xweş e.
Every guest that comes to you doesn't feel suffocated, every
time with a neighbor, they are all very pleasant, all happy,
it's good. Its atmosphere is very good.
Cewî gund pir xweş, Hemdilah.
The village atmosphere is very good, Praise God.
Gundî Kutanê bilind e û xweş e.
Kutana village is high and beautiful.
No ez digerim mi teswîr kir pir xweş e.
Now I am walking, I filmed it, it is very beautiful.
Erê, xweş e.
Yes, it is beautiful.
Ez carê sêwlahatime gundî Kutanê.
It is the first time I have come to Kutana village.
Înşela emê her werin.
God willing we will always come.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Ez bi xweş gundî ba'dîno me.
I am originally from the village of Baadino.
Mm, tu silamî. Erê gundî ba'dîno tî derbarî vê jî liser awe
derket, ser tîk tok.
Mm, greetings. Yes, Baadino village, regarding that, it also
appeared on that, on TikTok.
We le seyr dikî?
Do you watch it?
Erê, elê seyr dikim.
Yes, yes I watch it.
Em pir kêf xweş dibin.
We become very happy.
Erê.
Yes.
Min got, te berê got min teşî rîstî?
I said, you said before that you spun wool?
Min çê nekir newna.
I didn't make those [rugs].
Ma çid çê dikir? Ma tevin dikirin.
What did we make? We did weaving.
Ma teşî diristin.
We spun wool (with a drop spindle).
Yanî ma cil dikirin.
Meaning we made bedding/mattresses.
Bes çokatê dresî mi qet çê nekirbî.
But truthfully, I never made rugs/carpets.
Evro bikim, eyî xo nizanim çêkim.
To do it today, I don't know how to make my own.
Nanê tenûrê me çêdikir, nanê tîrê me çêdikir. Tiştê wina me
dikir.
We used to make tandoor bread, we used to make thin bread.
We used to do things like that.
Te giş dê...?
Did you [do] it all...?
Te bi xwe çêdikir?
Yes!
Did you make it yourself?
Lê, ma çima min çênekiribe, dêkê xora.
Yes, why wouldn't I have made it, for my mother [or like my
mother].
Dêkê min bi xwe jêbera?
Did my mother herself used to do it?
Dêkê te bi xwe jêbera?
Did your mother herself do it?
Min loyê û pixê dêkê xwe kirî.
I did the kneading and baking of my mother.
Esnan şêr?
Asnan Sher? [Likely a local dish or bread name].
Gofkê esnan şêr, û dêkê min va, bi xwedê va rokî ev nîşta.
Meatballs of Asnan Sher, and my mother, by God, one day this
sat.
Dêkê, te jî gundî Kutanê bî... pîrkê me mesela... dan,
awe...
Auntie, you are from the village of Kutan... our
grandmothers for example... [made] boiled wheat, that...
Tev da çeqilmok jî te birin?
Did you take thistles [çeqilmok] with it too?
Erê! Yek bi yekî!
Yes! One by one!
Erê, yek bi yekî.
Yes, one by one.
Xaltîka Henîfe, lawkî te... lîstikvana gogê ye.
Aunt Hanife, your child... is a football player.
A.
Yes.
Em silav dikin li vir...
We send greetings here...
Silavê min pir jêra hene. Xwedê sehhetêk xweş bidê jî, bidê
jî.
I have many greetings for her. May God give her good health,
give her.
Xwedê quwetê kî pê de. Xwedê wekî ew divê ro bigre, vê ro bi
serkeftîyê ne.
May God give her strength. May God grant her the path she
wants, may she be successful on this path.
Ê dê vê hekî, wî hem 'efrîn, ekê mesela çû xweşika tedrîb
ke, tişta gogê dileyîze, bixwe lîstikvana.
She is going to... Afrin, for example she went to train
well, she plays football stuff, she is a player herself.
Ozan, Xaltîka Henîfe, Ozan kijan salê da destpêkir?
Ozan, Aunt Hanife, which year did Ozan start?
Ê lo weleh kî, hekî te re bêjim safî, ya kî safî di dê bî
mekirî, nedî heftan, heştan.
Oh well, if I tell you clearly, exactly clearly as it was
done, maybe seven, eight [years old].
Noko emrê xwe bîst û du sal e.
Now her age is twenty-two years.
Xwedê emrê dirêj bidê.
May God give her a long life.
Sax bî.
Be healthy [Thanks].
Meraq e?
Is she passionate?
Pir meraq e, lêê, meraq e lêê!
Very passionate, yes, passionate yes!
Noko li Heleb, da rê gogê. Takro li Heleb tê, dîsa tê Efrîn
jî dileyîze.
Now in Aleppo, she goes to football. She comes repeatedly
from Aleppo, again comes to Afrin and plays again.
Bixwe reîs nedî deha, li Efrîn tîne, mokî ne xulsî dare
tîne.
The president himself... brings to Afrin, when it's not
finished he brings back.
Ferîq da rê Heleb, da rê Efrîn.
The team goes to Aleppo, goes to Afrin.
Yanî pir meraq e.
Meaning she is very passionate.
Silavê me jêra hene.
Our greetings to her.
Silavê me ji giya ra hene. Xwedê sehhetêk xweş bidê te jî,
ji giya de.
Our greetings to everyone. May God give you good health too,
to everyone.
Xwedê ji te jî razî be.
May God be pleased with you too.
...ji wa jî razî be, Xwedê sehhetêk xweş bu wa de. Hemdillah
ji Xwedê re, serê me bi giya bilind e, hemdillah.
...be pleased with them too, may God give them good health.
Praise be to God, our heads are held high by all of them,
praise be to God.
Saeta te xweş, bixwedê, dest xweş.
Health to you, by God, health to your hands.
Te emir kir, te gotin te hene.
You commanded, whatever you said.
Xwedê weşta razî be, û Xwedê sehhetêk xweş bu we de. Xwedê
canê we sax bike.
May God be pleased with you, and God give you good health.
May God keep your souls healthy.
Me ragiya silav kir, qîçka jî... qîçka xwa jî û î giya.
We greeted everyone, the girl too... her own girl [daughter]
and all of them.
Tu wek qîçka di mala me, û Xwedê saeta te xweş bide.
You are like a daughter in our house, and may God give you
good health.
Ekîd neha miletî Kurd guhdarî me seyr dikin, silavê me ji
giya ra heye.
Surely now the Kurdish nation is listening and watching us,
we have greetings for everyone.
Û qîçka te, li te seyr dike sa, qîçkê xwa re tiştekî nabêjî,
ya silav tiştek?
And your daughter, if she is watching you, won't you say
something to your daughter, or a greeting or something?
Ê de wela qîçka min yekê li derba, dîsa silavê min lê re
hene. Hinek li Heleb in, silavê min lê re hene.
Oh well, my daughter is one abroad, again my greetings to
her. Some are in Aleppo, my greetings to her.
De wekî gotî, qîçkê... giya wek qîçkê me ne. Silavê me ji
giya ra hene.
As said, the girl... they are all like our daughters. Our
greetings to everyone.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Saet xweş.
Thanks.
Wextê te jî xweş.
Your time be good too.
Ehlena wesehlen.
Welcome.
Miletê kîbar û delal, neha jî emê lehza tirba jî wera
mûşareke kin.
Noble and dear people, now we will share the moment of the
graves with you too.
Xwedê rehma xwe li mirîyê we giya ke.
May God have mercy on all your dead.
Silav û rêz ji şênî gundî Kutanê, ro li her derê li me seyr
dikin, saeta we xweş.
Greetings and respect from the residents of Kutan village,
who watch us every day from everywhere, health to you.
Û neha jî bimînin heta dawî vîdyo, lehza tirba emê ji wera
mûşareke kin.
And now stay until the end of the video, we will share the
moment of the graves with you.
Xwedê rehma xwe li mirîyê we giya ke.
May God have mercy on all your dead.
Bang dikim ban we dikim, silavê li we rîz dikim.
I am calling, I am calling out to you, I am lining up
greetings for you.
Bang dikim ban we dikim, silavê li we rîz dikim.
I am calling, I am calling out to you, I am lining up
greetings for you.
Dengbêj û xwandevan e, karker û cotkar hozan e.
Bards and readers, workers and farmers and poets.
Karker û cotkar hozan e.
Workers and farmers and poets.
Dê dîsa rabin werin, em Efrîna xweş ava bikin.
Come stand up again and come, let us rebuild beautiful
Afrin.
Dê dîsa rabin werin, em Efrîna xweş ava bikin.
Come stand up again and come, let us rebuild beautiful
Afrin.
Çi hebu çi tûne bu, em giştî ji bîr bikin.
Whatever there was or wasn't, let us forget it all.
Bi hevra çêkin seyranê, dawetê li merc û bêderan.
Let's make picnics together, weddings on meadows and
threshing floors.
Bi hevra çêkin seyranê, dawetê li merc û bêderan.
Let's make picnics together, weddings on meadows and
threshing floors.
Li bakin şal û desmala, ser govenda û ahîla.
Wave the shawls and handkerchiefs, on the dances and crowds.
Ser govenda û ahîla.
On the dances and crowds.
Dê dîsa rabin werin, em Efrîna xweş ava bikin.
Come stand up again and come, let us rebuild beautiful
Afrin.
Dê dîsa rabin werin, em Efrîna xweş ava bikin.
Come stand up again and come, let us rebuild beautiful
Afrin.
Çi hebu çi tûne bu, em giştî ji bîr bikin.
Whatever there was or wasn't, let us forget it all.
Kom bibin li cejn û erfata, bi çîrokên sed sala.
Gather on feasts and holidays, with stories of a hundred
years.
Kom bibin li cejn û erfata, bi çîrokên sed sala.
Gather on feasts and holidays, with stories of a hundred
years.
Ber ronahiya hîva gunda, çêkin ken û sohbeta.
In the light of the village moon, make laughter and
conversation.
Ber ronahiya hîva gunda, çêkin ken û sohbeta.
In the light of the village moon, make laughter and
conversation.
Çêkin ken û sohbeta.
Make laughter and conversation.
Dê dîsa rabin werin, em Efrîna xweş ava bikin.
Come stand up again and come, let us rebuild beautiful
Afrin.
Dê dîsa rabin werin, em Efrîna xweş ava bikin.
Come stand up again and come, let us rebuild beautiful
Afrin.
Çi hebu çi tûne bu, em giştî ji bîr bikin.
Whatever there was or wasn't, let us forget it all.