للأسبوع الثاني كمان، وقبل ما يبدأ موسم الزيتون وبشهر تشرين
الأول، رح نبقى معكم بقرية معامل أوشاغي لنحكي عن العادات
والتقاليد ونحكي عن بعض الشخصيات المعروفة، المحببة كتير
بهالضيعة، ولنحكي أيضاً عن أنماط الحياة، تابعونا.
For the second week as well, and before the olive season
begins in October, we will stay with you in the village of
Mamel Ushaqi to talk about customs and traditions, and to
talk about some of the well-known and much-loved
personalities in this village, and also to talk about
lifestyles. Stay tuned.
معامل أوشاغي، قرية سورية تقع جنوب غربي ناحية راجو في منطقة
عفرين وتتبع لها.
Mamel Ushaqi, a Syrian village located southwest of the Rajo
sub-district in the Afrin region and is administratively
part of it.
تبعد عن حلب 87 كيلومتر باتجاه الشمال الغربي، وعن عفرين 27
كيلومتر باتجاه الشمال الغربي.
It is 87 kilometers northwest of Aleppo, and 27 kilometers
northwest of Afrin.
يسكن فيها 350 عائلة من العوائل الكردية، وهم أصل سكان القرية،
It is inhabited by 350 Kurdish families, who are the
original inhabitants of the village,
إضافة إلى 35 عائلة هُجرت قسراً من مناطق سورية مختلفة.
In addition to 35 families who were forcibly displaced from
various Syrian regions.
يوجد في القرية مدرسة واحدة للتعليم الابتدائي والإعدادي، تضم
220 طالباً، ومعصرتان للزيتون.
There is one primary and middle school in the village, with
220 students, and two olive presses.
حيث يوجد في القرية قرابة 80 ألف شجرة زيتون من النوعين
الزياتي والخلخالي.
There are nearly 80,000 olive trees in the village of the
Zayati and Khalkhali varieties.
يبلغ إنتاج الزيت في معامل أوشاغي حوالي 35 ألف تنكة زيت
سنوياً،
The oil production in Mamel Ushaqi is about 35,000 tins of
oil annually,
ويوجد في القرية 500 رأس من الغنم والماعز، وكذلك ألف شجرة
لوز.
There are 500 head of sheep and goats in the village, as
well as 1,000 almond trees.
أهالي معامل أوشاغي يتصفون بالبساطة والكرم وارتفاع نسبة
التعليم بينهم، وقد هاجر عدد كبير من الشباب نحو تركيا
وأوروبا.
The people of Mamel Ushaqi are characterized by simplicity
and generosity, and a high rate of education among them. A
large number of young people have migrated to Turkey and
Europe.
رح نزور هلا إم خليل، وهي وحدة من الشخصيات التقليدية في ضيعة
معامل أوشاغي.
We are now going to visit Umm Khalil, who is one of the
traditional personalities in the village of Mamel Ushaqi.
بلباسها، بحكيها، بطريقة حياتها، بالمفردات البسيطة اللي
موجودة في بيتها.
With her dress, her speech, her way of life, and the simple
items present in her home.
واللي هي قديمة كتير، بعضها ورثته من والدتها والبعض الآخر من
كدها وتعبها وعرقها.
Which are very old, some of which she inherited from her
mother, and others from her hard work, effort, and sweat.
بيتها كتير بسيط، عبارة عن حديقة صغيرة كتير كتير، فيها شوية
أشجار وشوية زهور وورود.
Her house is very simple, consisting of a very, very small
garden, with a few trees and some flowers and roses.
حالياً رح نتعرف على إم خليل، ويمكن في عندها ضيوف هلا متل ما
أنا شايف.
Currently, we will get to know Umm Khalil, and she might
have guests now as I can see.
خالة إم خليل.
Aunt Umm Khalil.
Ahlan, ahlan. Keremkin, keremkin, keremkin, keremkin.
Welcome, welcome. Please come in. Please come in, please
come in, please come in.
أهلاً وسهلاً، السلام عليكم.
Welcome, peace be upon you.
عليكم السلام، مية السلامة وأهلاً وسهلاً، بixwazî bi kurdî ez
xeber dim?
Peace be upon you too, a hundred welcomes, and welcome. Do
you want me to speak in Kurdish?
الله يحييكي.
May God greet you.
Ê we ehlan û sehlan. Ji we re geştekî xêrê, mît selame. Ser
çavên me hûn hatin.
Yes, welcome to you. Have a good trip, a hundred welcomes.
You came upon our eyes.
الله يسلمك. تفضلوا.
May God keep you safe. Please.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
السلام.
Peace.
يا مرحبا.
Welcome.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
شرفي خالة إم خليل.
Please, Aunt Umm Khalil.
يا رب.
Oh God.
أنا كتير سعيد ومبسوط إنه قالولي إنه إم خليل هون بالضيعة
شغلة.
I am very happy and pleased that they told me Umm Khalil is
a real figure here in the village.
Û we jî xêştekî xêrê, mît selame, sefa hatin, ser çavên me
hatin.
And a good trip to you too, a hundred welcomes, welcome, you
came upon our eyes.
شخصيتها كتير حلوة ومحبوبة كتير.
Her personality is very sweet and very loved.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
Dibê... yanî di nav gund de Mebest... ku Umm Xelîl heye, û
însanekî rind e, û tebîetê wê... pir kêfxweş e, û pir şareza
ye.
He says... I mean in the village the meaning... that Umm
Khalil is here, and she is a good person, and her nature...
is very cheerful, and very sociable.
ههههههه.
Hahaha.
قبل كل شي، لفت نظري اللبسة اللي لابستيها إنتي، شو لابسة؟
First of all, what caught my eye is the dress you are
wearing. What are you wearing?
Saetên xweş, te jî rind dît. Te jî teybet e. Ahlan û sehlan,
mît selame.
Good times, you also saw it well. You are also special.
Welcome, a hundred welcomes.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
Hai? Ev libsê... libasê... libasê Cizîrê. Cizîrê.
This? This clothing... clothing of... clothing of Cizîrê.
Cizîrê.
جزيرة؟
Jazeera?
Ê, Cizîrê.
Yes, Cizîrê.
إي هادا شو اسمه؟
Yes, what is this called?
Fîstan.
Fîstan. (Dress)
فستان.
Dress.
Xeftan... Na, hawa xeftan yak din heye.
Kaftan... No, this kaftan, there is another one.
بس هادا شو اسمه؟ فستان ولا خفتان؟
But what is this called? Fistan or khaftan?
Fîstan, fîstan, xeftan fî... bes...
Fîstan, fîstan, there is a kaftan... but...
يعني إنتي عم تقولي لبس جزيرة، فستان.. المرأة الجزراوية.
So you are saying it's the dress of Jazeera, a dress.. The
Jazeera woman.
Ê, Sûriyê tab'en, Hesekê...
Yes, Syria of course, Hasakah...
جزيرة السورية.
Syrian Jazeera.
إي طبعاً حسكة..
Yes of course, Hasakah...
هادا شو هادا، فستان ولا خفتان؟
What is this, a dress or a kaftan?
Na fîstan, fîstan. Xeftan fî.
No, fîstan, fîstan. There is a kaftan.
أنا ملاحظ إنه هادا كمامو عراض.
I noticed that its sleeves are wide.
Hawa ji ta dirûyên xwe naye, û hîn dawet dibin jî, vedikin,
aha pê re direqisin.
This is how it is sewn, and when there are weddings, they
open it, like this they dance with it.
بالاعراس بيفكوا الكمام وبيرقصوا فيها.
In weddings, they untie the sleeves and dance with them.
Û direqisin.
And they dance.
يا سلام، شي كتير حلو.
Oh wow, that's very beautiful.
هلق معنتا إنتي صوتك حلو.
Now, that means your voice is beautiful.
Dibê dengê te yanî xweş e.
He says your voice is nice, meaning.
Ê wellehî, şway şway.
Yes by God, a little bit.
سمعينا، سمعينا هيك شي، شي بسيط، هيك حلو.
Let us hear, let us hear something, something simple,
beautiful.
Em kîjanî bibêjin...
Which one should we say...
أي شي.
Anything.
Havalê...
Friend...
Belê.
Yes.
He sal daxwezek daxwaze,
This year she has a request,
Bûk dixwaze boz in ga.
The bride wants grey oxen.
He sal daxwezek daxwaze,
This year she has a request,
Bûk dixwaze gustîlka.
The bride wants a ring.
He sal daxwezek daxwaze,
This year she has a request,
Bûk dixwaze qundira.
The bride wants shoes.
He sal daxwezek daxwaze,
This year she has a request,
Bûk dixwaze bazin û dora.
The bride wants bracelets and necklaces.
He sal daxwezek daxwaze...
This year she has a request...
Ma kî... ez ê te ... min şaş kir.
What... I will you... I forgot.
شو قالت، الله يعطيكي العافية، شو قالت؟
What did she say, may God give you health, what did she say?
عم تقول..
She is saying...
عن موسم، موسم الزيتون.
About a season, the olive season.
لا، هي بدأت مو بالزيتون.
No, she didn't start with olives.
قطن.
Cotton.
إي.. إنه العروس بدها كندرة، بدها جهاز، بدها خواتم، بدها هيك
شي..
Yes.. that the bride wants shoes, wants a trousseau, wants
rings, wants something like that..
بكل موسم بدها شي.
In every season she wants something.
طيب.
Alright.
تفضلي خلينا نشوف هيك لجوا شوي.
Please, let's take a look inside a little bit.
أنا شايف في كتير ورد، كتير زرع. بتحبي الزرع كتير؟
I see there are many roses, many plants. Do you like plants
a lot?
Ê wellehî, gul... ey çîçekên bîstan. Hey top rihan...
Yes by God, roses... oh garden flowers. This is a bunch of
basil...
ريحان إي..
Basil yes..
Hey rihan. Ev xetmî ye, lûkî.
Oh basil. This is hibiscus, loki.
لوكي إي.
Loki yes.
Ewa, û hey sîddace, û hey waraq salona...
Yes, and this is sidaje, and this is salon leaves...
هي شو اسمها؟
What is this called?
Welleh ez navê wê nizanim, inu cedîd e.. ji Helebê.
By God I don't know its name, it's new.. from Aleppo.
جايبتيها جديدة.
You brought it recently.
Na, ji Helebê anîne..
No, they brought it from Aleppo...
طيب، يا خالتي، بس لحظة.
Alright, Auntie, just a moment.
هلق أنا شايف هيدي..
Now I see this..
Quffik.
Small basket.
قفة.
Basket.
Ê, quffik.
Yes, small basket.
وهادا؟
And this?
Lûkis.
Lamp.
لوكس، قديم كتير.
Lamp, very old.
Qedîm...
Old...
هدول شو هدول اللي بالحيط، فوق؟
What are these on the wall, up there?
Hey hik... bi sawî.. teşî..
This is like... to make.. spindle..
شو يعني؟
What does it mean?
Teşî.
Spindle.
مغزل.
مغزل، هادا مغزل قديم كتير.
Spindle, this is a very old spindle.
كتير.
Very.
يعني عمره..
I mean its age..
بآلاف السنين، أول ما نسج الإنسان، اعتمدوا على الغزل هي.
Thousands of years, when humans first wove, they relied on
this spinning.
كنتي تنسجي إنتي؟
Did you used to weave?
كنتي تنسجي إنتي؟ كانت تنسج؟
Did you weave? Did she weave?
Tu bi xwe çê dikir?
Did you make it yourself?
Ê! Esiha, ewî me kirî, kitiyê me na ye. Esiha fî...
Yes! Honestly, we bought that one, it's not our spinning.
Honestly there is...
لسا في آلة صنع السجاد.
There is still a machine for making carpets.
عندك؟
You have it?
سجاد يدوي..
Handmade carpet..
تمام، عندك، الله يعطيكي العافية.
Perfect, you have it, may God give you health.
Allah yiafik.
May God give you health.
هادا شو اسمه هادا؟
What is this called?
Aw... urzelik.
That... urzelik.
أورزلك، ليش؟
Urzelik, why?
Urzelik, me'nê.. nezer e..
Urzelik, it means.. evil eye..
مشان العين، ما تصيب العين البيت.
For the evil eye, so the evil eye doesn't hit the house.
ما شاء الله.
Mashallah.
طيب، خليني هلق شوف هون، هادا.. هادا قنويشة هادا؟
Okay, let me see here now, this.. is this kanwesha?
Ê qenewîc, la ana iştiğiluh.
Yes kanwesha (embroidery), no I make it.
إنتي بتشتغلي؟
You make it?
Bi zeman, ewa.. Û hay jî makîne... a deya min e.
In the past, yes.. And this is also the machine... of my
mother's.
شو يعني؟
What does it mean?
Dêk... dayika min..
Mother... my mother..
امي هي.
It's my mother's.
من إمك؟
From your mother?
Ewa.
Yes.
شقد عمرها يعني؟
How old is it?
عمرها شي 150 سنة.
Its age is about 150 years.
بركي هون شوي..
Maybe here a little bit..
شغيلة لسا هي؟ بتشتغل؟
Is it still working? Does it work?
Ê, îşteğilu.
Yes, it works.
بتشتغلي عليها إنتي؟
Do you work on it?
Ev de şixulê we...
This is your work...
ما شاء الله عليكي.. ما شاء الله عليكي.
Mashallah on you.. Mashallah on you.
هلق أنا في شغلة، خبرتها هون.. إنه أهل الضيعة..
Now there is something I was told here.. that the village
people..
لما بيطلعوا على الزيتون.. اللي أخدوا دوبركة..
When they go to the olives.. those who took doberka..
بيطلعوا بدهم يحوشوا زيتون.. دوبركة بيدهنوا على الخبز..
They go out to harvest olives.. they spread doberka on the
bread..
مع الزيت؟
With the oil?
Ê...
Yes...
وقتي كاملي فطور دن...
When they complete their breakfast...
Dibê hûn.. yanî çêke.. ne?
He says you.. I mean make.. right?
حرحلي ع الصاج خبز الصاج يعني..
Hurhuli on the saj, saj bread I mean..
Ê.
Yes.
إي.. خبز.. خبز صاج مع.. مع الدوبركة والفليفلة..
Yes.. bread.. saj bread with.. with doberka and pepper..
Ê, ehlen û sehlen..
Yes, welcome..
Dims û bîber e.
Syrup and pepper.
دبس بيبارو.
Syrup of pepper (bell pepper paste).
Dims û bîber e û... dube... rûn e. Dibê hûn rûn...
Syrup and pepper and... dube... oil. He says you oil...
دبيبة...
Dubayba...
خالة إم خليل..
Aunt Umm Khalil..
Le hunik, me bro hunik..
There, let's go there..
يلا.
Let's go.
تفضلي لهونيك، عند الشباب.
Please go there, to the guys.
Yaş can celal...
Long live the soul of majesty...
تفضلي.
Please.
شفت عندك خبز.. خبز صاج وينه؟
I saw you have bread.. saj bread, where is it?
Cîbo.. cîbo la... hay.. xebit...
Bring it.. bring it for... this.. bread...
تفضلي.
Please.
Lo ni... sêle... xubuz sêle...
Oh here... saj... saj bread...
خبز الصاج.
Saj bread.
Xubiz sêle.
تفضلي.
Please.
الله يعطيكي العافية.
May God give you health.
Allah yi'afiki, ehlen û sehlen...
May God give you health, welcome...
إي هلق شلون بدك تساوي؟ شو بتعملوا أنتو؟
Yes, now how will you do it? What do you do?
Em çend in, çend cira vebikin, em çend in?
How many are we, how many pieces should we open, how many
are we?
Çend e?
How many?
Wê...
This...
بدها تساوي ع العدد.
She wants to make according to the number.
لا هلق وحدة بس.
No, just one for now.
Firê ... firê lê...
Spread ... spread on it...
شغلة الضيعة هي..
This is the village's thing..
شغلة الضيعة وشغل إيدها..
The village's thing and her handiwork..
ما شاء الله، والدوبركة كمان شغل إيدها؟
Mashallah, and the doberka is also her handiwork?
إي.
Yes.
Hawa.. mastî kîsê.. hawa dimsê bîber e..
This is strained yogurt.. this is pepper syrup..
شو عم تقولي؟
What are you saying?
Hay mustîka kamundî duberke. We hada...
This is kamundi duberke. And this...
Şû isma btsammûha intû? Mustîka kamundî?
What is its name, what do you call it? Mustika kamundi?
Mustîka kamundî.
Mustika kamundi.
Kamundî. Hada el-duberke.
Kamundi. This is the duberke.
Duberke.
Duberke kamundî.
Duberke kamundi.
Ew jî nene ye.
And that is mint.
Na'na.
Mint.
Hay byaklûha wella birûhû a-zaytûn es-subh? A-hawwaş ez-
zaytûn.
Do they eat this or go to the olives in the morning? To
harvest the olives.
Byifrû aleyha...
They have it for breakfast...
Êwa.
Yes.
Heni bşa'lû canbon lamma btsîr weqt el akil...
They light a fire next to it when it's time to eat...
Bşa'lû canbon nar w bsaxnû aleyha w byaklû.
They light a fire next to them and heat it on it and eat.
Ya selam. W smi'it inno kaman min el-duberke byiṭbuxû xêr
şî, şakriye meselen?
Wow. And I heard that they also cook other things with
duberke, shakriye for example?
Mabyiṭbuxû şakriye bid-duberke?
Don't they cook shakriye with duberke?
Lebenîye şakriye...
Labaniye shakriye...
Lebenîye şakriye?
Labaniye shakriye?
Lê, erê erê, em bi zeytê diqelînin, dima em... û em dikin
lebenîyê.
Yes, yes yes, we fry it with oil, then we... and we make it
into labniye.
Lebenîyê. Êwa. Bas... em dikelînin.
Labniye. Yes. But... we boil it.
Şû am tqûl?
What is she saying?
E ba'd et-ṭabix.
After cooking.
Ah after cooking.
Hada ma bsîr... hada xubz tannûr?
Doesn't this become... is this tannour bread?
La, sac. Sac had.
No, saj. This is saj.
Sac. Şukran. Şukran. Allah ya'ṭîkum el-afiye.
Saj. Thank you. Thank you. May God give you health.
Allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye daymen ya xaltî um Xelîl, rah ndûqa
hala ba'd şway.
May God give you health always Auntie Um Khalil, we will
taste it in a bit.
Es-selamu aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleykum es-selam.
And upon you be peace.
Ehlen.
Hello uncle.
Welcome.
Şlonak?
How are you?
Nt'arraf aleyk?
Thank God.
Can we know your name?
Ehle w sehle, Ebû Mes'ûd.
Welcome, Abu Masoud.
Ehlen w sehlen ammî Ebû Mes'ûd. Şû am tsawî hala?
Welcome my uncle Abu Masoud. What are you doing now?
Wallah am nsawî clel la hatta a-hmar w biddna nrûh a-cebel.
By God, we are making a saddle to put on the donkey and we
want to go to the mountain.
Allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye. Şû beddak tsawî bil cebel? Şû fî
andak el-yom?
May God give you health. What do you want to do in the
mountain? What do you have today?
Bedna ncîb haṭebat w şexlet qaşş w hêk mşan el-bêt.
We want to bring firewood and some straw and such for the
house.
Maşallah, Allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye. Kull nehar btrûh a-cebel?
Mashallah, may God give you health. Do you go to the
mountain every day?
Ê kull nehar.
Yes every day.
Kull nehar btrûh a-cebel... êmêt btrûh es-subh wella el-
masa?
Every day you go to the mountain... when do you go, morning
or evening?
El-masa wel subh bnrûh bncîb haṭeb... hada el-haṭeb şwayet
haṭeb w şexle w bnrûh abên ez-zaytûnat...
Evening and morning we go and bring firewood... this
firewood, a little firewood and things and we go among the
olive trees...
Allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye, andak zaytûnat?
May God give you health, do you have olive trees?
Elhamdulillah, fî xamsîn şejera.
Thank God, there are fifty trees.
Xamsîn şejera andak? Allah yirziqak. Înşallah el-mosem
kwayyes?
You have fifty trees? May God provide for you. Hopefully the
season is good?
La wallah, mosem cebelî ya axî w şûfî maba'rif...
No by God, it's a mountain season my brother, and I don't
know...
W ibnî mardan ya'nî ta'rif... ibnî mardan ma'o kilye, kull
yom bnrûh a-duktor w nicî ya'nî haletna ta'bana şway.
And my son is sick, you know... my son is sick, he has a
kidney issue, every day we go to the doctor and come back,
meaning our situation is a bit tired.
Selamto, selamto. Allah yi'înkum, Allah ykûn ma'kum.
Get well soon, get well soon. May God help you, may God be
with you.
Ene am şimm mehşî... w ya'nî rîhet mehşî ṭabxet mehşî... w
haṭeb şexxîl. Min andak?
I'm smelling stuffed vegetables... I mean the smell of a
stuffed vegetables dish... and firewood burning. Is it from
your place?
Ê.
Yes.
Udxul la cuwwa şway ma'leş?
Can I go inside a little bit, is it okay?
Ehlen w sehlen, tfeddel.
Welcome, go ahead.
Nt'arraf a-xaltî Um Mes'ûd?
Can we meet Auntie Um Masoud?
Ehlen w sehlen.
Welcome.
Ya rabb... rîhet el-haṭeb w rîhet ṭabxet el-mehşî...
Oh Lord... the smell of firewood and the smell of the
stuffed vegetables dish...
Axî el-xaz xalî, ma nahsin niştarî... w nehna niştexil
a-haṭeb.
My brother, gas is expensive, we can't buy it... and we work
on firewood.
Allah ya'ṭîkum el-afiye. Halikun ta'ban ya'nî, şû bedna
na'mil. Allah yirziqkum w ykûn ma'kum.
May God give you health. Your situation is tiring, what can
we do. May God provide for you and be with you.
Hay şû isma haydî?
What is the name of this?
Ê?
Yes?
Fuxara isma?
Is it called a clay pot?
Ê fuxara. Fuxara ene amalta hay, w iştexelt fîha w sawayt
mişan na'mil biş-şitwîye niştexil tahta.
Yes a clay pot. I made this clay pot, and worked on it and
made it so we can work under it in the winter.
Mabta'rifî arabî?
You don't know Arabic?
La şway.
No, a little.
Bî'înek Ebû Mes'ûd şway. Tfeddelî. Tfeddelî.
Help her a little Abu Masoud. Go ahead. Go ahead.
Allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye. Xallîna nrûh la and el-mehşî.
May God give you health. Let's go to the stuffed vegetables.
Dolma.
Dolma... Sorma?
La bes dolma.
No, just dolma.
Ma fî sorma?
There's no sorma?
La, la.
No, no.
Ma fî yabraq l-yom?
No grape leaves today?
La.
No.
Êşû haṭṭîtîlo el-yom la-dolma?
What did you put in the dolma today?
Me dimis kirîye... bîber... hinek sîr... û pîvaz...
We put molasses... pepper... some garlic... and onion...
Basal.
What?
Onion.
Basal w flêfle... w ruz w zêt.
Onion and pepper... and rice and oil.
Ruz w zêt, zêt aslî.
Rice and oil, original olive oil.
Zêt aslî. Kwayyes ktîr.
Original olive oil. Very good.
Ehlen w sehlen.
Welcome.
W êşû fî aklat kaman meşhûra hon bed-day'a?
And what other famous dishes are here in the village?
Şerref ammî Ebû Mes'ûd.
Tell him, uncle Abu Masoud.
Dolma xweş e... û boranîye xweş e...
Dolma is good... and boraniye is good...
Şû am btqûl hala?
What is she saying now?
Boranîye.
Boraniye.
Boranîye xweş e...
Boraniye is good...
Û kutilk xweş e...
Yes.
And kutilk is good...
Kuṭṭayîye.
Kutayiye.
Kuṭṭayîye şû hay?
Yes, kutilk.
What is kutayiye?
Hada qameh bnhuṭṭo a-nar w bnhuṭ aleyh şwayet lahme w nduqo
a-cirin...
This is wheat we put on the fire and put a little meat on it
and pound it in the mortar...
Ṭaybe ktîr. W xêro?
Very tasty. And what else?
Û fasûlîye.
And beans.
Fasûlîye.
Beans.
Û riz, û firîk, û kutilk.
And rice, and freekeh, and kutilk.
Ya selam. Ehlen w sehlen. W lebenîye.
Wow. Welcome. And labaniye.
Û lebenîye. Û kofte.
And labniye. And kofta.
Kofte êş el kofte ba'a qûlîlî?
Kofta.
Yes.
Kofte êş el kofte ba'a qûlîlî?
Kofta, what is kofta then tell me?
Kofte bi lahm... kibbeh û paşê kofte...
Kofta with meat... kibbeh and then kofta...
Kofte... kofte... goşt û...
Kofta... kofta... meat and...
Kibbeh w qraş kofte... lahme... w dibs rumman... w guşt...
Kibbeh and kofta patties... meat... and pomegranate
molasses... and meat...
Goşt yanî goşt.
Goşt means meat.
W haṭṭî lahme ma'o ya'nî w a-qraş... w kuṭṭayîye...
And you put meat with it, you know, and patties... and
kutayiye...
Hala ene smi'it inno andkun hon el kibbeh en-nayye
mabiṭhuṭṭûla lahme?
Now I heard that here you don't put meat in the raw kibbeh?
Ê, kibbeh xav bê goşt e. Kibbeh başqe e û kofte başqe e.
Yes, raw kibbeh is without meat. Kibbeh is different and
kofta is different.
Es-subh amilnûha.
We made it in the morning.
Es-subh amiltûha? Hazna mû kwayyes, kunna aklna ma'kun.
You made it in the morning? Our luck is not good, we would
have eaten with you.
Ê wallah kan fîha şway yumkin, fîha qursên tlatî.
By God there was a little bit maybe, there are two or three
patties.
Tenê kofte.
Only kofta.
Ṭaybe. Allah ya'ṭîkum el-afiye. Allah yirziqkun ya rabb
yiftah aleykum.
Alright. May God give you health. May God provide for you,
oh Lord, may He open doors for you.
Es-selamu aleykum. Allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye.
Peace be upon you. May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health.
Allah hêk yilabbiskun el-afiye ya rabb. Wên kintû?
May God clothe you in health, oh Lord. Where were you?
Walla a-zaytûnat.
By God, at the olive trees.
Am tkasshûhon?
Are you pruning them?
Ê mşan eş-şite.
Yes for the winter.
Allah ya'ṭîkum el-afiye. Min êmêt ṭli'tû?
May God give you health. Since when have you been out?
Hala es-sa'a tintên ṭli'na.
Now at two o'clock we went out.
Wes-subh btuṭla'û?
Do you go out in the morning?
Ê subh w min tlatî w nos w hêk şî.
Yes morning and from half past three and such.
Kull nehar am btsawû hal şexle?
Do you do this work every day?
Ê kull nehar. Ê.
Yes every day. Yes.
Mû sa'be aleykun?
Isn't it hard for you?
Şway sa'be şû bedna nsawî.
A little hard, what can we do.
Xallîna nimşî hêk şway. Hala hada ez-zaytûn had?
Let's walk a little bit. Now is this olive?
Ê ê hada zaytûn.
Yes yes this is olive.
Zaytûn sintyan hada, min foq min el-cebel ya'nî min el-hirş.
This is sintyan olive, from up from the mountain, meaning
from the woods.
Ê.
Yes.
Şû btsawû fî, hada bitbî'û, şû btsawû fî?
What do you do with it, do you sell this, what do you do
with it?
La la ma minbî'o. Naxdo a-bêt mişan eş-şite.
No no we don't sell it. We take it home for the winter.
Ta'al la hon şway ammî inte.
Come here a little, my uncle, you.
Şlon wladak?
How are your children?
La, hada axûy.
No, this is my brother.
Ibn axûk. Imşî şway. Kem kîlo kull hmar şayel?
Your nephew. Walk a bit. How many kilos is each donkey
carrying?
Himar byiṭla' axaff... byiṭla' tisa'în hêk şî.
The donkey takes less... it takes ninety or so.
Tisa'în, mîye.
Ninety, a hundred.
Imşî.
Walk.
Şqad kîlo el-yom, hal bî hal fetra hay?
How much is a kilo today, in this period?
Kîlo? Byiṭla'... mîye.
A kilo? It comes to... a hundred.
Kîlo bi mîye?
A kilo for a hundred?
La mû bi mîye, lakin... mîyat kîlo byiṭla' aw akṭar.
No not for a hundred, but... it comes to a hundred kilos or
more.
Hala hada eş-şîdan hada maṭrat el-may hay? Hay btsawû fîha
may mṭhuṭṭûla... imşî.
Now this canteen... this is a water canteen? You put water
in it... walk.
Allah ya'ṭîkum el-afiye. Am tqussû bil minşar el-adî wella
minşar kehreba?
May God give you health. Are you cutting with a normal saw
or an electric saw?
La minşar adî, minşar îdên.
No normal saw, hand saw.
Minşar adî.
Normal saw.
Kull is-sine hêk, ala wuquf şway bas.
All year like this, just stand still a bit.
Kem şahar btiştexlû hêk bi hal şexle hay?
How many months do you work like this in this job?
Bas hal fetra.
Just this period.
Bas hal fetra hay.
Hala hada xurc... xallîna bas nihkî şway. Hada xurc mû hêk?
Now this is a saddlebag... let's just talk a bit. This is a
saddlebag, right?
Ê hada xurc.
Yes this is a saddlebag.
Hada intû mfelsîno?
Did you make this?
Ê nehna mfelsîno.
Yes we made it.
W had?
And this?
Lihna kaman. Hada clel.
Us too. This is a saddle.
Hada clel.
This is a saddle.
Kaman fî hada hon byiştexlo bid-day'a?
Is there anyone who makes this here in the village?
La la, kan awwalî wahed bi Xelîlko am byiştexil, huwwe mat.
No no, there used to be one in Khalilko who worked on it, he
died.
Mat. Lakan hala mîn am byiştexlo?
He died. Then now who is making it?
Hala a-sûq am niştirî.
Now we buy it from the market.
A-sûq am tiştirû. Şqad byiswa?
You buy it from the market. How much is it worth?
Hada? Xamsta'ş alif.
This? 15 thousand.
Xamsta'ş alif.
15 thousand.
W had şqad byiswa?
And how much is this worth?
Hada alfên.
This is two thousand.
Alfên.
Two thousand.
Allah yirziqkun. W allah ya'ṭîkum el-afiye. W alif şukr
ilkun, ya rabb allah yihmîkun. Ma' es-selame. Allah ma'kum.
May God provide for you. And may God give you health. And a
thousand thanks to you, may God protect you oh Lord.
Goodbye. God be with you.
Es-selamu aleykum. Şlonak?
Peace be upon you. How are you?
Elhamdulillah.
Thank God.
Şlon sahtak? Allah yxallîk. Nt'arraf aleyk?
How is your health? May God keep you. Can we know your name?
Min rîf Heleb el-xerbî, Sa'ad Necmuddîn el-Xalid.
From western rural Aleppo, Saad Najmuddin el-Khaled.
Ehlen w sehlen fîk. Mnên biz-zabt min rîf Heleb el-xerbî?
Welcome. From where exactly in western rural Aleppo?
Min Kefr Nûran.
From Kafr Nouran.
Ya ehle w sehle b-ahel Kefr Nûran. Nazihîn la hon?
Welcome to the people of Kafr Nouran. Are you displaced
here?
Ê na'am.
Yes, yes.
Ehle w sehle fîkum. Mîn eş-şebab hadol?
Welcome to you. Who are these boys?
Wlad axûy. Bes had ibn cîranna hon w wlad axûy.
My nephews. But this is our neighbor's son here and my
nephews.
Ya ehle w sehle fîkum. Wên saknîn hon?
Welcome to you. Where do you live here?
Saknîn hon, bid-day'a... hay hon, ma'mal hon, cuwwa.
We live here, in the village... this is here, a factory
here, inside.
Mumkin hêk bas tiftahlî el-bab ta'rrifnî... ma fî bab ed-dar
hon, hada el-ihram.
Can you just open the door and introduce me... there is no
house door here, this is a blanket.
Wên ahlak, wên mîn fî ma'kun saken?
Where is your family, who lives with you?
El-hacce hiyye bil xerbî, bukra aw ba'd bukra bticî, w ene w
axûy hon am niştexil w m'ayyîn fî halna hon qa'dîn.
The old lady is in the west, tomorrow or the day after she
will come, and my brother and I are working here and looking
after ourselves sitting here.
Allah yqawwîkum ya rabb. Allah yqawwîkum. Şlon el-wada' hon?
May God give you strength oh Lord. May God give you
strength. How is the situation here?
Wallah el-wada' şlon ma kan... mkerkeb. Bas elhamdulillah
ayşîn hala la bukra byifrija Allah.
By God the situation is whatever... messy. But thank God we
are living now, tomorrow God will bring relief.
Elhamdulillah, haydî... haydî kelam hilû ktîr. Înşallah hêk
am tiştexlû w allah hêk bî'înkum ya rabb.
Thank God, this... this is very sweet talk. God willing you
are working and may God help you oh Lord.
Qaddêş amrek inte?
How old are you?
Ihda'ş aw tlata'ş... Ihda'ş, ustad.
11 or 13... 11, teacher.
Ihda'ş... şlon hon êşû... fî byût ya'nî cahze, hal xuriftên
hadol şayfon ene?
11... how is it here what... are there ready houses, these
two rooms I see?
Ê cahzat.
Yes they are ready.
Bas ene şayef kanu hnîk fî ihram kaman bab ihram?
But I see there was a blanket there, also a blanket door?
Hadêk waqt mnam msakkero mşan el-bsas aw kaza...
That one when we sleep we close it because of the cats or
something...
Mşan el-qiṭat ya'nî.
Because of the cats, meaning.
Ê na'am.
Yes, yes.
Êwa. Xubz, sarif sahhî, may, wad'kun şlon?
I see. Bread, sewage, water, how is your situation?
Wallah elhamdulillah. Bas el-xubz awqat mabnilqa ma'na xubz
mnrûh and cîranna mncîb şway w hêk. Mnrûh la hon mnixbiz,
awqat mndayyin mnixbiz, hêk ayşîn elhamdulillah.
By God thank God. But bread sometimes we don't find bread
with us, we go to our neighbors and bring a little and such.
We go here and bake, sometimes we borrow and bake, we live
like this thank God.
Fî hon byixbizû ya'nî a-tannûr aw şî?
Are there people who bake here on the tannour or something?
Ê byixbizû ustad.
Yes they bake, teacher.
Êwa. Yalla allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye ya Sa'ad.
I see. Alright may God give you health Saad.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health.
Allah yqawwîkum ya rabb.
May God give you strength oh Lord.
Yalla, es-selamu aleykum.
May God give you health.
Alright, peace be upon you.
Allah ma'ak ustad.
God be with you teacher.
Es-selamu aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleyk is-selam.
And upon you be peace.
Şlonik immî?
How are you my mother?
Hemdulillah ustad.
Thank God teacher.
Allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk.
Intî min hon?
Are you from here?
Min Ma'mela.
From Ma'mala.
Ehle w sehle fîkî, umm êş?
Welcome to you, mother of who?
Umm Celal.
Um Jalal.
Ehlên w sehlên bî um Celal.
Welcome Um Jalal.
Allah yselmak.
May God keep you safe.
Ihkîlî şlon wada' el-mara hon andkun?
Tell me, how is the situation of women here with you?
Ê arabîytî da'îfe ya'nî şway.
Ah, my Arabic is a bit weak meaning.
B-ellî bta'rfî.
With what you know.
Şlon biddî qillak?
What can I tell you?
Kurmanji
Yeah, look at Aisha, she studies, learns, and works...
Yeah, what studies, we don't have studying here.
Kurmanji
In the past?
In the past? There was, actually.
Kurmanji
They used to study and work?
Of course.
Kurmanji
So, for example, did you have female doctors, lawyers,
engineers, teachers...
Kurmanji
You mean here in our village or what?
Yes.
Kurmanji
Yes, we do. We have a doctor.
Alright.
Kurmanji
We have lawyers.
I am talking about women, mind you!
Kurmanji
Women? No.
None?
Kurmanji
No, none.
In the past, there weren't any?
Kurmanji
No. Here in the village, there aren't any.
There aren't any?
Kurmanji
Of course, there aren't.
Not at all. Don't they get educated, I mean, don't the girls
here study and get an education, did they in the past?
Kurmanji
Of course, they used to study.
Alright. Now you work the land, just like your husband.
Kurmanji
Of course, yes.
Tell me, you know, a proverb from your village's proverbs.
Kurmanji
Well, I don't know how.
You haven't memorized any proverb from your village?
Kurmanji
Not really, no.
Not at all. What do the women in your village wear?
Kurmanji
Like this, you know, just like this...
What is this? Tell me about it.
Kurmanji
Well, what am I... I don't really have Arabic.
The thing you put on your head in this manner, what do you
call this way of wearing the scarf on your head?
Kurmanji
She doesn't know this.
How many children do you have?
Kurmanji
I have five.
May God keep them safe.
Kurmanji
Boys and girls?
No, five girls and a boy.
Kurmanji
May God keep them safe. What do they do for a living?
They don't do anything, my son is coming to us...
Kurmanji
And the girls?
Two girls are married, and three are with me.
Kurmanji
What did they study?
Up to the eleventh grade.
Kurmanji
Eleventh grade. And the man of the house? Abu Jalal?
Abu Jalal is a farmer.
Kurmanji
A farmer? Upon my head, indeed.
This shy young lady, come here a little bit, come here let
me see. Come, where are you going?
Kurmanji
Come on, you shy girl. Come here, mother, let me talk to you
a bit. You've honored us, I want to talk to you. How is she
related to you?
Kurmanji
She is my neighbor.
Your neighbor? Let me hear her. Umm what?
Kurmanji
Umm Muhammad.
Umm Muhammad, please come over here, come here a little bit.
Kurmanji
Peace be upon you.
May God give you health.
Kurmanji
How are you? How is your health?
Welcome to you.
Kurmanji
Abu Jalal?
No, not Abu Jalal, Abu Jalal is her husband. I am Muhammad
Abu Shoukri.
Kurmanji
Abu Shoukri. Welcome to you.
May God keep you safe and prolong your life.
Kurmanji
Please step over here.
How are you?
Kurmanji
Good.
How is your health?
Kurmanji
والله مافي شي. Rind û narind e.
شو يعني رند ونرند إي؟
Kurmanji
Naxweş im, dil dikişe, şekir pê re, عم أقول أنا تعبانة معي
سكر معي كلشي.
Kurmanji
Get well soon, it's an honor.
You speak Arabic, of course?
Kurmanji
Yes, Arabic, yes. Welcome to you all.
Tell me, now I want you to be the judge. She says the
situation of women here is very good, absolutely, and they
are even oppressing the men on top of that. Is that true?
Kurmanji
You mean women are oppressing men?
Yes!
Kurmanji
I don't think so.
It's like that wherever you go?
Kurmanji
It's like that wherever you go.
What is your opinion?
Kurmanji
He passed away, my husband passed away.
Your husband passed away?
Kurmanji
Yes.
May God have mercy on him.
Kurmanji
May God have mercy on your deceased ones.
What do you do for work?
Kurmanji
Well, I'm a farmer.
What are you working on these days? Are you pruning olives,
what are you doing?
Kurmanji
No, pruning is in the spring, and now on the 15th of the
month, this month I mean the 10th, we will start the olive
harvesting season, God willing.
Kurmanji
So right now you are preparing, which means you are burying
the stones under the olive tree, so that...
Kurmanji
Yes, we clear out, we clear under the tree, so that we can
harvest easily.
Kurmanji
Easily, fertilizing? How is the oil this year?
Well, thank God, the oil is good this year.
Kurmanji
Oh Lord, may God provide for you. Do you have animals? Do
you have animals?
Kurmanji
No, there are no animals, none.
My house was in Aleppo, with the situation we came here.
Kurmanji
May God provide for you all. May God give you health, thank
you. Peace be upon you. Goodbye, welcome to you.
Kurmanji
Peace be upon you.
And upon you be peace and the mercy of God.
Kurmanji
How are you?
Welcome. Welcome, welcome sir.
Kurmanji
May God give you health.
Welcome.
Kurmanji
It seems I see the press in a phase of, you know, operation?
Preparation for operation?
Kurmanji
Yes, by God, we have started now, we started its maintenance
and finished.
Kurmanji
Maintenance now?
Maintenance is finished, thank God, yesterday, the day
before yesterday we finished.
Kurmanji
May God give you health.
And in two or three days, God willing, we will start working
for the season.
Kurmanji
For the season? God willing. Exactly when?
What?
Kurmanji
Exactly when?
Saturday, God willing.
Kurmanji
So on Saturday?
I mean the middle of the tenth month, approximately.
Kurmanji
Ah, the middle of the tenth month. Well, before we enter the
press and talk about the preparations, let's go in and look
at the olive groves here, from here, from this high spot,
please go ahead.
Kurmanji
Here you go.
The view from your house is very beautiful. Now this is your
house and your press here, right?
Kurmanji
Yes, the house and the press.
The house and the press.
Kurmanji
Now here we are located roughly on the western side of the
village, right?
Kurmanji
Roughly, yes, the western side.
The western side. I see, and are these olives? For the
village?
Kurmanji
For the village, it's all for the village. From here it
starts from that hill over there, and to the valley down
below, and on the hill, behind the hill as well... it's all
for the village.
Kurmanji
And Amra Ushaghi, for the village of Amra Ushaghi?
Amra Ushaghi is on that hill over there... past the hill to
Amra Ushaghi and to Qudekwi.
Kurmanji
And to Khalil Gulkwi, like that?
Past that hill to Khalil Gulkwi. The broadcasting station,
past the broadcasting station I mean. Khalil Gulkwi,
whatever Khalil Gulkwi. Korkan as well.
Kurmanji
And Korkan is further inside, past the hill too, that
village.
Kurmanji
Alright. I want to ask you, approximately how many olive
trees are there in the village?
Kurmanji
Here, on the mountain roughly, around... I'd say, roughly
around 15 thousand.
Kurmanji
15 thousand?
Yes.
Kurmanji
And in the entire village?
In the whole village, there is a plain over there, a plain
down below... roughly, I mean, it comes out to another 15
thousand too.
Kurmanji
So you have 30 thousand olive trees.
Approximately, yes.
Kurmanji
What type of olives do you have?
80 percent Zayyati.
Kurmanji
Zayyati?
Yes. And the rest?
Kurmanji
The rest is a mix, I mean Khalkhali, Sourani... it's a mix.
How is the production this year? How is the season?
Kurmanji
The season this year, thank God. I mean, you could say 80
percent, 75 percent.
Kurmanji
Good. I mean, what is your yield rate, normally I mean here
in the village, I mean how much do the olives yield for you,
does it produce very good oil?
Kurmanji
The yield... is about 20 percent roughly.
20 percent?
Kurmanji
Yes, 20. Every 100 kilos of olives, 20 kilos of oil.
Every 100 kilos of olives, 20 kilos of oil.
Kurmanji
Yes, 20 kilos of oil. Every 100 kilos...
Mashallah.
Kurmanji
Let's move inside, to the press, let's see how you've set it
up.
Kurmanji
Come in.
Come in, welcome.
Kurmanji
How old is this press?
About 8 years.
Kurmanji
8 years. So it's modern.
Modern, a modern press.
Kurmanji
What is its capacity?
Its capacity is from 50 to 60 tons.
Kurmanji
50, 60 tons? In 24 hours or...
In 24 hours.
Kurmanji
And how many workers work here?
About 10 workers.
Kurmanji
10 workers. Now what are its sections here, just briefly,
what are its sections?
Kurmanji
Its sections, this is it here, its start is the conveyor
belt. The olives come down from here, and it pulls.
Kurmanji
I see. Meaning here...
Yes, here. Here he empties the olives. He empties the olives
here, and the conveyor belt operates, taking it to the
washer.
Kurmanji
The washing stage is over there?
They wash the olives. And it goes up to the crusher, it
crushes... the pits I mean, it crushes the pits. And it goes
up to the kneaders here, it kneads.
Kurmanji
And it goes up to the decanter, this is the main machine
right here. The decanter, the main machine is the one that
separates the oil, the olives, and the pomace from each
other.
Kurmanji
Look sir, and after the decanter, it goes up to the
separator. These are two separators, one for water...
Kurmanji
The oil separator.
That one is for the black water...
Kurmanji
The black water...
And this is for the olive oil. It separates the water from
the oil.
Kurmanji
The olive basin.
The oil basin is here, and this is the scale... and...
Kurmanji
Alright, okay, let's stop here for a bit, let's have a brief
chat... What is the price of oil this year? Currently...
Kurmanji
Well, the price currently, the first is around 25 dollars.
The first? The first. This year's season?
Kurmanji
The season, this year's season hasn't started for us yet...
In two or three days, God willing, we will start.
Kurmanji
Last year's season.
Last year, about 25.
Kurmanji
Go ahead... I mean the oil from last year's season, its
price now is 25 dollars...
Kurmanji
25 dollars.
And the new season, what do you expect?
Kurmanji
The new season means it will be slightly less... this is the
first batch, I mean. A bit less, like 24, 24 and a half
dollars.
Kurmanji
24 and a half. I mean why would the new season be cheaper?
The new season, the olives now, I mean, the pomace, all the
heat from the pomace makes it... later on, it gets a bit
sharper.
Kurmanji
It gets a bit sharper, it gets a bit bitter like that...
After 20 days, for example, after the 20th of the month...
the sweet oil comes out. Rain falls too, if it rains, even
the peroxide decreases... and the acid goes down... I mean
its acidity comes out too... Even, you know, the taste
changes too.
Kurmanji
Okay. When do the people of the village start with the
olives I mean, when do they harvest the olives?
Kurmanji
The olives, those with a light load start right about now...
since four or five days ago, they have started.
Kurmanji
And at the very latest, when?
At the latest I mean they delay it until 1/1 approximately.
Kurmanji
Mashallah. About two and a half months.
About two and a half months, yes.
Kurmanji
Mashallah. May it be blessed. And the season, God willing,
will be good this year.
Kurmanji
Thank God, honestly I mean the grace is from God, and thank
God...
Kurmanji
How much do you take here from the farmers, from the
peasants?
Kurmanji
Basically, they set it for us... at 7 percent.
7 percent.
Kurmanji
May God provide for you, and give you health...
Upon my head, thank you... welcome sir.
Kurmanji
And God willing we didn't waste your time.
May God give you health...
Kurmanji
Thank you. Thank you, welcome sir, welcome, goodbye.
The heritage and musical folklore in the village of Maamal
Ushaghi is the same folklore known throughout the entire
Afrin region in its various districts. In this special
segment, in the second tour in the village of Maamal
Ushaghi, we will get to know examples of this folklore with
the Nay player, Uncle Abu Jakar, along with the small dance
troupe and the Bouzouki player, Mr. Hasan. Welcome to you,
dear viewers, in this short segment.
Kurmanji
Uncle Abu Jakar, what are you going to play for us now?
شو هذا أخ حنان، أنا ما بعرف عربي مزبوط.
What is this brother Hanan, I don't know Arabic well.
باللي بتعرفه.
With whatever you know.
Ew bi Tirkî... çi jê ra digotin... kaval... na, na, fîq e.
In Turkish... what did they call it... kaval... no, no, it's
fîq.
Fîq e, fîq.
It's fîq, fîq.
شغل تراثي قديم.
Old traditional work.
يا سلام.
Oh wow.
وهذا الناي تراثي من ابوه ابوي.
And this Ney is traditional, from my father's father.
هذا من ابو ابوك.
This is from your father's father.
عن جدي، ونحنا راعي ابن راعي، وشباب الضيعة كلهم موجودين.
From my grandfather, and we are shepherds, sons of
shepherds, and all the village youth are present.
نحنا راعي ابن راعي واجدادنا الرعيان.
We are shepherds, sons of shepherds, and our ancestors were
shepherds.
اهلا وسهلا فيك، من بيت معمو، اصل الضيعة.
Welcome. From the Ma'mo family, the origin of the village.
بيت معمو.
The Ma'mo family.
تفضل سمعني، معناتها هلق رح تسمعني يعني عزف الرعاة.
Please, let me hear. So now you will let me hear, I mean,
the shepherds' playing.
مضبوط.
Exactly.
الله يعطيك العافية، مشكور.
May God give you health, thank you.
Mala we ava. Spas dikim.
Thank you. I thank you.
... ji bo hemû cemaetê. Geştka we xweş.
... for all the gathering. Have a good trip.
شو هاد اللي عزفته؟ شو هلق عزفت؟ شو عزفتلنا؟
What is this that you played? What did you just play? What
did you play for us?
Te çi lêxist?
What did you play?
Ev Us û Ezîz e.
This is Us and Ezîz.
Dalêl.
Û Lobab e. Û evê dîtir jî sivik e pê.
And Lobab. And this other one is fast with it.
Te got ev Us û Ezîz e, û Dalêl, û Lobab e, û evê dîtir jî
sivik e pê. Yanî mîna teqsîmat.
You said this is Us and Ezîz, and Dalêl, and Lobab, and the
other one is fast with it. Meaning like taqsims.
تقسيمات، الله يعطيك العافية، شكرا الك.
Taqsims, may God give you health, thank you.
هلق بدنا نشوف شي من الشباب، استاذ حسن عازف البزق، ومعنا ايضا
معزوفة وبدنا نشوف الشباب كيف بيرقصوا هون بالضيعة.
Now we want to see something from the youth, Mr. Hassan, the
bouzouki player, and we also have a piece and we want to see
how the youth dance here in the village.
تفضل استاذ شرف.
Please, sir, go ahead.
Werin, ha werin!
Come on, come on!
Ha Xelîlo ha!
Come on, Khalil, come on!
Ha Şêxo ha! Şêxê min, bide ha!
Come on, Sheikh, come on! My Sheikh, give it!
Çavê te bixwim înşallah! E rasî vallah!
I will eat your eyes, God willing! On my head, by God!
الله يعطيك العافية، مشكور.
May God give you health, thank you.
بس بدي اعرف هاي الرقصة اللي رقصتوها والموسيقى اللي سمعناها،
شو اسمها؟
I just want to know this dance that you danced and the music
we heard, what is its name?
والله مابعرف شو اسمها.
By God I don't know its name.
مابتعرف؟
You don't know?
أنت بتعرف؟
Do you know?
بتعرف انت؟ بتعرف شو اسم الموسيقى، شو اسم الرقصة؟
Do you know? Do you know what the music's name is, what the
dance's name is?
لحن تركي.
A Turkish melody.
تركي؟ وشو اسمه؟
Turkish? And what's its name?
والله مابعرف شو اسمه بس لحن تركي.
By God I don't know its name, but it's a Turkish melody.
والرقصة؟
And the dance?
والرقصة عادي، عم يرقصوا تركي.
And the dance is normal, they are dancing Turkish.
تركي ولا كردي تراث المنطقة؟
Turkish or Kurdish, the region's heritage?
تراث، هي تراث الاكراد هنيك، يعني الاكراد بتركيا.
Heritage, it's the heritage of the Kurds there, meaning the
Kurds in Turkey.
استاذ عزت؟
Mr. Izzat?
اي، هدول بيشتغلوها، بيرقصوا اثنين شخصين، اسمها جفتة تلة.
Yes, they do it, two people dance, it's called Çiftetelli.
جفتة؟
Çifte?
جفتة يعني اثنين، اثنين عم يرقصوا مع بعضهم اسمها جفتة تلة.
Çifte means two, two are dancing together it's called
Çiftetelli.
وحتى البردة هاي على الوترين بتندق، مو اكثر.
And even this fret is played on two strings, no more.
وترين، شخصين بيرقصوا، وترين بيندق اسمها جفتة تلة.
Two strings, two people dance, two strings are played, it's
called Çiftetelli.
يعني هلق هنن رقصوا تراث المنطقة؟
Meaning now they danced the region's heritage?
اي طبعا، جفتة تلة معروف بالضيعة بالمنطقة كلها، يعني...
Yes of course, Çiftetelli is known in the village, in the
whole region, meaning...
أعزائي المشاهدين، الى هنا تنتهي هذه الجولة الثانية والأخيرة
من قرية معمل اوشاغي التابعة لناحية راجو غربي منطقة عفرين في
ريف حلب الشمالي.
Dear viewers, here ends this second and final tour of the
village of Ma'mal Ushaghi belonging to the Rajo sub-district
west of the Afrin region in the northern Aleppo countryside.
سنكون معكم في الاسابيع القادمة في جولات جديدة من مناطق سورية
اخرى حبيبة.
We will be with you in the coming weeks in new tours from
other beloved Syrian regions.
لمتابعة برنامجنا تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة وايضا
موقعنا على الانترنت حلب تودي تي في دوت نت.
To follow our program, follow the channel's special Facebook
page and also our website halabtodaytv.net.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.