ميدانكي قرية سورية تتبع ناحية شران في منطقة عفرين في ريف حلب
الشمالي.
Maydanki is a Syrian village belonging to the Sharran
subdistrict in the Afrin region, in the northern countryside
of Aleppo.
وهي تقع في الجزء الشمالي من جبل الكرد، وعلى السفح الجنوبي
الشرقي لمرتفع كلسي بجانب نهر عفرين.
It is located in the northern part of Kurd Mountain, and on
the southeastern slope of a limestone elevation next to the
Afrin River.
وبتتألف من قسمين، ميدانكي تحت وميدانكي فوق، أو ميدانكي
الصغيرة وميدانكي الكبيرة.
It consists of two parts: Lower Maydanki and Upper Maydanki,
or Little Maydanki and Great Maydanki.
بهالحلقة من برنامج جولات رح نكون معكم من قرية ميدانكي. يلا
معنا.
In this episode of the "Tours" program, we will be with you
from the village of Maydanki. Let's go.
قرية ميدانكي، من قرى جبل الأكراد في منطقة عفرين
The village of Maydanki is one of the villages of Kurd
Mountain in the Afrin region.
وتبعد عن مدينة حلب 65 كيلومتراً باتجاه الشمال
It is located 65 kilometers north of the city of Aleppo
وتتبع لناحية شران.
and belongs to the Sharran subdistrict.
تقع شمال مجرى نهر عفرين، حيث كان يوجد شلالات كبيرة تعرف باسم
شلالات ميدانكي
It is located north of the course of the Afrin River, where
there used to be large waterfalls known as Maydanki
Waterfalls.
إلى جانب جسر أثري قديم يعود إلى العصر الروماني،
Next to an ancient archaeological bridge dating back to the
Roman era,
ومطحنة قمح تعمل بالطاقة المائية المتولدة من سقوط مياه النهر.
and a wheat mill powered by water energy generated by the
river's falling waters.
وقد غمرت جميعها في مياه بحيرة السد الذي بدأ العمل فيه عام
All of these were submerged by the waters of the dam lake,
which began construction in 1986
وأصبح قيد الاستثمار عام 2002.
and became operational in 2002.
تشكل القرية نقطة الربط بين قرى ناحية شران وقرى ناحية بلبل في
منطقة عفرين.
The village serves as a connection point between the
villages of the Sharran subdistrict and the villages of the
Bulbul subdistrict in the Afrin region.
وهي محاطة بغابات كثيفة من بساتين الزيتون والكروم وأشجار
السرو والصنوبر،
It is surrounded by dense forests of olive groves,
vineyards, and cypress and pine trees,
وتحتضنها البحيرة من الجهة الجنوبية.
and embraced by the lake from the southern side.
أصبحت منطقة سياحية مهمة يرتادها السوريون من كافة المحافظات،
It became an important tourist destination frequented by
Syrians from all provinces,
بعد تشكل البحيرة.
after the formation of the lake.
بلغ عدد سكانها قبل الثورة 5500 نسمة.
Before the revolution, its population reached 5,500 people.
مجتمع قرية ميدانكي مجتمع زراعي بالأصل يعتمد على الزراعة
The community of Maydanki village is originally an
agricultural society that relies on farming,
وخاصة زراعة الزيتون والعنب،
especially the cultivation of olives and grapes,
وعلى الصيد من بحيرة سد ميدانكي الموجودة جنوب القرية.
and on fishing from the Maydanki Dam lake located south of
the village.
نسبة لا بأس فيها من سكان القرية كانت تعمل في الوظائف العامة.
A significant percentage of the village's residents worked
in public sector jobs.
أيضاً هاجر قسم لا بأس فيه من أبناء القرية إلى خارج سوريا
بسبب الحرب.
Also, a considerable number of the village's youth migrated
outside Syria due to the war.
يوجد في القرية عدد كبير من المثقفين من حملة الشهادتين
الثانوية والجامعية من مختلف الاختصاصات.
The village has a large number of educated individuals
holding high school and university degrees in various
specializations.
بنيت أول مدرسة في القرية في عام 1950.
The first school in the village was built in 1950.
رح نكون معكم بهالفقرة بجولة قصيرة داخل حارات وسوق قرية
ميدانكي
In this segment, we will take you on a short tour inside the
alleys and market of Maydanki village
لنتعرف على وضع الناس هون. يلا معنا.
to learn about the situation of the people here. Let's go.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام أهلاً.
And peace be upon you, welcome.
مرحباً عمو.
Hello, uncle.
مرحباً أهلاً وسهلاً أهلاً بك سيدي.
Hello, welcome, welcome sir.
شلونك؟ نتعرف عليك؟
How are you? Can we get to know you?
أنا اسمي محمود أحمد عيسى، من أهالي قرية ميدانكي، وهي ضيعة
اسمها ميدانكي هاي.
My name is Mahmoud Ahmed Issa, from the people of Maydanki
village, and this village is called Maydanki.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
You are very welcome.
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God keep you safe.
شو بتشتغل؟
What do you do for a living?
بشتغل أنا فلاح، مو مزارع، فلاح بالضيعة ميدانكي.
I work as a peasant, not a farmer, a peasant in the village
of Maydanki.
إي شو زارع؟
Yeah, what do you plant?
زارعين زيتون وكرم عنب.
We plant olives and grapevines.
كرم عنب؟
Grapevines?
إيوه.
Yes.
هلق كأنك إنت جاي من الأرض، من الكرم؟ كأنك جاي من الكرم هلق
من الزيتون؟
It looks like you just came from the land, from the
vineyard? Like you just came from the vineyard, from the
olives?
إي زيتون حوشنا نحن، بس ضيعة في منهم لسا في زيتون بالأرض لسا
ما حوشوه.
Yes, we harvested the olives, but in the village, there are
still some olives on the land that haven't been harvested
yet.
ونحن حوشنا زيتون هلق هالسنة، إيوه.
And we harvested the olives now this year, yes.
شلون الزيتون هالسنة؟
How are the olives this year?
والله مو كويس يعني، شلون بدي قلك، موسم مو كويس.
To be honest, not good, how should I tell you, the season is
not good.
تقريباً نص الموسم يعني.
Almost half a season, I mean.
ليش؟
Why?
إي ما لأن الخدمات ما في، بدك تقول في أهالي كتير من الضيعة
هون رحلوا على حلب
Well, because there are no services. You could say many of
the village residents here moved to Aleppo
وصار نتيجة الحرب وظروف وهيك شو اسمه، تركوا أراضيهم وتركوا
الزيتون.
and as a result of the war, circumstances, and
whatchamacallit, they left their lands and left the olives.
هالسنة يعني موسم بدك تقول نص الموسم هالسنة.
So this year, the season is, you could say, half a season
this year.
طيب والزيت كويس؟
Okay, and is the oil good?
زيت لا زيت كويس، اللي حوش زيتون وأخذه عالمعصرة زيت كويس إي.
The oil, no, the oil is good. Whoever harvested olives and
took them to the press, the oil is good, yes.
قد إيش طلع يعني شقد قطع الزيتون عندكم؟
How much did it yield, I mean how much oil did your olives
produce?
قطع يعني عالهوى، زيتون بدك تقول، هوى زيت في عندك زيتون ناعم،
في عندك خشن، في عندك نوعيات زيتون لحتى يقطع الزيت.
It produced, I mean, it depends. You could say it depends on
the oil. You have small olives, you have large ones, you
have different types of olives that determine the oil yield.
هلق زيتونك مثلاً إنت خادمه وفالح وكويس، مثلاً بقطع زيت كويس
بيطلع زيت إنتاجه منيح يعني.
Now, if you take care of your olives, plow the land, and
it's good, for example, it yields good oil, its oil
production is good, you know.
قديش نسبة الناس اللي معتمدين عالزراعة هون؟
What is the percentage of people who rely on agriculture
here?
نسبة الناس المعتمدين عالزراعة تقريباً 75%.
The percentage of people relying on agriculture is about
75%.
75%؟
75%?
إيوه.
Yes.
كله زيتون؟
Is it all olives?
إي كله زيتون وكرم عنب هذا هو.
Yes, it's all olives and grapevines, that's it.
أكتر شي زيتون؟
Mostly olives?
أكتر شي زيتون إي.
Mostly olives, yes.
والعنب شلون العنب؟
And grapes, how are the grapes?
عنب والله يعني بدك تقول 10% عنب.
Grapes, well, I mean you could say 10% grapes.
10%؟
10%?
إيوه والباقي 85، 90% كله عالزيتون إي نعم.
Yes, and the rest, 85 or 90%, is all olives, yes indeed.
كله عالزيتون.
All on olives.
إيوه.
Yes.
وضع الفلاحين شلون؟
How is the situation of the peasants?
وضع الفلاحين والله خدمات يعني بدك تقول ما في مين يعتني
بالفلاح أو ينتبه عليه
The situation of the peasants, honestly, in terms of
services, you could say there's no one to take care of the
peasant or pay attention to him.
أو نتيجة هالسنتين ها، هالسنتين بس.
Or as a result of these two years, just these past two
years.
صار فيه حرب وظروف هيك، ورحلت هالفلاحين، ووضع الفلاحين هالسنة
مو مضبوط والله. هالسنتين يعني.
A war happened and such circumstances, and these peasants
moved away. The situation of the peasants this year isn't
right, really. These past two years, I mean.
الله يعطيكم العافية ويقويكم.
May God give you health and strength.
الله يعافيك يا أهلاً وسهلاً أهلاً بك.
May God give you health, welcome, welcome.
يلا.
Let's go.
مرحباً يا شاب. شلونك؟
Hello, young man. How are you?
أهلاً.
Welcome.
مرحبا يا أخينا.
Hello, our brother.
أهلاً بك.
Welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
حضرتك صاحب المحل؟
Are you the owner of the shop?
لا والله.
No, honestly.
لكان؟
Then?
عامل هون.
I am a worker here.
إنت من وين؟
Where are you from?
من حمص.
From Homs.
من حمص. وصاحب المحل من وين؟
From Homs. And where is the shop owner from?
من حمص كمان، من الخالدية.
Also from Homs, from Al-Khalidiya.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم.
You are very welcome.
إيش شو أحوالكم هون، إنتو الوافدين النازحين لهون؟
How are your conditions here, you the displaced newcomers
here?
يعني..
Well...
احكيلي، إيش شو يعني، هيك؟ إن شاء الله مرتاحين؟
Tell me, how are things, really? Hopefully, you are
comfortable?
ما حدا مرتاح.
No one is comfortable.
كيف؟
How come?
من ناحية الشغل، ما حدا عم يلاقي شغل.
In terms of work, no one is finding work.
كويس.
Okay.
من ناحية الآجار، آجار المحلات.
In terms of rent, shop rents.
من ناحية الـ... شو بدي أحكي لك يعني...
In terms of... what can I tell you...
البيوت شلون؟
How about the houses?
الواحد ماله غير يقول الحمد لله.
One has no choice but to say praise be to God.
الحمد لله. إيش شو الشغل اللي عم تشتغلوا فيه هون؟
Praise be to God. What kind of work are you doing here?
أنا اللي عنده مصلحة عم يشتغل.
Whoever has a profession is working.
وغير مصلحة، ما حدا بيشتغل في الأراضي، ما حدا بيشتغل بصيد
السمك...
And those without a profession? Does no one work in the
fields? Does no one work in fishing?
صيد سمك... حيوانات ما في حيوانات هون...
Fishing... Animals, there are no animals here...
زراعة أقصد يعني...
I mean agriculture...
الزراعة ما هي كتير، خفيفة.
Agriculture is not much, it's light.
خفيفة.
Light.
امم.
Mhm.
هلق إنت شو كانت صنعتك قبل ما تيجي لهون؟
Now, what was your profession before coming here?
ما في صنعة.
I didn't have a profession.
ما كنت بتعرف شي؟
You didn't know any trade?
ما كنت أعرف شي.
I didn't know any trade.
هلق إنت تعلمت هون هالمسألة هون؟ الفول والحمص والمطعم؟
Did you learn this trade here? Fava beans, hummus, and the
restaurant business?
تعلمناها هون.
We learned it here.
تعلمتها هون؟ هلق شو عم تساوي هون؟
You learned it here? What are you making now?
عم نقلي فلافل.
I'm frying falafel.
أنا خايف يحترقوا.
I'm afraid they might burn.
لا.
No.
شقد بتاخدوا هون أجرة؟
How much wage do you get here?
1500.
في اليوم؟
Per day?
إي.
Yes.
الله يرزقك.
May God provide for you.
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God keep you safe.
يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health too.
لا يزيد عمر قرية ميدانكي عن 300 عام، رغم وجود الجسر الروماني
على نهر عفرين جنوب القرية،
The village of Maydanki is no more than 300 years old,
despite the presence of the Roman bridge on the Afrin River
south of the village,
والذي غمرته مياه بحيرة سد ميدانكي.
which was submerged by the waters of the Maydanki Dam lake.
ومع ذلك، كان لهذه القرية دور مهم جداً في النضال ضد الفرنسيين
أثناء الاحتلال الفرنسي،
However, this village played a very important role in the
struggle against the French during the French occupation.
وكان لرجل من رجالها يدعى الشيخ عبدي، دور أساسي في هذه
الثورة.
And one of its men, called Sheikh Abdi, played a fundamental
role in this revolution.
للحديث عن تاريخ قرية ميدانكي، سيكون معنا الأستاذ محمد شيخ
عبدي ابن عكاش،
To talk about the history of Maydanki village, we will have
with us Mr. Muhammad Sheikh Abdi Ibn Akkash,
وهو حفيد الشيخ عبدي، رجل الثورة السورية في قرية ميدانكي.
who is the grandson of Sheikh Abdi, the man of the Syrian
revolution in Maydanki village.
تحياتي أستاذي.
Greetings, my professor.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome, welcome.
شلونك؟ شلون صحتك؟
How are you? How is your health?
أهلاً، أهلاً.
Welcome, welcome.
تحكيلي شوي عن تاريخ هالضيعة؟ وحضرتك إنت حفيده للشيخ عبدي.
Can you tell me a little bit about the history of this
village? And you are the grandson of Sheikh Abdi.
إي نعم، شرف، تفضل.
Yes indeed, it's an honor, go ahead.
سيدي، هالضيعة عمرها أكتر من 300 سنة،
Sir, this village is more than 300 years old.
وأتت عشائر من المناطق الحوالي القرية، سكنوا مع هالقرية.
Clans came from the areas surrounding the village and
settled with this village.
وعدد القرية يتجاوز الـ 5000 نسمة.
And the village's population exceeds 5,000 people.
الآن؟
Currently?
إي نعم.
Yes indeed.
بس أنا بدي قبل ما نحكي عن عدد سكان القرية، تحكيلي من وين
أجوا سكان القرية بالأصل؟
But before we talk about the village's population, I want
you to tell me where the village's original inhabitants came
from?
بالأصل أجوا من الشيخ عيسى.
Originally, they came from Sheikh Issa.
الشيخ عيسى اللي جنب تل رفعت؟
Sheikh Issa, which is next to Tal Rifaat?
جنب إعزاز، نعم. تل رفعت وإعزاز. بين تل رفعت وإعزاز.
Next to Azaz, yes. Tal Rifaat and Azaz. Between Tal Rifaat
and Azaz.
وكانوا جايين من جيلان بشمال العراق.
And they had come from Gilan in northern Iraq.
استقروا بالشيخ عيسى.
They settled in Sheikh Issa.
وبالشيخ عيسى بالظاهر ضايقهم بيت الجابري، كان إله المزارع
هنيك.
And in Sheikh Issa, apparently, the Al-Jabiri family
harassed them, they owned the farms there.
كان عندهم بنت حلوة،
They had a beautiful daughter,
فهجوا من الشيخ عيسى إلى قرية عقيبة.
so they fled from Sheikh Issa to the village of Aqiba.
عقيبة أين تقع؟
Where is Aqiba located?
غربي دير جمال.
West of Deir Jamal.
نعم.
Yes.
ما ثبتوا هنيك، رحلوا إلى تل حمو.
They didn't settle down there; they moved to Tal Hamo.
من تل حمو ما استقروا هنيك أيضاً، أجوا ع بيلان كوي.
From Tal Hamo, they didn't settle there either; they came to
Beylan Koy.
وين بتصير بيلان كوي؟
Where is Beylan Koy?
بيلان كوي صايرة تابعة لناحية بلبل، قريبة عميدانكي.
Beylan Koy belongs to the Bulbul subdistrict, close to
Maydanki.
نعم.
Yes.
بعدها أجوا... في مرة بناز أوشاغي لدغتها حية.
Then they came... There was a woman in Naz Uşağı who was
bitten by a snake.
أجوا مصّوا لها السم، المرأة طابت.
They came and sucked the poison out for her, and the woman
recovered.
المرأة قالت لهم روحوا اسكنوا بهداك الميدان.
The woman told them, "Go and live in that square."
كانت أحراش، كلها منطقة حراجية.
It was woods, all a forested area.
منطقة ميدانكي كانت ميدان؟
The Maydanki area was a square?
ميدان، ميدان صغير.
A square, a small square.
فقالت لهم اسكنوا بهذا الميدان.
So she told them to live in this square.
أيوة. بعدين سموها ميدانكي، تصغيراً للميدان.
Yes. Later they named it Maydanki, as a diminutive of
"Midan".
للميدان.
Of "Midan".
إي نعم.
Yes indeed.
مين أول ما سكن هون؟ مين يعني...
Who was the first to live here? I mean who...
الشيخ صالح. هو مؤسس هذه القرية.
Sheikh Saleh. He is the founder of this village.
الشيخ صالح مؤسس هذه القرية؟
Sheikh Saleh is the founder of this village?
نعم.
Yes.
ومين من أولاده؟
And who were his children?
من أولاده الشيخ محمد، والشيخ عيسى.
His children were Sheikh Muhammad and Sheikh Issa.
هدول أولاده الكبار.
Those are his older children.
ليش عم تقول شيخ شيخ؟
Why are you saying Sheikh, Sheikh?
Tayyib, xallina nibda bil-asl mubaşer. Eşîret Gêlanî.
Okay, let's start directly with the origin. The Gelani
tribe.
Gêlaniye bil-Iraq.
The Gelanis are in Iraq.
Bil-Iraq, e na'am.
In Iraq, yes.
Kan fî terîqa hon?
Was there an order (tariqa) here?
E na'am.
Yes.
El-Gêlaniye.
What is the order?
The Gelani order.
El-Gêlaniye.
E na'am. We l-zalik ya'nî axzet ism el-qarye killa inno
Gêlanî.
Yes. That's why the entire village took the name Gelani.
Hatta ciddî sammû, Ebdellah Gêlanî.
They even named my grandfather Abdullah Gelani.
Huwwe Şêx Ebdî.
He is Sheikh Abdi.
Na'am.
Yes.
Sammû Gêlanî.
They called him Gelani.
Na'am.
Yes.
W fî kunyet Gêlanî bid-day'a kaman.
And there is also the surname Gelani in the village.
Na'am. Izen min tlat mît sine tşakkalet had-day'a.
Yes. So this village was formed 300 years ago.
E na'am.
Yes.
Hkilî hallaq 'an şî... teb'an nihna hon hal-jami' 'ala
yesarna.
Tell me now about something... of course, here is the mosque
on our left.
Qaddeş 'umr hazal-jami'?
Yes.
How old is this mosque?
Wallah hawali mît sine teqrîban.
It is about 100 years old.
Mît sine.
100 years.
E. Xirib w ciddî 'ammaro min cdîd.
Yes. It was ruined, and my grandfather rebuilt it.
Na'am. Ciddak Ebdî huwwe lli 'ammaro?
Yes. Did your grandfather Abdi build it?
Şêx Ebdî 'am, caddad bina'o.
Sheikh Abdi rebuilt it.
Caddad bina'o.
He rebuilt it.
Kan qabil mawcûd.
Yes.
It existed before.
E na'am.
Yes.
Tayyib, hkilî hallaq rah nidkol 'al-jami' nihkî 'anno.
Okay, tell me, we'll go inside the mosque now and talk about
it.
Bass hkilî 'an ciddak Şêx Ebdî, w dawro bi-sawrat Sûriye.
But tell me about your grandfather Sheikh Abdi, and his role
in the Syrian revolution.
Ya sîdî, Şêx Ebdî kan minel-mucahidîn el-qudama fis-sawra
s-sûriye.
My friend, Sheikh Abdi was one of the early fighters in the
Syrian revolution.
Iştarak ma' Salih el-'Alî,
He participated alongside Salih al-Ali,
Sa'dullah el-Cabirî, Yûsif el-'Azma,
Saadallah al-Jabiri, Yusuf al-Azma,
w Ahmed Ruto, w Mistefa Şêx Huseyn,
and Ahmed Roto, and Mustafa Sheikh Hussein.
w l-qadat el-Etrak kaman kano yiltaqo fîh.
And the Turkish commanders also used to meet with him.
Yiltaqo fîh.
They used to meet with him.
Ibrahîm Henano kaman?
Ibrahim Hanano as well?
Ibrahîm Henano kaman.
Ibrahim Hanano as well.
Kan yizûr Ibrahîm Henano yrûh w yicî, w fî muraselat
beynaton.
Yes.
Kan yizûr Ibrahîm Henano yrûh w yicî, w fî muraselat
beynaton.
He used to visit Ibrahim Hanano, going back and forth, and
they exchanged letters.
W qawamo l-Fransiyîn.
They resisted the French.
W qata'o t-tarîq el-hadîd 'iddet marrat.
They cut off the railway several times.
Harabuwwon, w asaro minnon asra, w axado aslihtun.
They fought them, captured prisoners from them, and took
their weapons.
W tahawwar el-qitar fîyon fî Qurtqulaq.
And they derailed their train in Qurtqulaq.
Na'am.
Yes.
Tqassid ciser el-hadîd?
Do you mean the iron bridge?
La', la', sikket el-hadîd.
No, no, the railway.
Sikket el-hadîd.
The railway.
Mû l-ciser. E na'am.
Not the bridge. Yes.
E kan ilo dawr kbîr fil-muqawama.
Yes, he played a major role in the resistance.
L-zalik el-Fransiyîn hakamo 'aleyh bil-i'dam.
That's why the French sentenced him to death.
Harab 'a Turkiye, w istaqarr hnîk.
He fled to Turkey and settled there.
Na'am.
Yes.
W waldî kaman rah ma'o.
And my father went with him too.
Ba'd ma kibir waldî, daras bi-Turkiye lit-tasi'.
When my father grew up, he studied in Turkey up to the ninth
grade.
W xadam bil-ceyş et-turkî,
He served in the Turkish army,
bi-Antakiye, bir-Rîhaniye, kan darib alikat bi-ciddî... e
abûy.
in Antakya and Reyhanli. He was a typist with my
grandfather... I mean, my father.
Na'am.
Yes.
Ica la-hon istaqarr.
He came here and settled.
Fî madafet waldo.
In his father's guesthouse.
lli kan msaytir 'aleyha wlad 'ammo.
Which was controlled by his cousins.
Istiqarr hon.
He settled here.
La beyn ma...
Until...
Emet tuwuffiya ş-Şêx Ebdî, w weyn?
When did Sheikh Abdi pass away, and where?
Bis-sitta w xamsîn.
In '56.
Bi-Turkiye.
Where did he pass away, in Turkey?
In Turkey.
Bi-Turkiye. Tayyib, xallina nidkol hallaq 'al-jami', nşûfo.
Şarrif.
In Turkey. Okay, let's enter the mosque now and see it.
Please go ahead.
Tifaddal.
Please.
Şarrif.
Please go ahead.
Hallaq wadih hon ma'na inno maktûb...
Now it's clear here that it is written...
buniya 1341 hicrî.
built in 1341 Hijri.
Şarrif şway.
Yes.
Please come closer a bit.
E na'am.
Yes.
Es-selamu 'aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
W 'aleykum es-selam w rahmetullah.
And peace and mercy of God be upon you.
Şi'ar Hadret Namiq...
The emblem of Hadrat Namiq...
Namiq beig.
Namiq Bey.
Ewe.
Yes.
Wîla... wîla 'alê...
Or... or on it...
Ma batzayyar, nass...
I can't figure it out, a text...
Na'am.
Yes.
Bil-kitabe bit-Turkiye.
The writing is in Turkish.
Ewa. Lakin hon maktûb taht...
Yes. But here it is written below...
Ewa.
Yes.
Tacaddada hazal-mescid...
This mosque was renovated...
bisabab xarabî, bisab' sanawat
due to its ruin, after seven years
bifadl Şêx Ebdî Gêlanî, fî 1366.
thanks to Sheikh Abdi Gelani, in 1366.
Sitt w sittîn.
Sixty-six.
Izen 1366...
So 1366...
Tamm ticdîdo.
It was renovated.
Tamm ticdîdo, w huwwe mabnî 1341.
It was renovated, and it was built in 1341.
Ya'nî nihna l-yom taqrîban...
Meaning we are roughly today...
Taqrîban ba'd mît sine.
Approximately 100 years later.
Ya'nî hazal-'umr, hazal-jami' mît sine.
Meaning this age, this mosque is 100 years old.
E na'am.
Yes.
Hallaq eş-şekil el-jami', haza huwwe? Haza huwwe ya'nî min
cuwwa? Nşûf haş-şekil.
Now the shape of the mosque, is this it? Is this it from the
inside? Let's see this shape.
E na'am. Tifaddal.
Yes. Please.
Es-selamu 'aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Tifaddal.
Please.
Şarrif 'ammo, tifaddal.
Please come in uncle, please.
Haza huwwe ş-şekil el-asasî.
This is its original shape.
Ha şekil el-asasî?
This is the original shape?
Haza huwwe l-qism el-asasî lil-jami'.
This is the main part of the mosque.
E na'am.
Yes.
Şarrif la-hon.
Come over here.
E. Hallaq haza huwwe ş-şekil el-asasî lil-jami'.
Yes. Now this is the original shape of the mosque.
Haza huwwe heyk.
Yes.
It was like this.
Kan bil-asl heyk ġamis? Willa min cdîd haza?
Was it originally vaulted like this? Or is this new?
La', bil-asl heyk.
No, it was originally like this.
Haza huwwe şekil el-ġamis.
This is the vaulted shape.
E na'am.
Yes.
W haza d-darac byitla' la-foq mşan el-azan.
And these stairs go up for the call to prayer.
Ah. L-ma'zane kano yitla'o 'aleyha hî...
Ah. Did they use to go up to the minaret...
Ma kan fî ma'zane, la'kan 'as-satih. 'As-satih y'azzin.
There was no minaret, they'd go to the roof. He'd make the
call from the roof.
Li-anno qarye kanit zġîre?
Because the village was small?
Ewa, e, hallak kibrat.
Yes, yes, now it has grown.
W haza huwwe l-mihrab.
And this is the mihrab.
E na'am, haza l-mihrab.
Yes, this is the mihrab.
Haza, haza l-minbar, w haza l-mihrab.
This is the minbar, and this is the mihrab.
E na'am, ewa.
Yes, exactly.
Allah yu'tîkel-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health too.
Şukran ya ustazî. Hayyakallah.
Thank you, sir. May God greet you.
Ya ahla w sahla.
You are very welcome.
Li-buhayret Sadd Meydankî w li-miyah nahar 'Efrîn...
The Meydanki Dam lake and the waters of the Afrin River...
Ahammiye kebîre ciddan fî hayat ahalî Meydankî.
hold a very great significance in the lives of the people of
Meydanki.
Li-sababeyn asasiyyeyn: as-sabab el-awwal w huwwa...
For two main reasons: the first reason is...
Mihnet es-seyd, elletî ya'taş minha nisbe la ba'sa biha min
ahalî Meydankî.
The fishing profession, which provides a living for a
considerable number of the people of Meydanki.
Wa s-sabab es-sanî, kawn enno buhayret Sadd Meydankî asbahat
wiche siyahiyye
And the second reason is that the Meydanki Dam lake has
become a tourist destination
li-'adad kebîr min sukkan muhafazat Haleb, w huwwa ma
yuşakkil masdar 'eyş li-ahalî qaryet Meydankî.
for a large number of residents from the Aleppo governorate,
and this provides a source of income for the people of
Meydanki village.
Bihal-faqara rah nkûn ma'kun bi-liqa' ma' ahad sayyadî el-
asmak...
In this segment, we will be with you in an interview with
one of the fishermen...
el-kibar fî hazihil-qarye, wa aydan sanakûn ma'kun fî cawle
fî qarib seyd daxil buhayret Sadd Meydankî.
the older ones in this village, and we will also take you on
a tour in a fishing boat on the Meydanki Dam lake.
Tabi'ûna.
Follow us.
Es-selamu 'aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
W 'aleykum es-selam.
And peace be upon you.
Şlonak 'ammo?
How are you, uncle?
Ahla w sahla, şlonak inte?
Welcome, how are you?
Şlon sihtak?
How is your health?
Allah yxallîk, t'arraf 'aleyk.
Thank God.
May God keep you. Let's get to know you.
Abû 'Abdo.
Abu Abdo.
E ahla w sahla. Min weyn?
Welcome. Where are you from?
Min Meydankî.
From Meydanki.
Ahla w sahla fîk.
You are very welcome.
Hallaq inte şû 'am tsawî? 'Am tşîd bi-sinnara, wila... bi-
şabake?
What are you doing now? Are you fishing with a hook, or...
with a net?
'Am nsîd bi-şabake.
We are fishing with a net.
Şabake m'allaqa bi-sinnara w 'am nşidd.
Is this a net?
It's a net attached to a hook, and we pull it.
Ah, ya'nî fî şabake w fî sinnara, w fî şabake w sinnara
sawa.
Ah, so there is a net and a hook, and a net and hook
together.
Ewa, fî ibre, fî sinnara bi'alliqo,
Yes, there is a needle, they attach it to a hook,
W hallaq m'alliqîn eş-şabake.
And now we have the net attached.
Eş-şabake. Eş qad sarlak bihal... bihal-mihne hay?
The net. How long have you been in this... this profession?
Wallah sarlî yumkin 'işrîn sine.
Honestly, I have been doing it for maybe twenty years.
'Işrîn sine?
Twenty years?
Min siġarna.
Since we were young.
Min siġarak?
Since you were young?
Ewa.
Yes.
Tihkîlî şway heyk 'an hal... hal-seyd es-samak?
Can you tell me a little bit about... this fishing?
Eşşû lli byi'icbak fîh? Eşşû lli byibsitak fîh? Eşşû lli
byişiddak ilo?
What do you like about it? What makes you happy about it?
What draws you to it?
Wallah hadi hiwaye.
Honestly, it's a hobby.
'Am nsîd w 'am naxod mşan el-beyt nakol bass.
We fish and we take it home for the family to eat, that's
all.
Bil-asl huwwe l-inno inte bit'îş minna? 'Andak ġeyr haş-
şuġle, wila inno inte bithib hal-mihne?
Do you actually make a living from it? Do you have another
job, or do you just love this profession?
La', 'ala fadawtî acî 'ala seyd es-samak.
No, in my free time I come fishing.
'Ala fadawtak?
In your free time?
Mm.
Mm-hmm.
W şû btiştaġil?
And what do you work as?
Fallah.
A farmer.
'At-traktor 'am biştaġil.
I work on the tractor.
'At-traktor. Allah yu'tîkel-'afiye.
On the tractor. May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health too.
Ahla şî b-seyd es-samak şû huwwe?
What's the best thing about fishing?
Ahla şî... Ahla samak... ya'nî karb, karsîn.
The best thing... The best fish... meaning carp, karsin.
Mm.
E ana ma'ak, bass aqsod ahla şî bis-seyd şû huwwe?
Yes I'm with you, but I mean what is the best thing about
catching them?
Biş-şabake.
With the net.
Ewa.
The net.
Yes.
Emet bitsîr es-seyd fiha l-hayah l-'adiye?
When does fishing become normal life for you?
Bis-seyfiye.
In the summer.
Ewa.
Yes.
B-ey sa'a qasdî ya'nî?
I mean at what time?
Ya'nî, ma mbayyin.
I mean, it's not predictable.
Haza hasab el-hazz haza.
It depends on luck.
Ma bta'rif eyna sa'a biddo yiştigil.
You never know what time it will work out.
Xallîna nibrok şway.
Let's sit down for a bit.
Yallah.
Okay.
Ana ba'rif es-sayyadîn byitla'o bakkîr, ya'nî qabl tlû' eş-
şams, ma' adan es-subih.
I know fishermen go out early, like before sunrise, with the
morning call to prayer.
E byitla'o, ahyanan bil-leyl bîcû kaman, bi-sîdû bis-
sinnara.
Yes they do, sometimes they also come at night, they fish
with hooks.
Bi-sinnara, mû biş-şabak?
With a hook, not with a net?
Bis-sinnara, ewa.
With a hook, yes.
Leş bil-leyl?
Why at night?
Bil-leyl, es-samake 'am bitharrak, 'am bidûr, 'am byakol.
At night, the fish moves around, roams, and eats.
Mşan haş-şî.
Because of this.
Ah, bikûn ya'nî m'ammin?
Ah, meaning they feel safe?
E lakan m'ammin.
Yes, of course they feel safe.
E. Hallaq bihal-waqt haza bizzat, fî, fî samak?
Yes. Now, at this specific time, are there, are there fish?
Fî. Fî samak.
Yes. There are fish.
Fî? Ya'nî nisbato mlîha?
There are? I mean is the amount good?
La', el-hamdullah, mlîh, fî nas 'am bit'îş wara s-samak.
Yes, thank God, it's good, there are people living off the
fish.
Hallaq haliyen?
Right now currently?
Haliyen ewa.
Currently yes.
Hallaq ana şayef hadi, şû hadi?
Now I see this, what is this?
Hada bori had.
This is a mullet.
Şqad kil nahar bitsîd ya'nî?
How much do you catch every day?
Wallah hey kil nahar kîlo, kîloweyn, ha... mşan el-beyt
bass.
Honestly, every day a kilo, two kilos, just for the house.
Allah yirziqak ya rabb.
May God provide for you.
Amîn.
Amen.
Tihkîlî ya'nî heyk mawqif zarîf, hilu, sar ma'ak w inte 'am
tistad samak?
Can you tell me a nice, funny situation that happened to you
while you were fishing?
Ya'nî 'ala tûl ma bicî 'as-samak hatta yisîr ma'î şî.
Honestly I haven't been fishing long enough for something to
happen to me.
'Ala fadawtî.
Only in my free time.
Bass cît miş-şuġil, mil-flaha...
Just when I come back from work, from farming...
Heyk bicî, mîcînî maraq...
I come like this, I get the urge...
Başil sinnarta, sinnara, w acî... eş-şabake, w ba'allqa w
bacî 'as-seyd.
I pick up my hook, the hook, and I come... the net, and I
attach it and I come to fish.
Şqad nisbet es-sukkan, aw ahalî Meydankî lli bi'îşo 'as-
samak aw bistadû samak aw biştuġlo bihal-mihne?
What percentage of the residents, or people of Meydanki,
live off fish or catch fish or work in this profession?
Wallah ktîr el-'alam biştuġlo.
Honestly, a lot of people work in it.
Ya'nî baqdir aqullak tlat irba' Meydankî bi'îşo wara
s-samak.
I mean, I could tell you three-quarters of Meydanki live off
the fish.
Hallaq?
Now?
Hallaq ewa.
Now yes.
Allah yu'tîkel-'afiye w Allah yirziqak.
May God give you health and may God provide for you.
Allah y'afîk, ahla w sahla. Ya ahlîn w sahlîn.
May God give you health too, welcome. You are very welcome.
Es-selamu 'aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Wa 'aleykum es-selam wa rahmetullahi, ya ahla w sahla fîk.
And peace and mercy of God be upon you, welcome to you.
Tifaddal.
Please.
Nita'arraf 'aleyk?
Can we get to know you?
Muhammed 'Arif.
Muhammad Arif.
Allah yu'tîkel-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk.
May God give you health too.
Abû Doğan.
Abu what?
Abu Dogan.
Ahleyn abû Doğan.
Welcome, Abu Dogan.
Inte sahib hazil-markab?
May God bless you, welcome.
Are you the owner of this boat?
La', ana şaġġîl 'aleyh, şofêr.
No, I work on it, as a driver.
W bi-nafs el-waqt mîkanîsiyyen.
And at the same time a mechanic.
W bi-nafs el-waqt... ġawwas... w sayyad bi-nafs el-waqt.
And at the same time... a diver... and a fisherman at the
same time.
Maşallah 'aleyk! Bi-sab' karates.
Mashallah! A jack of all trades.
Hallaq rah taxodna bi-rihle... daxil el-buhayre.
May God keep you, may God keep you safe.
Now you'll take us on a trip... inside the lake.
Mît salame, mît ahla w sahla.
A hundred welcomes, a hundred times welcome.
Mît salame. Yallah tfaddal. Yallah.
A hundred welcomes. Let's go please. Let's go.
Qabl ma tġîb eş-şams. Qûl ya rabb.
Before the sun sets. Say oh God.
Tifaddal, wada'ti.
Come on in, please.
Tihkîlî, tihkîlî 'an es-siyaha hon?
Tell me, tell me about tourism here?
Bîcû el-'alam min kil el-manatiq...
People come from all regions...
Biyhibbo yitla'o rihle mitl halol eş-şabab lli icû hallaq
ma'on 'iyal...
They like to take a trip like these young men who came just
now with families...
Ma'on 'iyal?
With families?
W 'aleyna inno nkûn mintibhîn...
And we have to be attentive...
W fî tab'an awamir w şaġlat lazim yiltizmo fîha.
And of course there are rules and things they must abide by.
Lakin qabl... qabl ma tqillî l-awamir lazim yiltizmo fîha,
min weyn n-nas lli btîcî lahon?
But before... before you tell me the rules they must abide
by, where do the people who come here come from?
Min weyn n-nas bitîcî?
Where do people come from?
Btîcî min Idlib...
They come from Idlib...
Min 'Ezaz...
From Azaz...
Min hon, min 'Efrîn...
From here, from Afrin...
Ya'nî...
I mean...
Min kil el-manatiq ya'nî... el-manatiq el-muharrara tab'an.
From all regions I mean... the liberated regions of course.
Ewa.
Yes.
E... afdal aw aktar el-işhir lli bsîr fîha harake siyahiyye
emet?
What... what are the best or the most months that have
tourism activity?
El...
The...
Taqrîban ya'nî min awwal er-rabi'... laş-şahr et-tasi'
'andak...
Approximately, I mean from the beginning of spring... up to
the ninth month...
Ya'nî aktar in-nas btîcî. Bîkûn fî takasuf sukkanî...
I mean most people come then. There is a high density of
people...
Takasuf.
High density.
Ewa. Takasuf... nas...
Yes. High density of... people...
Hallaq hadi, ana ka-inno şayef quddamî cezîre?
Now this, it seems as if I see an island in front of me?
E, cezîre, na'am.
Yes, an island, yes.
Xallîh 'al-kamera bil-'aks... na'am tifaddal. layşûfoha.
Let's get it on the camera from the other side... yes, go
ahead. So they can see it.
Na'am.
Yes.
Hey cezîre.
This is an island.
Na'am.
Yes.
Şû isma?
What is its name?
Cezîret Meydankî.
The Meydanki Island.
Cezîret Meydankî ma'rûfe.
The Meydanki Island is well-known.
كبيرة؟
Is it big?
إي كبيرة نعم.
Yes, it's big.
فيها شي؟ إيش فيها؟ في حدا ساكن فيها شي؟
Is there anything in it? What's in it? Does anyone live in
it?
لا ما فيها حدا، ما في، سكان ما فيها. فيها أرانب، فيها طيور،
فيها بط.
No, there's no one, there are no inhabitants in it. It has
rabbits, birds, ducks.
حيايا، هيك بس.
Snakes, just that.
هلق بالحياة العادية أنتو بتوقفوا هون الناس؟
Now, in normal life, do you stop people here?
إي بيوقفوا، إي بيوقفوا بيتصوروا وهيك.
Yes, they stop, yes, they stop and take photos and such.
تفضل... شلون هيك؟
Here... how is this?
آه، حلو كتير.
Ah, very nice.
أيوا.
Yes.
الجو كتير ظريف.
The weather is very nice.
نعم، بس مشان نطلع، أيوا.
Yes, just so we can go up, yes.
هلق بهاد الوقت، يعني تقريباً قبل الغروب بعشر دقايق أو ربع
ساعة...
Now, at this time, almost ten or fifteen minutes before
sunset...
نعم.
Yes.
عادةً بتطلع أنت هيك رحلات؟ ولا بيصير في خطورة؟
Do you usually go out on such trips? Or is there danger?
لا بطلع، بطلع، بطلع بعد هلق كمان.
No, I go out, I go out, I go out even after this time too.
يعني بشغل الإنارة، في عندي إنارة، ألوان.
I mean, I turn on the lights, I have colored lights.
فبشغلها وبطلع.
Yes.
So I turn them on and go out.
احكيلي الناس اللي بيطلعوا لهون هيك... شو الأغاني بيسمعوها؟
Tell me about the people who come out here like this... what
songs do they listen to?
طبعاً... لأذينة العلي، يا موج خدني معك، يا بحر غرقني.
Of course... for Udhaina Al-Ali, "Oh Waves Take Me With
You", "Oh Sea Drown Me".
أيوا.
Yes.
يا موج خدني معك يا بحر غرقني. نعم.
"Oh Waves Take Me With You, Oh Sea Drown Me." Yes.
أيوا.
Yes.
يعني، مزاجهم شو بيكون؟
I mean, what is their mood like?
بيكون مزاجهم رايق، طبعاً اللي بدو يطلع إذا مزاجه مو رايق ما
بيطلع.
Their mood is relaxed. Of course, whoever wants to go out,
if his mood isn't relaxed, he won't go out.
مو هاد قصدي.
That's not what I meant.
لكان؟
Then what?
يعني مزاج الطرب تبعهم، هل هو شرقي، هل هو ساحلي، هل هو جبلي؟
I mean their musical mood, is it oriental, is it coastal, is
it mountainous?
يا أخي كل إنسان بيهوى، بيقول لك حط لي الغنية الفلانية.
My brother, every person has their preference, they tell you
to play this or that song.
فبحط له، ما في مشكلة عندي.
So I play it for them, I have no problem.
أنت شو مزاجك؟
What is your mood?
أنا بالنسبة إلي ساحلي.
As for me, it's coastal.
إي، عتابا جبلية.
Coastal.
Yes, mountainous 'Ataba.
عتابا جبلية. حافظان شي بتغني شي؟
Mountainous 'Ataba. Do you have anything memorized, do you
sing anything?
بصراحة هيك...
Honestly, like...
ممكن تحكيلنا هيك يعني... اسحب لنا سحبة.
Could you tell us something like... sing us a piece.
إذا بدي اسحب لك، بسحب لك حلبي.
If I'm going to sing for you, I'll sing you an Aleppian
piece.
اسحب لي شو بدك.
Sing whatever you want.
أيوا، لأنه...
Yes, because...
اللي حافظانه حلبي بس النمط وسمعي ساحلي.
Sing.
What I have memorized is Aleppian, but my style and what I
listen to is coastal.
طيب.
Alright.
آآآه، يا يابا.
Ahhh, oh father.
آه.
Ah.
كم نوب أهواك، كم نوب أهواك، كم نوب أهواك.
How many times I love you, how many times I love you, how
many times I love you.
يا أبو عبدو كم نوب أهواك.
Oh Abu Abdo, how many times I love you.
وك رن القصب بغيابك.
And the reed flute echoed in your absence.
يابا ويل دمعي شبه السيل بغيابك يا يا يا حبيبي.
Oh father, woe, my tears are like a torrent in your absence,
oh my beloved.
تسلم.
Bless you.
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God bless you.
طيب هلق نحنا بطريق العودة.
Alright, now we are on the way back.
نعم.
Yes.
بدك تحكي شي، احكيلي أطرف يعني حدث حصل معك شي مرة...
Do you want to say anything, tell me the funniest incident
that happened to you once...
حدا طلع معك في القارب وصار معه دوار البحر؟
Did someone go out with you on the boat and get seasick?
لا لا لا، الحمد لله رب العالمين.
No, no, no, praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds.
حدا وقع معك وأنقذته؟
Did someone fall in with you and you saved them?
لا، أبداً كمان.
No, never either.
في سبيحة بيطلعوا بيشلفوا حالهم ما في مشكلة، طبعاً بيخبروني
وبيشلفوا حالهم.
There are swimmers who come out and throw themselves in,
there's no problem. Of course, they tell me and then throw
themselves in.
بس يعني ما حصل معك موقف طريف؟
But I mean, you haven't had a funny situation?
لا لا، الحمد لله رب العالمين، إنه لا طريف ولا إنه شي مزعج
مثلاً، ما وصلنا لهالموصول.
No, no, praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds, neither funny
nor anything annoying, for example, we haven't reached that
point.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا سيدي، أهلاً وسهلاً أخي أبو عبدو شرفتونا.
May God give you health, sir. Welcome brother Abu Abdo, you
honored us.
على وقع تمايل أمواج بحيرة سد ميدانكي، ومع غروب شمس هذا
اليوم.
To the rhythm of the swaying waves of the Maydanki Dam Lake,
and with the sunset of this day.
تنتهي جولتنا التي قدمناها لكم من قرية ميدانكي التابعة لناحية
شران، منطقة عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي.
Our tour, which we presented to you from the village of
Maydanki, belonging to the Sharran sub-district, Afrin
region in the northern countryside of Aleppo, comes to an
end.
سنكون معكم في الأسابيع القادمة في جولات جديدة من مناطق سورية
أخرى حبيبة.
We will be with you in the coming weeks on new tours from
other beloved Syrian regions.
لمتابعة برنامجنا، تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة، وأيضاً
موقعنا على الإنترنت حلب تودي تي في دوت نت.
To follow our program, follow the channel's Facebook page,
and also our website halabtodaytv.net.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.