Ev çiyayê Lêlûn e. Ez ji Zaretê me.
This is Mount Lelun. I am from Zaret.
Ez li vir cî me.
I live here.
Emrê min, heştê û du sal in.
My age is eighty-two years.
Çaxê min xwe dinê dî, heftiya hene.
When I opened my eyes to the world, there were tents.
Gelek hene.
There were many.
Şkeftê de hene.
There are some in the caves.
Ê... Însaniyê xwe ...
Uh... Its people...
... yanî bi ser Çiyayê Lêlûn ve têt hesibîn.
... I mean, they are considered part of the Mount Lelun.
Û bi Seyfiyê leqeb e.
And it is nicknamed Seyfiye.
Xelk şixulî.
People worked.
Bixwe re gund ko... bi dar û bi yomîye... şixulîn, zehf
şixulîn.
The village itself... with trees and daily wages... they
worked, they worked a lot.
Giştan îşê xwe meşandin.
Everyone ran their business.
Îşê xwe meşandin, rind bûn.
They ran their business, they became well-off.
Welle rind bûn.
By God, they became well-off.
Dar me çandin.
We planted trees.
Hinar, zeytûn...
Pomegranates, olives...
Genim... Ceh...
Wheat... Barley...
Ev tişta me çandin.
We planted these things.
Şe'bê gund jî, şe'bekî misalim e.
The people of the village are a peaceful people.
Yanî... teşkela meşkela nakin.
I mean... they don't make trouble.
Di xwar e, di şixulin, dixwin û vedixwin.
They work down there, they eat and drink.
Û çiya jî, bi xwe...
And the mountain itself...
...berê kox û rez qe tê ne bû.
...before there were no huts and vineyards in it at all.
Kox û rez qe tê ne bû.
There were no huts and vineyards in it at all.
Rêkî adî bû.
It was an ordinary road.
Em meş diçûn Efrînê, dihatin.
We used to walk to Afrin and come back.
Meş...
Walking...
Geliyek heye li binî derê.
There is a valley below the area.
Derê jor şkeftek a tê de, şkeft diqatî ne, yeka jêr e, yeka
jor e.
At the upper door there is a cave, the caves are in layers,
one is below, one is above.
Gelî... mezin e şkeft.
The valley... the cave is big.
Wê salê ew hatin, Yabanî...
That year they came, the foreigners...
Hatin, vedan.
They came, they dug.
Eser qedîm...
Ancient ruins...
Vedan... vedan...
They dug... they dug...
Du-sê salan tê de şixulîn.
They worked in it for two to three years.
Seriyekî qicik dîtin.
They found a small skull.
Qicikek dîtin, yê çûçik bû.
They found a small one, it was of a child.
Ewan derman kirin, derkirin, kirin sendûqê, birin Ewropa.
They treated it, took it out, put it in a box, and took it
to Europe.
Em malxirab pê şixulîn. Pê sekinîn.
We poor things worked on it. We stood by it.
Jin, mêr, law, qîz...
Women, men, sons, daughters...
Yanî xelk di şixulî.
I mean, people were working.
Ê çiya bi xwe, çiyakî asê ye.
And the mountain itself, it's a steep mountain.
Berê bi dar bû, nika dar neman.
It used to be covered with trees, now there are no trees
left.
E... ez yê oxcî bûm.
Uh... I was a hunter.
Li van çiyan... ez digeriyam. Du kewa... du têra... du
dara...
In these mountains... I used to wander. Two partridges...
two birds... two trees...
Me dikuşt, anî, qicikê me dixwarin.
We used to kill them, bring them, our children used to eat
them.
Ê em hatin, vê derê gund...
Then we came, to this village here...
Pir xweş bû. Şebabên xwe rind bûn.
It was very nice. Its youth were good.
Şebabên xwe hawa bûn.
Its youth were like that.
Yanî, îxtilata me tev alemê hebû.
I mean, we had interactions with the people.
Rind bû.
It was good.
Me ji hev hez dikir, alemekî...
We loved each other, a people...
Em... her êvar... panzdeh diçûn malekê disehirîn berê.
We... every evening... fifteen people used to go to a house
and stay up late in the past.
Heyat xweş bû.
Life was good.
Me... e... te dît me rind e, kes xirmişê me nebe.
We... uh... you saw we are good, nobody should bother us.
Ne em ariz dibin e, ne kesek.
Neither we bother, nor anyone else.
Em di xwara di şixulin.
We work down there.
Navbera xortên gund...
Among the youth of the village...
Ne tenê nav gund, ew her hez ji hev dikirin...
Not only in the village, they always loved each other...
Tişt nabe...
Nothing happens...
Em bi hev re, ev hez dikirin.
We together, we loved each other.
Û qîzikê wan... jinên wan wekî jinên me ne, destmalê xwe
wekî jinên me eyb nedidîtin e.
And their daughters... their women are like our women, they
didn't see it as a shame for their veils to be like our
women's.
Qîzikê wan bi kurmancî xeber didin...
Their girls spoke in Kurmanji...
Ez berê... cem Şêx Faris me xwend.
I used to... read with Sheikh Faris.
Min Qur'an xetim kir.
I finished reading the Quran.
Ez çûme Îskê...
I went to Iska...
Min kirne sefê diduyan.
They put me in the second grade.
Sefê diduyan, ez bi giştî zanîbûm bixwînim.
In the second grade, I generally knew how to read.
Bes yazî ... nedabû me, ez nizanibûm yazî bikim.
But writing... wasn't given to us, I didn't know how to
write.
Ê...
Uh...
Em hatin vê derê...
We came here...
Salekê basûtê ez çûm, sefê sêyem hebû.
A year later I went to Basute, there was the third grade.
Sefê sê derece ûla min hilanî berî îskê.
Third grade, I took first degree before Iska.
Ez hatim Basûtê, min dî derece ûla bir.
I came to Basute, I saw I took first degree again.
Em ketne Efrînê.
We entered Afrin.
Ketme mekteba Efrînê.
I entered the school of Afrin.
Em ketne...
We entered...
Heqê sindoqa iqtisadê 5 wereqe dixwestin.
The economic fund fee required 5 papers.
Pere tune bûn, bavê min nav gund gerya, nikarî 5 wereqe
bidîta.
There was no money, my father searched the village, he
couldn't find 5 liras.
Ê...
Uh...
Ê Qur'an dixwend, Qur'an xwend.
The one who was reading the Quran, read the Quran.
Û ê sef xwendin, sef xwendin.
And the one who read the grade, read the grade.
Şeş mehan me xwendin, dan qeçek gihîştin sefê pêncê...
We read for six months, they gave it so some kids reached
the fifth grade...
Herfek û tenê...
Only one letter...
Yê di xwendinê de hebûn... qewaid elimîn, înşa elimîn, hesab
elimîn, yazî elimîn.
Those who were in reading... they learned grammar, they
learned composition, they learned math, they learned
writing.
Cema xwendin, û çûn Efrînê, ê pereyên xwe hene çûn Efrînê.
They read together, and went to Afrin, those who had money
went to Afrin.
Welle bekelorya jî birin, hinek o...
By God some even got their baccalaureate...
Û min, ez paşê ji xwendinê ketim.
And me, I later dropped out of reading.
Cem xwe... me kîtêb mîtêb dixwendin, derdikirin...
By ourselves... we used to read books, we used to take them
out...
Ê...
Uh...
Sefê nehan meselê sefê nehê mi hel dikirin...
The ninth grade, for example I used to solve the problems of
the ninth grade...
Ê...
Uh...
O înşa, qewaid...
And composition, grammar...
Min giş hel dikir, dima sefê nehan ew.
I used to solve all of them, the ones remaining from the
ninth grade.
Me giş meşand, ... ew qicikane pir pêş ketin.
We ran it all, ... those kids advanced a lot.
Pir rind bûn.
They became very good.
Heta noka li cem min, a niha li gund da...
Until now with me, right now in the village...
Îhtiramê didine min.
They give me respect.
Ji wan talaban.
From those students.
Ez dixwazim dinya bi xêr be.
I want the world to be well.
Ev herbê bes kin a, ev aleme biftile mala xwe...
Stop this war, let these people return to their homes...
Her kes here malê xwe.
Everyone should go to their home.
Xerîb, ...
Stranger, ...
Ê herne ciyê xwe.
Uh let them go to their places.
Em... wanan gişt selamet bin, dinya bi xêr be.
We... may they all be safe, may the world be well.
Ê... waha ne.
Uh... it is like this.
Dinya waha ne.
The world is like this.