فوق هضبة كلسية موجودة على الطرف الشمالي لمجرى نهر عفرين،
Above a calcareous plateau located on the northern edge of
the Afrin River course,
تحيط فيها غابات الزيتون من كافة الجهات.
surrounded by olive forests from all sides.
وعلى بعد أكثر من 13 كيلومتر جنوب غرب عفرين، تقع قرية كفرزيت.
And at a distance of more than 13 kilometers southwest of
Afrin, lies the village of Kafar Zeit.
جولتنا لهالأسبوع رح تكون من قرية كفرزيت التابعة لمركز ناحية
عفرين. تابعونا.
Our tour for this week will be from the village of Kafar
Zeit, belonging to the Afrin district center. Stay with us.
كفرزيت، قرية سورية تتبع ناحية عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي.
Kafar Zeit, a Syrian village belonging to the Afrin district
in the northern Aleppo countryside.
وهي مبنية فوق هضبة جبلية في سهل الجوم.
It is built on a mountainous plateau in the Joum plain.
تبعد عن عفرين 13 كيلومتر باتجاه الجنوب الغربي.
It is 13 kilometers away from Afrin towards the southwest.
يمكن الوصول إليها من حلب عن طريق محوري دارة عزة وعفرين.
It can be accessed from Aleppo via the Darat Izza and Afrin
axes.
تبعد عن طريق عفرين - جنديرس 4 كيلومترات.
It is 4 kilometers away from the Afrin - Jindires road.
إلى الشمال منها تقع قرية تلف، ومن جنوبها يعبر نهر عفرين.
To its north lies the village of Telefe, and from its south
the Afrin River crosses.
أصل سكان القرية يعود إلى عائلتي خاستيان وبيركان الكرديتين.
The origin of the village's residents dates back to the
Kurdish Khasteyan and Berkan families.
ويبلغ عددهم حالياً 1000 نسمة من الأكراد الإيزيديين
والمسلمين.
And their number currently reaches 1000 people from Yazidi
and Muslim Kurds.
كما يسكن فيها حالياً 65 عائلة مهجرة من ريفي حماة وإدلب
الجنوبي.
Also, 65 displaced families from the countryside of Hama and
southern Idlib currently live there.
النشاط الاقتصادي الأساسي لمعظم سكان القرية الزراعة.
The main economic activity for most of the village's
residents is agriculture.
خاصة زراعة الزيتون والرمان والفواكه.
Especially the cultivation of olives, pomegranates, and
fruits.
إضافة إلى تربية الأغنام والماعز والأبقار.
In addition to raising sheep, goats, and cows.
تبلغ مساحتها 400 هكتار، وفيها 40 ألف شجرة زيتون.
Its area is 400 hectares, and it has 40 thousand olive
trees.
كما يوجد فيها مدرسة ابتدائية تضم 40 طالباً ومعصرة زيتون
وجامع.
There is also a primary school with 40 students, an olive
press, and a mosque.
مين؟ واحد. تفضل.
Who? One. Go ahead.
كفرزيت هالضيعة البسيطة والحلوة كتير والمشهورة بزيتونها
والأغنام الموجودة فيها،
Kafar Zeit, this simple and very beautiful village, famous
for its olives and the sheep found in it,
بيشدك فيها ريحة خبز الصاج المشهورة فيه.
draws you in with the smell of the saj bread it's famous
for.
وبتعرف من هالريحة اللي بتجذبك لبيوتها بإنو هالناس كريمين.
And you know from this smell that attracts you to its homes
that these people are generous.
خالتي أم أحمد، وحدة من نسوان هالقرية الطيبة والمعروفة كتير،
My aunt Um Ahmad, one of the kind and very well-known women
of this village,
دعتنا لحتى نشوف كيف عم تساوي اليوم خبز التنور، خبز الصاج مع
المحمرة.
invited us to see how she is making tannour bread today, saj
bread with muhammara.
المحمرة الطيبة كتير بطريقة أهل كفرزيت.
The very delicious muhammara in the way of the people of
Kafar Zeit.
وعم بتقول إنه عازمتنا كمان عالرز والفاصولية الخضرا باعتبار
اليوم عطلت من الزيتون.
And she's saying she's also inviting us for rice and green
beans since she took a day off from the olives today.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
أهلين ابني.
Welcome, my son.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله، شلونكن إنتو؟
Praise be to God, how are you?
والله نحن بألف خير من الله.
By God, we are perfectly fine, thanks to God.
الله يعطيكن العافية، أهلاً وسهلاً ابني، يعطيكن العافية.
May God give you health, welcome my son, may God give you
health.
الله يعافيكي. هلا إنتي يعني قلتي إنه محضرة اليوم أكلة كتير
طيبة، الخبز الأبيض عالصاج والمحمرة.
May God give you health. Now you said that you prepared a
very delicious meal today, white bread on the saj and
muhammara.
احكيلنا هيك شوي شلون عم تساويهم وأيش اللي بيميزهم بكفرزيت؟
Tell us a bit about how you make them and what distinguishes
them in Kafar Zeit?
عجنا ابني.
We kneaded, my son.
نعم.
Yes.
الله ينعم عليك. وسويتها وخمرت، وبعدين سوينا محمرة وخبز.
May God bless you. I made it and it fermented, and then we
made muhammara and bread.
من ايمتى عجنتيها؟
When did you knead it?
الصبح.
In the morning.
الصبح بكير كتير؟
Very early in the morning?
هلق إنتو بالأيام العادية بموسم الزيتون، بتعجنوا من بكير، ولا
قبل مثلاً...
Yes.
هلق إنتو بالأيام العادية بموسم الزيتون، بتعجنوا من بكير، ولا
قبل مثلاً...
Now, on normal days during the olive season, do you knead
early, or before for example...
لا لا ابني، منروح عالزيتون يعني ما منساوي خبز.
No, no my son, we go to the olives, meaning we don't make
bread.
بتجيبوا جاهز.
You bring it ready.
منجيب جاهز.
We bring it ready.
وإذا بدكن تعجنوا ايمتى بتعجنوا؟
And if you want to knead, when do you knead?
ايمتى بدنا نساوي قبل بكم ساعة.
Whenever we want to make it, a few hours before.
آها، قبل بكم ساعة.
Aha, a few hours before.
إي.
Yes.
أيوة، حطينا خميرة وشوي زيت وملح وعجنا.
You let it ferment?
Yes, we put yeast, a little oil, and salt and kneaded it.
تمام، وهيدي مونة المحمرة، إيش فيها؟
Great, and this is the muhammara mix, what's in it?
هي حمستها، بصلة فرمتها، بصلة وحمستها. وبعدين حطيت دبس فليفلة
I roasted it, I chopped an onion, an onion and I roasted it.
And then I put pepper molasses,
وسمسم وحبة البركة.
sesame, and black seed.
آها، ليش حمستي البصلة؟
Aha, why did you roast the onion?
مشان تستوي.
So it cooks.
تستوي بتصير أطيب؟
It becomes tastier when cooked?
إي.
Yes.
طيب خلينا نشوف هلق قدامنا إيش رح تساوي هلق.
Okay, let's see now in front of us what you are going to
make.
تكفي ابني.
Enough, my son.
هادا شو اسمه؟
What is this called?
هي شوبك.
This is a rolling pin.
شوبك. وهاد؟
A rolling pin. And this?
خشب هادا، تخت.
This is wood, a board.
تخت. هادا تخت؟
A board. This is a board?
إي، وهي تيرك.
Yes, and this is a tirek.
تيرك؟ يعني هو نفسه الشوبك؟
A tirek? Meaning it's the same as the rolling pin?
أيوة.
Yes.
أيوة. تفضلي.
Yes. Go ahead.
إي يلا، الله يفضلك.
Yes come on, may God bless you.
هلق أنا حسب ما عرفت إنه إنتي عشتي فترة طويلة من عمرك بالرقة.
Now, as far as I know, you lived a long period of your life
in Raqqa.
إي.
Yes.
لأنه عمي أبو أحمد كان يشتغل مهندس هنيك.
Because my uncle Abu Ahmad used to work as an engineer
there.
هنيك كمان نفس الشي بساووا هيك الخبز؟
Yes.
Do they also make this kind of bread there?
لا والله ابني ما نساوي. كله جاهز.
No, by God, my son, we don't make it. It's all ready-made.
كان عندهم يعني من زمان بالضيع ما كانوا يساووا هيك خبز؟
Did they use to make this kind of bread in the villages a
long time ago?
بس سمبوسك بساوي.
I only make sambousek.
سمبوسك.
Sambousek.
إي.
Yes.
فطاير.
Fatayer (pies).
فطاير. هنيك بالرقة.
Fatayer. Over there in Raqqa.
إي بالرقة. إي والله.
Yes, in Raqqa. Yes, by God.
وحتى ما أدشر أعجن العجينة، بجيب جاهز.
I don't even bother kneading the dough, I bring it ready-
made.
كمان؟
Really?
إي والله. بس هون عجنا. أحسن.
Yes, by God. But here we kneaded. It's better.
يعطيكن العافية ابني.
May God give you health, my son.
الله يعافيكي. إنتي من كم سنة بتعجني وبتخبزي؟
May God give you health. How many years have you been
kneading and baking?
من أنا وصغيرة. من 10 سنين.
Since I was young. Since 10 years old.
إنتي وصغيرة عمرك 10 سنوات.
Since you were a 10-year-old child.
إي وعم نساوي.
Yes, and we've been making it.
كانوا أول كمان عالصاج ولا عالتنور؟
Used they to make it on the saj or the tannour before?
لا التنور ما بعرف والله ابني.
No, the tannour, I don't know, by God, my son.
ما بتعرفي. هلق هادا... هادا قصاصة زيتون؟
You don't know. Now this... are these olive prunings?
إي.
Yes.
مو هيك؟
Right?
أطراف الزيتون، إي.
Olive branches, yes.
أولي كانوا على شو يعني يشعلوا النار؟
What did they use to light the fire with in the past?
كمان تبع الزيتون بس هيك ناعم، متل هدوك ناعم.
Also olive branches but fine ones, like those fine ones.
أولي كانوا عالقصلين بعرف، بقايا القمح وهيك شي.
In the past they used wheat stalks I know, wheat remains and
things like that.
بقايا الحنطة.
Wheat remains.
أنا ما لحقت هدول.
I didn't catch those times.
هرار أكياسه.
Just sack shreds.
ما بتحطوله لتبلة المحمرة رمان؟ باعتبار مشهورين بالرمان.
Don't you put pomegranate in the muhammara seasoning?
Considering you are famous for pomegranates.
إي والله ابني نسيتها.
Yes, by God, my son, I forgot it.
آها.
Aha.
بتحطولها رمان يعني؟
So you do put pomegranate in it?
إي منحط لها. منحط لها جوز، لوز، كل شي.
Yes, we do. We put walnuts, almonds, everything.
وكأنه كنتي عم تقوليلي قبل شوي إنه بقدونس كمان.
And you were telling me a while ago that you also add
parsley.
بقدونس إي والله بحط لها بقدونس كمان، اطلعت هيك مو شوي ما
بصير.
Parsley, yes by God, I put parsley in it too, but it turned
out this way, just a little is not okay.
ما بصير. شو زارعين بأرض الدار هون؟
It's not okay. What have you planted in the home's yard
here?
بقدونس، فجل، جرجير، رشاد، بصل، سلق، سبانخ هاد هي.
Parsley, radishes, arugula, cress, onions, chard, spinach,
that's it.
ما شاء الله، عندك كل شي.
Mashallah, you have everything.
الحمد لله ابني.
Thank God, my son.
طيب خلينا نشوف هلق إيش عم تساوي.
Alright, let's see now what you are making.
رح أساويها أكبر أكبر خبزة.
I'm going to make the biggest, biggest bread.
بساويها هلق. خلص هي.
I'm making it now. This is done.
ريحة خبز الصاج بتجيب الضيوف.
The smell of saj bread brings guests.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
متل الطريصة هي، بتجي لهون مو هيك؟
Like the spark, it comes here, right?
إي، بس شخطة راحت هيك إجت.
Yes, a spark just flew this way.
بس راحت هيك معناتها في ضيوف.
When it flies this way, it means there are guests.
هيدي معناها...
This means...
بدها تجي.
She's coming.
هيدي قناعة عندك إنه بس راحت الطريصة هيك معناتها في ضيوف.
You have this belief that when the spark flies this way, it
means there are guests.
لا ابني، كل العالم مو بس أنا.
No my son, everybody, not just me.
كل العالم هيك؟
Everybody is like that?
إي.
Yes.
هلق بركة النسوان عالصاج هون معناها بركي حلوة. شو بتحكوا مع
بعض؟ هلق مين الأخت هون معك؟
Now, the gathering of women at the saj here is a beautiful
gathering. What do you talk about with each other? Now, who
is the sister here with you?
مرت خاله لأبو أحمد.
Abu Ahmad's uncle's wife.
مرت خاله لأبو أحمد. يا أهلاً وسهلاً.
Abu Ahmad's uncle's wife. Welcome.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
جاية تساعديها لأم أحمد؟
Did you come to help Um Ahmad?
إي. هيك شغلات عم نساعد بعضنا.
Yes. In things like this, we help each other.
هي كمان بتساعدك.
She also helps you.
إي.
Yes.
بس تخبز أنا بجي بساعدها.
When she bakes, I come and help her.
إيش شو بتساووا كمان غير الخبز هاد؟ مثلاً بتساووا مطبقة،
بتساووا سمبوسك، شيش برك.
What else do you make besides this bread? For example, do
you make mutabbaq, sambousek, shish barak?
إي. خبز صاج، شيش برك، المحاشي، كل شي عم نساوي متل... يعني عم
نساعد بعض.
Yes. Saj bread, shish barak, stuffed vegetables (mahshi), we
make everything like... I mean we help each other.
إيش شو في أكلة خاصة هون بالضيعة؟ أهم أكلة خاصة هون إيش شو
هي؟
What is a special dish here in the village? What is the most
important special dish here?
والله أكلة خاصة، هاد هي...
Well, a special dish, this is it...
برانية، شيش برك...
Boraniyeh, shish barak...
عندنا يعني المحشي، وهي المحمرة.
We have the stuffed vegetables, and this muhammara.
الله يعطيك العافية يا خالتي أم أحمد. في سؤال عم يخطر على
بالي. هاد اللي لبستيه التوب اللي لبستيه شو هاد؟
May God give you health, my aunt Um Ahmad. A question comes
to my mind. This dress you are wearing, what is it?
روب كردي.
A Kurdish dress.
كردي.
Kurdish.
إي.
Yes.
هيك بتسموه روب كردي.
You call it a Kurdish dress like this.
إي.
Yes.
هيك مكسر هون و... تمام. وهادا اللي لبستيه هون؟ اللقلق هاد شو
بتسموه هاد؟
It's pleated here and... alright. And what is this that you
are wearing here? This laqlaq, what do you call it?
هي كمان... هي روب كرمانجكي.
This too... this is a Kurmanji dress.
كرمانجكي.
Kurmanji.
وهي هنكلت.
And this is henkilt.
هنكلت؟
Henkilt?
إي.
Yes.
والحطة ع راسك؟
And the head cover?
هي كمان، شال، بيتش، وحوره.
This too, a shawl, wrapped, and an aura.
هادا اللباس الكردي بهالمنطقة هون.
This is the Kurdish attire in this area here.
إي.
Yes.
هلق عم بطلع فيه أبو أحمد وعاجبه لأبو أحمد كتير.
Now Abu Ahmad is looking at it and he likes it a lot.
إيش شو بتغنوا إنتو وباركين عم تخبزوا عالصاج؟
What do you sing while you are sitting and baking on the
saj?
ما منغني شي.
We don't sing anything.
أبداً؟
Not at all?
لا والله. ما بعرف.
No, by God. I don't know.
بتغنوا شي؟ خلينا نسمع شي بتغنوه هيك.
Do you sing anything? Let us hear something you sing like
this.
ابني والله ما بعرف.
My son, I really don't know.
أبو أحمد عم يقلي خليها تغني.
Abu Ahmad is telling me to let her sing.
شو رأيك؟
What do you think?
Wera delal, wera malê, delal wera malê, delal wera malê.
Come handsome, come home, handsome come home, handsome come
home.
Tera dibêjim delalê xwe ra serjê kim, lo delalo berxê wî
beranî.
I say I will slaughter for my handsome, oh handsome, that
ram lamb.
Wera delalo doşek erd e balgî kevir e, ooo lo delalo wera
malê.
Come handsome, the mattress is the ground, the pillow is a
stone, oh handsome come home.
Wera gava te delalê xwe xwedan kim, bi şekir û şîrê Helebê,
Heleb a mîran.
And when I raise my handsome, with the sugar and milk of
Aleppo, Aleppo of the princes.
Lo delalê min o, wera malê.
Oh my handsome, come home.
Wera malê, wera malê, wera malê.
Come home, come home, come home.
الله يعطيك العافية، سلم تمك. إيش شو غنيتي، إيش شو قلتي
بالعربي، ترجميلي.
May God give you health, bless your mouth. What did you
sing, what did you say in Arabic, translate for me.
عربي ما بعرف!
I don't know Arabic!
ما عم تعرفي تترجميها.
You don't know how to translate it.
هي دلال... مدلل.
This "delal"... means pampered.
آه مدلل.
Oh, pampered.
أيوة.
Yes.
يا عيني، يا عيني. الله يعطيك العافية. شكراً إلك.
Oh my, oh my. May God give you health. Thank you.
ريحة خبزك بتدل على ريحة كل الأمهات السوريات الطيبات
والسالمين. يعطيكن ألف عافية.
The smell of your bread points to the scent of all the good
and peaceful Syrian mothers. May God give you a thousand
healths.
الله يرزقكم يا رب.
May God provide for you.
الله يسلمك. كلياتكن إن شاء الله. السلام عليكم.
May God keep you safe. All of you, God willing. Peace be
upon you.
مع السلامة أهلاً وسهلاً.
Go in peace, welcome.
السلام عليكم
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته
And upon you be peace, and the mercy of Allah and His
blessings.
هلا أخوي
How are you?
Welcome, brother.
الله يعافيك أهلاً وسهلاً
May God give you health.
May God grant you health, welcome.
حدا قلي إنه أنتوا جايين عم تشتغلوا بأراضي الزيتون
Someone told me that you came here to work in the olive
fields.
نعم
Yes.
وموسميين يعني بتتنقلوا من مكان لمكان، موسم الزيتون وموسم
الرمان وايش في مواسم ما بعرف يجوز
And you are seasonal workers, moving from place to place,
for the olive season, the pomegranate season, and whatever
other seasons there might be.
مزبوط
Exactly.
منين حضرتكم؟
Where are you from?
نحن من ريف حلب الجنوبي
We are from the southern countryside of Aleppo.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً
You are very welcome.
احكيلي عن أحوالكم هون
Tell me about your conditions here.
والله شوفت عينك
Well, as you can see.
يعني شوفت عينك، عالم نازحة ومخيم
How so?
I mean, as you can see, displaced people and a camp.
شقد صرلكم بهالمنطقة؟
How long have you been in this area?
والله صرلنا تقريباً شي تلت سنين
We've been here for about three years.
تلت سنين، وتنقلي من مكان لمكان مع خيمكم؟
Three years, moving from place to place with your tents?
مع خيمنا إي
With our tents, yes.
وهلا عم تشتغلوا بموسم الزيتون
And now you are working in the olive season?
موسم الزيتون وبعد الزيتون لـ... الله يفرجها، لنشوف نلاقينا
إن شاء الله بغير بلاد.
The olive season, and after the olives... May God bring
relief, we'll see if we can find something in other areas,
God willing.
طيب هلا أنتو بتاخدوا الأرض كرم كامل، يعني بتاخدوه ضمان، ولا
شلون؟
So do you take the whole orchard, meaning you lease it, or
how does it work?
لا، هي الأرض لزلمة صاحبنا من زمان.
No, this land belongs to a man who has been our friend for a
long time.
أنا عم بحكي بشكل عام، عم بحكي الزيتون الزيتون
I am talking in general, about the olives.
الزيتون لا
The olives, no.
شو عم تاخدوه؟ شلون؟
How do you take it? How?
بنشتغل بالحصة بالحصة
We work for a share.
شلون احكيلي؟
Tell me how?
يعني سبع شوالات إله والتامن إلنا، أو سبع تنكات إله والتامنة
إلنا.
Meaning seven sacks for him and the eighth for us, or seven
tins for him and the eighth for us.
بتاخدوا الأرض كاملة؟
You take the whole land?
إي أرض كاملة.
Yes, the whole land.
800 شجرة، 700 شجرة، 1000 شجرة، حسب.
800 trees, 700 trees, 1000 trees, it depends.
السبع شوالات إله والتامنة إلكم؟
Seven sacks for him and the eighth for you?
والتامنة إلنا إي.
The eighth is for us, yes.
شقد بتطالعوا بالموسم؟
How much do you make in the season?
والله يعني 10 شوالات، 15 شوال، ونعصر وبركة من الله.
Well, around 10 to 15 sacks, and we press the oil, and it's
a blessing from God.
ما شاء الله، الله يعطيكم العافية.
Masha'Allah, may God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God grant you health.
السلام عليكم
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام يا هلا بك.
And upon you be peace, welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
شلون صحتك؟
Praise be to God.
How is your health?
والله الحمد لله.
Well, praise be to God.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيكم أهلاً وسهلاً.
May God grant you health, welcome.
شقد عمرك؟
How old are you?
والله من الـ 50 للـ 60.
Well, between 50 and 60.
50 للـ 60؟
50 to 60?
إي، يفرق عشر سنين يا حماتي.
Yes, there's a ten-year difference, mother-in-law.
عم تزغري حالك؟ عم تزغري حالك؟
Are you making yourself younger? Are you making yourself
younger?
لكان؟
No, I swear!
Then what?
تعبانة حيشاك.
I'm tired, with all due respect.
سلامتك، سلامتك.
Get well soon.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
وين رايحة هيك؟
Where are you going like this?
وين رايحة؟ على بيتي دحج له بالكوخة هذيك.
Where am I going? To my house, look at it, in that hut.
أيوا. بتشتغلي معهم بالزيتون؟ بتشتغلي معهم بالزيتون أنتي؟
I see. Do you work with them in the olives? Do you work with
them in the olives?
أنا؟ والله ما أقدر يا خاي.
Me? I swear I can't, brother.
يعني صبية 50 60
But you're a young woman of 50 or 60.
والله صبية بس السكر هلكني.
A young woman indeed, but diabetes has exhausted me.
سلامتك.
Get well soon.
May God keep you safe.
سلامتك.
Get well soon.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
احكولنا هون شلون وضعكم؟ كيف عايشين؟ يعني...
Tell us about your situation here. How are you living? I
mean...
والله معيشة عن الموت.
We're barely surviving.
من قلة الموت عايشين.
We are alive only because death hasn't taken us.
والله. وعندي هذول ثلاث يتامى وأبوهم ميت وأمهم الله أخذها.
Indeed. And I have these three orphans, their father is dead
and God took their mother.
في سؤال عم يخطر على بالي أسألكم إياه لو سمحتوا.
There's a question that comes to mind that I'd like to ask
you, if I may.
يعني ليش أنتو مثلاً صرلكم ثلاث سنوات ما بركتوا بمكان محدد؟
Why is it that for three years you haven't settled in a
specific place?
كب الدخان، كب الدخان.
Throw away the cigarette, throw away the cigarette.
ليش ما بركتوا بمكان محدد؟ ليش مثلاً ما سكنتوا بقرية محددة
بمكان محدد؟
Why haven't you settled in a specific place? Why, for
example, haven't you lived in a specific village or a
specific place?
والله احنا كنا بالباب.
Well, we used to be in Al-Bab.
كنتوا في الباب.
You were in Al-Bab.
مو اجيت لعندنا على المدجنة؟
Didn't you visit us at the poultry farm?
آه، قابلناكم سابقاً بالمدجنة أنتو؟
Ah, we interviewed you previously at the poultry farm?
إي هذا نحن.
Yes, that was us.
وجيتوا لهون هلا؟
And now you came here?
إي مو عم نشتغل.
Yes, aren't we working?
يلا الله يعين.
May God help you.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
والله يرزقكم ويفتح عليكم يا رب.
May God grant you health.
May God provide for you and open doors for you.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
وترجعوا لبلادكم سالمين غانمين.
And may you return to your hometowns safe and sound.
إن شاء الله، إن شاء الله.
God willing, God willing.
يا رب، السلام عليكم.
Amen, peace be upon you.
السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace be upon you, and the mercy of Allah and His blessings.
هناك ارتباط تاريخي كبير بين الغزاوية وبرج عبدالو وقرية برج
حيدر الموجودة في أعلى جبل ليلون، والتي تقع بالجهة الشرقية من
قرية كفرزيت، وبين تاريخ كفرزيت الواقعة فوق هضبة كلسية في
منطقة سهل جومه أو الجوم.
There is a great historical connection between Al-
Ghazawiyya, Burj Abdalo, and the village of Burj Haidar
located at the top of Mount Simeon (Jabal Lelun), which is
situated to the east of the village of Kafr Zeit, and the
history of Kafr Zeit located on a limestone plateau in the
Joumah or Joum plain.
للحديث عن تاريخ قرية كفرزيت، سيكون معنا الأستاذ المهندس
مصطفى جنيد، أحد أبناء هذه القرية والمهتم بتاريخها.
To talk about the history of Kafr Zeit village, we will be
joined by Mr. Engineer Mustafa Jneid, one of the sons of
this village who is interested in its history.
تحياتي أستاذ مصطفى.
Greetings, Mr. Mustafa.
أهلاً وسهلاً أستاذ مصطفى.
Welcome, Mr. Mustafa.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
نتشرف بكم وبحضوركم بقناة حلب اليوم، نتشرف فيكم وأهلاً وسهلاً
وميت مرحبا.
We are honored by you and your presence on Halab Today TV,
we are honored and you are very welcome.
الله يكرمك، خلينا نمشي هيك شوي.
May God honor you, let's walk this way a bit.
يلا تفضل أستاذ.
Let's go, please go ahead, sir.
نحن اليوم، هلق الان واقفين بظن في الحارة الأقدم في القرية.
Today, right now, I think we are standing in the oldest
neighborhood in the village.
نعم نعم، في منتصف القرية. سابقاً إنه هذه القرية كفرزيت تتبع
لمنطقة عفرين الواقعة في سهل الجوم.
Yes, yes, in the middle of the village. Previously, this
village, Kafr Zeit, belonged to the Afrin region located in
the Joum plain.
المكون السكاني بقرية كفرزيت، أكراد سوريين قديماً منذ الأزل،
منذ أجدادنا.
The population of Kafr Zeit consists of Syrian Kurds,
historically since ancient times, since our ancestors.
قديش عمر القرية؟
How old is the village?
التركيب السكاني الحالي بالقرية يعني متكون من قبيلتين أو من
عشيرتين؛ الدنادلة (فخذ الخاستيان) والبيركان.
The current demographic structure in the village consists of
two tribes or clans; the Danadila (the Khastiyan branch) and
the Pirkan.
سابقاً هذه القرية منذ 100 عام كانوا إيزيديين.
Previously, 100 years ago, this village used to be Yazidi.
نعم.
Yes.
كانوا إيزيديين ومن 100 عام أسلموا تباعاً. قسم أسلموا منذ 100
عام، القسم الثاني منذ 40 أو 50 حتى 70 عام، وقسم باقٍ بعض
البيوت حوالي 7 إلى 8 بيوت باقين إيزيديين.
They were Yazidis, and 100 years ago they gradually
converted to Islam. One part converted 100 years ago, the
second part converted 40 or 50 up to 70 years ago, and a
remaining part of about 7 to 8 houses are still Yazidi.
طيب، قبل ما يكونوا، قبل 100 سنة شو كانت الضيعة؟
Well, before that, 100 years ago, what was the village like?
قبل 100 سنة، نفس السكان موجودين بس نمط أصغر. يعني مرحلة
السكان القديمين قبل 100 سنة أو 150 عاماً كانوا ضمن نمط بدوي.
100 years ago, the same population was here but on a smaller
scale. Meaning the stage of the ancient inhabitants 100 or
150 years ago was a nomadic lifestyle.
متنقلين.
Moving around.
متنقلين رعاة. يتبعون المواشي والأغنام والأنهار. والقريبين من
يعني أي موقع يوجد فيها مراعي طبيعية ينزلوا فيه.
Moving around as shepherds. Following their livestock,
sheep, and rivers. Whenever they were close to a location
with natural pastures, they would settle there.
منين اجوا هنه؟
Where did they come from?
قسم من القرية (الخاستيان) اجوا من جبل ليلون، كيف شلون، يعني
على أقربائهم كانوا هنيك.
One part of the village (the Khastiyan) came from Mount
Simeon (Jabal Lelun), following their relatives who were
there.
ببرج حيدر.
In Burj Haidar.
إي ببرج حيدر. القسم الثاني من قرية سينكا، هنه البيركان.
Yes, in Burj Haidar. The second part came from the village
of Sinka, who are the Pirkan.
منين اجوا البيركان؟
Where did the Pirkan come from?
عائلة وحدة، عائلة اجت من سينكا تابعة لمنطقة شكاكي ناحية
شران، منذ 150 عاماً، عائلة وحدة.
One family, a family that came from Sinka, which belongs to
the Shikaki area in the Sharran sub-district, 150 years ago,
just one family.
العائلة الثانية إجت من جبل ليلون ونزلوا هون. صارت التركيبة
السكانية حالياً تعداد القرية حوالي 150 إلى 200 بيت، التعداد
السكاني يتجاوز 1000 نسمة.
The second family came from Mount Simeon and settled here.
Currently, the demographic structure makes up about 150 to
200 houses in the village, with a population exceeding 1000
people.
طيب أنا سألتك قبل 150 سنة قبل ما يجوا الإيزيديين لهون، يعني
في أنا قرأت عن وجود بعض الآثار الرومانية، مغر ومغر يعني
مرتبطة بمجرى نهر عفرين.
Well, I asked you about 150 years ago before the Yazidis
came here. I read about the existence of some Roman ruins,
caves, connected to the course of the Afrin River.
نعم نعم، بالنسبة لقرية كفرزيت كانت خربة قديماً منذ 500 عام
أو أكثر.
Yes, yes. As for the village of Kafr Zeit, it was an old
ruin 500 years ago or more.
اسم القرية موجود منذ العصر السرياني، كونها كلمة سريانية
بمعنى مزرعة الزيتون.
The name of the village has existed since the Syriac era, as
it is a Syriac word meaning "olive farm".
كفر مزرعة.
"Kafr" means farm.
كفر كلمة سريانية بمعنى مزرعة، والزيت بمعنى مزرعة الزيتون.
"Kafr" is a Syriac word meaning farm, and "Zeit" refers to
the olive farm.
يعني مشتقة كون أن هذه القرية منذ الأزل منذ 500 عام أو أكثر
تخصصها بزراعة الزيتون وعصر الزيت، سميت بمزرعة الزيتون أو
كفرزيت. وحتى عصرنا الحديث ما زال هذا الاسم موجود، اسمها
كفرزيت.
It is derived from the fact that this village, since ancient
times, for 500 years or more, specialized in cultivating
olives and pressing oil, so it was called the Olive Farm or
Kafr Zeit. Even in our modern era, this name still exists,
it is called Kafr Zeit.
إذن الاسم مربوط بالزيتون.
So the name is linked to olives.
الاسم مربوط بالزيتون.
The name is linked to olives.
في معصرة قديمة؟
Is there an old olive press?
في معصرة كانت قديمة قريبة علينا وحالياً غير موجودة، كون
التقنية الحديثة حلت مكانها. شايف شلون، لا تفي بالغرض الموجود
حالياً يعني بكثرة أشجار الزيتون.
There used to be an old press close to us, but it is no
longer there, as modern technology has replaced it. You see,
it doesn't serve the current purpose with the abundance of
olive trees.
سابقاً عدد أشجار الزيتون كانت قليلة جداً، الزراعات كانت
بعلية (الشعير وقمح وجلبان وعدس وحبوب). توسعت محاصيل الزيتون
بشكل كبير، وصار استثمار الزراعة استثمار رأسي بما يفي الغرض
يعني مع تزايد السكان.
In the past, the number of olive trees was very small, the
agriculture was rainfed (barley, wheat, vetch, lentils, and
grains). Olive crops expanded greatly, and agricultural
investment became a vertical investment to meet the needs
with the growing population.
سابقاً كان الاستثمار أفقي، كون عدد السكان كان قليل. ازدياد
السكان على وحدة المساحة، الإنسان يفكر بطرق حديثة لتأمين
المادة أكثر.
Previously, the investment was horizontal, as the population
was small. With the population increase per unit area,
people think of modern ways to secure more resources.
طيب، خليني أحكي شوية عن العلاقة التاريخية بين كفرزيت وبين
برج عبدالو والغزاوية والقرى الموجودة على أطراف مجرى نهر
عفرين بسهل الجوم.
Well, let me talk a bit about the historical relationship
between Kafr Zeit, Burj Abdalo, Al-Ghazawiyya, and the
villages located on the edges of the Afrin River in the Joum
plain.
نعم، نحن كجيران أولاً، وفي أقرباء قربة نسوان، هي أهم شغلة
شايف شلون، التزاوج.
Yes, we are neighbors first, and there are relatives through
women, which is the most important thing, you see,
intermarriage.
عملية تزاوج بين السكان، بين هالقرى المحيطة، بيزيد القربى،
عملية التزاوج بالذات بتزيد القربى.
The process of intermarriage among the population, among
these surrounding villages, increases kinship; the
intermarriage process specifically increases kinship.
بينكم وبين جيرانكم؟
Between you and your neighbors?
بين برج حيدر، بين غزاوية، بين برج عبدالو، بين إيسكان، بين
شادير، هالقرى المحيطة فينا. يزيد القربى وما زال القربى
موجودة يعني.
Between Burj Haidar, Al-Ghazawiyya, Burj Abdalo, Iskan,
Shadir, these villages surrounding us. It increases kinship,
and the kinship is still there.
نحضر أعراس بعضنا، نساعد بعضنا ببعض الأمور، ببعض المشاكل.
We attend each other's weddings, we help each other with
some matters, with some problems.
كان في تاريخ مشترك قديماً؟ قبل 500 سنة؟
Was there a shared history in the past? 500 years ago?
تاريخياً، طبعاً، قبل 200 عام كان باعتبار قلنا إن هالقرية
كانت خربة، المعتقدات كان قبور الموتى بهالقرية من البيركان
يدفنوه بشادير.
Historically, of course. 200 years ago, considering we said
this village was a ruin, due to their beliefs, the graves of
the dead in this village from the Pirkan were buried in
Shadir.
ليش؟
Why?
كون هنيك مقبرة قديمة، مقبرة إيزيدية قديمة زرادشتية.
Because there is an old cemetery there, an old Yazidi
Zoroastrian cemetery.
شو اللي بيميز القبور الإيزيدية؟
What distinguishes Yazidi graves?
ما في تمييز بين، نفس الشيء، نفس الـ شو اسمه، نفس الطريقة.
There is no distinction, it's the same thing, the same, what
do you call it, the same method.
حسب ما فهمت إنه الصليب الإيزيدي؟
From what I understood, it's the Yazidi cross?
الصليب الزرادشتي.
The Zoroastrian cross.
Salîb ez-Zerdeştî, bi şikil za'id.
The Zoroastrian cross, in the shape of a plus sign.
El-edla' mutsawiye bi heysu yedillu 'ala...
The sides are equal, which indicates...
Xelefû şemis.
Behind it is a sun.
Erba' eqtab, ye'nî erba' edla' bin-nisbe leha es-salîb...
Four poles, meaning four sides for this cross...
Yedillu 'ala 'anasir el-heyat el-arba',
It indicates the four elements of life,
Li enne Zerdeşt qeddes et-turab, wen-nar, wel-hewa, wel-ma'.
Because Zoroaster sanctified earth, fire, air, and water.
Hinne 'anasir el-heyat el-arba'.
They are the four elements of life.
Temam.
Exactly.
Biqî su'al exîr...
One last question remains...
Ye'nî 'elaqet hal-qerye, Kefer Zêt, bi mukewenat el-
ictima'iye el-Kurdiye me' el-'Ereb?
I mean, the relationship of this village, Kafr Zeit, its
Kurdish social components with the Arabs?
Nihne fî beynatna seqafe muştereke.
We have a shared culture between us.
Ye'nî fereden kên 'enna, ye'nî cîranna, 'elaqetna me'
el-'Ereb el-'Umêrat... mewcûde we qedîme.
For example, we had, I mean our neighbors, our relationship
with the Umayrat Arabs... is present and ancient.
El-'Umêrat mewcûdîn weyn?
Where are the Umayrat located?
Bi Efrîn we bi hewalî fereden Kefer... Frêriye, Benî Zêd.
In Afrin and around, for example, Kafr... Frieriye, Bani
Zaid.
Frêriye.
Frieriye.
Kefer... fereden Kawkabe, Basûte...
Kafr... for example Kawkabe, Basouta...
Qisim minhum mewcûdîn bil-Birc... ye'nî 'elaqetna ceyyide.
Şêf şlon?
Some of them are located in Al-Burj... I mean, our
relationship is good. You see?
Ma heda yumeyyiz inno haza Kurdî aw haza 'Umêrî, şêf şlon?
Yes.
No one distinguishes that this is Kurdish or this is Umayri,
you see?
Fî tezawic, musahere?
Is there intermarriage, affinity?
Fî tezawic beyn el-'Umêrat wel-Ekrad mewcûd.
There is intermarriage between the Umayrat and the Kurds.
Li'enne kown el-'Umêrat eqdem, qedîmîn...
Because the Umayrat are older, ancient...
Bin-nisbe, ye'nî... lî muxtelitîn me' el-Ekrad bi mentiqet
Kurdax- Efrîn...
In relation to, I mean... those mixed with the Kurds in the
Kurd Dagh region - Afrin...
Qedîmîn, eqdem min Benî Zêd aw min el-Bûbenna.
Ancient, older than Bani Zaid or Al-Bobanna.
Ye'nî wucûdum teqrîben me' wucûd el-Ekrad hown, fe kên fî
'elaqet musahere, 'elaqet tezawic, 'elaqet 'emel muşterek...
I mean, their presence is almost with the presence of the
Kurds here, so there was an affinity relationship,
intermarriage relationship, shared work relationship...
Ne'em, ne'em.
Yes, yes.
Tarîx muşterek.
A shared history.
Ne'em, tarîx muşterek we seqafe muştereke.
Yes, a shared history and a shared culture.
We te'ayuş muşterek.
And shared coexistence.
Temam. Allah ye'tîk el-'afiye ya Ustad Mistefa.
Great. May God give you health, Mr. Mustafa.
Ehlen Ustad Mistefa... Nrehhîb fîkum merre saniye.
Welcome, Mr. Mustafa... We welcome you once again.
Nişkurkum 'ala muqabeletkum el-ceyyide wel-cemîle. We
mahbûbîn intu.
We thank you for your good and beautiful interview. And you
are beloved.
Heyyakallah ustad.
God bless you, sir.
Allah yeselmek.
May God keep you safe.
Irtibat tarîxî kebîr beyn tebî'et el-mentiqe el-cuğrafiye
el-mewcûde fîha Kefer Zêt,
A significant historical connection between the nature of
the geographical region where Kafr Zeit is located,
We beyn nemet el-bina' ellezî 'ummira fîha.
And the style of construction in which it was built.
Heysu enne mu'zem hazihî el-buyût buniyet min el-meqle' el-
ehcar el-mewcûd fî eş-şerq min hazihî el-qerye,
As most of these houses were built from the stone quarry
located in the east of this village,
We eyden kên lehu 'alaqe bi mecra nehr Efrîn el-mewcûd cenûb
el-qerye.
And it also had a connection with the course of the Afrin
River located south of the village.
Lil-ida'e hewle nemet el-bina' fi el-qerye, se yekûn me'ena
fî hazihî el-feqere...
To shed light on the construction style in the village, we
will have with us in this segment...
Muxtar el-qerye, Zuheyr 'Ezîz, liyuhaddisena 'en eşkal el-
bina' fîha.
The village mukhtar, Zuhair Aziz, to talk to us about the
forms of construction there.
Ye'tîk el-'afiye muxtar.
May God give you health, Mukhtar.
Allah ye'afîk, ehlen we sehlen ustad.
May God give you health, welcome sir.
Hela nihne quddam teqrîben yumkin eqdem beyt hown.
Now we are in front of what is probably the oldest house
here.
Fî 'enna şî erba' xems buyût min el-qedîmat el-mewcûdat
'enna haliyen,
We have about four or five old houses currently here,
We sahib el-beyt haza ismuh Nasîr Derwîş, muteweffa.
And the owner of this house is named Nasir Darwish,
deceased.
Sar lu 15 sene mehjûr teqrîben. Ba'd ma tuwuffiya...
It has been abandoned for about 15 years. After he died...
Haza eqdem beyt hown?
Is this the oldest house here?
Haza eqdem beyt hown 'enna bid-dey'a.
This is the oldest house here in our village.
Şed 'umru ye'nî?
How old is it, I mean?
'Umru şî 100 sene.
It is about 100 years old.
Ne'em.
100 years?
Yes.
Teyyib... hela haza es-sexr hown êş?
Okay... now this rock here is what?
Haza sexr hewwarî şerqî ed-dey'a, fî 'enna meqle'.
This is chalky rock, east of the village, we have a quarry.
Nwaqqif hown...
Let's stop here...
Yirûhû yiqte'û el-hecer... we yicîbû we yibnû fîhû.
They go and cut the stone... and bring it and build with it.
Wel-bina' 'ibare 'en hecer we tîn.
And the building is made of stone and mud.
We esqufu... esqiftu e'midet xeşeb, we squftun trab.
And roofs... its roofs are wooden pillars, and their roofs
are dirt.
Trab.
Dirt.
Ne'em.
Yes.
Êş mektûb hown?
What is written here?
"Maşa'allah."
"Mashallah."
1958.
Maşa'allah.
Mashallah.
El-bannîy hûwe ismuh Merwan Ibn Hesen.
The builder is named Marwan Ibn Hasan.
Merwan Ibn Hesen, haza min...
Marwan Ibn Hasan, this is from...
Min Barad.
From Barad.
Min Barad... Ey, hazihî bi... ye'nî bi... senet el-wecde,
beyn Sûriya we Misir.
From Barad... Yes, this is in... I mean in... the year of
unity, between Syria and Egypt.
Ne'em, ne'em.
Yes, yes.
Bi hazek el-weqt kênit kull el-buyût bi hazihi et-terîqe?
At that time, were all the houses built this way?
Ne'em, kull el-buyût, ağlebiyeta kênit min tîn.
Yes, all the houses, mostly they were made of mud.
Fî 'enna erba' xems buyût kênû mumeyyezîn bil-hecer.
We had four or five houses that were distinguished by stone.
Biddî is'elek, kênit el-buyût kulla mebniye bi haza eş-şekil
ye'nî quddama erdi diyar, me' sahat wasi'a?
I want to ask you, were all the houses built in this way, I
mean, in front of them a courtyard, with wide spaces?
Kulla la kên fî siyacat wela kên fî şî.
All of them, there were no fences nor anything.
Bes el-ğuref mewcûde, we quddama kulla fesehat fadiye.
Only the rooms were present, and in front of them all empty
spaces.
Temam... Hazihi şeceret tût?
Great... This is a mulberry tree?
Hey şeceret tût qedîme, ne'em.
This is an old mulberry tree, yes.
Şeceret et-tût... ye'nî murtebite bi wucûd el-miyah?
The mulberry tree... I mean, is it connected to the presence
of water?
Ye'nî nihne hown qarîbîn min mecra nehr Efrîn.
I mean, we are close here to the course of the Afrin River.
We bit-talî ye'nî ene bilahiz inno fî intişar le şeceret et-
tût.
And therefore, I mean, I notice that there is a spread of
the mulberry tree.
Fî 'enna miyah sethiye bin-nisbe lil-qerye.
We have surface water for the village.
We eş-şecer biynem... biynem fî el-qerye, ye'nî.
And the trees grow... they grow in the village, I mean.
Eywa. Haza hown êş hown? Xellîna nşûf hown...
I see. What is this here? Let's see here...
Fîna nitla' hown?
Can we go up here?
Nitla'.
Let's go up.
Şû haza hown? Menhel ma' haza?
What is this here? Is this a water source?
Haza menhel ma' kên, ewwelî fî 'enna may... kên mrekbîn el-
henefiye, yiğislû we yiclû hown kênû.
This was a water source, previously we had water... they had
installed a faucet, they used to wash and do dishes here.
Ye'nî el-may min eyn tîcî?
I mean, where does the water come from?
Hey el-may qedîmen kênit tîcî min Ğezzawiye.
This water used to come from Ghazawiya in the past.
Min Ğezzawiye?
From Ghazawiya?
'Eber eqniye ye'nî?
Yes.
Via canals, I mean?
'Ibare 'en eqniye... We fî 'enna biyar qedîme kên.
They are canals... And we had old wells.
Merdûme hown, kên fî hown 'enna bîr... hown... el-bîr
merdûm.
Filled in here, there used to be a well here... here... the
well is filled in.
Ma ista'melûh. Fe redemû, hellaq mâlû wucûd.
They didn't use it. So they filled it in, now it doesn't
exist.
Ye'nî hay el-may kênit tîcî min el-Ğezzawiye bi-eqniye welem
menahil...
I mean, this water used to come from Ghazawiya through
canals, and were they sources...
Bi-dexx 'ed-dey'a.
By pumping to the village.
Bi-dexx 'ed-dey'a, haza le-kull ahl el-qerye? mû le... mû
lil-'a'île feqat ellî hown?
By pumping to the village, this is for all the people of the
village? Not for... not for the family only that is here?
Teb'en, haza kên le-ahl el-qerye, kulla tîcî t'ebbî hown we
trûh.
Of course, this was for the people of the village, everyone
would come fill here and go.
Eywa. Le-êmat hal-hekî istemerr?
Wow. Until when did this continue?
Hal-hekî haza istemerr le-2011... 2011.
This continued until 2011... 2011.
We êmat bede'? Ye'nî min kem sene 'em tişrebû min el-
Ğezzawiye?
And when did it start? I mean, for how many years have you
been drinking from Ghazawiya?
Wallahi min el-Ğezzawiye teqrîben sar lina şî 20 sene.
By God, from Ghazawiya, it's been about 20 years for us.
20 sene...
20 years...
Ne'em.
Yes.
Êmat tehewwel şekil el-bina', min haza eş-şekil, lil-bina'
el-cedîd, ye'nî el-hedîs, hecer we isment we heyk?
When did the form of building change, from this form, to the
new building, I mean the modern one, stone and cement and
such?
Wallahi beda' el-bina' min senet 1990.
By God, the building started in the year 1990.
1990?
1990, beda' yitğeyyer şekil el-bina' we yiste'milû el-hecer
wel-isment.
1990, the form of building started to change and they used
stone and cement.
Şû es-sebeb lêş?
What is the reason, why?
Es-sebeb... kênit el-buyût min tîn min el-hecer...
The reason... the houses were made of mud from stone...
Kên yinzil metar yihtirû hal-buyût hazol...
It would rain and these houses would deteriorate...
Hat-tîn haza yinşal 'enhun. El-a'mide kênit 'umra ziyade,
kên yidxul fîha ed-dûd we titkesser...
This mud would be removed from them. The pillars were too
old, worms would enter them and they would break...
Feste'melû el-esquf el-ismentiye.
So they used cement roofs.
Ismentiye.
Cement.
Allah ye'tîk el-'afiye muxtar... Şukren ilek.
Yes.
May God give you health, Mukhtar... Thank you.
Allah ye'afîk, bi-selame, ehlen we sehlen... meşkûrîn.
May God give you health, goodbye, welcome... thanks to you.
Heyyakallah.
God bless you.
Hikayet Kefer Zêt hiye hikayet nehr Efrîn wez-zeytûn wel-
insan el-Kurdî...
The story of Kafr Zeit is the story of the Afrin River, the
olive tree, and the Kurdish human...
Ellezî 'aşe fî hal-mentiqe we 'anede et-tebî'a we zera' ez-
zeytûn we 'aşe fîha.
Who lived in this region and defied nature, planted olives,
and lived in it.
Fîha ekser min 1000 insan el-yewm min el-Ekrad el-esliyîn,
el-Êzidiyîn wel-Muslimîn.
In it there are more than 1000 people today from the
original Kurds, Yazidis and Muslims.
We fîha eyden hewalî 400 insan nazih min rîf Îdlib el-cenûbî
we rîf Hema.
And there are also about 400 displaced people from the
southern countryside of Idlib and the countryside of Hama.
Mu'zem sukkan hown biştiğlû biz-zira'a we biştiğlû bi
ri'ayet el-heywanat, xassaten el-ağnam wel-ma'iz.
Most of the residents here work in agriculture and work in
animal husbandry, especially sheep and goats.
Heyatum besîta rîfiye, te'temid eyden 'ala terbiyet el-
ağnam.
Their life is simple and rural, depending also on sheep
rearing.
Xellîna... ye'nî nqûm me' ba'd hellaq nimşî şwey bi-heş-
şewari' wnqabil en-nas,
Let's... I mean let's get up together now and walk a little
in these streets and meet the people,
Nşûf ehwalum, kîf 'ayşîn... nmirr 'ala kurûm ez-zeytûn,
wnşûf eyden el-'ummal ez-zira'iyîn... Tabe'ûna.
See their conditions, how they live... pass by the olive
groves, and see also the agricultural workers... Follow us.
Selamû 'aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
'Aleykum es-selam.
Peace be upon you too.
Allah ye'tîkum el-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah ye'afîk, ehlen we sehlen... tefeddel.
May God give you health, welcome... please come in.
Şlonkun?
How are you?
El-hemdulillah, ehlen we sehlen...
Praise be to God, welcome...
Şlon sihetkun?
How is your health?
Allah ye'tîk el-'afiye... ehlen... ehlen şebab.
May God give you health... welcome... welcome guys.
Ihkû lî şwey 'en hed-dey'a el-hilwe... Kefer Zêt.
Tell me a little about this beautiful village... Kafr Zeit.
Ehkî lî...
Tell me...
Êş tebî'et en-nas hown?
What is the nature of the people here?
Tebî'eta... ye'nî şlon beddek?
Its nature... I mean, how do you want?
Ye'nî mecazum şlon?
I mean, how is their mood?
Wallah tebî'et ahl ed-dey'a kwayyise, ademiyîn, kurama.
By God, the nature of the village people is good, decent
people, generous.
Kurama?
Generous?
Ey... we meselen... etba'um kwayyise, bi'erfû qîmet ba'd.
Hîk ye'nî...
Yes... and for example... their characters are good, they
know each other's value. Like that, I mean...
Bihebbû ba'd? Mutekatifîn? Mute'ayşîn?
Do they love each other? United? Coexisting?
Bihebbû ba'd... eh...
They love each other... yeah...
Ihkî lî bil-efrah wel-ehzan êş bîsîr?
Tell me, what happens in weddings and sorrows?
Wallah bil-efrah... ye'nî kullum byiltemmû 'ala 'irsû... we
bisa'dû ba'd, we bil-mowt keman nefs eş-şey.
By God, in weddings... I mean, they all gather for his
wedding... and help each other, and in death it's also the
same thing.
Nefs eş-şey. Hada qallî inno hown... inno esna' el-'iris,
nihar el-'iris el-kull bi'ettil.
The same thing. Someone told me that here... that during the
wedding, the day of the wedding, everyone takes the day off.
El-kull bişarik bil-wacib.
Everyone participates in the duty.
We nefs eş-şey fî nihar el-'eza?
And the same thing on the day of mourning?
Keman...
Also...
Wallah bil-'eza keman yowmeyn keman byicûz yowmeyn tlête
keman.
Isn't that so?
Wallah bil-'eza keman yowmeyn keman byicûz yowmeyn tlête
keman.
By God, for the mourning also two days, maybe also two or
three days.
Yowmeyn... bi'ettlû?
Two days... they take off?
Kullatun...
All of them...
Ebeden?
Completely?
Ebeden.
Completely.
Maşa'allah 'aleykun.
Mashallah on you.
Biddî is'el hown eş-şebab...
I want to ask the guys here...
Min weyn el-ex?
Where is the brother from?
Min hown, min Kefer Zêt.
From here, from Kafr Zeit.
Kefer Zêt? Êş 'em tiştiğil?
Kafr Zeit? What are you working as?
Fellah.
Farmer.
Fellah... ye'nî zeytûn?
Farmer... I mean olives?
Êş fî 'endkun ğeyr ez-zeytûn?
Yes.
What do you have other than olives?
Wallah hey şeğletna, ez-zeytûn... ye'nî bes nizra' u niflah
u nikseh. Hay şeğletna.
By God, this is our job, olives... I mean, we just plant,
plow, and prune. This is our job.
Ma 'em thintû, tşe'rû, keza?
Aren't you planting wheat, barley, such things?
Eh... fî hinte u şe'îr.
Yes... there is wheat and barley.
Ey fî keman tizra'û hinte u şe'îr.
Yeah, you also plant wheat and barley.
Eh fî... fî keman qisim minnu fewakih u rumman u...
Yes, there is... there is also a portion of it fruits and
pomegranates and...
Ey 'ala harf en-nehr ye'nî, mû...
Fruits...
Yes, on the edge of the river, I mean, not...
Ey... bes el-eşher hûwe hûwe el-... zeytûn.
Yeah... but the most famous is the... olive.
Ez-zeytûn, hey qedîme hey, hey mû... min zeman li hedd el-
an.
The olive, this is old, this is not... from the past until
now.
Min zeman li hedd el-an.
From the past until now.
Eh...
Yes...
Idxul 'el-mehel şwey le hown... me'liş? Nşûf el-es'ar
şlon...
Go into the shop a little here... is it okay? Let's see how
the prices are...
Ya rebb... Selamû 'aleykum.
Oh Lord... Peace be upon you.
Ya selam.
Oh, peace.
Şlonak 'ammo?
How are you, uncle?
Şlon sihtek?
Welcome.
How is your health?
Ehleyn bîk.
Welcome to you.
Merhaba 'ammo.
Hello uncle.
Ehleyn we sehleyn, ehleyn we sehleyn.
Welcome and welcome, welcome and welcome.
Nite'erref 'aleyk?
May we know you?
Iş beddek ti'rif 'eleyi?
What do you want to know about me?
Ismek el-kerîm?
Your noble name?
Slêman.
Suleiman.
Ya ehla we sehlen mid-dey'a?
Oh, welcome, from the village?
Eh mid-dey'a.
Yes, from the village.
Allah ye'tîk el-'afiye. Cey tişterî êş cey tsawî?
May God give you health. Have you come to buy, what are you
doing?
La wallah hey... ziyara.
No, by God, just a... visit.
Ziyara... Allah ye'tîk el-'afiye. Hadritak sahib el-mehel?
Visit... May God give you health. You are the owner of the
shop?
Eh, wallah b...
Yes, by God...
Ihkî lî wede' en-nas hown şlon... iqtisadiyen, me'îşiyen
şlon?
Tell me, how are the people's situation here...
economically, living-wise, how?
Te'banîn.
Tired.
Eh, el-wede' te'ban kull el-'alem, nisbet tês'în bil-miye
wed'un te'ban.
How?
Eh, el-wede' te'ban kull el-'alem, nisbet tês'în bil-miye
wed'un te'ban.
Yes, the situation is tiring for everyone, ninety percent of
them have a tiring situation.
Bima'na? Min el-ğela?
Meaning? From the inflation?
Eh, we ma fî... şeğul fures 'emel ma fî.
Yes, and there is no... work, job opportunities are non-
existent.
El-'alem êş 'em tiştiğil?
What are the people working as?
Ma fî şuğul, êş biddun yiştığilû?
There is no work, what do they want to work as?
Biyaxdû min 'endek bid-deyn wila...?
Do they take from you on credit or...?
Fî minhom bid-deyn, fî minhom naqdî, fî minhom meselen
lifetra şeher, şehereyn û baedeyn.
Some buy on credit, some in cash, some for a period of a
month, two months, and then...
Biyaetûk?
Do they pay you?
Ê, biyaetû.
Yes, they pay.
El-nazihîn keman biyaexdû bid-dayn wihêk?
Do the displaced people also take on credit and such?
Ê, keman biyaexdû.
Yes, they also take.
Yaenî mitlû mitl ehl id-dey'a?
So, like the people of the village?
Ê, mitlû. Nefs iş-şî.
Yes, exactly like them. The same thing.
Allah yaetîkum il-eafiye.
May God give you health.
Şukren ilkun. Fursa saeîda. Es-selamu aleykum.
Thank you all. Nice to meet you. Peace be upon you.
Nidkol ala ehad il-biyût.
We are entering one of the houses.
Ya Rab.
Oh God.
Es-selamu aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Ismehulna nidkol laandkon şwey?
Will you allow us to come in for a bit?
Nidkol laandkon şwey?
Can we come in for a bit?
Es-selamu aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Bêt hilû û mbeyyin min berra.
A beautiful house, it shows from the outside.
Yaenî şehhanî idkol netearraf ala ehlû.
It made me want to enter and get to know its people.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Şlonak?
How are you?
Ehlayn, şû halek?
Welcome, how are you?
El-hemdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Şlonak inte?
How are you yourself?
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Merheba ya immî.
Hello, mother.
Şlonik?
How are you?
El-hemdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Zewcitak?
Your wife?
Ya ehlen wa sehlen.
Yes.
Oh, welcome.
Bêtkon hilû ktîr.
Your house is very beautiful.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Şlon sihtak?
How is your health?
El-hemdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Nitearraf aleyk?
Can we know your name?
Cumaa.
Jumaa.
Ya ehlen wa sehlen.
Oh, welcome.
Min hon sekkan id-dey'a l-aslîyîn?
Are you from the original residents of the village?
Ê.
Yes.
Hkilî an ehl Keferzît.
Tell me about the people of Kafar Zeit.
Axa ez nizanim.
Brother, I don't know.
Eşû yaenî?
What does that mean?
Nizanim.
I don't know.
Yaenî eşû yaenî qillî?
I mean, what does that mean, tell me?
Ê eş bidî eqillak?
Yes, what should I tell you?
Qillî inte, qillî hkilî an ehl Keferzît.
You tell me, tell me about the people of Kafar Zeit.
Birûh and il-hecce...
I'll go to the Hajja...
Taal maeî.
Come with me.
Mabeddî ihkî.
He doesn't want to talk.
Şlonik?
How are you?
Ena bi erebî nizanim wile.
I don't know Arabic, by God.
Am tihkî maî erebî wbitqillî mabtihkî erebî.
You are speaking Arabic with me and telling me you don't
speak Arabic.
Na.
No.
Hkilî ehl he-ddey'a teyybîn?
Tell me, are the people of this village good?
Nizanim, nizanim.
I don't know, I don't know.
Keman? Mabitihkî?
Also? You don't speak?
Nizanim.
I don't know.
Yaxî ena cay is'el an ehl hed-dey'a.
Brother, I came to ask about the people of this village.
Şlonhon, eş tebîethon, kerîmîn?
How are they, what is their nature, are they generous?
Rind in, rind in.
They are good, they are good.
Rind in kwaysîn yaenî. Baxîlîn şî?
"Rind in" means good. Are they stingy?
Na.
No.
La. Kerîmîn?
No. Are they generous?
Ê kerîm in.
Yes, they are generous.
Bihibbu el-xerîb?
Do they like strangers?
Leke. Rind in.
Of course. They are good.
Xerîb hez dikin.
They like strangers.
Şû yaenî?
What does that mean?
Xerîb hez dikin.
They like strangers.
Ê nizanim.
Yes, I don't know.
Yallah. Daymen ya hecce. Allah yaetîkî l-eafiye.
Alright. Always, Hajja. May God give you health.
Allah maeak xalo.
God be with you, uncle.
Allah yirzuqak.
May God provide for you.
Es-selamu aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Ehlen wa sehlen, ehlên, serçava.
Welcome, welcome, upon my eyes.
Wsilna teqrîben la'ind ehl il-kerim wel-ummal illî am
yiştixlû.
We have almost arrived at the vineyard owners and the
workers who are working.
Rah nihawil niderdiş maeon şwey.
We will try to chat with them a bit.
Lenişûf kîf kan yomon ilyom.
To see how their day was today.
Ya Rab.
Oh God.
Ya Rab. Es-selamu aleykum.
Oh God. Peace be upon you.
Fînî ihkî maeak şwey?
Can I talk with you a bit?
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Şlonak?
How are you?
Heyyallah.
God bless you.
Nitearraf aleyk?
Can we know your name?
Alî.
Ali.
Allah yaetîk il-eafiye ya exî Alî. Min wên?
May God give you health, brother Ali. Where are you from?
Tela el-Deman.
Tal al-Daman.
Axzîn hel-kerim deman şlon axzînû wila ummal?
Did you rent this vineyard as a guarantee, or are you
workers?
La, ummal.
No, workers.
Allah yaetîkum il-eafiye.
May God give you all health.
Allah yeafîk ya Rab.
May God give you health, oh Lord.
Şlon mawsam is-sine?
How is the season this year?
La l-hemdulillah, maşî l-hal.
No, praise be to God, it's going fine.
L-hemdulillah. Hed eşû naweû hed?
Praise be to God. What kind is this?
Zêtî.
Zeiti (Oily).
Heda zêtî?
Is this Zeiti?
Ê.
Yes.
Heda l-zêt ktîr kways. Wmusmuh kways is-sine mu hêk?
This is very good for oil. And its season is good this year,
isn't it?
Ê inşallah.
Yes, God willing.
L-hemdulillah. Eşqad yaenî şedde tabaek il-ummal kem wahid?
Praise be to God. How many workers are in your group, how
many people?
L-bereke, 13 amil.
The blessing, 13 workers.
13 amil. Eşqad am tiştixlu bin-nehar kem şuwal?
13 workers. How many sacks are you working on per day?
L-bereke 15, 16, l-20.
The blessing, 15, 16, up to 20.
Maşallah. Eşqad am taexdû?
Mashallah. How much are you getting paid?
Es-sabiae wel-tamin wallah.
The seventh and the eighth, by God.
Yaenî kil sebie şwalet taexdû şwal?
You mean for every seven sacks you take one sack?
Tamin.
The eighth.
Yaenî intacxun bilyom tlêt şwalet.
So your production per day is three sacks.
Ê naem tamin.
Yes, exactly, the eighth.
Allah yaetîkum il-eafiye. asertû şî?
May God give you health. Did you press any?
Asarna marra.
We pressed once.
Eşqad l-qitaa zeytun is-sine?
How much is the yield of olives this year?
Tenekew w kîlo w kîloyen tene... hêk.
A tin and a kilo, or two kilos, a tin... like that.
Kil şwal zêtun kem tneke?
Every sack of olives is how many tins?
Kil şwal.
Every sack.
Tneke w kîlo w kîloyen.
A tin and a kilo or two kilos.
Maşallah.
Mashallah.
Hed şû ismû?
What is this called?
Heda wallah neal-şeytan sîbe.
This, by God... curse the devil, it's a ladder (sîba).
Sîbe?
Ladder (sîba)?
Ê.
Yes.
W heş-şeb eşû maeû foq? Merheba.
And what does this young man have up there? Hello.
Mişşata.
A comb.
Mişşata?
A comb?
Ê.
Yes.
Şlonak?
How are you?
Temam? Lîş mixettî wiccek?
Fine.
Fine? Why are you covering your face?
Mişan l-xubra wila mişan l-korona?
Because of the dust.
Because of the dust or because of Corona?
L-xubra wallah. Ma dillit korona is-sine.
Dust, by God. Corona didn't stay this year.
Xallîna nimşî, xallîna nişûf fî hada hon nihkî mae l-hecce.
Şû bitqirbek?
Let's walk, let's see if there is anyone here, we'll talk
with the Hajja. How is she related to you?
Maret ammî.
My uncle's wife.
Maret ammak.
Your uncle's wife.
Ê.
Yes.
Maşallah hel-lî maddînû taht il-ard şû bitsimmû hed hon?
Mashallah, this thing spread under the ground, what do you
call it here?
Şwadir.
Tarps (Şwadir).
Şwadir? Ilû hêk isim eş-şwadir wila bisimmû isim tanî hon
bid-dey'a?
Tarps? Is it called tarps like that or do they call it
another name here in the village?
Şwadir, hrûs.
Tarps, hrûs.
Hrûs.
Merheba ya hecce.
Hello, Hajja.
Ehlen wa sehlen xalo.
Welcome, uncle.
Şlonik?
How are you?
Inte şû am tsawwî?
What are you doing?
Enî ammal ennekkî el-wareq...
I am picking out the leaves...
Am tifsilî l-waraq an il-zêtun.
You are separating the leaves from the olives.
Ê, allahi yaetîk el-eafiye.
Yes, may God give you health.
Allah yeafîkî. Şlon heş-şixil el-yom?
May God give you health. How is this work today?
L-hemdulillah.
Praise be to God.
Fî taeab?
Is it tiring?
La ma fî taeab.
No, it's not tiring.
Billah?
Really?
Min êmet cîtû s-sibih lahon?
By God.
What time did you come here this morning?
Cîna mnis-saea sitte.
We came at six o'clock.
Sitte s-sibih? Laêmet tibqû hon?
Six in the morning? Until when do you stay here?
L-hazina hl-baed saea.
Now, after an hour.
Ê wallah.
After an hour.
Yes, by God.
Btirtahû saeat dhur, saeat sibih btiftarû btitxaddû?
Do you rest at noon, in the morning, do you have breakfast,
do you have lunch?
Nirtah, w nedîr sîre, nakol elliqme w ngul yallah.
We rest, and we chat, we eat a bite and say let's go.
Taklû hon yaenî?
You eat here, I mean?
Ê leh.
Yes, of course.
Şû btitbuxû? Şû tubaxtû l-yom?
What do you cook? What did you cook today?
L-yom?
Today?
Ê.
Yes.
L-yom tobaxna fasolîye.
Today we cooked fasuliya (beans).
Fasolîye xedra?
Green fasuliya?
Ê wallah.
Yes, by God.
Sihtên w hena yallah.
Double health and happiness.
İnşallah l-intac kways hêk, allah tireh l-bereke?
To your heart.
I hope the production is good like this, God bless it?
L-hemdulillah, l-hemdulillah, maşî l-hal, l-hemdulillah ala
hal w kil hal.
Praise be to God, praise be to God, it's going well, praise
be to God for this situation and every situation.
Hkilî eş fî andik wlad intî, wên zocik?
Tell me, what children do you have, where is your husband?
Zocî mitweffî.
My husband passed away.
Ê wallah.
Passed away?
Yes, by God.
W intî am tieîlî bi-ewladik?
And you are supporting your children?
Eş andik ewlad?
Yes, by God.
What children do you have?
Indî whayid w tlet banat.
I have one boy and three girls.
Hinne maeik?
Are they with you?
Kibar wila zxar?
Yes.
Old or young?
Cewwezit tnên, w wahde azzabîye.
I married off two, and one is single.
Wiş-şeb?
And the boy?
Wiş-şeb cewweztû, w indî kaman darra.
And the boy, I married him off, and I also have a co-wife.
Keman?
Also?
Indî maeay zade enî esrof aleyha.
I also have her with me, I spend on her too.
Allah yirzuqik.
May God provide for you.
Allah iselmik.
May God save you.
Yaenî şayla himl eyle.
So you are carrying the burden of a family.
Êwa.
Exactly.
Wwên saknîn?
And where do you live?
Ihna bieifrîn.
We are in Afrin.
Bixiyam wila byût?
In tents or houses?
Bil-eşrefîye, la wallah bixiyam.
In Ashrafieh, no by God, in tents.
Xiyam keman?
Tents too?
Ê wallah.
Yes, by God.
Yallah, allah yaeînkun, allah yaetîkum il-eafiye.
Alright, may God help you, may God give you all health.
Allah yeaafîk û yirzuqkom.
May God give you health and provide for you.
Mae rucûe in-nas min krûm iz-zêtun, baed yom amal tewîl...
With people returning from the olive orchards, after a long
day of work...
Wşaq, fî qitaf iz-zêtun...
And hardships, in picking olives...
Btintihî cewlitna lalyom, min qaryet Keferzît, et-tabiaa
limarkaz nahiyet Eifrîn, birîf Haleb iş-Şimalî.
Our tour for today ends, from the village of Kafar Zeit,
which is part of the Afrin district center, in the northern
countryside of Aleppo.
Sinekûn maakum fîl-esabîe il-qadime, fî cewlat cedîde, min
menatiq Suriya uxrî, hebibî.
We will be with you in the coming weeks, in new tours, from
other Syrian regions, my dear.
Limutabaet bernamicna, tabieû safhet il-fês il-xassa bil-
qanat.
To follow our program, follow the channel's special Facebook
page.
Waeyden mewqiena alel-internêt, halabtodaytv.net.
And also our website on the internet, halabtodaytv.net.
Es-selamu aleykum w rahmetullah w berekatuh.
Peace, mercy and blessings of God be upon you.