[Muzîk]
[Music]
Mirad Hemoya ji Çolaqa me.
I am Mirad Hemoya from Çolaqa.
Hema gundê me ye. Ev gundê çar pênc aîle malbatên mezin tê
de hebûn.
This is our village. There were four or five large families
in this village.
Aîleyek mezin malbata Seydî Mêmo bû.
A large family was the Seydî Mêmo family.
Û dudu, malbata Rihanî hebûn, malbata Şêx Heyder hebûn,
malbata Bego hebûn.
And secondly, the Rihanî family, the Şêx Heyder family, and
the Bego family.
Aîle, malbatên hûrik hûrik dîsa hebûn.
There were also other smaller families as well.
Û paşê di bidayê (destpêkê) de ne li gund rûniştî bûn.
And in the beginning, they were not settled in the village.
Her yekî ji malbatan şiketekê (şikeftekê) wan hebû.
Each family had a cave of their own.
Û gişkan ji hevdu hez dikirin, û çûyîn û hatinê wan, bi
dilkî pak bi hev re bûn.
They all loved each other, and their visits with each other
were with a pure heart.
Û heta ciyê em lê nihêrîn, evên malbatên Betal Axa ye.
And the place we are looking at belongs to the Betal Agha
family.
Yekî wisa serokê gund bû.
He was sort of the leader of the village.
Berê, ku hebû Xelîl Axayê Seydî Mêmo.
In the past, there was Xelîl Agha of Seydî Mêmo.
Însanekî wisa gîştî bû, zana bû, diyar bû.
He was a very well-known person, wise, and prominent.
Û em her û her bala xwe didinê,
And we always pay attention to this,
elhemdulîllah dîsa gund rind e, û gîş jî em ji hev hez
dikin.
thank God, the village is still good, and we all love each
other.
Em dixwazin ku, em ji vî tiştî zêdetir jî pêş bikevin.
We want to progress even further than this.
Natiqeya (encama) dilpakbûna me bi hev re ye.
This is the result of our pure hearts towards each other.
Ev rewşa gund wisa ye, bi xêr û xweşî.
This is the situation of the village, in goodness and joy.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Navê min Ednan Mihemed Şêxo, ji gundê Çolaqa.
My name is Ednan Mihemed Şêxo, from the village of Çolaqa.
Em di gund de, di nav de muqîm in (niştecî ne).
We are residents in the village.
Ev gund, teqrîben ji sê çar sed salî de çêbûye.
This village was formed approximately three to four hundred
years ago.
Û zêdetir jî dibe heye.
And maybe even more than that.
Ev gund asilê xwe, ne li vî derî bû. Li pişta gund bû.
Originally, this village was not located here. It was behind
the village.
Di şikeftan de bûn, pê ra qefal (zinar) digotin. Li nav dar
û beran bûn.
They lived in caves, they called them "qefal" (rocks). They
were among the trees and rocks.
Paşê piştî wextekî derketin. Giş gihîştin hev û hatin van
deran.
Later, after some time, they came out. They all gathered and
came to these areas.
Rûniştin, avkî derxistin ji keviyan.
They settled down, and they brought out a spring of water
from the rocks.
Çaxê wê kaniyê dîtin, ku av tê de ye, gotin temam e, li vê
derê derketin.
When they saw that spring, and that water was flowing, they
said it was perfect, and they settled here.
Rûniştin wê wextê li Çolaqa... bi cihekî ecêb.
They settled in Çolaqa at that time... in a wonderful place.
Wan wisa ava kirin. Wextê wê avê derxistin...
They built it like that. When they brought out that water...
Biniya wê, malê Seydî Mêmo bû.
Its foundation was the Seydî Mêmo family.
Malê Seydî Mêmo, malek mezin e, ayleyek axa ne.
The Seydî Mêmo family is a large family, a family of aghas.
Û tiştekî din jî, ev gundê me, bîrek di nava gund de heye.
And another thing is, in our village, there is a well in the
middle of the village.
Ew bîr jî aserî (dîrokî) ye.
That well is also historical.
Teqrîben sêsed dînaran wê demê lêçûye.
They spent approximately three hundred dinars on it during
those old times.
Berî wê, xelkê gund û pezên xwe, heywanên xwe, giş diçûn
cihên din av didan û dihatin.
Before that, the village people, their sheep, and their
animals, all used to go to other places to drink water and
come back.
Gundên din digotin ji ber diziyan diçûn... Çolaqa pir qedîm
e.
Other villages used to say they went because of thefts...
Çolaqa is very ancient.
Mekteb (dibistan) di gundan de tune bû, di gundê me de çêbû.
Axayên me çêkirin.
There were no schools in the villages, but it was built in
our village. The aghas built it.
Camî (mizgeft) tune bû, axa çêkirin.
There was no mosque, the aghas built it.
Malê Seydî Mêmo malek mezin e, ev malên Betal Axa ne.
The Seydî Mêmo family is a large family, these are the homes
of Betal Agha.
Di pey wî re jî, mêvanên wan hebûn.
After him, they had guests.
Kî bihata gund, teslîmî wan dibû.
Whoever came to the village, was entrusted to them.
Çi qas mirov bûn, ew nav çûn...
No matter who they were, those names went...
Kî bûya jî, teslîm dibûn vê derê, ev qesr e.
Whoever it was, they were entrusted to this place, this
mansion.
Ezet û Mihemed wisa ne.
Ezet and Mihemed are like this.
Û gundê me jî, gundekî mezin e, qedîm e.
And our village is also a large village, an ancient one.
Nav lê kirine Çolaqa, çima gotin Çolaqa?
They named it Çolaqa, why did they call it Çolaqa?
Yekî destê xwe, xwar (çolak) bû.
Someone's hand was crooked (paralyzed).
Wisa digotin, ev Çolaq e, bi navê wî...
They used to say, this is Çolaq, by his name...
Navê gund derket, hin kesan ev nav derxistin. Lê belê wê
demê gotin Çolaqa.
The name of the village emerged, some people came up with
the name. But at that time they said Çolaqa.
Bi navê wî, nav lê kirin Çolaqa. Û gundê me jî...
It was named Çolaqa after him. And our village too...
Ji malbatan e, malbata Seydî Mêmo ye.
Is made up of families, the Seydî Mêmo family.
Malbata Rihanî ye, malbata Kerro ye.
The Rihanî family, the Kerro family.
Malê Beskê hene, malê Şêxî hene.
There is the Beskê family, there is the Şêxî family.
Malê Rihanî hene, evna giş aîle ne.
There is the Rihanî family, these are all families.
Ji pênc-şeş biran da, heta deh biran da, wisa aîleyek mezin
in.
From five or six brothers, up to ten brothers, they are
large families like this.
Û gundê me jî pir qedîm e. Û elhemdulîllah giş ji hev hez
dikin.
And our village is very ancient. And thank God, they all
love each other.
Û rind e.
And it's lovely.
Ziraetê ku em dikin jî zeytûn in, rez in...
The agriculture we do is olives, vineyards...
Mişmiş in (qeyisî ne), meselen tiştên wisa hûn zanin, ev der
gund e. Û pir zeytûn in.
Apricots, for example, things like that, you know, this is a
village. And there are a lot of olives.
Û elhemdulîllahî rebil alemîn, saet xweş.
And praise be to God, the Lord of the worlds, have a good
time.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Navê min Ebdilrehman Osman ibn Ebdilrehman e.
My name is Ebdilrehman Osman ibn Ebdilrehman.
Leqeb (nasnav) Ebû Hisên dibêjin.
My nickname is Abu Hussein.
Mixtarê gund im, teb'en (bêguman) di vê demê de, ez mixtarê
gund bûm.
I am the mukhtar of the village, of course in this period, I
was the mukhtar of the village.
Û berî wê jî ez serokê Cemiya Felahiyê (Komeleya Cotkaran)
bûm.
And before that, I was the head of the Farmers' Association.
Ji ber vê yekê, gundê me...
Therefore, our village...
Eyda me, wek eydên xelkê derbas dibe.
Our Eid, passes just like the Eids of other people.
Eydê meselen Qurbanê, Eyda El Etha.
For example, the Eid of Sacrifice, Eid al-Adha.
Her kes qurbana xwe serjêdike.
Everyone slaughters their own sacrifice.
Û bela dikin li feqîran, giş bela dikin.
And they distribute it to the poor, they all distribute it.
Û teb'en mexiyên xwe hene yani, eyd ne wekî berê ne.
And of course they have their own delights, meaning, Eid is
not like it used to be.
Ne wekî berê kom dibin.
They don't gather like they used to.
Ji ber wê yekê dîsa em berdewam dikin.
But nonetheless, we still keep it going.
Em diçin...
We go...
em diçin cem hevdu, cejna hevdu pîroz dikin.
we visit each other, and celebrate each other's Eid.
Teb'en helwiyat, û xwarin û gişt tişt hene.
Of course there are sweets, and there is food and
everything.
Û eydê din jî eynî tişt (Cejna Remezanê).
And the other Eid is the exact same thing.
Dawet... dawet eynî tişt.
Weddings... weddings are the same thing.
Dawet lî gund da dibin.
Weddings take place in the village.
Dawet xêra gundiyan e.
Weddings are the joy of the villagers.
Dawet li nav gund dibin.
Weddings happen inside the village.
Malek... merivê xwe gişkan dewet dikê (vedixwîne).
A family... invites all their relatives.
Bi def, bi zirne, bi bûk, xwarin û vexwarin, gîş derbas
dikin pê re, rind e yanî.
With daf, with zurna, with the bride, food and drinks, they
all spend time with it, it's really nice.
Xwarina meşhûr, wek menasif (mensef) e.
The famous food here is like mansaf.
Goşt, dikin hundirê...
They put meat inside...
...dîlan, û gêrima, û fêrîk, û tirş, û dar. Hava bi
munasebeta îd meşhûr in hava l'gund giştîk.
...weddings, and calling out, and roasted chicken, and sour
things, and wood. These are famous on the occasion of Eid in
the whole village.
Ga 'aîle mezin be. Me'zûmîn pir bin. Xedeyekî fîne nava wan
heye.
If the family is big. The guests are many. A fine lunch is
among them.
Û înema hindik bin da, gî bi şewayê meşwî dar dar bas dikin.
Ga hindik bin ha.
And if they are few, they all pass the time with grilling on
wood. If they are few.
Î gundê me ha ye, bîr heye, dar li ortê gund heye...
This is our village, it has a well, it has a tree in the
middle of the village...
Camî... pir kevin heye... Camî heye, mekteb heye, yê pir
kevin.
It has a very old... mosque... It has a mosque, it has a
school, which is very old.
Mekteb meselen di pêncî û heyştan da hatî girtin...
The school, for example, was founded in '58...
Camî di pêncî û heyştan da hatî girtin. Yani pir... yanî
eseriyek rind e yanî.
The mosque was founded in '58. I mean, it is very... it is a
beautiful historical monument.
Û bes çîçek teslîhat me kirîye, camiyê, bes mekteb kema
huwe, hindî wekî berê ye yanî.
And we just made a few renovations, to the mosque, but the
school is as it is, it is exactly like before.
Etxaricîn hene... Etxaricîn hene, hebûn...
There are graduates. There are graduates, there were.
Mistefa Sîdo Mêmê hebû... Xelîl Sîdo Mêmê hebû, Rifat 'Umer
Zênelûş vêra dibên hebû...
There was Mustafa Sido Meme. There was Khalil Sido Meme,
there was Rifat Omar Zainalush as they call him.
Kemal Cemîl Axa hev a, evê tilfîzyon ba tilfîzyon û eflam
temsîl dikirin, evnakî çûn Elmanya.
Kemal Jamil Agha, this one... he used to act on television
and in movies, these ones went to Germany.
Rifat tib... tib xelas kir, îxtîsasa xwe kulîye û bawliye
derbû.
Rifat finished medicine. His specialization was nephrology
and urology.
Mistefa îxtîsasa xwe daxilîye, havnake li Elmanya bûn a.
Mustafa specialized in internal medicine. These ones were in
Germany.
E... em pê nizanin yanî... di şêst salî da havna çûn
Elmanya. Ji şêst salî da çûn Elmanya havna.
Uh... we don't know them. I mean... in the sixties these
ones went to Germany. In the sixties they went to Germany.
Me nedîtin havnake.
We didn't see them.
Umrê min bûye şêst û pênc, min nedît li vederê bûn.
I am sixty-five years old, I didn't see them being here.
Tab'en êd kilama digotin, hebûn, Cemîl Horo hebû li vederê.
Of course, those who sang songs, there were, Jamil Horo was
from here.
Ji gund... Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, ji gund bû.
From the village... May God have mercy on him, he was from
the village.
Bavkê xwe li vir bû... dêk û bavê xwe li vir bû, erê nas
dikim.
His grandfather was here... his parents were here, yes I
know them.
Li cem me rûniştî bûn. Havanakî xarîcîn li vir... doxtor...
cem me xarîcîne... muhendîsîn hene, hene yanî... muhendîsîn
hene...
They lived with us. These graduates here... doctors...
graduated with us... there are engineers, there are, I
mean... there are engineers...
Êêê, pir hene yanî... hene di menasibê dewlê da...
Uh... there are many, I mean... there are, in state
positions...
Meselen cem me hebû, Ebû Goran... Ebû Goran me'rûf bû,
mudîr...
For example, we had Abu Goran... Abu Goran was well-known,
he was a director...
Mudîr'am ê Îskan Eskerî te ev da bû li Şamê. Mudîr'am ê
Îskan Eskerî te ev da bû.
He was the General Director of Military Housing back then in
Damascus. He was the General Director of Military Housing
back then.
Xwedê rehma xwe lê ke, ew jî mir.
May God have mercy on him, he also died.
Û însanêkî pir yanî, bi navî gund da, bi ê wî gundî çol û
qat da dewekî wan çol û qat da hatin nas kirin yanî... gî
hene.
And a very... person, in the name of the village, in that
village, in the wilderness and floors, things like those in
the wilderness and floors they were known, I mean... there
are all.
Heta bihus 'ilmiye li cem me hene... xarîcîne bihus 'ilmiye,
majîstêr, doktorah... ta naqişê bihus 'ilmiye dane.
Even scientific researchers we have... graduates of
scientific researchers, master's, doctorate... there are
even those who gave scientific researchers.
Cihên tewrî meşhûr di gundî me da, inu xelk tê û 'ecêba xwe
dibîne.
The most famous places in our village, that people come and
are amazed by.
Darek çinarê li ortê gund da heye. Darek çinarê...
There is a plane tree in the middle of the village. A plane
tree...
Dar jî... wekî nemûzec e yanî, xelk tê sûretê xwe li bin
dikişîne.
The tree is... like a model, people come and take their
pictures under it.
Dar kokê xwe pir qalind e. Pir qalind bi ye.
The tree's roots are very thick. They are very thick.
Û meşkol xelk pir jê dikir, inu vê darê çiqas wext heye, kî
çand, kî anî, kesî nizanîbû tenê.
And people wondered a lot about it, how old is this tree,
who planted it, who brought it, nobody knew exactly.
Êd texmîna me ye, 'umrê darê heq e sêsed sal û jor da hebe
yanî.
Our estimation is, the age of the tree must be 300 years and
above.
Dar... yek nemûzecek û fere bi ye. Sersiya xwe pir bi ye.
The tree... is a model and it's wide. Its shade is very big.
Û du darê çûçik jî, mil kêleka gund me dîti bû yanî, me
anîbû çandin, ha ew jî çinar e bûn.
And two small trees as well, we had seen at the side of the
village, we had brought them to plant, they were also plane
trees.
Û yek tûy e.
And one is a mulberry tree.
Haco êdî sersî pir bû ye, êdî dewatek hebe, şîraniyek hebe,
tiştek hebe, gî li bin wê darê dikin.
So its shade is very big, when there is a wedding, a
celebration, anything, they do it all under that tree.
Û ewê xwe derbaz dikin. Di bin wê darê da, bîrek heye, bîr
pir kevin e.
And they pass their time. Under that tree, there is a well,
the well is very old.
Teb'en wextê... e... di pêncî, di şêst salî da, wextê ku
keşif bûye û xelk hatine... ji tevî wê bîrê hatin.
Of course in the times... uh... in the fifties, in the
sixties, when it was discovered and people came... they came
because of that well.
Wê bîrê, ava xwe pir rind bû, ava xwe pir pir bû.
That well, its water was very good, its water was very
plentiful.
Yanî... barê gund giş dikişand ser xwe, û ele dewatê ji wê
av dibirin, pezê xwe, darên xwe, gî dihatin ji wê bîrê av
dikirin.
Meaning... it carried the burden of the whole village, and
even the weddings took water from it, their sheep, their
trees, everyone came and watered from this well.
Felîzalîk... yanî, di sala heyştê û şeşan da...
Therefore... meaning, in the year eighty-six...
Ya sîdî, ewel însan min dînamo kirî... kehrabe di heyştê û
şeşan da hat gund.
Sir, I was the first person to buy a dynamo... electricity
came to the village in eighty-six.
Min dînamo kirî û min danî ser wê bîrê, û min şixuland li
ser motora kehrabê.
I bought a dynamo and put it on that well, and I ran it on
the electric motor.
Û min av berda mal, yanî xelk ecêb ma. Xelk bi hesî. Berê
giş bi xwe û bi jin û bi dewaran dihatin av dibirin mal.
And I released water to the house, people were amazed.
People found out. Before, everyone came themselves and with
women and animals to take water home.
Yê êdî xelkê gî li min nihêrî, û giştekî dînamo û xetas û
derkirin wê bîrê.
So then the people all looked at me, and everyone put
dynamos and submersibles in that well.
Li talî teqrîben bû şeş dînamo li ser wê bîrê, şeş dînamo,
xertûm û der... her kes kehraba xwe ji mal biriye û...
In the end there were almost six dynamos on that well, six
dynamos, hoses and stuff... everyone brought their
electricity from home and...
...ew kirî ye vederê, êdî xelkê kêf kir yanî.
...put it there, so the people enjoyed it.
Sahet we xweş. Ehlen û sehlen.
Good health to you. Welcome.
Hava kewy e. Hava berê, li ser fehmê dişixulandin
derdikirin.
This is an iron. This one in the past, they used to work it
on charcoal.
Tişt dikirin... û kincên xwe ev diki... didanîn ser, diçûn,
dihatin wekî du oqre dikirin, dûd dibû, derdibû hav a.
They used to do things... and they put their clothes... they
put it on, they went back and forth, they pressed it twice,
it smoked, it came out, this is it.
Hava qahwîde kî ye. Hava mezharîk e... wekî mezyet e.
This is a coffee pot. This is a vase... like a decoration.
Mezyet e, zênet dikirin, derdikirin, pê xwarin marîn
derdikirin, derdikirin.
A decoration, they used to decorate, put things out, put
food in it, put it out.
Hav nakî nefad e ne... sifir in... e hav na...
These are ashtrays... they are copper... uh these ones...
Hava jî sêniyê binî yê der a, e yek jê wan a, meselen pê de
diyafê ew dikirin derdikirin, ev jî sifir e, tişta der in...
ha va...
This is also the bottom tray, where they used to, for
example, serve guests with it, this is also copper, they put
things out... this...
Havo kefgîr e. Kefgîr pê ew dikin, derdikirin, pê şorbe da
rû...
This is a ladle. They do things with a ladle, they put out,
with it in soup...
...şîv dikin, barîk... maz in derdikirin derdikirin, pê ha
vî, tef didan, pê dikirin derdikirin...
...they make dinner, thin... they put it out, put it out,
with this, they stirred, they did it, put it out...
Hava... evê qahwê ye, destar e... destarê qahwê çûçik e...
hava menzer e yanî...
This... this is for coffee, it's a hand mill... a small
coffee hand mill... this is a decoration, I mean...
Hav nakî şem'dan in... şem' dikirin ed derdikirin, menzer
sifir in... hav na.
These are candle holders... they used to put candles, put
them out, copper decorations... these.
Vê ra dibên semawer... Şixulê tirkî ye ev na. Sifir in...
They call this a samovar... These are Turkish made. They are
copper...
Li ve derê çay dika tê der dike... çay li ve derê... giran
e.
Here tea is put... tea in here... it's heavy.
Li vir jî av dikirin e, li ser kerabê jî dişixule û li ser
fehmê jî dişixule.
And here they put water, it works on electricity and it also
works on charcoal.
Wextê ew dikirin derdikirin, ji vê boştî, ji vê boştî a dî
nîv qedeh dikirin e, ê dî boştî dikirin e... çay dibû xemîre
derdiket. Ha vî.
When they used to do it, put it out, from this tap, from
this tap, they would fill half a glass, and the rest from
the tap... the tea brewed and came out. This.
Havo ji sukkeriye ye... şekir dikin ê da... derdikin pê
diyafê der a, tişt mişt... ha we dikir... ha va.
This is a sugar bowl... they put sugar in it... they put it
out to serve guests, things... they did it like this...
this.
Havo jî fanos e... fanos... fanosê çirê... kerabê pê da
diso... hanakî der a.
This is a lantern... lantern... kerosene lantern... it burns
with electricity... like this.
Hava tembûr e... Tembûrek kurmancî ye, zatan bızıq bi erebî
ye.
This is a tanbur... It's a Kurdish tanbur, essentially a
buzuq in Arabic.
Hava jî sindoq e, sindoqê deykê min rehmtiyê ye. Ûmriyê giş
teqrîben nêzîka sed, sed û deh sal 'umriyê vî heye.
This is also a chest, the chest of my late mother. The age
of all this is approximately close to a hundred, a hundred
and ten years this has.
Hane heye...
It is here...
Û dê ha nav jî teper in, barê te gotin teper. Vê ra dibêjin
teper. Teper çî ye teper?
And these inside are also tapers (woven trays), you just
said tapers. They call this a taper. What is a taper?
Şûnê... we... sîniyê nedît di dênin ser, li ser wana me
dixwar...
Instead of... well... they didn't see trays, they put it on,
we used to eat on them...
Ê gîşti me... yanî me li ser wana... deykê min rahmetî ew
dikir derdikir, me nan dixwar, derdikir diçûn dişûştin
derdikirin. Paqij dibû, derdibû.
All of us... I mean on them... my late mother used to put it
out, we ate food, she put it out, they went, washed it, put
it out. It became clean, it came out.
Ji çî çêdibiya? Ji qiş... Ewe... merx... e çî ewê... e...
What was it made from? From straw... That... juniper... uh
what's that... uh...
Genim dar a... jê we... qamûş mûşa çêdikirin derdikirin hav
a... hav a.
Wheat stalks... from that... they made it from reeds, put it
out, this... this.
Hav sehet a jî qadîm e... Ine ke teqrîban, ez umrê min bû
şêst û heft, ha va bû çil sal in, pêncî sal in li cem min e,
ev sehet a jî.
These watches are also old... It means that approximately, I
am sixty-seven years old, this has been with me for forty
years, fifty years, this watch too.
Û vî şûr a, e vî şûr a jî, taqrîban 'umrê gêndî bi ye nêzîka
sed sal, çil sal, cem me bû ye hav o...
And this sword, and this sword too, its age is approximately
near a hundred years, forty years, it has been with us,
this...
Me anî, hat menzer me dîna yê mal der kirî...
We brought it, it became a decoration, we put it in the
house, put it out...
E tiştê hana, pir jê hez dikim da kêm. Torasî ye... qedîm e.
These things, I love them a lot. It is heritage... it is
old.
Me'ne însan... de qiseti me re ra der e filan û bêvan...
zanebin çî ye ne çî ye, filan û bêvan... der e.
Meaning people... so our story can come out to so and so...
so they know what it is and what it isn't, so and so... it
comes out.
Siba dor in da... weleh hav ê bav-kalê gund bû, hav ê bav-
kalê gund bû, hav tiştên ê wî bû, hav hanakî bû... me'nê
çe...
Tomorrow they will gather... by God this belonged to the
grandfathers of the village, this belonged to the
grandfathers of the village, these were his things, this was
like this... meaning what...
Bila tim torasê me ra hebe. Û zate toras ji nema... qîmetê
me ra jî namîne. Û sehata we xweş... Xwedê ji we razî be. Û
mîta sahet...
Let our heritage always be with us. And besides, if heritage
doesn't exist... our value won't remain either. And good
health to you... May God be pleased with you. And a hundred
hours...
[Lêdana tembûrê]
[Instrumental music playing]
[Muzîka dawiyê]
[Outro music playing]