English Translation
كفر دلي تحتاني قرية سورية تتبع مركز منطقة عفرين في ريف حلب
الشمالي.
English Translation
Kafardali Tahtani is a Syrian village belonging to the
center of Afrin district in the northern countryside of
Aleppo.
English Translation
وتبعد عنها مسافة 13 كيلومتراً باتجاه الغرب.
It is located 13 kilometers away from it to the west.
English Translation
كما أنها تبعد مسافة 18 كيلومتراً عن ناحية جنديرس باتجاه
الشمال الشرقي.
English Translation
It is also 18 kilometers away from the Jindires sub-district
towards the northeast.
English Translation
و 65 كيلومتراً عن مدينة حلب باتجاه الشمال الغربي.
And 65 kilometers from the city of Aleppo towards the
northwest.
English Translation
أما بعدها عن الحدود السورية التركية فهو 25 كيلومتراً من
ناحية بلدة الحمام السياحية.
English Translation
As for its distance from the Syrian-Turkish border, it is 25
kilometers from the side of the tourist town of Al-Hammam.
English Translation
بنيت القرية فوق سهل منبسط وعلى السفح الشمالي الغربي لجبل
يحاذيها.
English Translation
The village was built on a flat plain and on the
northwestern slope of an adjacent mountain.
English Translation
يقسمها وادٍ كان يمر فيه مسيل مائي قادم من قرية كفر دلي
فوقاني حيث يقسمها إلى قسمين غربي وشرقي.
English Translation
It is divided by a valley through which a water stream used
to pass, coming from the village of Kafardali Fawqani,
dividing it into a western and an eastern part.
English Translation
تبلغ مساحة القرية 450 هكتاراً مزروعة بأشجار الزيتون.
The village's area is 450 hectares, planted with olive
trees.
English Translation
وأيضاً مزروعة بالحبوب المختلفة والكمون وحبة البركة إضافة إلى
خضراوات متعددة.
English Translation
And also planted with various grains, cumin, and black seed,
in addition to various vegetables.
English Translation
تفصلها تلة بركانية تربتها سوداء من الجهة الشرقية عن قرية
معراتة المحاذية لها.
English Translation
A volcanic hill with black soil separates it from the
eastern side from the adjacent village of Maarateh.
English Translation
يبلغ عدد سكانها الحالي 1500 نسمة من أهلها الأصليين ومن عوائل
سورية مهجرة قسراً من ريفي حلب الغربي ومن جبل الحص في ريف حلب
الجنوبي.
English Translation
Its current population is 1,500 people, consisting of its
original inhabitants and Syrian families forcibly displaced
from the western countryside of Aleppo and from Jabal al-
Hass in the southern countryside of Aleppo.
English Translation
أشهر عوائلها الكردية بيت نجار ودادو وطاطوز ومن عوائلها
العربية بيت خليل عربو.
English Translation
The most famous of its Kurdish families are the Najjar,
Dado, and Tatouz families, and of its Arab families is the
Khalil Arabo family.
English Translation
هاجر قسم من أبنائها يعادل 70 بالمئة من سكانها إلى تركيا
وأوروبا للعمل.
English Translation
A portion of its native residents, equivalent to 70 percent
of its population, emigrated to Turkey and Europe for work.
English Translation
مصادر الدخل الأساسية لسكانها هي الزراعة والتحويلات النقدية
التي يرسلها أبناؤهم إليهم من المهجر إضافة إلى العمل ببعض
المهن الحرة والتجارة.
English Translation
The main sources of income for its residents are agriculture
and the cash remittances sent to them by their children from
the diaspora, in addition to working in some freelance
professions and trade.
English Translation
بنيت أول مدرسة في القرية في عام 1973 وهي مدرسة ابتدائية.
The first school in the village was built in 1973, which is
a primary school.
English Translation
يشتهر أهلها بالأعمار الكبيرة للرجال والنساء والتي قد تبلغ
125 سنة كما أنهم مشهورون بالسماحة والطيبة والبساطة والكرم.
English Translation
Its people are known for the long lifespans of men and
women, which may reach 125 years. They are also famous for
their tolerance, kindness, simplicity, and generosity.
English Translation
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
English Translation
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
English Translation
مرحبا عمو.
Hello, uncle.
English Translation
يا أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
English Translation
شلونك؟
How are you?
English Translation
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
English Translation
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health too.
English Translation
نتعرف عليك؟
Can you introduce yourself?
English Translation
نعم، تفضل.
Yes, go ahead.
English Translation
نتعرف عليك؟
Can you introduce yourself?
English Translation
خليل حاج حنان.
Khalil Hajj Hanan.
English Translation
يا أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
English Translation
أهليين فيك.
Welcome to you.
English Translation
ابن الضيعة من هون من كفر دلي تحتاني؟
A son of the village from here, from Kafardali Tahtani?
English Translation
نعم، من كفر دلي تحتاني، نعم.
Yes, from Kafardali Tahtani, yes.
English Translation
مزارع؟
A farmer?
English Translation
إن شاء الله.
God willing.
English Translation
إن شاء الله.
God willing.
English Translation
حضرتك؟
And you, sir?
English Translation
يا أهلا وسهلا عمو، 100 سلامة. شرفتوا بهالضيعة.
Welcome uncle, 100 welcomes. You honored this village.
English Translation
100 سلامة فيك. الله يسلمك.
100 welcomes to you. May God keep you safe.
English Translation
وأهلا وسهلا فيك.
And welcome to you.
English Translation
نتعرف عليك؟
Can you introduce yourself?
English Translation
أنا محمود عبد الرحمن عبد القادر، من بيت خوجة.
I am Mahmoud Abdel Rahman Abdel Qader, from the Khoja
family.
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
Welcome.
English Translation
100 سلامة، أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
100 welcomes, welcome.
English Translation
كمان مزارع؟
Also a farmer?
English Translation
مزارع، كل شي. نزرع، نزرع مثلاً حنطة، شعير، عدس، جلبان.
A farmer, everything. We plant, we plant for example wheat,
barley, lentils, vetch.
English Translation
وبدنا، بدكم تساعدونا معنا مشان السماد، مشان المي، الري.
And we need, we need you to help us with fertilizers, with
water, irrigation.
English Translation
مشان نحرك شوي الزراعة، يعني.
So we can stimulate agriculture a bit, you know.
English Translation
تكرم.
You got it.
English Translation
تكرم عينك.
Your eyes are honored.
English Translation
خليني أسأل عمي خليل أول شي.
Let me ask my uncle Khalil first.
English Translation
إي يلا، ماشي.
Yes, come on, alright.
English Translation
عمي خليل، احكي لي يعني هلأ أنا شايف معظم أراضي الضيعة هي
عبارة عن زيتون.
English Translation
Uncle Khalil, tell me, now I see that most of the village's
lands are olive trees.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
الزيتون شقد عمره هون؟
How old are the olive trees here?
English Translation
الزيتون أشكال وأنواع فيه.
The olive trees are of various shapes and kinds.
English Translation
تطلع على هالوجه هذا، يعني حوالي 50 سنة هيك زارعينهم، كله كان
جبل فاضي كان.
English Translation
Look at this side, they planted them about 50 years ago, it
was all an empty mountain.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
وهالوجه هذا كمان.
And this side too.
English Translation
وهالوجه هذا قديم هذا حوالي 70، 60 سنة.
And this side is old, about 70, 60 years.
English Translation
قبل الزيتون شو كان؟
What was there before olives?
English Translation
أراضي. أراضي فاضية متل هوني.
Lands. Empty lands like here.
English Translation
هلأ أنا اللي فهمته إنه قبل ما يكون في زيتون كانت مشهورة
الضيعة بزراعة العنب. وفي معاصر عنب كتير.
English Translation
Now what I understood is that before there were olives, the
village was famous for planting grapes. And there were many
grape presses.
English Translation
إي، كان في معاصر. معاصر عنب من هالطرف هذا من تحت ومن تحت،
وهالوجه هذا كله كان عنب.
English Translation
Yes, there were presses. Grape presses from this side down,
and from down, and this whole side was grapes.
English Translation
وفي محصرتين تلاتة كان بالضيعة، واحد هنيك وواحد بالطرف الغربي
وواحد هون.
English Translation
And there were two or three presses in the village, one
there and one on the western side and one here.
English Translation
أنا شفتهم تلاتة.
I saw them, three.
English Translation
كان يحصروا هنيك الدبس، بالاجر كانوا يدوسوا ويعصروه.
They used to press molasses there, they used to step on it
with their feet and squeeze it.
English Translation
ممم. طيب وبنفس الوقت اللي كان فيه عنب كان في عندكم هون يعني
فواكه، تين، و...
English Translation
Mmm. Well, at the same time there were grapes, did you have
fruits here, figs, and...
English Translation
فواكه، تين وبين الكروم كان في كتير، نعم بين الكروم.
Fruits, figs, and among the vineyards there were a lot, yes,
among the vineyards.
English Translation
شجرة هون، شجرة هنيك، شجرة هنيك، نعم كان متل هدول هيك ها.
A tree here, a tree there, a tree there, yes, it was like
these here.
English Translation
طيب خلينا نسأل الأخ شوي.
Well, let's ask the brother a bit.
English Translation
هلأ هون منين عم تسقوا الأراضي؟ شايف أنا المنطقة كلها خضرا.
Now here, where are you watering the lands from? I see the
whole area is green.
English Translation
يعني هلأ اليوم أراضي خضرا، حاطين لوحة طاقة شمسية.
Well, today the lands are green, we put solar panels.
English Translation
مشان عم نطالع مي بالغطاس وعم نسقي وعم نشتري من عندهم يعني.
Because we are extracting water with the submersible pump
and we are watering and buying from them, you know.
English Translation
الكهربا ما في عنا بهالضيعة، كفر دلي تحتاني كهربا ما في.
We don't have electricity in this village, Kafardali Tahtani
has no electricity.
English Translation
نتمنى يجي كهربا، ما إجا كهربا.
We wish electricity would come, electricity didn't come.
English Translation
عم نسحب عالطاقة الشمسية، على هالخضار وعلى هال...
We are drawing water using solar energy, for these
vegetables and these...
English Translation
يعني ما في نهر بيمشي هون؟
So there's no river running here?
English Translation
لا، ما في نهر. كلها بيار مي، كلها بيار مي عم...
No, there is no river. It's all water wells, all water wells
are...
English Translation
شقد معدل الأمطار عندكم؟
What is the rainfall rate here?
English Translation
معدل الأمطار والله هالسنة كان شوي يعني نص بالنص.
The rainfall rate, well this year it was a little, like half
and half.
English Translation
بالمية 70 هيك بدك تقول.
70 percent, you could say.
English Translation
إي بس يعني معدل الأمطار كبير، مرتفع عنكم بالحالة العادية
بيجي مطر كويس؟
English Translation
Yes, but I mean the rainfall rate is high, higher than
usual, do you get good rain?
English Translation
إي إجانا التلج هالسنة، الحمد لله، تلج كان كثير، والمطر كمان
شوي صار.
English Translation
Yes, we got snow this year, thank God, there was a lot of
snow, and there was also a little rain.
English Translation
بس المي هلق البيار نقصوا.
But the water in the wells now has decreased.
English Translation
نقصوا.
Decreased.
English Translation
نقصوا، نعم.
Decreased, yes.
English Translation
طيب السنة، أهم موسم عنكم شو هو؟
Well this year, what is your most important season?
English Translation
يعني الموسم، الموسم هلق اليوم اللي شلناها...
You mean the harvest, the harvest today that we gathered...
English Translation
شلنا جلبان، شلنا عدس، شلنا حبة البركة.
We harvested vetch, we harvested lentils, we harvested black
seed.
English Translation
هي، هي موسم شلناها.
This, this is the harvest we gathered.
English Translation
موسم كويس إن شاء الله؟
A good harvest, God willing?
English Translation
والله الحمد لله، العالم استفادت شوي، عالم استفادت.
Well thank God, people benefited a bit, people benefited.
English Translation
حنطة وشعير؟
Wheat and barley?
English Translation
حنطة وشعير كمان، كمان حصدوه، كمان استفادوا عالم.
Wheat and barley too, they also harvested it, people also
benefited.
English Translation
بس بدنا، بدنا مي. يكون مي أحسن شي.
But we need, we need water. Having water would be the best
thing.
English Translation
المي هي ري بيشتغل وكل العالم بيشتغل وبيصير حركة وبيصير بركة.
With water, irrigation works, everyone works, and there's
movement, and there's a blessing.
English Translation
صحيح.
True.
English Translation
عمي قرب شوي لهون بس أسألك. الزيتون موسم السنة شلون كان؟
Uncle, come a little closer here, let me ask you. How was
the olive season this year?
English Translation
هالسنة الزيتون بالمية 40، 45، 50 يعني نص بالنص.
This year, the olives are at 40, 45, 50 percent, meaning
half and half.
English Translation
ليش؟
Why?
English Translation
فاضي. كل المنطقة هون حوالي عم ندور هذا هو، فاضي.
Empty. The whole area here around us, as we go around, this
is it, empty.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
احكي لي عالحيوانات، شو في عنكم حيوانات هون أهل الضيعة شو
بيربوا؟
English Translation
Tell me about the animals, what animals do you have here?
What do the people of the village raise?
English Translation
حيوانات الضيعة، كل واحد، مو كلهم، يعني في حوالي عشر بيوت كل
واحد عنده معزتين تلاتة، غنمة غنمتين هذا هو.
English Translation
The animals of the village, everyone, well not everyone, but
there are about ten houses, each one has two or three goats,
one or two sheep, that's it.
English Translation
ما عندكم قطعان؟
You don't have flocks?
English Translation
شلون؟
What?
English Translation
قطعان أغنام وماعز، ما عندكم؟
Flocks of sheep and goats, you don't have them?
English Translation
لا لا كتير ما عندهم، كل بيت متل ما عم بقلك شي حوالي عشر بيوت
متل هالأخ هذا عنده معزتين تلاتة يعني هيك.
English Translation
No, no, they don't have many, every house as I am telling
you, about ten houses like this brother, he has two or three
goats, like that.
English Translation
تاريخياً كانت الضيعة مشهورة بتربية الأغنام؟
Historically, was the village famous for raising sheep?
English Translation
كان، نعم، كان.
It was, yes, it was.
English Translation
في حوالي 2000 غنمة كان بالضيعة.
There were about 2,000 sheep in the village.
English Translation
كان في 2000 غنمة؟
There were 2,000 sheep?
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
English Translation
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health too.
English Translation
شكراً إلكون.
Thank you both.
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً. أهليين سلامات.
Welcome. Welcome, greetings.
English Translation
يا أهلاً وسهلاً، 100 سلامة. يا أهلاً وسهلاً. أهليين عمو.
Welcome, 100 welcomes. Welcome. Welcome uncle.
English Translation
على راسي.
Upon my head.
English Translation
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
English Translation
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, the mercy of God, and His blessings.
English Translation
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
English Translation
شلونك عمو؟
How are you, uncle?
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم.
Welcome to you.
English Translation
نتعرف عليك؟
Can you introduce yourself?
English Translation
محمد عمر عبدي.
Muhammad Omar Abdi.
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
English Translation
أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
Welcome to you.
English Translation
من هون من كفر دلي؟
From here, from Kafardali?
English Translation
من كفر دلي التحتاني.
From Kafardali Tahtani.
English Translation
يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
Welcome to you.
English Translation
أهلاً بك.
Welcome.
English Translation
احكي لي عن الخدمات بهالضيعة.
Tell me about the services in this village.
English Translation
أول شي في آبار، آبار ارتوازية هي من قبل كان من النظام.
First thing, there are wells, artesian wells that were
previously from the regime.
English Translation
نعم.
Yes.
English Translation
هي حفروها لتلات أربع ضيع.
They dug them for three or four villages.
English Translation
مشان شو المي يعني؟
What is the water for, I mean?
English Translation
إيوه، هي خدمات لكفر دلي التحتاني، كفر دلي الفوقاني، تل غازي،
والكبير.
English Translation
Yes, this is a service for Kafardali Tahtani, Kafardali
Fawqani, Tal Ghazi, and Al-Kabeer.
English Translation
تمام.
Okay.
English Translation
على أساس إنه في، في هنيك شو اسمه، في خزانين.
On the basis that there is, there is what do you call it,
there are two tanks.
English Translation
خزانين.
Two tanks.
English Translation
خزانين، بتل غازي واحد...
Two tanks, one in Tal Ghazi...
Ev dixwaze ya Kefedelê ya jorê û Keferdelê bixwe bi xwe
mezin e.
This is feeding the upper Keferdelê, and Keferdelê itself is
big.
Û ev mensebê li vir... Ji vir ve xezanek heye dikêşe
Keferdelê ya jorê û yê jêrê.
And this one is proportional here... From here, there's a
tank feeding upper Keferdelê and lower Keferdelê.
Berê me kar dikir... Gund bi ser xwe ve girêdayî bû.
Before, we used to work... The village used to rely on
itself.
Me cemiyet çêkir û me teawin çêkir, me mazot dikirî û
wilo... Me dixebitand.
We formed a cooperative and collaborated, we bought diesel,
and so on... We used to run it.
Niha êdî mazot biha bû û ava gund nayê vexwarin.
Now diesel has become expensive, and the village's water is
undrinkable.
Ava bîra sêsed û bîst metir e.
The well water is 320 meters deep.
Yanî niha hûn di qeyrana avê de ne?
So now you have a water crisis?
Ewe. Ji ber ku pêwîstiya gund pê heye...
Yes, because the village needs it...
Niha hûn avê ji ku tînin?
Where are you getting water now?
Em avê ji sihrîcan tînin.
We buy water from the tankers.
Sihrîc. Baş e û ava avdana erdê?
Tankers. Okay, and irrigation water for the lands?
Avdana erdan, di erdan de bîrên îrtîwazî û ne îrtîwazî hene.
For irrigation of the lands, there are artesian and non-
artesian wells in the lands.
Qenata avdana Meydankê jî nêzîkî we ye?
Is the Meydankê irrigation canal close to you as well?
Nêzîkî me ye. Berê me ji qenata Meydankê îstîfade dikir.
It's close to us. In the past, we used to benefit from
Meydankê's irrigation water.
Çawa?
How?
Me erd û wilo av dida.
We used to irrigate lands and so on...
Niha?
Currently?
Niha, îdare ne tiştek e.
Currently, the administration is doing nothing.
Em hewl didin, em hewl didin mesela ev gund, Keferdelê ya
jorê û Keferdelê ya jêrê... Ji ber ku erd yê mişterek e.
We are trying, we are trying for example this village, upper
Keferdelê, lower Keferdelê... Because the land is shared
between these villages.
Yanî niha hûn dixwazin ku erd û zeviyên we ji Meydankê bên
avdan.
So now you demand that your lands and fields be irrigated
from Meydankê.
Ewe. Qenata Bablîtê heye, ji vê qenatê re muherekeke qewî
lazim e, te fêm kir?
Yes. There is a canal at Bablît, this canal needs a strong
engine, you know?
Ku bidê serê çiyê, ji ber ku ji serê çiyê, ji vir de diçe.
To push it to the top of the mountain, because from the top
of the mountain, it goes from here.
Niha ez dibînim riyên we jî ne zîftkirî ne.
Now I see the roads in your village are not paved either.
Ji ber ku kes... Kes guh nade vê meselê.
Because no one... No one pays attention to this issue.
Nan çawa ye?
How is the bread?
Nan, tu xizmetê dizanî. Nan rojane tê.
The bread, you know the services. The bread comes daily.
Rabte bi çendî ye?
How much is a bundle?
Rabte bi 10 lîreyan e.
A bundle is 10 liras.
Kêşa wê çend e?
How much does it weigh?
Ez kêşa wê nizanim, 10 nan in.
I don't know its weight, 10 loaves.
Kehrebe heye?
Is there electricity?
Kehrebe, kehrebe nîne. Ev li ser taqê ye. Kehreba dewletê
nîne.
There's no electricity. Everyone relies on solar energy.
State electricity doesn't exist.
Xwedê eafiyetê bide te xalo.
May God give you health, uncle.
Xwedê eafiyetê bide te.
May God give you health.
Înşelleh dê mesûl dengê we bibihîzin û daxwazên we bi cî
bînin.
Hopefully, the officials will hear you and respond to your
demands.
Kerem ke. Piştî wê... Hûn... Destê me di destê we de ye.
Hûn... Em malbata we ne.
Welcome. After all... You guys... Hand in hand with you
guys. You guys... We are your family.
Em jî malbata we ne, înşelleh. Xwedê eafiyetê bide te.
We are your family too, God willing. May God give you
health.
Ya Rebî!
Oh God!
Selamun eleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Eleykum selam. Kerem bikin.
And upon you be peace. Welcome.
Esrbaş ji te re. Çi dikin? Çi vedixwin? Çi dixwin?
Good afternoon to you. What are you doing? What are you
drinking? What are you eating?
Em dadikevin ser kar, em dixebitin li vir di malên xwe de.
Elhemdulillah me medaris heye, zarokên me diçin medreseyê,
dixwînin.
We are coming down to work. We are working here in our
homes. Thank God, we have schools. Our children go to school
and study.
Her tişt li cem me baş e, em alîkariya hev dikin. Çi muşkele
li cem me tune.
Everything is fine for us. We help each other. We have no
problems at all.
Te her tişt ji min re got, tenê bihêle ez pirsekê ji te
bikim. Xwe bide naskirin.
You told me everything. Just let me ask you a question.
Introduce yourself.
Navê min Melek Mislim Mislim.
My name is Melek Muslim Muslim.
Bi xêr hatî. Tu ji Keferdelê Tehtanî yî?
Welcome. Are you from Keferdelê Tahtanî?
Ewe mêrê min ji Keferdelê Tehtanî ye.
Yes, my husband is from Keferdelê Tahtanî.
Çi karî dike?
What does he do?
Mêrê min wefat kir, weleh.
My husband passed away, by God.
Xwedê rehma xwe lê bike. Û tu çi karî dikî?
May God have mercy on him. And what do you do?
Ez di mal de dixebitim.
I work at home.
Zarokên te hene?
Do you have children?
Du keç û du lawên min hene.
I have two daughters and two sons.
Xwedê ji te re bihêle. Ev mala we ye eslî?
May God keep them. Is this your original house?
Ewe mala me ye.
Yes, this is our house.
Ji min re behsa rewşa jinan li vir bike. Ji min re bêje, ma
fêr dibin, dixwînin, dixebitin mîna mêran?
Tell me about the situation of women here. Tell me, do they
learn, study, work like men?
Ewe, dixebitin. Alîkariya mêrên xwe dikin di kar de. Diçin
ser kar.
Yes, they work. They help their men at work. They go to
work.
Hinekan di malên xwe de rûdinên, hinek diçin ser kar, ev e
halê dinyayê.
Some of them stay at home, some go to work. This is the
state of the world.
Lîbasên jinan li vir çi ye?
What are the women's clothes here?
Eadî, tebîeî.
Normal, natural.
Çawa tebîeî, ji min re bêje?
How natural, tell me?
Baş e.
It's good.
Tu niha çi li xwe dikî? Ev lîbasê jinan e?
What are you wearing now? Is this women's clothing?
Ez fîstan û vê li xwe dikim.
I'm wearing a dress and this...
Bila ez pirsekê ji te bikim. Xwarinên navdar li Keferdelê
Tehtanî çi ne?
Let me ask you a question. What are the distinctive foods in
Keferdelê Tahtanî?
Her tişt xweş e.
Everything is delicious here.
Ez bawer im her tişt xweş e, lê çend xwarinan ji min re
bihejmêre.
I'm sure everything is delicious, but count a few foods for
me.
Her tişt em dipêjin. Mehaşî em dipêjin, tu çi bixwazî em
dipêjin.
We cook everything. We cook stuffed vegetables (mahashi),
whatever you want, we cook.
Xwarina herî navdar ku tu hez dikî çi ye?
What is the most famous food you love?
Ez pirtir ji bamiyê û birincê hez dikim.
I like okra and rice the most.
Ez pir jê hez dikim.
Why?
I love it a lot.
Ev mewsima wê ye niha?
Is this its season now?
Ewe lekan.
Yes, it is.
Ya Xwedê canê te sax be. Zarokên te diçin medreseyê
dixwînin?
May you have good health. Are your children studying in
school?
Elhemudillah lekan, min 3 hene li medreseyê dixwînin.
Thank God, yes, I have three studying in school.
Çi ref e?
Which grade?
Ya min a mezin refa nehan e, û yek refa pêncan e, lawik jî
refa çaran e.
My eldest is in ninth grade, one is in fifth grade, and the
boy is in fourth grade.
Maşelleh. Xwedê ji te re bihêle û we kêfxweş bike.
Mashallah. May God protect them for you and make you happy.
Xwedê we saxlemiyê bide, bi xêr hatin.
May God keep you safe. Welcome.
Spas ji te re.
Thank you.
Efû, ehlen we sehlen.
You're welcome, welcome.
Dîroka naskirî li Keferdelê Tehtanî ne nivîskî ye, û tu
pirtûkên rastîn tunene ku bi riya wan em bikarin dîroka vî
gundî lêkolîn bikin.
The well-known history of Keferdelê Tahtanî is not
documented, and there are no real books through which we can
investigate the history of this village.
Lê tiştê ku tê zanîn û di nav rûspiyên gund de tê veguhestin
ku temenê gundê heyî ji 350 salî derbas dike.
But what is common knowledge and passed down among the
elders in the village is that the current village's age
exceeds 350 years.
Û ev dîroka hebûna malbatên kurd ên resen e di vî gundî de,
bi taybetî malbata Neccar, Al-Dado, û Al-Tawz.
And this is the history of the original Kurdish families in
this village, specifically the Neccar family, Al-Dado, and
Al-Tawz.
Berî wê jî dê ji me re behsa vê serdemê bike, Parêzer Sadiq
Neccar.
Before that, the lawyer Sadiq Neccar will tell us about this
period.
Yek ji kurên vî gundî ye û bi taybetî guh dide dîroka wê.
He is one of the sons of this village and is very interested
in its history.
Xwedê eafiyetê bide te, Mamoste Sadiq.
May God give you health, Mr. Sadiq.
Bi xêr hatî, em xêrhatina we dikin ji qenata we bi silametî.
Welcome, we welcome you from your channel in peace.
Berî ku ez ji te bipirsim, ez dixwazim pirsekê ji te bikim.
Niha diyar e ku gund dîrokî ye.
Before I ask you, I want to ask you a question. Now it is
clear that the village is deeply rooted.
Erê.
Yes.
Gelek diyar e ji avahiyên wê, ji geliyê Seylî yê ku ji
Keferdelê ya Jorê tê, ji avan, dêra ku li vir e...
It is very clear from its buildings, from the Seilî Valley
that comes from Keferdelê Fawqanî, from the waters, the
church here...
Lê ez dixwazim bizanim girîngiya cografî ya gund di
dirêjahiya dîrokê de çi ye?
But I want to know what the importance of the geographical
location of the village is throughout history?
Weke ku diyar dibe ji hebûna dêrê li vî gundî û di gundên
derdorê de tune, yanî xwedî girîngiyek dînî bû.
As it appears from the presence of the church in this
village, and there are none in the surrounding villages, it
means it had religious importance.
Hebûna dêrê nîşan dide ku gund xwedî girîngiyek dînî ya
mezin e. Yanî di nav 10 gundan de, li vir dêr tune.
The presence of the church indicates that the village had
great religious importance. It means among the ten villages,
there is no church here.
Bi aliyê dînî ve, ciyên dînî yên mesîhî yên herî nêzîk wek
dêr li ku ne?
Religiously speaking, where are the closest Christian
religious sites as churches?
Çiyayê Seman.
Mount Simeon.
Li cem te Kîmar heye. Ev gundên li ser çiyayê Seman. Di van
gundan de dêr hene.
You have Kimar. These villages above Mount Simeon. In these
villages, there are churches.
Çiqas e mesafeya wir?
How far is the distance there?
Ji vir nêzîkî 20 kîlometre, 25... 20, 25.
From here, about 20 kilometers, 25... 20 to 25.
Di çarçoveya 25 kîlometreyan de...
Within a radius of 25 kilometers...
Yanî em niha li pêşiya dêrê ne, li vir. Ev dêr e?
This means we are now in front of the church here. Is this
the church?
Ewe.
Yes.
Ji kîjan serdemê re vedigere?
To what era does it belong?
Cihê ku em lê dimeşin, ev dêr e. Wek ku bav û bapîrên me
digotin.
Where we are stepping, this is the church. As our father and
grandfather used to say.
Dêrek li vir hebû, ji du malan pêk dihat, û di navbera wan
de qentereke kevirî hebû.
There was a church here consisting of two houses, with a
stone arch between them.
Û derî ji başûr e, texmînen firehiya wî metre û nîvek e û
bilindahiya wî nêzî du metre û nîv, sê metreyan e.
The door is from the south, approximately one and a half
meters wide, and about two and a half to three meters high.
Bi çi hatibû nixumandin?
Roofed with what?
Bi daran nixumandî bû. Her du alî... her du mal bi daran
nixumandî bûn û li hev vekirî bûn.
Roofed with wood. Both sides... the two houses are roofed
with wood and open to each other.
Niha xuya ye ku şûnwarê dîwarekî heye.
Now it is clear that there are ruins of a wall.
Ewe, şûnwarê dîwarê paşîn heye. Her kevirek wek tu dibînî
dirêjiya wî metreyek e û bilindahiya wî jî nêzîkî metreyekê
ye.
Yes, there are ruins of the back wall. Every stone you see
is a meter long and about a meter high as well.
Lê ji kîjan serdemê re? Serdema Bîzansî?
But to what era? The Byzantine era?
Xuya ye ev girêdayî dêra şerqî ye.
It seems to belong to the Eastern Church.
Dêra şerqî?
The Eastern Church?
Ewe, bo Stenbol, Qostentîniye berê...
Yes, to Istanbul, Constantinople previously...
Û Entakiya.
And Antioch.
Û Entakiya helbet.
And Antioch, of course.
Paytexta rojhilatê dewleta Bîzansî. Baş e.
The eastern capital of the Byzantine state. Okay.
Bila ez niha derbasî qonaxa... qonaxa niha bibim, Keferdelê
Tehtanî ya niha.
Let me now move to the stage... the current stage of
Keferdelê Tahtanî.
Ji kengî ve rûniştvan li vir hene, temenê we çend e?
Yes.
How long have the residents been here? How old are you?
Min ji bavê xwe zanî, bavê min ji bavê xwe zanî û ew gişt
umî ne ji xeynî min.
I learned from my father, my father learned from his father,
and all of them are illiterate except for me.
Neh bapîr em nas dikin.
Nine grandfathers we know.
Neh bapîr li vir in.
Nine grandfathers here.
Erê. Sadiq, Mihemed Elî, Xelîl, Mihemed, Resûl û Mihemed.
Yes. Sadiq, Muhammad Ali, Khalil, Muhammad, Rasoul, and
Muhammad.
Û Resûlê ku hatî sekiniye, çimkî li vir xirabe hebûn nêzîkî
gund.
And there's also Rasoul who came and settled because there
were ruins here near the village.
Tê gotin ku ew li wir bû, paşê derbasî van xirabeyan bûye.
Xirabe hebûn...
It is said he was there and then moved to these ruins. There
were ruins...
Neh bapîr?
Nine grandfathers?
Neh bapîr.
Nine grandfathers.
Yanî nêzîkî çend salan?
Meaning almost how many years?
Nêzîkî sêsed û pêncî ber bi çarsedan ve. Ji ber ku li gorî
civakê heger her sî û pênc heta çil salî cîlek be, wan bi 9
caran lê bide.
About 350 to 400. Because socially, if every 35 to 40 years
is a generation, multiply them by 9.
Pirs ev e ku...
The question is...
Kes ji ku hatin, li ku bûn?
Where did people come from? Where were they?
Di vê navçeyê de bûn, lê li ser ava... li ser alif û
giyayê... Ji ber ku ew koçer bûn.
They were in this area, but depending on the water,
depending on the pastures. Because these were nomads.
Piranî koçer bûn. Çêlekên wan hebûn, û hespên wan hebûn...
hêstir, û pêzên wan hebûn, bizin.
Most of them were nomads. They had cows, and they had
horses... mules, and they had sheep and goats.
Li pey cihên avê û giyayê ji bo heywanan digerin.
They follow water sources and pastures for animals.
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Kî hat vir, ji min re malbatan bijmêre.
Who came here? List the families for me.
Malbat, xaneya me xaneyek e û muxtarê gund heye, nêzîkî 4
bapîr... Mala Neccar.
The families, we are one family, and there's the village
Mukhtar, approximately four grandfathers... the Neccar
family.
Ewe, mala Neccar.
Yes, the Neccar family.
Û Neccarê gund e û ji Cindirêsê ta vir, xeynî wî tu neccar
tunebû.
And the village's carpenter, and from Jindires to here,
there was no carpenter other than him.
Paşnavê xwe ji pîşeya xwe girtiye.
He took his surname from his profession.
Ji pîşeya wî.
From his profession.
Erê.
Yes.
Niha neccarek di Gewrîkan de heye. Ew ji cem apê min fêr bû.
Apê min, yanî berî 100 salî.
Now there's a carpenter in Gewrika. He learned from my
uncle. My uncle, meaning about 100 years ago.
Yek li Efrînê jî neccar e, ew jî fêr bûye. Ev çend gund,
Cwêq... ev neccarên navçeyê di bin destê wî de fêr dibûn.
Dihatin cem wî dibûn şagirt.
There's a carpenter also in Efrîn, he also learned from him.
These are several villages, Cwêq... these carpenters in the
area learned under his hands. They would come to him to
become apprentices.
Îcar mala Neccar.
So, the Neccar family.
Erê, mala Neccar xaneyek e.
Yes, the Neccar family is one family.
Û ev apê me ne, mala Resûlo fexzek ji mala Neccar e.
And these are our uncles, the family of Rasoul, a branch of
the Neccar family.
Neccar û Xelîl Resûl ev bira bûn... malbatek e.
Neccar and Khalil Rasoul, these were brothers... one family.
Paşê mala Hec Henan heye, ev mal a wan e.
Then there's the house of Hajj Hannan, this house is theirs.
Mala Tatoz heye, ew mal ji bo Elî Axa bû ji Keferdelê
Fawqanî, feodal bûn, ew mal a wan bû.
There's the house of Tatoz, that house was for Ali Agha from
Keferdelê Fawqanî. They were feudal lords.
Ew mal ya wan bû ji cotkarên xwe re. Çima, ji ber ku cotkar
ji Keferdelê Fawqanî bê ser erdê xwe li vir seetekê
dikişîne, êvarê jî seetek.
That house belonged to them, for their farmers. Why? Because
instead of the farmer coming from Keferdelê Fawqanî to his
lands here, it takes him an hour, and in the evening, an
hour...
Dibe du seet di rê de. Wan jî jê re mal ava kirin û
rûniştandin.
It would be two hours on the road. So they built a house for
him and settled him here.
Cotkar rûniştandin.
They settled farmers.
Lihêla no ne, mala Brahîm Omer Sefûnê, ev malê wana kanê? Ee
mehelê vê mala ev kanê wana ye.
To here, the house of Ibrahim Omer Safouneh, this was their
house and the location of this house was theirs.
Û fî betê hanîka wara hê betî kaman wana ye.
And there are two houses behind this house that are also
theirs.
Ee fî bet Hesen Efendî bi ma'ena...helaq yimkin...kanê şifna
hanîka bavê Kenco
There is the house of Hasan Afandi, meaning... now maybe...
we saw there Abu Kanjo
Ebdî, Mihemed Ebdî, evana Hesen Efendî dibên wan re ismê wan
Hesen Efendî, efendî ye ye'nî...
Abdi, Muhammad Abdi, these are Hasan Afandi, they call them
Hasan Afandi, Afandi meaning...
Ev hemû malbatên Kurd in?
Are these all Kurdish families?
Hemû malbatên Kurd in. Ma fî enna xeyr 'aîlê Erebîyê, ecet
min şî min teqrîben tmanîn, tis'în sinê, Xelîl Erebo û exûh
la Îsmaîl Erebo. Îsmaîl Erebo bis ismû bi Cindirês halîyen
They are all Kurdish families. We don't have any other than
an Arab family, that came about 80, 90 years ago, Khalil
Arabo and his brother Ismail Arabo. Ismail Arabo, his name
is currently in Jindires
xenî û endo qadî û me qadî, me'rûf ye'nî Îsmaîl Erebo. Xelîl
Erebo eca xerbiyê gund, sar endo weledê Ehmed û Arif. Arif
tiwefa min şî sinê û nis sinê, emro wisil la mîyê û eşir
sanewat.
rich and has a judge and what not, well-known meaning Ismail
Arabo. Khalil Arabo came to the west of the village, he had
two sons, Ahmed and Arif. Arif passed away about a year and
a half ago, his age reached 110 years.
Wulid hon.
He was born here.
Baş e.
Okay.
Xwezî ez tenê tiştekî bizanibim, an jî em bibêjin, li gorî
zanyariyên min, ev zeviyên gund hemû aîdî sê malbatan in. Bi
eslê xwe mala Omer Sefûnê, ev axa ne. Û ji Hesen Efendî, ji
Xazî Dêpe. Û Elî Axa ji Keferdelê Fokhanî. Ev ê ji derve ne.
Let me just know one thing, or let's say it, according to my
information, these village lands all belong to three
families. Originally the house of Omar Safouneh, these are
the Aghas. And from Hasan Afandi, from Ghazi Tepe. And Ali
Agha from Kafr Dila Fokani. These are from outside.
Bi nisbê me, em xwediyê milkên bav û kalane. Ye'nî bi eslê
xwe em bi edaletî xwediyê milkan e, ye'nî bi edaletî.
For us, we are the owners of the ancestral properties.
Meaning basically we own properties quite fairly, meaning
fairly.
Û milk û erden we li gundên cûda hene?
And you have properties and lands in different villages?
Belê.
Yes.
Pirsa min a duyemîn, bi awayekî dîrokî jî li vir zêdetir ji
yek masereya tirî hebû, ji ber ku herêm bi rezan dewlemend
bû. Û paşê masereyên zeytûnê tê de hatin çêkirin.
My second question, historically too there was more than one
grape press here, because the region was rich in vineyards.
And later olive presses were built in it.
Bi nisbe bo rezên tirî. Aliyê qiblî ji gund, ta xerbiyê
gund, ta şemalê gund, ev hemû rez bûn.
Regarding the vineyards. The southern side of the village,
to the west of the village, to the north of the village,
these were all vineyards.
E'maro, em... ez û te... ye'nî emarê wê demê... di nav de
ciz'ê zeytûnê hebûn wisa ciz'a ... wate... wê demê berî sed
salî ev ciz'ê şecerê.
Its age, we... you and I... meaning the age of that time...
among them there were olive trunks like trunks... meaning...
at that time a hundred years ago this tree trunk.
Ma'sera, tu dibînî li wir ev avahî, avahiyek piçûk li wir
xuya ye, ew qurmê zeytûnê ye. Ev der ma'sera me ye. Ev erd a
me ye.
The press, you see there this building, a small building is
visible there, that olive trunk. This is our press. This
land is ours.
Ye'nî li vir masereyên tirî hebûn, ez dixwazim zanibim.
Meaning there were grape presses here, I want to know.
Ma'sera li vir... ma'seran li wir... ma'sere li wir... ez
şeş ma'seran dizanim, ew li derdora gund bûn.
Press here... presses there... press there... I know six
presses, they were around the village.
Tirî. Ma'serên tirî ku tirî dijiqivandin û dimsê tirî
çêdikirin.
Grape. Grape presses that pressed grapes and made grape
molasses.
Belê.
Yes.
Ew makîne bûn an... ?
Were they machines or... ?
Na bi destan.
No, manual.
Bi destan? Li ser heywanan?
Manual? On animals?
Na welleh. Na. Curnekî mezin hebû, tiştekî çar metro, sê
metro bi sê metro ye, cizmeyan ango naylon bi lingên xwe li
xwe dikin û bi piyan li tirî dixin. Curnek li jêr e, ava wê
dadikeve... ew şerab e bo wê dadikeve, di nav qazanê de an
jî tiştekî de datînin. Li ser agir dipêjin û paşê didin ber
tavê.
No by God. No. There was a large trough, something four
meters, three meters by three meters, they put on boots or
nylon on their feet and step on the grapes. A trough is
below, its juice comes down... that drink it goes down to
it, they put it in a cauldron or something. They cook it on
the fire and then put it in the sun.
Masereya zeytûnê, ma li vir masereyeke me heye?
Olive press, do we have a press here?
Ev masereya me ye, ev di 61'an de dîroka wê li ser hatiye
nivîsandin, di sala 61'an de.
This is our press, this in 61 its date is written on it, in
the year 61.
Ev masere, mamoste?
This press, sir?
Belê.
Yes.
Ev gelî. Bêguman ev gelî ji sê geliyan kom dibe, Geliyê
Mezin... Em li vir bisekinin... bila li me xuya bibe... em
li vir bisekinin. Were vir, mamoste.
This valley. Of course this valley comes together from three
valleys, the Great Valley... Let's stop here... let it be
visible to us... let's stop here. Come here, sir.
Ev gelî. Ev nû hatiye avakirin di hewşa gelî de, di nava
gelî de. Çima? Ji ber ku baran mîna berê pir nabare.
This valley. This has been newly built in the courtyard of
the valley, in the middle of the valley. Why? Because it
doesn't rain as much as before.
Niha 61'ê tu dibêjî çi hebû?
Now 61 you are saying what was there?
Em masereyê ava dikin di 61'an de. Li ser dîrok heye.
We build the press in 61. There is a date on it.
Di vî geliyî de av diherikî heta meha Tebaxê, kengî
rawestiya?
In this valley water flowed until the month of August, when
did it stop?
Meha Tebaxê carinan heta Îlonê, ev nêzîkî ji sala 65'an ve û
paşê ji 70'ê ve rojan... ye'nî eger baran pir be û berf
bibare, ev salên ku berf lê bariye, dihat... me li wir
bendavek danî li dawiya avahiyê, me bendavek danî. Çuwal bi
xîzê... me bendavek çêkir heta vir. Masî tê de bûn, ji Şêx
Ebdurehman dihatin, em bi navê Efrînê diçûn me masî
digirtin.
The month of August sometimes until September, this about
from the year 65 and then from 70 days... meaning if it
rains a lot and snows, these years that it snowed, it
came... we put a dam there at the end of the building, we
put a dam. Bags with sand... we made a dam up to here. There
were fish in it, they came from Sheikh Abdulrahman, we went
in the name of Afrin we caught fish.
Av bû, bendavek avê... We ew zeviyên li jêr li vir avdan û
ev zeviya me ji vir ji cem mala me. Ew aliyê hundir, me hemû
avdan.
It was water, a water dam... You watered those lands below
here and this land of ours from here from our house. That
inside part, we watered all of it.
Pirsek din mamoste ma, av kengê sekinî ?
Another question sir, when did the water stop?
Di heftêyan de av nema.
In the 70s, the water stopped.
Heger sala xêrê be, şiliyê me gelek e, berf tê, dimîne heta
meha pêncan. Pêncan... şeşan... pêncan... şeşan... carnan
digiha, carnan negihaştî, yek kîlometre bakurî gund e.
If it is a good year, we have a lot of rain, snow comes, it
stays until the fifth month. Fifth... sixth... fifth...
sixth... sometimes it reached, sometimes it didn't reach, it
is one kilometer north of the village.
Pirsa dawî. Xortan ev masera, bi xwe çêkirine?
Last question. The young men built this press themselves?
Pirsek min heye: Ev gund navdar e ku emrek dirêj a mêr û
jinan heye, çîrok çî ye?
I have a question: This village is famous for having a long
lifespan for men and women, what is the story?
Erê... pir dijîn... bawer im girêdayî xwarinê ye, ku ev
mirov bi xwe diçînin, bê ku dermanan û tiştekî bi kar bînin.
Yes... they live long... I believe it depends on the food,
that these people plant themselves, without using chemicals
or anything.
Ji xwe tirî... mewîj, hejîr, hejîrên hişk, dims. Wek mînak,
mêşên hingiv hene, deh malan hebûn, û her malekê nêzî bîst
kûwar mêşên hingiv hebûn.
Grapes themselves... raisins, figs, dried figs, molasses.
For example, there are bees, ten families had them, and each
family had about twenty hives of bees.
Nedihat firotin, dîsa jî rûn... rûnê erebî... rûnê kurdî,
rûnê erebî.
It wasn't sold, still butter... Arab butter... Kurdish
butter, Arab butter.
Rûnê kurdî nizam, fêm nakim, rûn e, rûnê pez, rûnê mîhan,
penêr û şîr. Gavan, bi taybetî gavanek pez heye, bi kurdî jê
re dibêjin... gavan.
I don't know Kurdish butter, I don't understand, it is
butter, sheep butter, sheep butter, cheese and milk. Herder,
specifically there is a sheep herder, in Kurdish they call
him... herder.
"Ga-van"... gavan e... "Ga", wate dewar, ga... anku gavan
nêrevanên dewaran. Û pez... ji şivanê wî re "şivan"
dibêjin... Şivan ji bo pez, gavan ji bo dewaran...
"Ga-van"... it is a cowherd... "Ga", meaning cattle, cow...
so cowherd is a cattle watcher. And sheep... its shepherd is
called "shivan"... Shivan for sheep, gavan for cattle...
Ev nîşana jiyana dirêj e. Temenê herî navîn li vir çi ye?
This is the sign of a long life. What is the most average
age here?
Bi giştî nêzî 70 e. Lê hinek mirov hene, mînak di 125 saliya
xwe de, par yek çû rehmetê, Arif Xelîl Erebo nêzî 110 salî
bû.
Generally it is about 70. But there are some people, for
example at 125 years old, last year one passed away, Arif
Khalil Arabo was about 110 years old.
Dotmam Xelîl li gundê Enderiyê bû, nêzî 115 salî bû...
Kalikê min 125, Kalikê apê min 116 salî bû. Rêveberê
dibistanê jî heta 116 salan jiya, Xwedê rehma xwe lê bike,
ew jî 116 salî bû... Hêvîdar im ku ez jî bibim 150...
Cousin Khalil was in the village of Andariyah, she was about
115 years old... My grandfather 125, My uncle's grandfather
was 116 years old. The school principal also lived up to 116
years, may God have mercy on him, he was also 116 years
old... I hope I become 150 too...
Hinek mirov dema hevnasîna me kir, hewl dan hinek salan ji
temenê xwe kêm bikin... Lê min nizanibû ka ew ê çend salan
bijîn...
Some people when we got to know them, tried to subtract some
years from their age... But I didn't know how many years
they would live...
Ez texmîn dikim ku ew ê bigihin 100 salan... Pîroz be!
Jiyanek xweş ji bo te dixwazim. Mamoste, spas, jiyanek
bextewar.
I guess they will reach 100 years... Congratulations!
Wishing you a good life. Teacher, thank you, a happy life.
Selamun Aleykûm
Peace be upon you
Aleykûm Selam
And upon you peace
Merheba ya xaltî
Hello aunty
Ehlen
Welcome
Çawa ye?
How are you?
Hemd ji Xwedê re
Praise be to God
Xwe bide naskirin
Introduce yourself
Tu min nas nakî?
You don't know me?
Na, bila temaşevan te nas bikin
No, let the viewers know you
Em bi nan û xwarin û tiştek tune
We have no bread and food and nothing
Tu ji ku derê yî?
Where are you from?
Ez ji Qibtanê me
I am from Qibtan
Koçber bûye vir?
Migrated here?
Erê koçberê vir im
Yes I am a migrant here
Tu çend sal in li vir î?
How many years have you been here?
Ev sê sal in
It's been three years
Sê sal û... Hevserê te?
Three years and... Your husband?
Ev sê sal û heşt meh in
It's been three years and eight months
Sê... sê sal. Mêrê te li ku ye?
Three... three years. Where is your husband?
Mêrê min, wallah li Tirkiyeyê ye. Ez jêqetiyayî me... ji
mêrê xwe veqetiyam.
My husband, by God is in Turkey. I am separated... I
separated from my husband.
Zarokên te li ku ne?
Where are your children?
Bavê zarokan, wallah nizanim çûye ku derê.
The father of the children, by God I don't know where he
went.
Çûye ba Mixtêr? Mixtêr çi divê?
Went to the Mukhtar? What does the Mukhtar want?
Hûn li vir çawa dijîn?
How do you live here?
Wallah ne av... ne tiştek, ne tiştek tê me.
By God no water... no nothing, nothing comes to us.
Tu dibêjî ne av û ne tiştek, tu fêm nakî.
You say no water and no nothing, you don't understand.
Em avê bi pereyan dikirin... Ne alîkarî ne tiştek, em têra
xwe westiyayî ne, wallah.
We buy water with money... No help no nothing, we are tired
enough, by God.
Hûn ji xelkên gundin, an xelkên gund di rewşek xirab de ne?
Are you from the people of the village, or are the people of
the village in a bad situation?
Wallah xerabtir e... Tiştek... Tiştek ji alîkariyê nîne...
Piçekî alîkarî bikin... Zilam mezin e, temenê wî 60 sal e û
dixebite.
By God it's worse... Nothing... There is no help... Help a
little... The man is old, his age is 60 years and he works.
Çend kes? Hûn çend kes di malbatê de ne?
How many people? How many people are you in the family?
Em heşt kes in, ez û keçên xwe bi tenê ne.
We are eight people, me and my daughters are alone.
Çend kes in?
How many people are there?
Şeş kes, şeş kes in.
Six people, six people.
Çend odeyan we hene?
How many rooms do you have?
Ev yek e û li pişt wê yeka din jî, wê demê min kon danî.
Niha ez ê dîsa konekî din lêkim. Ne konê min heye ne
tiştek...
This is one and behind it another one, at that time I set up
a tent. Now I will set up another tent again. I have neither
a tent nor anything...
Ji min re bibêjin çawa dijîn, mesrefa jiyanê çawa peyda
dikin?
Tell me how you live, how do you afford the cost of living?
Mêrê min diçe kar, li Efrînê li bazarê kar dike. Yekî tirkî
alîkarî dike, ew xwarin û nan tîne û ewqas...
My husband goes to work, works in Afrin in the market. A
Turkish person helps, he brings food and bread and that's
it...
Çi kar dike?
What work does he do?
Di bazara fêkî û sebzeyan de... bi sebzeyan re kar dike.
In the fruit and vegetable market... he works with
vegetables.
Wek firoşkar li wir dixebite?
Works there as a seller?
Barkirin, pîvandin û pakêtkirina li ser barkirinê.
Loading, weighing and packaging on loading.
...يعني فعلاً القرية إلها ميزة خاصة.
...Indeed, the village has a special feature.
الميزة الخاصة هي هدوءها؟
The special feature is its calmness?
نعم قرية هادئة، وفي كل بيت، مزرعة صغيرة.
Yes, it's a calm village, and in every house, there is a
small farm.
بيزرع بهالمزرعة بستان صغير، بيستفيدوا من هالبستان.
They plant a small orchard in this farm, and they benefit
from this orchard.
بحيث انه ما يشتروا شي من برا.
So that they don't have to buy anything from outside.
طيب أنا كأنه عم لاحظ كأنه في ساحة القرية هون، قلب القرية
القديمة؟
Well, it seems to me like this is the village square here,
the heart of the old village?
نعم هون كان ساحة للقرية قديماً.
Yes, this used to be the village square in the past.
كان محل أوسع من هيك، كان ما في عمار لهالدرجة.
It was a much wider place, there weren't this many
buildings.
كان محل واسع وكان كل قرية اللي بدو يسوي عرس بيعمله بنص
الضيعة.
It was a wide place, and anyone in the village who wanted to
hold a wedding would do it in the middle of the village.
بهالساحة؟
In this square?
نعم بهالساحة، ساحة الضيعة بيسموها.
Yes, in this square, they call it the village square.
أمام الجامع؟
In front of the mosque?
نعم أمام الجامع، والجامع عنا قديم كمان.
Yes, in front of the mosque, and our mosque is also old.
طيب هاد البيت؟ هي البيوت من أقدم البيوت، شو عمر هالبيوت هي؟
لمين هدول البيوت؟
Well, this house? These houses are among the oldest houses,
how old are these houses? Whose houses are these?
هدول البيوت، بيت نجار، وبيت عمو كمان، بيت رسوله.
These houses, the Najar family's house, and his uncle's
house too, the Rasoulo family.
هنن ولاد عمام، يعني أقدم بيت في الضيعة تقريباً.
They are cousins, meaning it's almost the oldest house in
the village.
هي خانة رقم واحد؟
Is this house number one?
هون بيت تبع خليل عربو.
Here is Khalil Arabo's house.
تقريباً بشي، شي مية سنة اجوا عنا عالضيعة.
They came to our village approximately a hundred years ago.
طيب خليني اسألك هلق عن التعليم في القرية شلون؟ انت من شباب.
Well, let me ask you now about education in the village, how
is it? You are from the youth.
نعم التعليم أحسن من أول بكثير، الحمد لله.
Yes, education is much better than before, thank God.
يعني كان أول في مدرسة ابتدائية.
I mean, at first there was a primary school.
والمدرسة بعدين حولوها من ثلاث سنين، في عنا للصف السادس،
بيتخرجوا بيبطلوا المدرسة، لأنه مافي إعدادي.
And the school, three years ago they changed it, we have up
to the sixth grade, they graduate and drop out of school,
because there is no middle school.
ما فيهم يروحوا عفرين، نحن حاولنا بجهدنا انه نجيب، وبالتنسيق
كمان.
They couldn't go to Afrin, we tried our best to bring, and
through coordination as well.
نجيب الكادر التربوي، انه نورجيهم عالمعلوم، انه في عنا تلت
أربع ضيع عالطريق.
To bring the educational staff, to show them clearly, that
we have three or four villages along the road.
اللي بالسادس يتخرجوا، يجوا السابع والثامن والتاسع يدرسوا هون
إعدادي.
Those who graduate from the sixth grade, can come to study
seventh, eighth, and ninth grades here in middle school.
قام بفضل الله يعني انه تم فتح المدرسة إعدادي.
So, thanks to God, the middle school was opened.
صار عندكم إعدادي، وين بيكملوا الثانوي؟
You have a middle school now, where do they complete high
school?
بعفرين.
In Afrin.
بعفرين. طيب شو قد نسبة التعليم هون، المتعلمين؟
In Afrin. Well, what is the education rate here, the
educated people?
نسبة المتعلمين تقريباً 150 لـ 180 طالب.
The number of educated people is roughly 150 to 180 male
students.
وطالبة؟
And female students?
وطالبة طبعاً، نص بالنص تقريباً.
And female students of course, about half and half.
في تسرب شي؟
Is there any dropout?
بسيط قليل.
Very little.
بسيط. الكبار بالسن شلون تعليمهم هون؟
Little. How is the education of the elderly here?
نسبة التعليم الحمد لله كويس، كويسة نعم.
The education rate is good, thank God, it's good, yes.
في نسبة ثقافة عندهم، يعني في عنا الحمد لله دكاترة كمان وفي
مهندسين.
They have a good level of culture, meaning we have doctors,
thank God, and engineers.
وفي يعني خريجين جامعيين، وفي يعني صيادلة كمان، ان شاء الله
الحمد لله.
And we have university graduates, and pharmacists too, God
willing, thank God.
المرأة؟ تعليم المرأة شلون؟
Women? How is women's education?
بالمدرسة نص بنص عم بيدرسوا، في بنات وفي شباب كمان.
In school, they study half and half, there are girls and
there are boys too.
يعني مافي تمييز بالعلم انه هاد جنس ذكر هاد أنثوي، نعم.
Meaning there is no discrimination in education that this is
a male gender and this is female, yes.
بيتعلموا وبيدرسوا وبيتوظفوا؟
They learn, study, and get employed?
بيتوظفوا طبعا، اللي أخد الشهادة راح عفرين كمل دراسته.
They get employed of course, whoever gets their degree goes
to Afrin to complete their studies.
بيتوظف بعفرين أو بيصير معلم أو بيتخرج بشي دائرة بيتوظف.
They get employed in Afrin, or become a teacher, or graduate
and get employed in some department.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يارب أهلا وسهلا أستاذ يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health too, welcome sir, may God give you
health.
الفلكلور الغنائي والتراث في قرية كفر دلي تحتاني، هو جزء من
الفلكلور والتراث في منطقة عفرين بالعموم.
The musical folklore and heritage in the village of Kafr
Dalli Tahtani is a part of the folklore and heritage of the
Afrin region in general.
اللي أساتذته هنن المطربين والفنانين الكبار، جميل هورو ومحمد
علي تجو.
Whose masters are the great singers and artists, Jamil Horo
and Muhammad Ali Tajo.
وإضافة إلى أعداد كبيرة من الفنانين اللي حاولوا يتقفوا أثر
المطربين الكبار.
In addition to a large number of artists who tried to follow
in the footsteps of the great singers.
لنحكي شوي عن الفلكلور الغنائي في القرية رح يكون معنا الأخ
سربست من القرية.
To talk a little about the musical folklore in the village,
we will have Brother Sarbest from the village with us.
وأيضا الأستاذ صادق نجار اللي هو ماشاء الله يعني ذاكرة القرية
وربما ذاكرة المنطقة.
And also Mr. Sadiq Najar, who is, mashallah, the memory of
the village and perhaps the memory of the region.
وأيضا الأستاذ عبد الرحمن. نحن الآن مستضافين في بيته وتحت
عريشة العنب.
And also Mr. Abdul Rahman. We are now hosted in his house
and under the grape arbor.
وضيفونا التين، وحسسونا كأنه نحن اليوم في مصيف سوري وسوريا
الحبيبة اللي منحبها.
They offered us figs, and made us feel like we are in a
Syrian summer resort today, in our beloved Syria that we
love.
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
الله يعافيكم، أخي سربست احكيلي بداية عن النمط الغنائي اللي
هون اللي دارج في المنطقة في كفردلي بالتحديد؟
May God give you health. Brother Sarbest, tell me first
about the singing style that is popular here in the region,
in Kafr Dalli specifically?
طبعاً، هو النمط يعني، عندك محمد علي تجو وباڤێ صلاح، نعم.
Of course, the style is, you have Muhammad Ali Tajo and Bavê
Selah, yes.
باڤێ صلاح كمان كان فنان كبير.
Bavê Selah was also a great artist.
وجميل هورو، وباقي فنانين، في فنانين منهم قديمين، منهم جداد،
منهم تجددوا، يعني هدول هنن.
And Jamil Horo, and other artists, there are old artists
among them, new ones, and those who renewed themselves,
these are the ones.
طيب هدول كانوا يغنوا نفس اللون ولا كل واحد إلو لون خاص؟
Well, did they sing the same style or did each one have a
special style?
لا كل واحد إلو نمطه، كل واحد إلو أغنيته الخاصة ونمطه الخاص.
No, each one has their own style, each one has their own
special song and special style.
وحسب الظروف، في منهم ظروف اللي بيعدي عليها مثلا.
And depending on the circumstances, there are those who go
through certain circumstances, for example.
بيمر فيها هالظروف بيحللها بيسويها أغنية مثلا، من كلمة لأغنية
كذا بيطالعوها.
They go through these circumstances, analyze them, and turn
them into a song, for example, from a word to a song like
that, they create it.
تمام، الأكثر انتشاراً وتأثراً هون مين، انتو بمين تأثرتوا
أكتر؟ بجميل هورو ولا محمد علي تجو ولا مين؟
Alright, who is the most widespread and influential here?
Who were you influenced by the most? Jamil Horo, Muhammad
Ali Tajo, or who?
جميل هورو عندك أول شي، وباڤێ صلاح، طبعاً ثالثاً محمد علي
تجو.
First you have Jamil Horo, then Bavê Selah, and of course
thirdly Muhammad Ali Tajo.
طيب سمعنا شي من كل واحد قبل ما نسمع الأستاذ صادق شو رح يحكي.
Well, let us hear something from each one before we hear
what Mr. Sadiq is going to say.
De vî da û wê da, ez çol û çiya ketim e.
From here and there, I fell into deserts and mountains.
Ji hêvar da, ez bej û gundan derketim e.
Since evening, I left the lands and villages.
Bi çol û çiya de dikim, riya min asê ye.
I wander in deserts and mountains, my path is blocked.
Herçî meşaleqê min in, kevir û zinar in.
Whatever my obstacles are, they are rocks and boulders.
Erê ta zivistanê, em hêl me rasanin.
Yes, until winter, our strength has reached its limit.
Hema min dî ev ejdehayê, serê xwe rakir, nav kevir û zinar
nar e.
Suddenly I saw this dragon, raised its head, roaring among
the rocks and boulders.
Hezar salî bûye, çiyayê bejî da mezin bûye.
It is a thousand years old, grown in the wild mountains.
Zimanê xwe yê neçe, dilîskîne.
Flicking its deadly tongue.
Yekî min ji hayata dinê xelas ke.
Let someone save me from the life of this world.
Cihê we çaxê, me axîna xwe kir, Xwedanê erd û ezmanan.
At that moment, we sighed to the Lord of earth and heavens.
Milê xwe li ber kirin.
We submitted ourselves.
Mihstirê xwe barandin, Xwedanê erd û ezmanan.
We shed our tears to the Lord of earth and heavens.
Li vir ejdeha fîqandin qêre, serê xwe kir nav kevir û
zinara.
Here the dragon hissed and screamed, and hid its head among
the rocks and boulders.
Me zanî tivana hezar salî, hatî mane.
We knew the storm of a thousand years has come to stay.
Milê xwe da ye çol û çiya, orta biziravî ro şefaqê da der.
I turned to the deserts and mountains, amidst fear, the dawn
broke.
Dinê rûm bû, bihar kir rengîn e, gul û gupikê dar û tiyiyê
vebûn e.
The world lit up, spring became colorful, the flowers and
buds of trees and bushes opened.
Helkerek bû, min xwe da girê zinarek ker û nîştim piştê xwe
da zinêr.
It was a steep climb, I reached a deaf boulder and leaned my
back against the rock.
Ax, mihstirê xwe paqij kirin, keserê xwe kişandin.
Ah, I wiped my tears, drew my sighs.
Pozê rûyê min dî xelq û xunavê sibê ye.
I saw the face of creation and the morning dew.
Şelûr û bilbil û teyr dengê li hev dinin e.
The birds, nightingales, and eagles mix their sounds.
Me sekir navê çîk û şelûr nîn e, dengê yekî zêde hezîn e tê.
We noticed it's not the sound of common birds, the sound of
one is coming very sad.
Ewa ser darê ke, me dît bilbilî hezîn hezîn dixwîne.
That one on the tree, we saw a nightingale singing sadly.
هاد شعر ولا غناء؟
Is this poetry or singing?
شعر.
Poetry.
Ez kê bang kim wa bilbilo, geliyê xwa li ber bikim.
Who should I call, oh nightingale, to pour my heart to?
Erê ta hêl û qeweta min nemaye, bi çend rengî mi da ez
nizanim, xwîn xirab e, sor e, çengê min tê.
Yes, my strength and power are gone, I don't know in how
many colors I poured, the blood is bad, red, my arm is
bleeding.
Ez kê bang bikim bilbilo û geliyê xwa li ber bikim, rêk û
lox me hinda kirine.
Who should I call, nightingale, and pour my heart to, we
have lost the paths and roads.
Hey lo bilbilo... de bese, de bese, te oza dilê min xitand
lo bilbilo, lo bilbilo...
Oh nightingale... enough, enough, you have torn the core of
my heart, oh nightingale, oh nightingale...
Dera heft ro, heft şev bîn e, ez lê digerim, lo bilbilo, ma
te yara min nedî, ma te nedî...
It has been seven days, seven nights, I have been searching
for her, oh nightingale, haven't you seen my beloved,
haven't you seen her...
Çiyayê Rûm dîm, bêgav çol û çiya ketim e, sê neqla min mirin
bi çavê serê xwe dît kesa te nebîn e, mi dî mi dî lo
bilbilo.
I saw the Roman mountains, helpless I fell into deserts and
mountains, three times I saw death with my own eyes, may no
one see what I saw, oh nightingale.
سلامتك.
God keep you safe.
Hey lo bilbilo, zarta cî wisa ke min dosta xwa hinda kirî,
te teyrek xur e erd û ezmanan digerî ooy...
Oh nightingale, I cry out loud like this because I lost my
beloved, you are a free bird roaming the earth and heavens
ooy...
Dê li ortê bigerandin e, min e şev û roj, çol û çiya... hêl
û qeweta min nema, lo bilbiloy... te yara min nedî, qet nedî
yoy...
Wandering in the middle, day and night, deserts and
mountains... my strength and power are gone, oh
nightingale... haven't you seen my beloved, haven't you seen
her at all yoy...
De car kê, bilbilê malşewitî, bilbilê malşewitî, keserê xwe
kişandin, got de here zarderdê min ne bese, min law yara te
nediye yoy...
Then once, the poor nightingale whose house is burned, the
poor nightingale, drew its sighs, said go away, aren't my
own pains enough, boy I haven't seen your beloved yoy...
سلم تمك، خلينا يعني أفهم أنا شو حكيت، المشاهدين يعرفوا شو
حكيت بالعربي، وننتقل للأستاذ صادق. تفضل شو حكيت بالعربي؟
Bless your mouth, let me understand what you said, so the
viewers know what you said in Arabic, and we move to Mr.
Sadiq. Please tell us what you said in Arabic?
الأغنية هي، عبارة عن بلبل. بيغني عالبلبل واحد مثلا، طالع من
بيته، من ضيعته، يعني مهاجر.
This song is about a nightingale. Someone is singing to a
nightingale, for example, someone who left his house, his
village, meaning an immigrant.
نعم.
Yes.
مثلا هلق متلنا ومثل اخواننا العرب كذا ومهاجرين من بيوتهم
خيو.
For example, like us now, and like our Arab brothers and so
on, who migrated from their homes, brother.
بيطلع مافي مطرح بيطلع بيسكن بالجبل.
He goes out, there is no place, he goes out and lives in the
mountain.
بهالجبل بيلاقي مثلا ثعبان، هالثعبان بيجي مثلا انه هالثعبان
متل شي انه بدو ياكله لساته بالجبل، والثعبان بدو ياكله.
In this mountain, he finds a snake, for example, this snake
comes like it wants to eat him while he's still in the
mountain, and the snake wants to eat him.
نعم.
Yes.
بيدعي لرب العالمين، بيقول يا ربي انه تبعد عني هالثعبان هاد.
He prays to the Lord of the worlds, he says, "Oh my Lord,
keep this snake away from me."
فبيقوم رب العالمين بيبعد عنه، بيطلع عالشمس.
So the Lord of the worlds keeps it away from him, he goes
out to the sun.
بيطلع عالشمس، عند ما بيطلع عالشمس بيسمع صوت مثلا العصافير
كذا.
He goes out to the sun, when he goes out to the sun, he
hears the sound of birds, for example, and so on.
من بين كل هالصوت بيجي صوت بلبل.
From among all these sounds comes the sound of a
nightingale.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
And peace be upon you and the mercy of God.
بيجي صوت بلبل، عم هو كمان بيغني عالبلبل.
The sound of a nightingale comes, and he also sings to the
nightingale.
عم بيقول يا بلبل...
He says, "Oh nightingale..."
أنا طلعت ع هالجبل إنت شو جايبك لهون؟
I went up the mountain and said, "What brings you here?"
البلبل شو عم بيجاوبه؟ عم بيقول له... يعني أنا دردي ما
بيكفيني لسا إنت كمان جاي تحط همك فوق همي؟
What did the nightingale answer him? He said... "Isn't my
pain enough, that you come to put your sorrow on top of
mine?"
يعني لسا درد البلبل فوق همه.
I mean, the nightingale's pain is on top of his sorrow.
نعم، نعم، نعم، شي جميل.
Yes, yes, yes. It's beautiful.
أستاذ صادق... يعني الملاحظ إنو الغناء الكردي في المنطقة هو
غناء حزين... شو السبب؟
Mr. Sadiq... it is noticeable that the Kurdish singing in
the region is sad singing... What's the reason?
يعني صار له أربع خمس دقايق وهو عم بي... إشاراته كله وعلامات
وجهه كلها فيها حزن، فيها شجن.
He has been singing for four or five minutes and all his
gestures, and all his facial expressions have sorrow and
grief.
شو السبب إنه مرتبط الغناء الكردي في المنطقة بالشجن والحزن؟
What's the reason that the Kurdish singing in the region is
associated with sorrow and grief?
نتيجة ظروف طبيعية، كوارث، الآلام والآمال اللي عم بيتأملها،
وما عم بتصير هالآمال اللي عم يتمناها وعم يترجاها.
It's the result of natural conditions, disasters, pains and
the hopes that one wishes for, and these hopes that he
wishes and begs for do not happen.
وبضل بقيان بهالهموم وبهالكوابيس... يعني متراكمة...
And he remains with these sorrows and nightmares... I mean,
they are accumulated...
يعني متراكمة... وبالتالي صار كل التعبير عن الذات هو غناء
حزين.
Accumulated... so expressing oneself entirely became sad
singing.
نعم... تاريخ مليء بالمآسي، تاريخ مليء بالهجرات، تاريخ مليء
بالانكسارات... يعني من الواقع.
Yes... a history full of tragedies, a history full of
migrations, a history full of defeats... I mean, from
reality.
أنا بعرف إنه صوتك جميل إنت، من الأصوات الجميلة والقادرة.
I know your voice is beautiful. It's one of the beautiful
and capable voices.
كان، كان.
It was, it was.
بدنا نختم... بدنا نختم الآن الحلقة معك، خلينا نسمع شي من
وجدانك إنت يا أستاذ صادق نجار.
We want to conclude the episode with you now. Let us hear
something from your soul, Mr. Sadiq Najjar.
الأغنية الكردية مثل ما تفضلت أولاً... يعني... نوع من
الحزن...
The Kurdish song, as you mentioned first... I mean... it's a
type of sorrow.
مثل إذا واحد انجرح، بعدين بيجيها... يجي واحد يحط سبيرتو شوي،
شوية كحول، أو مرهم، بيبرد...
Like if someone gets injured, then comes... someone puts
some alcohol, a little alcohol or ointment, it cools down.
فالأغنية الكردية بتبدا بالحزن، بتنتهي بالفرح وبالمراخص وما
شابه.
So the Kurdish song starts with sorrow, and ends with joy
and dancing.
نعم. نسمع منك.
Yes, let's hear it.
قالوا لعبد التمور تاع ما أجا... صار زلمي وما أجا... شفت
هداك...
They told Abdul-Tamur, "Come," he didn't come. He became a
man and didn't come. I saw that guy...
واحد خربان وما بعرف... مع ذلك صار بني آدم وما أجا... شو
أساويله... تفضل.
A ruined person and I don't know what, yet he became a human
being and didn't come. What should I do to him? Go ahead.
Ay şaman, keleş şaman, lewend a min lê lê lê lê lê lê lê lê
lê lê lê lê. Ay şaman.
Oh shaman, beautiful shaman, my young one, le le le le le le
le le le le le le. Oh shaman.
Ay şê, zalim dînê, tu li hember a, fa dila ya min li hember
a,
Oh sheikh, cruel religion, you are opposite me, the sorrow
of my heart is opposite me.
Delala min, tu li hember a, min li hember a.
My beautiful one, you are opposite me, opposite me.
Ma qey ne bîra te wa, çîqe çîrka cencera li ser bênder a?
Don't you remember the squeaking of the threshing sleds on
the threshing floors?
Hawa hawa, ewî lo, keçikê tu dîtî bi kincê çir a.
Oh, oh, my first one, I saw the girl again in torn clothes.
Zalimê lê esmerê, çavreşê çavbikulê, esmera min tu yî lê lê
lê lê lê wey.
Cruel one, oh brunette, dark-eyed one, sorrowful-eyed one,
you are my brunette, le le le le le wey.
Ay şê, lewendê!
Oh sheikh, young one!
Ma bila dinya bima ji kê re, nema ji kê re.
Even if the world were to remain, it didn't remain for
anyone.
Siltan Silêman, dîsa dinya nema ji kê re.
Sultan Suleiman, again the world didn't remain for anyone.
Hin û cin û pêr e, gişt di bin emrî wî da bûn, dîsa dinya
nema ji kê re.
Jinn, spirits, and fairies, all were under his command,
again the world didn't remain for anyone.
Ay şaman lê lê lê lê wey.
Oh shaman, le le le le wey.
Dîsa bila dinya bima, nema ji kê re.
Again, even if the world were to remain, it didn't remain
for anyone.
Dîsa dinya nema ji Pêxemberê Ummetê, Mihemed (S.A.W), dîsa
dinya nema ji kê re.
Again, the world didn't remain for the Prophet of the Ummah,
Muhammad (PBUH), again the world didn't remain for anyone.
Ay şaman lê lê lê lê.
Oh shaman, le le le le.
Esmera min, çavreşa min tu yî lê lê lê lê lê.
My brunette, my dark-eyed one is you, le le le le le.
Ay şê, keleşê, lewendê, çavreşê, çavbikulê.
Oh sheikh, beautiful one, young one, dark-eyed one,
sorrowful-eyed one.
Dîsa bila dinya bima, nema ji kê re.
Again, even if the world were to remain, it didn't remain
for anyone.
Ne dima ji dîktatoran re, ji zaliman re.
It didn't remain for dictators, for tyrants.
Ji Fîr'ewnan re, dîsa dinya nema ji kê re.
For Pharaohs, again the world didn't remain for anyone.
Keko bi sêf dîsa dinya nema ji kê re wey.
Brother, by the sword, again the world didn't remain for
anyone, wey.
Na ji rindan re, na ji xiraban re, na ji dîktatoran re, ji
zaliman re.
Neither for the good, nor for the bad, nor for dictators,
for tyrants.
Û na ji yekî mîna Mela Mistefa Barzanî, yekî wekî Qazî
Mihemed, yekî wekî Pêxember (S.A.W), dîsa dinya nema ji kê
re.
And neither for someone like Mullah Mustafa Barzani, someone
like Qazi Muhammad, someone like the Prophet (PBUH), again
the world didn't remain for anyone.
Ta we dila, ta we dila, ta we dila xûnî ya dila.
To these hearts, to these hearts, to these bloody hearts.
Bi kerasa, kerasa hesreta dila, dila dila dila dila wey.
With shirts, shirts of the longing of hearts, hearts hearts
hearts hearts wey.
Ay şaman lê lê lê lê lê wey.
Oh shaman, le le le le le wey.
Go berde, berde, berde, we Hesen destê min berde.
Said let go, let go, let go, oh Hasan let go of my hand.
Go berde, berde, berde, ew Wistêf destê min berde.
Said let go, let go, let go, oh Wistef let go of my hand.
Evînî bi kul û derd e lo, evînî bi kul û derd e.
Love is with pain and sorrow, love is with pain and sorrow.
Ay delal, ay delal, ay delal, ay delal, ay delal, ay delal,
ay delal, ay delal!
Oh beautiful, oh beautiful, oh beautiful, oh beautiful, oh
beautiful, oh beautiful, oh beautiful, oh beautiful!
Ta emrê min î, bes e lo.
You are my life, it's enough.
Heh, ta we, heh ta we, saheta te xweş be, saheta te xweş be.
Oh, to you, oh to you, bless your voice, bless your voice.
Saheta te xweş be, ellah ya'tîk el-afiye, sahetxweş,
sahetxweş.
Bless your voice, may God give you health, bless your voice,
bless your voice.
Ev a Eşê ye, Eşê, ev a Eşê...
This is Eysha's, Eysha, this is Eysha's...
مين عيشة؟ عيشة، هي محبوبة؟
Who is Eysha? Eysha, is she a beloved?
هادا زلمة... أحداثها صارت عملياً بعين العرب، شرق عين العرب،
حلنج، ما حلنج، بديك الديار.
This is a man... its events happened practically in Ayn al-
Arab, east of Ayn al-Arab, Halanj, or whatever, in those
areas.
هادا واحد، متل سربست، كبر بالعمر... وصار بقلبه حسرة، بده
يتجوز.
This is someone, like Serbest, who grew old... and had a
longing in his heart, he wanted to get married.
هي ما بدي، وهاي ما بدي، بنت بيك بدي، بنت آغا بدي، بنت شيخ
عشيرة بدي، بنت كويسة وحلوة...
"I don't want this one, and I don't want that one. I want a
Bey's daughter, I want an Agha's daughter, I want a tribal
Sheikh's daughter, a good and beautiful girl..."
ما بعرف إيش... المهم.
I don't know what... Anyway.
هادا طلع شال راسه وركب ع حصانه ويالله.
He set out, raised his head, got on his horse, and off he
went.
وصل ع ديرة عيشة.
He arrived at Eysha's village.
شاف في نبع، وفي شي عشرين تلاتين بنت ع النبع.
He saw a spring, and there were about twenty or thirty girls
at the spring.
طبعاً أولي كان في هالسطل يحطوه ع الراس ويمشوا.
Of course, in the past, they used to put this bucket on
their heads and walk.
اتطلع في وحدة تختلف عن جميع البنات.
He looked at one who was different from all the girls.
جمالاً وطولاً وكذا وما كذا...
In beauty, height, and so on...
هادا ساق حصانه لعند هاي.
He drove his horse towards her.
"سلام عليكم." "وعليكم السلام."
"Peace be upon you." "And upon you be peace."
"مرحبا يا بنت العالم، بنت الناس." ما ردت.
"Hello, daughter of good people, daughter of respected
folks." She didn't answer.
قال، "سلمنا لله، سلمت عليكي، ما بتردي؟ بدي كاسة مي، أنا
عطشان. ضيف، مسافر."
He said, "We greeted for God's sake, I greeted you, won't
you answer? I want a cup of water, I'm thirsty. A guest, a
traveler."
قالت، "اطلب من غيري."
She said, "Ask someone else."
المهم والحاصل، بروح بيلحقها لبيتها. هادا بيتها.
Anyway, in short, he goes and follows her to her house. This
is her house.
بروح لعند الختيار، لعند بيت المختار، بيسأل خيو، "هالبيت
هالابنت لمين؟"
He goes to the old man, to the Mukhtar's house, and asks,
"Brother, whose house and daughter is this?"
قال: "لفلان."
He said: "To so-and-so."
بينا بيرجع ع بيته. بعدين بيبعت ناس لهنيك وبده عيشة، عيشة،
وعيشة وعيشة.
Meanwhile, he goes back to his house. Then he sends people
there, and he wants Eysha, Eysha, and Eysha and Eysha.
المهم بالزور أخدها. أخدها ومن أخدها، جهزوا ويبدوا هدول
أغنياء وهداك غني، جهزوا، ما في كفاية.
Anyway, he took her by force. He took her, and once he did,
they prepared, and it seems these people were rich and that
guy was rich, they prepared, there's no limit.
أغنية طويلة يعني، سبع تمان ساعات بتطول.
It's a long song, I mean, it lasts for seven or eight hours.
ما شاء الله، الله يعطيك العافية أستاذنا.
Mashallah, may God give you health, our master.
وصلوا كل هالأغراض هدول ع بيتهم.
They arrived with all these belongings at their house.
ليلة الدخلة، زلمة صار يمزح مع بعض، من هون لهون...
On the wedding night, the man started joking around, from
here to there...
هاي كل مالها ارخت، ارخت ارخت...
She kept getting more and more limp, limp, limp...
ربع ساعة، نص ساعة، قال بلكي عروسة عم تستحي.
A quarter of an hour, half an hour, he said maybe the bride
is feeling shy.
آخر شي اتطلع شاف ما فيها، شاف ما فيها روحا.
Finally, he looked and saw there was nothing in her, he saw
there was no soul in her.
يعني ماتت، روحا طلعت...
I mean, she died, her soul departed...
فلذلك صارت حزينة.
That's why it became sad.
نعم، نعم. الله يرحمها.
Yes, yes. May God have mercy on her.
عيشا أغي ديو...
Eysha of the Agha...
الله يعطيك العافية أستاذنا. بس خلصنا، خلصنا...
May God give you health, our master. But we are done, we are
done...
مجال الفن، مجال الفن، إذا تسأل أي واحد متلاً إيش مفتاح
الأغاني؟
The field of art, the field of art, if you ask anyone for
example, what is the key to songs?
بيقول لك أغنية عيشة.
He will tell you the song of Eysha.
Kiliya Eşê, yanî kiliya hemû kelaman e.
The key of Eysha, meaning it is the key to all words.
عروس الأغاني... مفتاح الأغاني.
The bride of songs... the key to songs.
بدي أشكرك أستاذ صادق، بدي أشكرك بنهاية هالحلقة.
I want to thank you, Mr. Sadiq, I want to thank you at the
end of this episode.
شكراً ممنون، وأشكر الأخ سربست، والأستاذ عبد الرحمن،
Thank you, I am grateful, and I thank brother Serbest, and
Mr. Abdulrahman,
ع استضافتكم إلنا في قرية كفر دلي تحتاني.
for hosting us in the village of Kafr Dalli Tahtani.
وختمتوه أيضاً بمفتاح الغناء الكردي عيشة أو عيشانة، أو الحسن
أفندي،
And you also concluded it with the key of Kurdish singing,
Eysha or Eyshana, or Hasan Efendi,
هدول... بالمفتاح وبالقفل... حياكم الله.
these... with the key and the lock... may God greet you.
أعزائي المشاهدين، انتهت هذه الحلقة التي قدمناها لكم من قرية
كفر دلي تحتاني،
My dear viewers, this episode which we presented to you from
the village of Kafr Dalli Tahtani has ended,
التابعة لمركز منطقة إعزاز...
affiliated with the center of Azaz district...
عفرين!
Afrin!
شو قلت ليش؟
Why, what did I say?
إعزاز.
Azaz.
يلا ماشي، عفرين إعزاز، ما بتأثر.
Alright then, Afrin, Azaz, it doesn't matter.
أعزائي المشاهدين، انتهت هذه الحلقة التي قدمناها لكم من قرية
كفر دلي تحتاني،
My dear viewers, this episode which we presented to you from
the village of Kafr Dalli Tahtani has ended,
التابعة لمركز منطقة عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي.
affiliated with the center of Afrin district in the northern
countryside of Aleppo.
سنكون معكم في الأسبوع القادم، في جولة جديدة من قرية أخرى
سورية حبيبة.
We will be with you next week, on a new tour from another
beloved Syrian village.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته. حياكم الله.
Peace be upon you, and the mercy of God and His blessings.
May God greet you.