Demê we baş be temaşevanên me yên hêja, bi xelekeke nû, ji
bernameya Gundê Me Welat.
Good day to our esteemed viewers, with a new episode of the
program Our Village is a Country.
Ez Rûliyan Hecî Ehmed me û îro dîsa li gel we me.
I am Ruliyan Haci Ehmed and I am with you again today.
Di vê xelekê de em ê mijarekê bêjin hinekî cuda ye, ji ber
ku zeytûn hatin, payîz jî hat û her weha baran jî vê ra hat.
In this episode we will talk about a topic that is a bit
different, because the olives have come, autumn has come,
and rain has also come along with it.
Em ê berê xwe bidin gundê Feqîra, deşta Cûmê ye, bi ser
navçeya Cindirêsê ve ye.
We will head to the village of Feqira, it is in the Cume
plain, belonging to the Cindires district.
Em ê niha bi hev re derbasî cem cotkaran bibin, kesên ku li
derve kar dikin ji ber mewsima zeytûnan. Bi me re bimînin û
li me temaşe bikin.
We will now go together to the farmers, the people who work
outside because of the olive season. Stay with us and watch
us.
Temaşevanên me yên hêja, naha xwediyê erd bi me re ye, bi
xwe cotkar e.
Our esteemed viewers, now the landowner is with us, he is a
farmer himself.
Li vê derê niha zeytûnan jê dikin. Em ê ji wî bipirsin, ka
rewşa zeytûnan çawa ye di mewsima zeytûnan ya vê salê.
They are picking olives here now. We will ask him how the
condition of the olives is in this year's olive season.
Merheba xalo.
Hello uncle.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser çavan, tu bi selametî hatî.
Welcome, you are welcome, you have come in safety.
Destpêkê em tenas bibin...
First, let's get to know each other...
Ez Nebî Minla Eynat im. Li vî gundî rûdinim, gundê Feqîra
me.
I am Nebi Minla Eynat. I live in this village, I am from
Feqira village.
Belê. Ser seran û ser çavan.
Yes. You are very welcome.
Serê we û çavê we sax bin, Xwedê we biparêze.
May your head and eyes be healthy, may God protect you.
Wek em dibînin û em di nav mewsima zeytûnan de ne, mewsim
hat.
As we can see and we are in the olive season, the season has
arrived.
Em dixwazin tu ji me re hinekî behsa mewsima zeytûnan ya
îsal bikî.
We want you to tell us a little about this year's olive
season.
Bi Xwedê bi şeklê am, gişt gund û ev herêm hemî, mewsim kok
tine ye yanî.
By God, in general, the whole village and this whole region,
the season is completely gone, I mean.
Ev sala bi hemdê Xwedê ev sala xwe ye. Gelek çewal jê dihat,
ev sal çewalek jê nayê yanî.
This year, thanks to God, it is what it is. Many sacks used
to come from it, this year not even one sack comes from it.
Berê av hebu, ava Qenetê hebu, me pê av dida.
Before there was water, there was canal water, we watered
with it.
Naha dar di eziyetê de ne, dîsan jî baran jî tinene.
Now the trees are suffering, and again there is no rain.
Sala çû hinekî baran hebu, mewsim hebu, zeyt jî erzan bu.
Last year there was some rain, there was a harvest, and oil
was cheap.
Em bibêjin, beriya vê çend salan, çiqas çewal jê dihat û
naha çiqas çewal jê tê?
Let's say, a few years before this, how many sacks came from
it and now how many sacks come from it?
Berê meselen, sed dar... Hema sed dar e.
Before, for example, a hundred trees... Let's just say a
hundred trees.
Dikir şêst çewalî, şêst û pênc çewal jê dihat.
It used to make sixty sacks, sixty-five sacks would come
from it.
Bi xwe çiqas dar in naha?
How many trees are there now?
Sed dar in.
There are a hundred trees.
Sed dar in...
A hundred trees...
Sed dar e, darên me jî rind in û me xizmet kiriye.
It's a hundred trees, our trees are also good and we served
them.
Me sala çû dabûne elefdaran, hîsal jî wekî baran kêm bû
tiştek jê nehat.
Last year we gave them to the grazers, this year too, as
there was little rain, nothing came from it.
Naha gundî di du çewalan re nayên, rinde yanî.
Now the villagers don't even get two sacks, it's fine, I
mean.
Em kî werin sedemê zanibin, çima?
If we want to know the reason, why?
Çima? Ya ewil baran tine.
Why? First of all, there is no rain.
Baran tine bi şeklê am.
There is no rain in general.
Û maddî îmkaniyet jî tine ye ku tu xizmetê bikî.
And financially, there is no possibility for you to serve
it.
Meselen semadê, dermanê kêzikan li darê xî.
For example, to use fertilizer, to spray insecticide on the
trees.
Gerek herî kêm tu salê du caran semadê lê xî.
You must use fertilizer at least twice a year.
Semada çelê lê xî, semada biharê lê xî, heta bişele.
Use the winter fertilizer, use the spring fertilizer, until
it blossoms.
Û avê jî heta bigre yanî.
And it also needs to get water, I mean.
Lê belê îmkaniyet tineye, yanî ev cotkarî ye, werê xizmeta
îdareyê kêm e.
But there is no possibility, I mean, this is farming, the
management of service is poor.
Naha tenê ev erdê we ye, ev mewsima we ye, ev parçeyê we ye,
li xêncî wê jî erdên we hene?
Now, is this your only land, is this your harvest, is this
your piece of land, or do you have other lands besides this?
Na erd giş weha ne, bi şeklê am giş weha ye. Îsal di cî de
neman.
No, all the lands are like this, in general, it's all like
this. This year they yielded nothing.
Berê hebu, sala çû hebu, zeyt erzan bu. Zeyt tenekeyek pêncî
dolar bu.
Before there was, last year there was, oil was cheap. A tin
of oil was fifty dollars.
Me bi sebeba wê firot, me mezaxtiyê xwe jê dernexist.
We sold it for that reason, we couldn't cover our expenses
from it.
Mezaxtî jê derneket, meaş derneket.
The expenses weren't covered, the income didn't come out.
Dema em dibêjin me'sere, çiqas tenekeyek... yanî em bêjin
bandora xwe li ser tenekeya zeytê kiriye.
When we say olive press, how much does a tin... I mean let's
say it has its impact on the tin of oil.
Meselen beriya çend salan, ha qas tenekeyên zeytê dihat...
Niha îsal kêm bûye, zêde bûye...
For example, a few years ago, this many tins of oil came...
Now this year it has decreased, has it increased...
Wella teqrîben... teqrîben berî şeş sal, heft sal... Çewalek
tenekeyek nîvek dihat.
By God, approximately... approximately six years, seven
years ago... One and a half tins used to come out of a sack.
Du teneke kêm dihat... vî çaxî... bu heft sal çewalek,
tenekeyek tê.
A little less than two tins used to come... at this time...
it's been seven years that one tin comes out of a sack.
Jî çima? Em zû beraf dikin.
Why is that? We harvest early.
Berê me hê dema yekê mehê beraf dikir... şûn de me beraf
dikir.
Before, we used to harvest in the first month... we
harvested later.
Naha ji meha heyştan em beraf dikin.
Now we harvest from the eighth month.
Zeytûn hê negihiştiye, em beraf dikin, dibên meqbesê... zeyt
jê naye.
The olives haven't ripened yet, we harvest them, they go to
the press... no oil comes out of them.
Çima hûn zû dikin sedemê bizanibin xêr e?
Why do you do it early, what is the reason?
Sedem em ditirsin em zû beraf dikin, em dibên meqbesa..
The reason is we are afraid, so we harvest early, we say the
press...
Me'dî ziyan e?
Is it a material loss?
Me'dî ziyan e...
It is a material loss...
Ebu yanî.
It happens, I mean.
Em werin hinekî behsa me'seran bikin li cem we.
Let's talk a little bit about the olive presses here.
Yanî wekî berê ye... yê... meselen bibêjin... ger me'sere
diçe yê pare dan, ger nîv bi nîv e, na pare nîne çiqasî
didin... dû wefîne yan na wefîne barê...
I mean, is it like before... the... for example let's say...
if the press goes, they pay money, if it's half and half, no
there is no money, how much do they give... is it profitable
or not profitable...
Na, nisbeya me'serê diwefîne ji me re.
No, the ratio of the press is very profitable for us.
Lê nisbeya prîtê jî wer e, ew jî ne wefîne.
But the ratio of the pulp is also like that, that is not
profitable.
Me'sere sedî... sedî heftan dibin.
The press takes seven... seven percent.
Sedî heftan e.
It's seven percent.
Sedî heftan e. Û gişt sal jî weha nîzamek e... ew nayê
şununê me'serê yanî.
It's seven percent. And every year there's a different
system... that doesn't fit the situation of the press, I
mean.
Yanî we dest pê kiriye?
So you have started?
Me dest pê kir, em tenê yanî... Em roj tenê.
We started, we are the only ones, I mean... We are just for
a day.
Berê me mehekê beraf dikir, naha roj tenêye, îro xelas be
yanî.
Before we used to harvest for a month, now it's just for a
day, it finishes today, I mean.
Naha weka ku tu dibînî, me li çend darî nerî, gişt zeytûn
hişk bûn.
Now as you can see, we looked at a few trees, the olives
were all dry.
Zeytûnên hûrik hûrik di nav de bûn.
There were very small olives in them.
Zeytûn hişk bûn... hişk bûn weha...
The olives were dry... dry like this...
Naha sêk hişk... gelek e di vî wextî de.
Now three parts are dry... there are a lot at this time.
Zeytûn gişt li dar de hişk dibin yanî. Av tineye, tine.
The olives dry up completely on the tree, I mean. There is
no water, none.
Ji hişkiyê ye.
From dryness.
It's from dryness.
Baran kêm bû...
Rain was scarce...
Av jî dehat... zêde jî dehat... naha tişt jê nehatî yanî.
Water used to come too... a lot used to come too... now
nothing came of it, I mean.
Kok hişk bû, dar hişk bû.
The roots dried up, the trees dried up.
Û hewa... li gundê Feqîra bi giştî em kanin bibêjin... wusa
ye?
And the situation... in Feqira village in general we can
say... is it like this?
Erê, bi şeklê am giş ev gund waha ye niha.
Yes, in general, this whole village is like this now.
Her naha, berê te bîst karker dibir nav zeytûnan, naha waşik
tenê ye.
Now, before you used to take twenty workers into the olives,
now there are only kids.
Xelas kirin gundiyan, xelas kir.
The villagers have finished, they have finished.
Em werin hinekî qala amalan bikin, kesên ku di vî erdî de
kar dikin.
Let's talk a little bit about the workers, the people who
work on this land.
Zeytûnan jê dikin. Hewa kirê wekî berê ye... lê erzan e, lê
buha ye?
Who pick the olives. Are the wages like before... or is it
cheap, or is it expensive?
Na wekî berê ye...
No, it's like before...
Bandoriya xwe li ser we tineye? Zirarê nake?
Doesn't it have an impact on you? Doesn't it cause a loss?
Na na na... na li ser emalan na. Emal na.
No, no, no... not on the workers. The workers do not.
Û nêrîna we di pêşerojê de, em bibêjin, misteqbel de.
And your view for the future, let's say, in the future.
Hûn tiştekî... bikin... em bêjin xizmeta vê zeytûna bikin.
Will you do something... let's say to serve these olives.
Temenê te hişk be, av tine be hişk be.
I mean if it doesn't rain again, will the olives dry up?
May your age be dry, if there is no water, it will be dry.
Berê ava Qenetê hebû, ava Qenetê dahat.
Before there was canal water, the canal water came.
Vî darê saqî, Henîfî heqê Qenetê avê wê da. Bû Henîfî...
This tree was watered, Hanifi paid for the canal water for
it. It was Hanifi...
Bajar de rê, berê me av da nav, me baxan da şûlanan.
The city closed the road, before we watered it, we gave it
to the orchards.
Dar di şixulîn... Înca jî da... Naha înca jî kok e tine.
The trees were working... Then it yielded... Now the root is
completely gone.
Yanî em dikarin bibêjin çareserî tine, xêcî baranê?
So we can say there is no solution, except for rain?
Xêcî baranê na, ji zeytûnan re ev e... Û semad bi rûşinîn,
em vî bikin... ev e.
No, except for rain, this is it for the olives... And we
sprinkle fertilizer, we do this... this is it.
Spasiya te dikim xalo, saeta te xweş.
I thank you, uncle, have a good time.
Ehlen we sehlen... ser çavan... bi xêr hatin... silamet bin.
Silamet, ser çavan.
Welcome... you are welcome... welcome... stay safe. Stay
safe, you are very welcome.
Merheba xaltîka min.
Hello my aunt.
Ehlen we sehlen bi te...
Welcome to you...
Em nas bibin... navê te bi xêr.
Let's get to know each other... your name, please.
Ez dayîka Îsmaîl im, Feqîra me.
I am Ismail's mother, I am from Feqira.
Tu bi xwe ji gundê Feqîra yî?
Are you yourself from the village of Feqira?
Erê... Bû pêncî sal ez li Feqîra me... Umrê min mezin.
Yes... It has been fifty years that I am in Feqira... I am
old.
Belê. Em dixwazin ji me re... te naha berê me hat te got
karêkî min heye.
Yes. We want you to tell us... now before we came you said I
have some work.
Min got çiye... te got pez e, dew e. Tiştekî ji me re behsa
vê karê xwe bike.
I said what is it... you said it's sheep, it's buttermilk.
Tell us a little about your work.
Pez... em xwedî dikin... pez diçêrînin... sibe heta êvarî.
Sheep... we keep them... we graze the sheep... from morning
till evening.
Êvarê jî, bu pênc şeş sal weha em şev ne diçêrîn.
And in the evening, for five or six years like this we
haven't grazed them at night.
Şev û ro em li çolê bun.
Night and day we were in the desert.
Porê min, ez derê me giş ber tîna rojê û sermê me xwarî ye.
My hair, I was out in all the heat of the sun and the cold
we endured.
Û naha jî em berîkê xwedî dikine...
And now we are raising sheep...
Û tu çend sal e vî karî dikî?
And how many years have you been doing this work?
Bû çel sal... Çel sal e ez vî senetî dikim.
It's been forty years... It's been forty years that I've
been doing this profession.
Tu hez ji vî karî dikî?
Do you like this work?
Erê...
Yes...
Çel sal e, hê bavkalê me da, Xwedê miriyên te jî
bibexşîne...
It's been forty years, since our ancestors, may God also
forgive your dead...
Ez pê mijûl dibim...
I keep busy with it...
Yanî naha tenê em bibêjin karê te ye, li gund jî xelkên we
vî karê dikin?
So is it only, let's say your work, do other people in the
village also do this work?
Berê dikin, naha gund xelkê we tenê ye... Xelkê we tenê ye.
Before they used to, now the village is only your people...
It is only your people.
Pênc şeş dewarên cîranê me hene, bû weş e.
There are five or six cattle of our neighbor, that's enough.
Çiqas dewarên te hene naha...
How many cattle do you have now...
Wekî sê dewarên min in.
I have about three cattle.
Tê... heftê dewar naha sê dewar mane.
You used to... seventy cattle now three cattle are left.
Gî dimirin û diheribîn em nikanin bi heqê wan...
They all die and get sick, we can't afford them...
Kîloyê kofikê gihiştiye pênc waraqan.
A kilo of bran has reached five liras.
Û kîloya cehî gihişte heft waraqan, deh waraqan, şeş
waraqan.
And a kilo of barley has reached seven liras, ten liras, six
liras.
Tiştek nemaye... kûr nemaye.
Nothing is left... no profit is left.
Belê.
Yes.
Û naha em şivanan kî bigirin, jinikên me nikanin xizmetê
bikin.
And now if we hire shepherds, our women cannot serve them.
Ne em gauriya xwe zêde kin em qeymê şivanekî bibin bidin wî
heywanî.
Neither can we increase our herd, nor can we afford a
shepherd to give to those animals.
Şeref bû çar mehan de rida...
Honor was in four months...
Ê xaltî, zirar e xuya ye, çima we naha firotin, Xwedê we...
çiye?
So aunt, it seems it's a loss, why did you sell them now,
God... what is it?
Gur ketiye nav keriyê me... Em çibikin?
Wolves attacked our flock... What should we do?
Xelas... de em naha heta... wê kêm bikin. Heta têlik...
That's it... now let's until... reduce them. Until the
calf...
Heta em dimirin. Bafkalê me mir, em ketin wê şûnê em jî
dimirin.
Until we die. Our ancestor died, we took their place, we are
dying too.
Ê kesekî bigire tenê ye. Ê kesekî bigire tenê ye.
If someone takes it, they are alone. If someone takes it,
they are alone.
Belê... niha we şîr yek di derê derdixin difroşin de...
Yes... now you take the milk out to one place and sell it...
Şîr tenê ye. Buharê eyan e. Xêrî dimîne têna şîr...
There is only milk. It is clear in the spring. Besides that,
only milk is left...
Ême rûn û şîr, mast e... sê meh e. Zêde tin e...
We have butter and milk, yogurt... for three months. Not
more...
Kîlo çend e rebî? Bîst, pêncî... sed waraq e. Ew zerar e...
Ê çawa em halê min e?
How much is a kilo my Lord? Twenty, fifty... a hundred
liras. That is a loss... So how is my situation?
Em werin xêcî mesela pez. Li vê derê cam em dibînin erd
hene, zeytûn hene...
Let's put aside the issue of sheep. We see here there are
lands, there are olives...
Tişkî ser çandiniyê de nakin? Xelkê gundê we çi karî dikî
xêcî pez?
Don't you do anything regarding agriculture? What work do
the people of your village do besides sheep?
Xêcî zeytûnan kar û kî nakin. Daran dihejon û vedidin û şox
e.
Besides olives, they don't do any work. They shake the trees
and gather them and that's it.
Û diçinin. Naha wextî ye, îsal zeytûna zerar e.
And they harvest them. Now is the time, this year olives are
a loss.
Em çûn kî derê, ji me ra wek te gotin.
Wherever we went, they told us the same as you.
Me gotin zerar e...
They told us it's a loss...
Wella zerar e me. Çorsed dar çiniye, welle xêcî sê teneke
gotinê natim ra...
Wella it's a loss for us. I harvested four hundred trees,
wella besides three tins, I got nothing to say...
Belê.
Yes.
Û salê xwe girtin e...
And the year closed in on itself...
Hebe.
Right.
Spasiya te dikim xaltî. Saeta te xweş.
I thank you aunt. Have a good time.
Te jî xweş e, rehmet li miriyê we be, ez ser çavan me. Xêr
hatî bi silametî.
You are also welcome, mercy upon your dead, you are very
welcome. Welcome and stay safe.
Silamet be, bi xatirê te.
Stay safe, goodbye.
Merheba xaltîk.
Hello, aunt.
Bixêr bi selamet, ehlan û sehlan.
Welcome in peace, welcome.
Em te nas bikin xaltîk?
Can we get to know you, aunt?
Min nas bikin, Hedîqa Ednîn im. Bixwe ji gundiya Feqîra me.
You may know me, I am Hediqa Ednin. I am from the village of
Feqira.
Xaltîk, em hatine cem te îro... gundê we.
Aunt, we have come to you today... to your village.
Bixêr bi selamet.
Welcome in peace.
Me dît tu li der û hundir dikişî, me xwest em selamekî bidin
te.
We saw you working outside and inside, so we wanted to say
hello to you.
Ya rebbî bixêr hatin.
Oh Lord, welcome.
Û em hinekî pirs bikin, ser jinên gundê Feqîra da. Em her
gundekî digerin em ser jina da pirs dikin.
And we wanted to ask a bit about the women of the village of
Feqira. We visit every village and ask about the women.
Jin berê çi kar dikirin, çi nakin? Her gundek dibêjin welleh
jina me bi kar û kofî hene.
What work did women do in the past, and what don't they do?
Every village says, by God, our women are hardworking.
Ê lê erê jina, berê kar dikirin, berê nan dikirin...
Well yes, women used to work before, they used to bake bread
before...
...berê av ji bîran dikişandin. Îcar berê haşa wekî zibil
çêdikirin dewar hebû...
...they used to draw water from wells before. And excuse me,
they used to make manure because there were cattle...
...pez hebû, rûtbûn hebû, kar hebû. Naha ko kar kêm e, ava
hesî nabe welleh...
...there were sheep, there were hardships, there was work.
Now that work is less, there's no running water, by God...
...naha jê tembel bûn, de we kar de cîh hazir e te, rûne te
re tiştê xwe dikin... naha...
...now they have become lazy, your workplace is ready for
you, you sit and do your things... now...
...Îja berê weha nebû, kar pir bû. Naha kar kêm e, cîh hazir
e.
...So it wasn't like this before, there was a lot of work.
Now the work is less, the place is ready.
Em werin ser gundê we... naha ko me pirs kir dibêjin ku li
gundê we tenê zeytûn hene.
Let's talk about your village... now when we asked, they say
that in your village there are only olives.
Hene elhemdulîllah.
There are, thank God.
Neko gundên mînak, mesela em bêjin li gundên derdorê wek
hinar in, mişmiş in, fîstan e, pirr tişt çêdibin.
Unlike other villages, for example, let's say in surrounding
villages there are pomegranates, apricots, orchards, many
things grow.
Karê we ji wan ferq e? (Karê jina gundê Feqîra?)
Is your work different from theirs? (The work of the women
of Feqira village?)
Karê me... na bes di zeviyan de zeytûn in. Jina kêm e bes bi
malê de kar e.
Our work... no, there are only olives in the fields. The
women's work is less, there is only work at home.
Û em dikarin bêjin mêwe ew tüne bûn, jê re dikirin mêşan
fîlan diçêrandin, ew jî nîn e naha kar kêm bû.
And we can say there were no fruits, they used to herd sheep
and such, that is also gone now, the work has decreased.
Jin û mêr bi hev re kar dikin?
Do men and women work together?
Ê mêr dikin wîca kêm nedikirin wîca fella... wî de fella
digirtin wane diçin ro der û ro... diçin xebatê.
Well, the men do it, they didn't do less, so workers... they
would hire workers and they go day out and day... they go to
work.
Em naha wek e me nekir naha ew naçin fella naha der... em
wek e mêran fella nakin. Felleh nînin bes zeytûna nakin kar
kêm e.
We didn't do it now, they don't go out as workers now... we
don't work as workers like the men. There are no workers,
they just don't do olives, the work is less.
Naha ku me pirs kir em ser mûneya hesas em bêjin ser mûneya
îsal. Çi tişt hûn ser mûneya îsal da dikin?
Now that we asked, let's talk about the sensitive
provisions, let's say this year's provisions. What things
are you making for this year's provisions?
Em dibînin ku em bêjin zeytûnan hûn hûr dikin... fîstan e,
kêm genim e, we ew tişt kir?
We see that, let's say, you crush olives... there are
orchards, there's a little wheat, did you do those things?
Yanî tiştên wek berê nema ye? Wa mûneya îsal we çawa kir?
I mean, are things not like before? So how did you make this
year's provisions?
Mûneya îsal welle çi bikim weke... de kêm e. Yanî welle wek
e me mûne nedikir weha.
By God, what should I do for this year's provisions... it's
just less. I mean, by God, it's like we didn't make
provisions like this.
Tenê, weke... bulxur me nekelandin, cênîk tene bû naha, bo
wê yekê.
There's only... we didn't boil bulgur, there was only wheat
grains now, for that reason.
Ew... de amade dikirin çi bikim welleh, hazir in. Îsal ne...
ew buha ye am jê kîlo bi kîlo em dikişînin jê hazir dibe.
They... used to prepare it, what should I do by God, they
are ready. Not this year... it's expensive, we buy it kilo
by kilo and it's ready.
Em bêjin dimsê hinaran, tişt... tiştek te nakî?
Let's say pomegranate molasses, things... do you not make
anything?
Hinar te tünne inşallah.
There are no pomegranates hopefully.
Dimsê tirî?
Grape molasses?
Dimsê tiriyan jî tiştek te tünne. Em dî çawa e ew jî em ne
em dikir. Em wek nîn in.
There's no grape molasses either. We saw how it is, we
didn't make that either. We don't have it like that.
Çil û pelê gûzan derman e ew te nakî?
Walnut leaves are medicine, don't you make that?
Çil û we nîn e em me weke. Em wî re karê şil û... wek em
şêrî me çi bî de em dikir wan ew we dî.
There are no leaves and such for us. We just worked with wet
things... like sweets or whatever we used to make, you saw
that.
Naha ku her sal wezê meha zeytûna... zeytûna xelxal e we
xelxal çêdikin mokeles azanî wisa ye?
Now that every year during the olive season... there are
cracked olives, you make cracked olives, crushed olives, is
it like that?
Erê me zeytûnê xalxal, wek e xelat in... me dikişandin me bi
mekîneyan didan me mokeles çêdikirin... şîr î ew bûn me wek
çêdikirin.
Yes, our cracked olives, like they are mixed... we used to
press them, we put them through machines and made crushed
olives... there was milk and such, we used to make them like
that.
Bi gûzan... me zeytê re, em weke mastîqe mendî... am de wek
de çêdikir.
With walnuts... with oil, we used to make things like
traditional fruit leather... we used to make them.
A mastîqe mendî we çêdikir?
Ah, you used to make traditional fruit leather?
Erê, mastîqê mendî me çêdikir û penêr me we girt ew çêdikir.
Yes, we used to make traditional fruit leather, and we made
the cheese we bought.
Em wilo biçin ser zeytûnan me pirs kir am weke pirs bikin me
heya kîjan... dema we wîca de zeytûn e.
Let's go to the olives like that, we asked to see what
kind... your time with the olives.
Wek e me naha dît wîca tu salan zeytûn wilo... te enwaç e
(cureyên) pênc cüre... çêdikir.
As we saw now, so you used to make olives like that over the
years... you made about five varieties.
Berê wisa çêdikirin. Îsal tünne weha.
They used to make them like that before. This year there's
none of that.
Xaltîk ji me re bêje te yek bi yek... ser sal e bi sal we
çawa cureyên zeytûnan te çawa dîtin û çawa çêdikir?
Aunt, tell us one by one... year by year, how did you see
the olive varieties and how did you make them?
Cureyên berê... me re wîca hewşek bû em re we dişkandin û em
wî zeytûn hûr dikir. Û em re mekîneyan de... mokeles avê
tehl de...
The varieties of the past... we had a courtyard, we would
crack them and we would crush those olives. And we put them
in machines... crushed olives in bitter water...
Avê germ ê em me dermankir me dikir reş. Dermankir ew naha
te tünne naha.
Hot water and we would cure them and make them black. That
curing doesn't exist now.
Yanî am karin bêjin çar pênc cure we hûn ji zeytûnan dikin.
So we can say you make four or five varieties from olives.
Erê wek em çar pênc cureya çêdikin. Hêsal wek kêm e.
Yes, it's like we make four or five varieties. This year
it's less.
Îsal ew tişt te hene? (Do you have these things this year?)
Do you have those things this year?
Îsal jî wek kêm e... tünne nîn e zeytûn... em ew we nake. Em
we e wek zeytûn de de wî... naha we mûne nîn e we tünne ne
te re we.
This year it's also less... there are no olives... we don't
do that. We don't do the olives like that... now there are
no provisions, there's nothing for you.
Am naha herin ser zeyta zeytûna...
Now let's move on to the olive oil...
Zeyta zeytûnan maşelleh heye e weha... de... welle me kêm e
welleh wê...
Olive oil, thank God, there is like that... well... by God
we have very little of it...
Yanî ji mûneyên gundî tu we mûneyê malê te dît e çêdikin?
So from the village provisions, do you see them making the
house provisions?
Weke we zeyta heye te bikirre de heye, welle zêde tünne ji
bo malê we... we dikirre welleh.
Like there is oil, you can buy it, there is, by God there's
not much for the house... you buy it, by God.
Me pirsî ji hinek kesan me we ku em gundên me pirsî wek
"Musim e, we dît hûn diçînin pêncsed dar şeşsed dar hezar
dar hene?" Dibên welle zeyt nîn e em pê de we em... am bi
zeyt diçûn wezê.
We asked some people, as we asked the villages, like "It's
the season, you see you plant five hundred trees, six
hundred trees, a thousand trees?" They say by God there is
no oil, we... we used to go for the oil.
De ê nîn e em... me ne... mûneyek dît welleh, wê bi zeyt bi
kîrriyê heye welleh afû wî de nîn e em...
Well, there isn't for us... we didn't... see any provisions
by God, there is oil by buying it, by God, excuse me but
there is none...
...Wekî naha hewqas te de tişt welle we me çênekir ew hinek
tişt am bajan we bajanî naha am dikin am wî wî çêdikir e me
hinek qeza bûn.
...Like now, there are so many things, by God we didn't make
those few things, we did eggplants, we do eggplants now, we
used to make them, we had some accidents.
Bîstan hûn naçînin gundê we...
You don't plant orchards in your village...
Nîn in bîstan... we te... naha welleh wî re em re em de
rûnin û wê tişt tünne we tiştek tünne...
There are no orchards... you see... now by God we just sit
and there's nothing, there's nothing...
Gundê we bi çi deng vedaye zêdetir?
What is your village most famous for?
Dar û we zeytûna. Bê reze û pê zeytûn e. Bê reze...
Trees and olives. It's known for vineyards and olives.
Vineyards...
Dema berê te we dem e we dît naxwînin?
In the past, did you see that they didn't study?
Naxwînin ez nizanim we naxwînin... We wext nîn e min
naxwend. Welleh wî çê... tünne min nexwend welle tiştekî de
tünne welle ne naxwînim de...
They don't study, I don't know, they don't study... There
was no time, I didn't study. By God, what to do... there's
nothing, I didn't study, by God there's nothing, by God I
didn't study...
Ez dibêjim dema de te re te çawa xêr ê de te kar e de...
wextê te çawa derbas dibû?
I'm saying in your time, how did you do good, how was your
work... how did you spend your time?
Dema re welleh e em wek bi re re mal bi mal am diçûn em bi
hevalî am re kar we wisa rûniştî we rûniştin de çêdibû. Wek
wisa nîn e naha saeta... em de weha de baş e naha we wek baş
e em xatir dixwazin.
In that time, by God, we used to go from house to house with
friends, we worked together, sitting around like that
happened. It's not like that now for an hour... we are fine
like this, now we want to say goodbye.
Gelek sipas xaltîk.
Thank you very much, aunt.
Merheba xalo.
Hello, uncle.
Selamet ehlan û sehlan bavo.
Peace be with you, welcome, my son.
Em te nas bikin?
Can we get to know you?
Navê min Mîro ye, Mîro muxtarê gundê Feqîra me.
My name is Miro, I am Miro, the mukhtar (headman) of the
village of Feqira.
Belê, niha em hatine vê derê, em kevş e bizanibin ku we ev
me'sere çawa kar dike.
Yes, now we have come here, we want to know how this press
works.
Te li me'serê karê te me'serê bi xwe çi ye?
What is your own job at the press?
Ez di me'serê de muhasib im, û muxtarê gund im.
I am the accountant at the press, and the mukhtar of the
village.
Muxtarê gund e û muhasibê me'serê ye jê.
He is the mukhtar of the village and also the accountant of
the press.
Temam.
Exactly.
Belê, em kevş e werin mûsema zeytûnê. Îsal mûsem hat.
Yes, let's talk about the olive season. This year's season
has arrived.
Em dî dibînin derdorê me çewal hene. Kî ji me re hinekî ser
mûsema îsal daxuyanî ke, çawa ye?
We see sacks around us. Could someone explain a bit about
this year's season to us, how is it?
Mûsema îsal bi şeklekî 'am teqrîben sere sedî deh û pênc e.
This year's season in general is approximately fifteen
percent.
Baran çênebû, fe zeytûn tuneye îsal.
There was no rain, so there are no olives this year.
Ev çewalên ku tu dibînî jê, gundî bi dorê hatine, gundiyê
erdê xwe qelaç e...
These sacks that you see, the villagers have come in turn,
the villager whose land is rocky...
...ardê deştê de zeytûn kok tuneye îsal.
...in the plains there are absolutely no olives this year.
Feqet ew çar pênc sed darên xwe heye zeytûn e, ew sê çewal,
çar çewal e zeytûnan tîne.
But the one who has four or five hundred olive trees, he
brings three sacks, four sacks of olives.
Mûsema îsal kok da'wa mirî ye.
This year's season is completely dead.
Û ji çi wextî da me'sere şuxulê xwe dest pê kir?
And since when did the press start its work?
Destpêkirina îsal, deh û pêncî meha dehan da bû. Bi biryara
mekteb zîraî.
The start this year was on the fifteenth of the tenth month.
By the decision of the agricultural office.
Û ji wê çaxê da we dest... milet dest bi zeytûnan kir tînin
vê derê û li vir me'serê dixin?
And since then people started bringing olives here and
pressing them here?
Temam, teb'en na bi ro re dixebite.
Yes, of course it doesn't work every day.
Lê?
Why?
Na ro hene kes lê nake zeytûn kêm in.
No, there are days when no one presses because olives are
scarce.
Fe dibe gundî ro lê nekin, dibe du ro lê bikin sê ro lê
nekin, naşuxule.
So it happens that villagers don't press for a day, it
happens they press for two days and don't press for three
days, it doesn't work.
Heta mûsema xwe berhev bikin?
Until they gather their harvest?
Ê çaxê doza zeytûn nekêşîne lê nakin makîne bes naşuxule...
dibe.
When there is no demand for olives, they don't press, the
machine just doesn't run... it stops.
Yanî bêriya am bêjin zeytûnan ev xelkê gund tînin, pêşî
xeberê didin we?
So before, let's say, the village people bring the olives,
do they inform you first?
Na gundî bi xwe amade nabe em lê nakin.
No, if the villager himself is not present, we don't press.
Xadeta me me'sera vê derê, xwedî zeytûn amade nabe em lê
nakin.
Our custom at this press is, if the owner of the olives is
not present, we don't press.
Her kes li ser malê xwe be.
Everyone should be present for their own property.
Zanî? Xeyrê vê yekê xwedî tunne be, xwedan me'sere razî nabe
zeytûnan bo xwe de wî lêke... kok.
You know? Other than that, if the owner is not there, the
press owner won't agree to press the olives for him... at
all.
Xalo îsal am bibêjin çiqas çewal zeytûn wa lêkiriye û çiqas
teneke zeyt biriyane? Xwestin wê bizanibin.
Uncle, this year, let's say, how many sacks of olives were
pressed and how many tins of oil were taken? We wanted to
know that.
Bavo, zeyt bi şeklê 'am... heval dibe maliyê qudret e heye.
My son, oil in general... sometimes it depends on the
ability.
Hinek hene mesela go zeytûna, zeytûn heye tenekek tey, heye
tenekek û nîv tê.
There are some, for example, who say olives, some olives
yield one tin, some yield one and a half tins.
Û nîmeta Xwedê hene, hinek hişt qat dihatin tenekek dihat.
And there are blessings from God, sometimes eight measures
would come and yield one tin.
Nako îhsaîyekî te ba cem te heye ê salên berê? Em bêjin
çiqas dihatin û çûbûn, û yê îsal jî heye?
So do you have any statistics from previous years? Let's say
how much came and went, and do you have it for this year
too?
Her sal pir dihat lê îsal pir hatî?
Every year a lot came, but did a lot come this year?
Ka tenê zeytûnan?
Only for olives?
Em dibêjin aha.
We say yes.
Zeytûn ekîd her sal, beştir bû wekî şeş qat heft qat dihat.
Olives certainly every year, it was better, like six times
or seven times more came.
Yanî îsal... nîsbeta mûseme, di sedî de deh û pênc e. Sera
sedî...
I mean this year... the season's percentage is fifteen
percent. In terms of percentage...
Yanî am karin bêjin na çewalê zeytûnan... zeytûna kêm hatî,
lê zeytûn ê te jî hişk e, av jî nîn e?
So we can say in the sacks of olives... fewer olives came,
but your olives are also dry, there is no water either?
Erê, av kêm e.
Yes, water is scarce.
Av te tunne ye ji ber hişkiyê.
There is no water because of the drought.
Heta yî bûn em ne di keyfa xwe bûn em di...
Even then we were not in good spirits, we...
Dar yê qentî ye... zeytûn reş bûye.
The tree is dying... the olive has turned black.
Daxwaza çîçekî zeytûn rind bû.
The bloom of the olive was good.
Feqet çîçek ra kir. Da wazê çiçikê.
But the flower fell off. The demand of the flower.
Paşê şewat hat, û... dar yê qentî bû, av te tunne bû kîse
rûn dijiqî.
Then the heatwave came, and... the tree was dying, there was
no water, the oil sac was drying up.
Û îtîmada fella jî bi şeklekî 'am...
And the reliance of the farmers in general...
We îtîmada fellehan jî bi şeklekî 'am... vê derê mentîqeya
me wekî tu dibînî çiya û deştê me... gişt zeytûn e.
And the reliance of the farmers in general... here in our
region as you can see our mountains and plains... are all
olives.
Erdê vala tunne ye, baxçe tunne, dar tunne...
There is no empty land, no orchards, no other trees...
Fe îtîmad, sere sedî nod sersedî zeytûnan e.
So the reliance is ninety percent on olives.
Meqbesa we li vê derê tenê xelkê gund tê de lê dike, an ji
gundê din jî tên?
Your press here, do only the village people press here, or
do they come from other villages too?
Na, meqbes ne tenê ye, kesên nêz...
No, the press is not alone, nearby people...
...bû berê... paşê bû kevir, paşê ew bû. Hate guhertin
gihişte vê merheleyê.
...it was like that before... then it became stone, then it
became that. It changed and reached this stage.
Wek tatwîr kir her car.
You upgraded it every time.
Wek tatwîr, bere bere gor zeman.
Upgrading it, gradually according to the times.
Zeytûnên ji we da digirin, Kaxrê da, Şîtkê da, ji Satiyê da,
wek gundên dor û derî me gî tê?
The olives you receive, do they all come from Kaxire,
Shitka, Satiya, and the villages around us?
Erê, dor û derî me gî tê. Her kî simet pak be, zibûn zêde
dibe. Û sal bi sal jî zibûn zêde dibe.
Yes, they all come from the surroundings. Whoever has a good
reputation, their customers increase. And year by year the
customers increase.
Heqê tenekê tefawût dibe. Zani? Hinek heye meselen... em
heqê xizmetê jê distînin.
The price of the tin varies. You know? Some people for
example... we only charge them a service fee.
Yanî hûn wek heqî jê nastînin?
So you don't take an actual fee from it?
Wek heqî hindik e, bes xizmet jê distînin. Yanî kar nakin
ser heqê tenekê.
As an actual fee it is little, we only take the service fee.
Meaning we don't profit off the price of the tin.
Naha teneke bi çiye teqrîben ê baş?
Now how much is a good tin approximately?
Ê baş teqrîben dolar û nîvek e.
The good one is approximately a dollar and a half.
Ne bihabûna we, havî ser cotkaran e?
Does this high price benefit the farmers?
Ser cotkar bo wê, lê sukonek e.
It is expensive for the farmer, but the market is stagnant.
Û neha nêzîkî zeytê bi çend e?
And roughly how much is the oil right now?
Tenekê zeytê neha hero 70, 75, 80 jêr de ye.
A tin of oil right now is around 70, 75, below 80.
Yanî gava ku werin heqê amaleyê derxin, mafê cotkar derxe...
Meaning when they come and deduct the worker's fee, and
deduct the farmer's share...
Bixwedê ev sal wehye. Ev sal gor mûsimê îsal, cotkar di
xisarê ye.
By God, this year is like this. This year, according to this
season, the farmer is at a loss.
Yanî em bêjin ne tenê cotkar, hûn bi xwedanê meqbesê jî,
xesarê digirin...
So we can say it's not just the farmer, you, the owners of
the press, also take a loss...
Xwedanê makbesê, makbesê xwe der naxe, bikêr nayê randa.
The owner of the press doesn't even make enough to cover the
press, it's not useful.
Û li ser çi dixebitin? Kahraba heye yan mûtor in?
And what do you operate on? Is there electricity or do you
use generators?
Na, heyîn kahraba nagihîje cem me. Belê... nav gund çebekê
belav kiriye, vê derê jî kahraba 20 hezar dolar xwestin,
saetê.
No, the electricity doesn't reach us. Yes... the network has
been distributed in the village, but here they asked for
$20,000 for electricity per hour.
Kahraba ew jî... şebeke ji we dûr e teqrîben kîlometrek e.
Eger 20 hezar dolar... 20 hezar dolar jî mûsimê îsal gî der
naxe. Fê sikinîn, temdîd nekirin.
And the electricity... the network is about a kilometer away
from us. If it's $20,000... this year's entire season won't
even make $20,000. So we stopped, we didn't extend it.
Rojê çend saet weha teqrîben mûtorê pê dixin?
Approximately how many hours a day do you turn on the
generator?
Bixwedê mûtor herro ji zû ve dikeve, îro saet 8'an da pê
ketiye û niha jî hîn saet çar e teqrîben hene, mûtor
nemiriye. Heta ku zibûn hene, ê pêketî bimîne.
By God, the generator is turned on early every day, today it
was turned on at 8 o'clock and now it is still around 4
o'clock, the generator hasn't been turned off. As long as
there are customers, it will stay on.
Hewa mazotê pir naxwe û mazot jî biha ye wek ku em dizanin.
Doesn't it consume a lot of diesel, and diesel is expensive
as we know.
Mazot biha ye, 180, 185 dolar e bermîlek.
Diesel is expensive, it is 180, 185 dollars a barrel.
We qasî wek we derdikeve wek em bêjin?
Does it come out even, so to speak?
Ê îcbarî, carek heye zibûnê ku alimî te ye... makbes kevn e,
ra... tu mecbûrî xizmetê bikî. Qey zibûnê xelkê em çawa
nekin? Wey, fe îcbarî...
Well, it's obligatory, once you have customers who are used
to you... the press is old... you are obligated to serve
them. How can we not serve the people's customers? So it is
obligatory...
Welew ku bes masarîf derê, emê bişixulin. He ye sal gelek
meqbesên hanê neşixulîn.
Even if it just covers the expenses, we will work. This year
many of the presses over there did not operate.
Yanî li gundên derdora we meqbes neşixulîn?
Meaning the presses in the villages around you did not
operate?
Ere, gundên hanê neşixulîn, wê ranewestin. Mûsim kêm bû. Ha
neşixulîn, sekinîn.
Yes, those villages didn't operate, they couldn't endure it.
The season was weak. So they didn't operate, they stopped.
Saetek xweş, oxir be.
Have a good time, goodbye.
Saet xweştir, hezar car bi xêr hatin, oxir be.
You too, you are welcome a thousand times, goodbye.
[Music]
Merheba.
Hello.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Çaw e mamoste?
How are you, teacher?
Welah rind e, hûn çawa ne? Baş in? Bi xêr hatin.
By God, I am fine, how are you? Are you well? Welcome.
Baş e. Serçava. Em destpêkê te nas bikin?
Good. Thank you. Can we get to know you first?
Navê min Luqman e. Luqman Heso Xelef.
My name is Luqman. Luqman Heso Xelef.
Ji gundê Feqîra.
From the village of Feqira.
Gundê Feqîra, ere.
From the village of Feqira, yes.
Lî pişt me, ma'sera ye.
Behind us, is the press.
Erê.
Yes.
Me xwest em werin cem we, ma'serê da...
We wanted to come to you, at the press...
Em bibînin zeytûn çawa derdixin, ji destpêkê ku zeytûn tê
ma'serê heta dema dibe zeyt û dikeve tenekê da. Kîjan
merheleyan re derbas dibe?
To see how you extract the olives, from the beginning when
the olives come to the press until they become oil and fall
into the tin. What stages does it go through?
Ser çava, ser çava.
With pleasure, with pleasure.
Em dest pê bikin, ji dema zeytûn dikeve...
Let's start, from the moment the olives fall...
Wê kîsê tînin, we çuwalê vala dikin we vir da... çi dibe?
They bring that sack, they empty the sack here... what
happens?
Erê, tînin vir e, berê li ba dikirin dertixistin. Naha ewe
tiştekî din, tije dikin tevî pelê xwe, dardixînin evê
helezon... helezon dikişîne... dertê û diçe.
Yes, they bring it here, in the past they used to winnow it
and take it out. Now it's something else, they fill it with
its leaves, they take it out to this spiral... the spiral
pulls it... it comes out and goes.
Piştî diçe bişo, dadikeve ser evê...
After it goes to be washed, it falls onto this...
Em tiştekî wisa fêhm bikin, ji we re... bi ava sar e yan bi
ava germ?
So that we can understand something, from you... is it with
cold water or with hot water?
Ava sar e. Ava sar e... Ava germ nabe.
It is cold water. It's cold water... It cannot be hot water.
Avî sar e, berê jî wisa dihat şûştin, merhaleyî ku derbas
dibe dixe yanî... we çolî...
It's cold water, in the past it was also washed like that,
the stage it goes through... putting it in... those twigs...
We peler e... ewê jî dertîne... hinek çiçike tê... bes ew
pir dernaxe.
Those leaves... it takes those out too... some twigs come
through... but it doesn't take out much.
Em berê bi destan ba dikir, berê tiştên weha tune bûn.
Meqbesên me berê kevn... şêst nodan da hebûn... bes ew wisa
bû... kevir bûn. Ser kavira bû, dar bû.
We used to winnow it by hand in the past, things like this
didn't exist before. Our old presses... we had them in the
sixties and nineties... but they were like that... they were
stones. They were on stones, they were made of wood.
Naha ew makbes e, asê ye...
Now it's a press, it's firm...
Hê we pêr yekî kevin me hebû... berê dişkota hebû... ew
abû... wa yanî e... ew wext da paş de diçû.
Yes, the day before yesterday we had an old one... before it
had a wheel... that was it... so... it went back in time.
Hûn bi xwe dikirin bûn?
Did you do it yourselves?
Em xwe dikirin. Ev dawere digerî ser kevir, û bi destan...
destan didîtin û destan dikirin, ew weha dikişandin.
We did it ourselves. This circular thing rotated on the
stone, and by hand... they did it by hand, they pulled it
like that.
Saz dikin heta...
They arrange it until...
Saz dikin ewteye, paşê ewa jêre da diçû, hêdî hêdî ...
siyaseta wê weha bu.
They arrange it in the middle, then it went down underneath
it, slowly... that was its system.
Gî sere dor lîk naha ko... kebis dikirin, ne mîna meqbesê
elî ko.
Everyone turned around it back then... they pressed it, not
like the mechanical press.
Piştî wê, naha te tewir çebû, bi fanî...
After that, now you have upgraded, mechanically...
Fenî jî yek berê, birayê min ê mezin hebû... rehmê xwedê lê
be ew ji min mezintir bû... ew jî hebû, dest birayê min.
Before, there was also a mechanical one, my older brother
had it... may God have mercy on him, he was older than me...
there was one, in my brother's hands.
Ew ji fannî bû... çûçuk bû...
It was also mechanical... it was small...
Millet jî za'f hebû, maşelah zeytûnên te pirr hebûn.
There were a lot of people too, mashallah, you had a lot of
olives.
Erê rabû yek hinek hadîs, naha min xwest ew jî, û naha eva
anî... we fannî ye.
Yes, then a modern one came along, now I wanted that too,
and now I brought this one... it is mechanical.
Beriya gî, xelk zeytûnê xwe tînin vir, dixe va şûştinê, pêşî
ewa helezo, hûn dibînin em vala dikin bi ava.
Before anything, people bring their olives here, put them in
this washer, first the spiral, you see we empty it with the
water.
Bi ava xwe re diçe li wê...
It goes with its water over there...
... silav tê, çilo paşê diçe wa ber ba. Paşê hare wî da
şûştin, ba wê ava sar...
... the twigs come through, then it goes to be blown. Then
it goes there to be washed, with that cold water...
Paşê dakeve herreyê...
Then it goes down to the grinder...
Paşê ev herriya... ev hûr dike?
Then this grinder... does it grind it?
Hûr dike, dike acîn... ew da herre.
It grinds it, makes it into dough... that's the grinder.
Yanî heta dihere wê derê de, we da carûşe?
So when it goes in there, that is a crusher?
Ew êdî carûşe... ewa we resxale ye, dike...
That is a crusher now... that is the washer, it makes it...
Piştî yê şûşt, hate carûşê, herrê da carûşê... piştî carûşê
diçe ber accane, acane lê dixe...
After it washed, it came to the crusher, the grinder in the
crusher... after the crusher it goes to the mixer, the mixer
beats it...
Di nav acane da, wek, daxilê wî tê da, dengê çi tê?
In the mixer, like, what's inside it, what is that sound
coming from?
Gî hûr dike, yanî ewa dîke ace, mîna macûnê.
It crushes everything, meaning it makes it into dough, like
paste.
Gî hûr dibe.
Everything gets crushed.
Paşê?
Then?
Acane lê dixe... lê dixe... lê dixe... hetanî ko rûn ewa...
wextê xwe heye... gava rûn dide.. derdikeve... ava germ ser
da dike... em naxwazin ava pirr germ jî be... naha em we rûn
zeytê nerm dikin.
The mixer beats it... beats it... beats it... until the
oil... it takes its time... when it yields oil... comes
out... it pours hot water on it... we don't want the water
to be too hot... now we soften the olive oil.
Çima hûn naxwazin pir ava we germ bibe?
Why do you not want your water to get very hot?
Dibê asît bilind dibe, çê dibe... germbûnê zêde ne rind e...
nizam em wisa dizanin. Berê, koka xwe... ava germ nedikir...
niha îcbarî em ava germ lê dikin... da ko zeyt zêde derxe.
The acidity rises, whatever happens... getting too hot is
not good... I don't know, that's what we believe. In the
past, originally... we didn't use hot water... now it's
mandatory that we add hot water... so that it extracts more
oil.
Ewe dekanter... ji wê da rind derdixe...
That is the decanter... it extracts it well from there...
Di nav dekanter da derdikeve yanî?
So it comes out in the decanter?
Ewa... dibe derdê merkêzî, erebî din... nizanim kurmancî çi
ye.
It... becomes centrifugal force, they say in Arabic... I
don't know what it is in Kurmanji.
Ew pê sûret digere. Û ew ava zeytê, av û zeytê davêje...
aliyekî û berînê em dibêjin, ewe yê olîkê...
It spins with speed. And it throws the oil water, water and
oil... to one side and what we call pomace, that is the
residue...
Yek xeteke zeyt e, yek xeteke av e û yek da ewa ye... ew em
jê ra dibêjin, qeçika we olîke e.
One line is oil, one line is water, and the other one is
that... we call it, the pieces of pomace.
Ev farze ye ko ew dibêjin farze ye.
This is the separator that they say is the separator.
Da dikeve ewe, ewa farze... dema evê avê derdixîne... ev
farz e, hinek av ko hebe yê safî dike...
It falls into that, that is the separator... when it
extracts this water... this is a separator, if there is any
water it purifies it...
Wê paqij dike? Qasî tenekeyê, teşteke ewa çi ye?
It cleans it? The size of a tin, what is that basin?
Ewe heta ewe... wazn e... safî derdikeve... qasî tenekeyê ko
bibe nîşan did e...
That is until it... it's a weight... it comes out clear...
when it reaches the size of a tin, it shows...
Xeyrî meznê tenekê yanî?
Without the weight of the tin, you mean?
Kilo yeke... wezney gî yeke.
The kilo is the same... the weight is all the same.
Û ev galonê... galonê wa te hûn çawa mezenê wê dikin?
And this gallon... your gallons, how do you measure them?
Ewa galon mişekkel e... we heryek çiqasî dixwaze, ewe bo
difrotane yê wê ye... em ne difroşin. Em ev we ji mala xwe
ra û ji ewa yê we tînin...
Those gallons are assorted... however much each person
wants, those are for selling... we don't sell. We bring
these for our own homes and for those...
Gî hecmê gî yek e.
The volume is all the same.
Eger bo galon... ew meznê wê te dît ko, bi yê din mezin, 20
jî heye, 25 jî heye, heryek qasî wî...
If it's for a gallon... you see its size, it's bigger than
the others, there's a 20, there's a 25, each one according
to its size...
Naha berînî... da derdixe... ewe hûn di bînin dikin çi?
Now the pomace... it extracts... what do you do with it?
Ewe berîne... dîke zeytê sabûnê. Ewa dibin meqbesê ewa...
ewe em we berînî dibin ... ewa canderistanê.
That is pomace... it's made into soap oil. They take it to
that press... we take that pomace to... the agricultural
area.
Candêrisê?
Jindires?
Candaristan... lî heba we Cindirêsê ye.
The agricultural area... over towards Jindires.
Ewa ê didin wî... wa wê berînê, yê xwişk dikin...
They give it to them... they dry that pomace...
Heraret... maşînê wa hene... wa avê gî jê derdixin... bes
berîn û zêt dimîne.
Heat... they have machines... they extract all the water
from it... only the pomace and the oil remain.
Paşî bi madeyekê dişon, ewa kerosîn e... ew da ewe... wekî
petrole...
Then they wash it with a substance, that is kerosene... that
is like... it's like petrol...
Ew... çi zeytê wê da hebê, ewa kerosîn radike... we da... û
madda... kerosîn da jor zeytî derdixe bîn e. Ewe avê jê
dikşînin... ew zeyt dikin sabûn. Û ewa yê dikişînin jê... we
tel e, weh ... we naxwazin. Tamî wî naxweş e, reş e...
Whatever oil is in it, that kerosene extracts it... in
there... and the substance... the kerosene extracts the oil
downwards. They pull the water out of it... they make that
oil into soap. And what they pull out of it... is bitter,
like that... they don't want it. Its taste is bad, it's
black...
Niha, makbes heta... wextê kîjan şixulî, yanî em wek meşgul
bûn...
Now, until... what time did the press work, I mean, you guys
were busy...
Wexta eger mûsim... mûsim îsal kêm e. Heta we dawiya mî...
meşa dî çû. Bes gava eger mûsim baş be... şev û ro
dixebite... wa dîke wek em dibên, du perçe, saet bi saet.
Ewa îsal, wa kêm e. Gava ewe ... ko makbesê berê, ser kevir
bû... hindik diqedî.
At the time if the season... the season this year is low. It
went until the end of the... the month. But when the season
is good... it works day and night... they do it, as we say,
in two shifts, hour by hour. But this year, it is low. When
that... when the old press was on stones... it finished
little.
Hingî zêde dem diçû, saet pir dima...
Then it used to take more time, it stayed for many hours...
Heta we meha sêyemîn diçû.
It used to go until the third month.
Naha ko, ev salê din a... hûn bişixulin, heta kîjan mehê hûn
dibêjin ko em amade ne...
Now, these other years... you working, until which month do
you say we are ready...
Heta... heta we mehê... we yekê yê diqediya.
Until... until the month... it used to finish in the first
month.
Heta meha duyemîn yan yekemîn?
Until the second month or the first?
Heta, dawiya yekê, dudu.
Until the end of the first, the second.
Em pêş de.. ez dixwazim vê tiştî zanibim... gellek... amûr
hene... weka me dît lî ma'serê... em bizanibin ko ewa wextê
xwe qedand, wa amûr hûn bi çi awa çawa diparêzin?
We first... I want to know this thing... there are many...
tools... as we saw in the press... we want to know when it
finishes its time, how do you preserve those tools?
Em wa alatan dişon... paqij dişon, û vedişêrin... hetanî ko
sala din.
We wash those tools... we wash them clean, and store them...
until next year.
Gava ko hûn vedişêrin bi wê we derman, bi zeyt yan tiştek
wisa, da zingar nebe?
When you store them, do you apply a chemical, with oil or
something like that, so it doesn't rust?
Nexê, wextê bi zeyt be.. wa xwe bi xwe zeyt e. Rûn, zeyta we
zingar negire. Bes em, pak dişon, wekî ewa da weke amûrê
zingar nagire.
No, since it is with oil... it's oily by itself. Oil, that
oil will not rust. We just wash it clean, and that tool
doesn't catch rust.
Made krôme. Ewa stalis tîl e. Heta eger şil bibe jî zingar
nake... wek ko krôme.
The material is chrome. That is stainless steel. Even if it
gets wet, it doesn't rust... because it's chrome.
Gelek spas... Em naha...
Thank you very much... We now...
Zengar nabe. Wî tiştî xarijî zengar jî pê ra me tesîr nake
ev. Ev di buha dikin yanî eva buhakirî ye.
It doesn't rust. Because it is foreign (stainless steel),
rust doesn't affect it, so it makes it expensive, I mean
this is priced.
Belê. Naha tiştê ku te bîrî min..
Yes. Now what comes to my mind..
Dibêjin naha sal mûsim têtin, ev ho sal dînin ewa yeke.
They say now year.. season comes.. every year they bring
this one.
Erê.
Yes.
Salek berî wê ye.
One year is before it (better than the other).
Erê.
Yes.
Gorî em zanin, gundek derdorê wê ve... giştî zeytûnê xwe
tînin vê derê. Û her sal çawa diçe ber bi me da digihişt.
As far as we know, the villages around here... all bring
their olives here. And every year is different than the one
before.
Yanî her sal mûsim tê naha, em vî fêm dikin ku her sal çawa
diçe ber bi me da.
I mean every year the season comes now, we understand that
every year was different than the one before.
Erê me makbesa we dît naha teb'en...
Yes, we saw your press now, of course...
Bes em ew de gelek şa bûn ro em dişixul in,
But we are doing it happily, we are working.
yanî em ew dikin... loma niha me cîhazê hedîs...
I mean we do it... that's why now we brought modern
devices...
tiron û mastiran anîne. Berê kûçik bû, me bar nedigirt,
salek sala her zibûnê me pir dibin, mûsim pir dibe,
tiron and master. Before it was small, we couldn't handle
the load, year by year our customers are increasing, the
season is increasing.
em jî hedîs dikin pir derdixin. Meselen berê me şêst ton
derdixist, niha em heştê tonî derdixin, rojekê.
We also modernize and produce more. For example, before we
produced 60 tons, now we produce 80 tons, per day.
Timî em, em jî gorî avê dimeşin.
You also walk according to the water/demand.
Te pirsê, te ser cîhaza te anî kir. Cîhazên we ji kûderê
tînin, we ji kûderê anîne?
You asked, you brought up your devices. Where do you bring
your devices from, where did you bring them from?
Cîhaz... em ji Îtaliya çêdibe bes wekî e... me jî mirov
tînin. Ji derve tînin.
Devices... we uh... from Italy they are made but like...
they bring them for us. From outside.
Kes hene îstîrad û tiştên wisa dikin yanî tînin difroşin.
People import and make modern things, I mean they bring them
and sell them.
Es'arên wî dikin wî çawa ne?
Are their prices heavy or how are they?
Wella mûşekkel in... haseb e. Ê, meselen Tirkiya çêdike,
erzan e...
Well, they vary, it depends. Uh, for example Turkey makes
them, they are cheap...
ê Îtalî buha ne...
the Italian ones are expensive...
Meselen, ê pir tiştê waha... dikenter e... dikenter, eva
tard merkezî,
For example, the most expensive thing... is a decanter...
decanter, that is a centrifuge,
ewa giştî buhatir e.
that is the most expensive of all.
Yê din... hinek li vir jî çêdibe ne... niha cerûş... li vir
hesasî çêdibe... Efrîn çêdibe... hene tiştê wisa hene îmkan
e li vir çêbikin yanî kanin çêkin.
The others... some are also made here... for example now
crushers here... Azaz makes them, Afrin makes them... there
are such things it's possible to make them here, I mean they
can make them.
Bes dikenter, mustehîl e, li vir çêbe.
But a decanter, it's impossible to be made here.
Em bêjin qudek, di... makserî da çêbibe, muselehê wê heye
çêke, çêneke?
Let's say a malfunction happens in the... press, is there a
repairman to fix it, or not?
Muselîha kî me heye ewa tê di meqbesê da ye. Ser cîhazê ye.
Eger qudek, meselen kanî çêkira, çêdikira... Eger nikanî
çêkira, hene mûxtes hene
We have a repairman, he is always at the press. He is on the
device. If a malfunction, for example he could fix it, he
fixes it... If he couldn't fix it, there are specialists.
yanî werşetê mezin, têne çêdikin cîhazên wan hedîs û ev...
rind tê çêkirin e.
I mean big workshops, they come and fix their modern devices
and these... they fix it well.
Yanî qûtbûnê bidin xelkê... çêdibin yanî...
I mean they give service to the people... they happen I
mean.
Teb'en, teb'en. Nîzîkî me ne, Cindirêsê... Efrînê ne... têne
çêdikin.
Of course, of course. They are near us, in Jindires...
Afrin... they come and fix them.
Kerec jî hene e... meselen bi elatên difarit e ne... hene
çêdikin... ewa qudek besîd be... ewa makînisyên yê me kanî
me ra çêke...
There are garages too uh.. for example with diagnostic tools
they fix them.. if it's a simple malfunction, our mechanic
can fix it for us.
Ez zanim me te irehet kir... me pir pirs ji te kir...
I know we made you tired... we asked you a lot of
questions..
Na, na mişkîle. Ehlû sehlen ser çava..
No problem. Welcome, on my eyes..
Em dixwazin bizanibin... emeliyyet pî û şirê' ... yanî kirîn
û firotin, li vî derê çêdibe, li makbesê, yan teqata?
We want to know, the buying and selling process... I mean
buying and selling. Does it happen here, at the press, or
elsewhere?
Tê.. ticar tê... tu digerî, dibêje si'rê min ev e, te xwestî
difroşî.. te nexwestî nefroşî.
They come.. the merchants come.. you look around he says my
price is this, if you want you sell, if you don't want you
don't sell.
Ya te dil heye salekî ... heta belkî buha be, yanî te ra tu
nagere kirê, xwarê di xeznê de îla ... heta salekê dî...
tişt nabe zeytê.
Or if you want for a year ... until maybe it drops again, I
mean you don't rent, you put it down in the tank it stays
... until another year... nothing happens to your oil.
Ez dixwazin bizanibin... cûdahî çi hene, meselen, welatî
hatin vê derê, zeytûn anîbû vê derê, zeytê xwe ji vir
rasterast mûbaşereten da ticar û difiroşe, çi cûdahî
navbeynê da heye?
I want to know, what are the differences for example, the
citizen came here, brought his olives here, his oil right
directly from here gives the merchant and sells? What
difference is there between them?
Ferq tenê ye, bide ticar yanî ji ra qûlayîtir e, meselen ewa
teklîfê ra nake.
There is no difference, giving to the merchant I mean it's
easier for him, for example he doesn't take the cost.
Ereyî, bibe û dîne û bar ke û... dake dîne... devê derî rast
diçe ewa radike... qûlayîtir e
Yes, take it and bring and load and... take it down bring...
straight from the door he picks it up... it's easier.
Û nefs hev si're e?
And is it the same price?
Nefs hev si'ra, teb'en...
The same price, of course...
Tecar, tecar divêcin asîdê... em jê ra dibêjin asîd...
nîsbetê hemûda... bîrerebî dibêjin. Eva tişt çiye?
The merchant, the merchant says acid... we call it acid...
acidity percentage ...in Arabic they say. What is that
thing?
Meselen ji şeş heta nabe... tu her rind bike... asîd em
dibêjin heta yek, yek û nîvek eva em dibêjin nûh ewel... î
yekî.
For example from six up to ten... you do everything well...
acid we say up to one, one and a half this we say first
new... the first.
Yek û nîvek, heta tişt din diduy e û ê din heta nika dî, her
bilind dibe, ev nîsbetil hemûda, yanî nîsbeta tirşbûna wê.
Tarjama wê be...
One and a half, up to another thing is two and the other up
to now... the higher it gets, this acidity percentage, I
mean its sourness percentage. The translation of it would
be...
Bêtir dibe, nexwaş e... meselen ev xwaş e... ev yanî...
It becomes more, it's bad... for example this is good...
this I mean...
Asîdê din bê... yek û şeş rabin.
Let the other acid be... let it be 1.6.
Yanî yek û şeş ra derbas bibe 4 kêm e yanî ev pîr... yek û
şeş eger zeytûn rind e noka ev pîr bû... kurm jê xistiye
be...
I mean 1.6 goes up to 4 is less I mean this is old... 1.6 if
the olives are good now this is old... a worm hit it...
Em bimar in, asîdê din be yek we...
Let's say, the other acid is one...
Erê.
Yes.
Si're wî çiqase ye noka?
How much is its price now?
Noka wele, berê ev ticarekî mera got şuxil tê dî şuxil te,
yanî yê kêmtirîn yek e, hema ew e... 77 wekî em dibêjin...
teneka wê... 77 dolar e te hesab bike.
Now well, before this merchant told us work comes sees
sees... I mean the one less than 1 is just that... 77 like
we say... its tin... count it as 77 dollars.
Ê her yê din mastî pê be s'er dadike.
Uh every other one that has more acidity the price drops.
Berî we wê kîloyê difirot... we noka tenekê len... ew teneke
gîyê yek in... şazdeh kîlo dibe baha qasî...
Before you sold by kilo... now you have tins... those tins
are all one... this sixteen kilos is about...
Hema teneke... qûlayîtir e, neha we dît pîve û ev bike û ter
bike û tujar çixêkî pê kire, şexwarê rast xwa, teneka vedi
ke her tişt wî dibîne ...
Just a tin... is easier, I mean you need to measure it, open
it, wet it, the merchant put a stick in it, looking straight
down opens the tin sees everything in it ...
Ew dike şûşekî, lî asîdê dixe, cîhaz heye... Ew dixwîne çend
xetên wî heye...
He puts a small bottle, puts it in acid, there is a
device... He reads it to see how many lines it has...
Heta yek û yek û nîvek bibe ev e, bes her xetek zêde dibe
si'er dadikê.
Up to one and one and a half it's this.. but every extra
line the price drops.
Spasiya te dikim
I thank you.
Ehlû sehlen ser çava, we her dem xêratî... ehlû sehlen...
Welcome, on my eyes, you are always welcome... welcome...
Xalê em bi kê ma re ye?
Uncle, who are we with?
Xalê te Evdirehman Heso bîn Xelef.
Your uncle Abdulrahman Hesso bin Khalaf.
Ji gundê Feqîran e.
From the village of Faqiran.
Erê ji gundê Feqîran me.
Yes, I am from the village of Faqiran.
Emrê te?
Your age?
Emrê min heştê û neh sal e.
My age is eighty-nine years.
Maşallah!
Mashallah!
Erê.
Yes.
Xwedê emrekî dirêj bide te.
May God give you a long life.
Mewalîdê sîyî me.
I was born in the thirties.
Heqîqî yanî wextê ez mezin bûm, di nav gund bû.. wekî te
bavkê min ji me re walda ye.
Truly I mean when I grew up, it was in the village.. like
you my grandfather raised us.
Li nav gund bû devê wextê xwe de te dayîm digot feqîr o bî.
It was inside the village during that time you always said
you were poor.
Yanî maleta dewlemendî awere nîbû.
I mean the condition of wealth wasn't like that.
Çil, sîyan de te dît.
You saw it in the forties, thirties.
Çil, sîyan de tebî... ge tu dikarî tiştekê ser te de derbas
bûye dîrokê da?
If you were in the forties, thirties... can you tell if
anything happened to you in history?
De em mezin bûn li vî gundî... ewa giştk xaniyekî beton tenê
bû.
When we grew up in this village... there was only one
concrete house in all of it.
Giş xaniyê dîrako bûn.
They were all mud houses.
Erê her yek dîrako.
Yes, every single one mud.
Hemberî me jî me re hildan.. şkeft ava da bûn, şkeftê me pir
in, nav gund bi şkefte.
Opposite of us they also took it for us.. caves were built,
our caves are many, inside the village is with caves.
Ev derî veşartî sala bi?
This hidden door was in which year?
Ewa.. wextê ez şeş, heft salî me te dît me hebû emrê xwa not
sal bû.. ji mere tim ewan digot.
That.. when I was six, seven years old you see we had
someone whose age was ninety years.. she always told us
those.
Digot eslê xwa gijk me xaniyekî beton di gund da tenê bû.
Nehê ha.
She said originally all of us there was only one concrete
house in the village. Not this one.
Devê em... ewa malbat kî avadiye? Kî yî avadiye?
We must... who built that family? Who built it?
Ev bî eyyem e.. erê.
This is from days.. yes.
Di pêncî û şeşan da... me du odek beton da nav gund.. wek...
bavkê min girt.
In the fifty-sixes... we put two concrete rooms in the
village.. like... my grandfather took.
Û di re ehlê gund yek û di xwa re beton kirin, hîrû derket.
And then the village people one and two built concrete for
themselves, it came out strong.
Gund çêkirinê di mabe... hezar û heftsed û pêncîyan da wina
kalikê me hatine wira.
The village building remained... in seventeen hundred and
fifties like that our ancestors came here.
Navê gund te tiştê?
Do you know the name of the village?
Navê gund Feqîran e.
The name of the village is Faqiran.
Feqîran. Çima navê wî kirin Feqîran?
Faqiran. Why did they name it Faqiran?
Husên Brahîm... Helebê hat.. mala xwa berê li Şêx Bekir
bû... ev gundê dor xwe.. berî me gundek mala Xwateyan e heye
bû. Digot malbata mala Îsa Bêzê... ewa dost hene tekellûf
kirin, tekellûf kir. Bab û kalikê me hat cem e.
Hussein Brahim... came from Aleppo.. his house before was in
Sheikh Bekir... this village around his.. before us was a
village of the Xwateyan family. He said the family of Isa
Beze's house... those friends are there they accommodated,
accommodated. Our father and grandfather came to him.
Hat cem, de meselok derket wê de.. gundek firotin e were ji
xwa re bikirre.. qale wî kir mera. Dibêje kalkê min jê re wê
de dibê wella ez ê bikirrim... ewa ticarî bû.
Came to him, then a problem arose there.. a village is for
sale come buy it for yourself.. he mentioned him to us. He
says my grandfather says to him there well I will buy it...
he was a merchant.
Qasid kirin û... pere wî hene, pere wê de han bûn... ew pere
anîn..
They sent a messenger and... he has money, the money was
there then... they brought that money..
Mezinên me ji me ra hildane..
Our elders told us..
Radibin digirin ew de dikirrin gund dikirrin.. bi şeşsed û
bîst û pênc zêran dikirrin.. bîst û pênc kîs.. her kîsek
bîst û pênc zêran... eva dikirrin.. piştî dikirrin...
They get up they take him there they buy the village they
buy.. with six hundred and twenty-five gold they buy..
twenty-five bags.. every bag twenty-five gold... this they
buy.. after they buy...
Tab'an hukûmeta Osmanî ye.
Of course it is the Ottoman government.
Tê.. daxwaza navekî dikin? Gund navek xwe lê nîne...
He comes.. they request a name? The village doesn't have a
name on it...
Ev jî tevrî xerbî şikeftek mezin hene. Vê derê qenc dibe?
Giş şkefta de ne. De yavaş yavaş xanîkî mezintir girtin,
qentereme nizam çî.
This is also the western style there is a big cave. It is
good here? They are all in the caves. Then slowly they got a
bigger house, arch I don't know what.
Odekê digirin, qehwe çêdikin, îzina cînarê derdora xwe didin
be nav qehwe dikutin, odê ava dikin, erê.
They take a room, make coffee, give permission to the
neighbors around to come inside crush coffee, build the
room, yes.
Ee mehe zeman îşte.. cê çê dibe. Yavaş yavaş..
Uh with time here.. the place is built. Slowly..
Gund, gund çê dibe, gund mezin dibe.
The village, the village is built, the village gets bigger.
Erê, gund mezin dibe.
Yes, the village gets bigger.
Feqîran... niha te min re min te pirse, devê gundî Feqîran
navê wî çima Feqîran gotin... ev tu ser min buhuştî.. Xalê
min.
Faqiran... now you to me I asked you, regarding the village
Faqiran why did they call its name Faqiran... this you
skipped for me.. My uncle.
Xarziyê min.. bavo.. berî gişka be gund re digotin
Baterkiyê.
My nephew.. father.. before everyone they called the village
Baterkiye.
Baterkiyê.
Erê.. anî hêzîna min Qîbarê, Qestelê, wê da digotin, ne
digotin Feqîran, digotin Baterkiyê.
Yes.. I mean my power Qibara, Qastel, there they called it,
they didn't say Faqiran, they called it Baterkiye.
Baterkiyê.
Baterkiye.
Eh... ji kî re derket ev Baterkiye em jî nizanin... Feqîro
ji kî re derket em nizanin..
Eh... who did this Baterkiye come from we also don't know...
Faqiro who did it come from we don't know..
Baterkiyê ji ajî tirkan e.. loma digotin Baterkiye.
Baterkiye is from the Turkish root.. that's why they called
it Baterkiye.
Belê.
Yes.
Wekî mezinê me jî me re hildaye ehsayê tirkan digere...
Like our elders also told us the Turkish census was
wandering...
Li gunda.. digot ehsa hat rûniştin, lî mezinê li ha derdorê
rûniştin.. ê ku pirsê dike.
In the villages.. he said the census came and sat, the
elders sat around here.. the one who asks questions.
Ev berî gîf û tiştê reş di danin ser xwe..
This before they put gif and black things on themselves..
Ew mezin.. berî zemana xwe di gîf û tiştê reş didane serî
xwe. Erê.
Those elders.. before their time they put gif and black
things on their heads. Yes.
Digot.. lîjne pirs kir... navê gundê we çî ye..
He said.. the committee asked... what is the name of your
village..
Li hev sêrkirin... fedi kirin bêjin Baterkiye.
They looked at each other... they were ashamed to say
Baterkiye.
E.. fedi kirin bêjin... digot yekê ji mezina fêhm kir awê
ye.. di Qerabaş e.
Uh.. they were ashamed to say... he said one of the elders
understood it is that.. in Qarabash.
Goya as bi manê ku ava serê me reş in.
As if by the meaning that our heads are black.
A wî esnê de heta nika... we sal danîn navê gund Qerabaş.
At that moment until now... they put the name of the village
Qarabash.
Qerabaş?
Qarabash?
Qerabaş... e..tercuma sûriye ku na hemza sê... wî axiriyê wî
axiriyê... navê xeyrandin gotin Ra's el Eswed.
Qarabash... uh.. Syrian translation which no hamza three...
that lastly lastly... changed the name they said Ras al-
Aswad.
Ra's el Eswed.
Ras al-Aswad.
U lugga şabîyê jî Feqîran.. erê.. dîrokê Êzîdiyan da...
xarziyê min mezin...
And popular language also Faqiran.. yes.. in the history of
Yazidis... my big nephew...
Şêx hene, û Pîr hene.
There are Sheikhs, and there are Pirs.
Şêx bi firtiqana yanê, Şêx Hesenî ne, Şêx Ebûbekirî ne, Şêx
Mendî ne... Ha ba yanê... Bes Pîr, ha wija nînin. Pîrê
Omerxala ne, noka em Pîrê Omerxala ne, erê.
Sheikhs are divided into branches, they are Şêx Hesenî, Şêx
Ebûbekirî, Şêx Mendî... Like this... But Pirs, there aren't
that many. They are Pîrê Omerxala, right now we are Pîrê
Omerxala, yes.
Û dereceya dîn da, pîr û mirîd berê hebûn. Şêx jî paşê tayîn
bûn. Demekî...
And in the degree of religion, there used to be Pirs and
Murids. Sheikhs were appointed later. This means...
Şêx, yanê cem miletê me muqades in.
Sheikhs, they are considered holy by our people.
Belê.
Yes.
Mirîd yanê sala xêrê xwe lê dikin, meselan.
Murids give them their charity every year, for example.
Meselan, rastî wan hatin, radibin ser piyan, destê wan maç
dikin, bi îhtîraman. Yanê ew qeder. Erê Şêx wisa ne.
For example, if they meet them, they stand up, kiss their
hands, with respect. Meaning, that much. Yes, Sheikhs are
like that.
Pîr, nabe ji mirîdan bizewicin? Pîr hene, şêx hene, û mirîd
hene.
Pirs, can't they marry Murids? There are Pirs, there are
Sheikhs, and there are Murids.
Belê.
Yes.
Şêx, her firtiqek bi hev re dizewicin. Nabe ji mirîdan
bizewicin. Muharrem e. Muharrem e.
Sheikhs, each branch marries within themselves. They cannot
marry Murids. It's forbidden. It's forbidden.
Ê pîran jî nefsî tiştî muharrem e. Ji mirîdan bizewicin, yan
ji şêxan bizewicin. Muharrem e ew jî, muharrem e. Îla her
yek ji malbata xwe, yanê ya xwe, fexdê xwe.
The same thing applies to Pirs, it's forbidden. To marry
Murids, or to marry Sheikhs. That is forbidden too, it's
forbidden. Only each from their own family, meaning their
own, their own branch.
Ev, ev cem miletê me heye.
This, this exists among our people.
Ev ji aliyê zewacê da.
This is in terms of marriage.
Erê ev jî zewacê da. Bes...
Yes, this is in marriage. But...
Xêncî wê çi adet û teqalîdên we hene, çaxê dibêjin şahî
hebin, eydên we meselan...
Besides that, what customs and traditions do you have, for
example, when there are weddings, your holidays...
Bes ev muharemat hene, ku goştê xenzîr muharrem e.
But there are these prohibitions, like pork is forbidden.
Ev cem we jî muharrem e?
This is forbidden for you too?
Erê, hemî dizanin. Û cem me xas muharrem e.
Yes, everyone knows. And for us, lettuce is forbidden.
Dewatê me, nefsî wekî dewatê kurmanca. Nefsî kurmancin em.
Dewatê me adî ne. Dawet adî ye. Dêmekî xwastek...
Our weddings are just like Kurdish weddings. We are Kurds
ourselves. Our weddings are normal. The wedding is normal.
It means, asking for the bride...
...derin, xwedanê zêva, keçekê ji lawê xwe re dixwazin,
qelend dibirin, qelend jî muteqîq heseb îtîfaqiyê.
...they go, the groom's family, they ask for a girl for
their son, they bring the dowry, the dowry is determined by
agreement.
Û diftilin daweta xwe dikin, diftilin dewatê xwe dikin.
And they return to hold their wedding, they return and hold
their wedding.
Adî, wekî kurmancên kî derê bin em mîna wan e yanê erê.
Dewatê dikin, xelata dikin, diherin dewatê xwe dikin wek
wisa.
Normal, like wherever Kurds are, we are like them, yes. They
hold weddings, give gifts, go and have their weddings like
that.
Şixrê digotin şixrê. Çi qas paleyî, şixrê, zirayet, bi merya
bû. Û bi dewêr dikişandin, bo ardî bêdera, bêder da danîn,
yê filanî hevbû, filanî hevbû, filanî hevbû, filanî... deka.
They used to call working, shighre. Harvesting, working,
farming, was done by people. And they transported it with
animals, to the threshing floor, placing it on the threshing
floor, so-and-so had some, so-and-so had some, so-and-so had
some... right.
Pale, û şixrê xelas kirin, şixre yanê cerin. Yanê kişandin,
komkirin hene. Ku xelas kirin bêderê dest bi cêrcêrê
dikirin, cêrcêr girêdidan, bêder xwe dikutan. Gelî cem hebin
kînekî heye.
The harvesters finished the work, working means bringing.
Meaning pulling, gathering. When they finished, they started
threshing, they tied the threshing sled, they threshed their
crops. Everyone had some together.
Bêder xelas bûn ba wê dikirin. Genimê xwe, dibirin dihiştin.
Zexîreyê xwe temîn dikirin. Bulxurê xwe dikelandin temîn
dikirin. Ko dikişandin... Ko dikişandin dewêrê xwara. Dewêrê
xwara. Ê cîhê xwe, a gîhayê xwe... ew bû.
When threshing was finished, they would do it. They would
take their wheat and store it. They would secure their
provisions. They would boil their bulgur and secure it.
Where they transported... Where they transported it with
their animals. Their own animals. Their space, their
grass... that was it.
Kesî bê dewêr tine bû. Teraktor ebeden li gundê me tinebûn.
Li gundê me tine bû, çunkî cot bi dewêran bû.
No one was without animals. There were absolutely no
tractors in our village. There wasn't any in our village,
because plowing was done with animals.
1956-an da me mekteb berda.
In 1956, we left school.
1956-an da...
In 1956...
Berdan. Di 56-an da bo çi em?
Left. Why did we in '56?
Bavê min û Îhsanê Çolax hebûn, ortaxê hev bûn, dîrektorê
kerî. Teraktor, navê wî teraktor... Yên ku kesî de tine bû,
wan çû şirîkatî kirin.
My father and Ihsan Cholax were partners, the director of
the herd. A tractor, it was called a tractor... Back when no
one had one, they went and partnered up.
Bira kêm çû eskeriyê. Ji mamosteyê tir... Ez mektebê
derxistim.
My younger brother went to the military. Fearing the
teacher... They took me out of school.
Çunkî me pirsker, dibêjin mekteb li gund tinene...
Because we asked, they say there are no schools in the
village...
Erê, em çûne Çolaxa. Çolaxa nêzîk e. Gundê me û Çolaxa. Berê
me daye vir...
Yes, we went to Cholaxa. Cholaxa is close. Our village and
Cholaxa. We headed here...
Nefsî, ez diçûme Çolaxa. Ev gundê wî wextî tinebû. Di xaniyê
gund ê ku vala bû...
Myself, I used to go to Cholaxa. There wasn't one in the
village at that time. In an empty village house...
Yekî boş bû, yan der bû. Me jê dest standin mekteb tê de
vekir ibtîdaî. Îca me...
One was empty, or outside. We took it over and opened a
primary school in it. Then we...
Ew çaxê, ew orta, xwedanê aîleya me ye.
At that time, that partner, is the head of our family.
Belê. Me zarokên xwe dişandin.
Yes. We would send our children.
Werê... Berê em çûne Çolaxa. Di 1956-an da mekteba Çolaxa
wisa girtin, heta Îbtîdaî...
Like that... Before, we went to Cholaxa. In 1956, they
closed the school in Cholaxa like that, until primary...
Paşê, me îbtîdaî xelas kir, em çûne Efrînê. Efrîn me xwend.
Ez diçûme Terendê min xew dikir... Adetê, sibê dihatime
mektebê, û diçûm. Êvarî, mekteb taybet, diçûme Terendê, min
xew dikir nêzîk e, wisa...
Then, we finished primary school, we went to Afrin. We
studied in Afrin. I would go to Terende and sleep...
Usually, I would come to school in the morning, and go. In
the evening, a special school, I would go to Terende, I
would sleep there, it's close, like that...
Paşê di sala 1977-an da, ez bûme ajokarê teksiyê. Teksîyeka
me hebû. Rêka gund, Efrîn ereba xwe diçû dajo. Belê. Erê şab
bû merî...
Then in 1977, I became a taxi driver. We had a taxi. On the
village road, he would drive his car to Afrin. Yes. Yes, one
was happy...
Erebê hedîdiyê mala Nehwêfê derbas dibin. Reîsê hedîdîyan
ne... Em çûn li Efrînê mesele, digotin hûn xwediyê we ne. Em
çûn çiyayê mesele, min got: go derne Têra, makîne we we me
ra bo ortaxê.
The Hadid Arabs of Nehwef's family passed by. The chief of
the Hadids wasn't... We went to Afrin for a matter, they
were saying we are your masters. We went to the mountain, I
said: don't go to Tera, your car with us for the partner.
Masrafê te, gî ser min, heta cixare jî ser min. Benzîn, zêt,
makîne gî ser min, û çûm ev girt, firot bi nîvê... nîvê
xwe... nîvê xwe we... Bes makîne teşkîlatî dît...
Your expenses, all on me, even cigarettes on me. Gas, oil,
the car, all on me, and I went, took it, sold it for half...
half... half... half of yours... But the car setup...
Di 1967-an de, 67-an de ez zewicîm e. U wî senetî... Vî
senetî... Wela qîza mamê min e.
In 1967, in 67 I got married. And that year... That year...
By God, she is my cousin.
Min bar nedaye. Heta 2011 min dewam kir.
I haven't quit. I continued until 2011.
Xalo, yanê we kar li kî derê dikir?
Uncle, where did you work?
Bavê min û birayê min ê ewilî mehsûlekî dikir. Berê em diçûn
deşta Sûriyê, diçûn Cizîrê, û paşê...
My father and my older brother used to grow crops. We used
to go to the Syrian plains, to Cizire, and then...
...Cizîrê. Cizîrê me dikir, me av dikir, ew sala ewilî, û
sala diduyan jî. Paşê em çûne Iraqê. Me li Iraqê kar dikir.
...Cizire. We worked in Cizire, we irrigated, that was the
first year, and the second year too. Then we went to Iraq.
We worked in Iraq.
Saetên te xweş xalo. Spasiya te dikim.
Bless you uncle. I thank you.
[Muzîk]
[Music]
Belê temaşevanên me yên hêja. Niha em gihîştin dawiya xeleka
bernameya îro. Wek hûn dibînin ku roj li pişt min çûye ava.
Ez û xalê Hecî Ehmed, em ê ji gundê Feqîra xatir ji we
bixwazin. Bi hêviya ku hûn demeke xweş biborînin. Li bendî
me bin bi xelekeke nû û ji cihekî nû.
Yes, our esteemed viewers. Now we have reached the end of
today's episode. As you can see, the sun has set behind me.
Uncle Haji Ahmed and I will bid you farewell from the
village of Faqira. Hoping that you have a good time. Wait
for us with a new episode and from a new place.
[Muzîk]
[Music]