جويق القرية الجبلية الجميلة جدا في ريف عفرين الغربي كما
ذكرنا في الحلقة السابقة
Jweq, the very beautiful mountainous village in the western
countryside of Afrin, as we mentioned in the previous
episode,
كان لها أهمية جغرافية وسياسية كبيرة في عموم منطقة عفرين
had great geographical and political importance in the
entire Afrin region.
وذلك بسبب النشاط الحزبي والسياسي لأبنائها وبسبب كثرة
الشهادات الجامعية من كافة التخصصات لهم.
This is due to the partisan and political activity of its
people, and the abundance of university degrees in all
specializations among them.
تتربع هذه القرية ما بين نهر عفرين وقرية قرتلاق شمالا، وقرية
داركير غربا.
This village is situated between the Afrin River and the
village of Qartlaq to the north, and the village of Darkir
to the west.
نسبة كبيرة من أبنائها كانوا يسكنون في مدينة حلب سابقا
A large percentage of its people previously lived in the
city of Aleppo,
وخاصة في أحياء بستان الباشا والأشرفية.
especially in the Bustan al-Basha and Ashrafieh
neighborhoods.
أما الآن فإن معظمهم مهاجرون إلى تركيا وأوروبا للعمل والدراسة
كما قلنا سابقا.
Now, however, most of them have migrated to Turkey and
Europe for work and study, as we mentioned earlier.
يتداخل في هذه القرية القديم التراثي بالحديث المبدع بشكل ملفت
للنظر
In this village, the traditional old intertwines with the
creative modern in an eye-catching way,
ليشكل لوحة إبداعية جميلة.
forming a beautiful, creative canvas.
ترتفع عن سطح البحر 440 مترا، ويعتبر مناخها معتدلا صيفا،
باردا شتاء.
It is 440 meters above sea level, and its climate is
considered moderate in summer and cold in winter.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
يعطيكم العافية. نتعرف عليك؟
God give you health. Can we get to know you?
وحيد بكر.
Wahid Bakr.
يا أهلا وسهلا فيك يا سيد وحيد. وحيد الحلاق الوحيد في الضيعة؟
Welcome, Mr. Wahid. Wahid, are you the only barber in the
village?
لا في عدة حلاقين.
No, there are several barbers.
إيه خمسة نحن.
Several barbers?
Yes, there are five of us.
قديش صار لك إنت هون؟
How long have you been here?
ست سنين.
Six years.
ست سنين، وحضرتك؟
Six years. And you?
أنا من ريف حماه.
I am from the countryside of Hama.
مهجر إيه.
Displaced here?
Yes, displaced.
يا أهلين وسهلين. هلق شو عم تحلق له؟ على ذوقك ولا على ذوقه؟
Welcome. Now, what kind of haircut are you giving him? Your
choice or his?
لا على ذوقه.
No, his choice.
شو ذوقه هلق هو؟
What is his preference now?
ذوقه هو بده يخفف وحنجرة، يعني يخفف دقن ويحنجر له إياها.
His preference is to trim and shape, meaning trim the beard
and shape the neckline.
وأنت شو ذوقك؟
And what is your preference?
[يضحك]
[laughs]
أنت بتحلق له على الزيرو؟
Do you give him a zero-guard shave?
لا هو طلب مني بدي احلق له إياها.
No, he asked me to, I will shave it for him.
شو الحلاقات اللي هون، أنواع الحلاقات اللي بيحلقوها الشباب
هون؟ القصات شو هي؟
What are the haircuts here, the types of haircuts the young
men get here? What are the styles?
القصات، عدة قصات عندك. عندك مارينز، عندك تركي، هلق بالشكل
العام قصات تركية في، مارينز...
The styles, you have several styles. You have Marines, you
have Turkish. Now, generally, there are Turkish styles,
Marines...
وعادي تدريج.
And a normal fade.
الكبار الختيارية؟
The older men, the elderly?
لا الكبار الختيارية بيختلف، الختيارية بيختلف، يعني حلاقة
تخفيف عادي، عالمقص فوق عادي، حلاقة ركز يعني عادية.
No, the older men are different, the elderly are different.
I mean, a normal trim, with scissors on top normally, a
standard, classic haircut.
والشباب الصغار؟
And the young guys?
الشباب الصغار عالموضة.
The young guys follow the fashion.
عالموضة.
Following the fashion.
عالموضة، خط وما خط و...
Following the fashion, lines and no lines and...
صار شيء تغيير بالذوق، يعني ذوق القصات الرجالية خلال هالسنوات
هي ست سبع سنوات الأخيرة؟
Has there been a change in taste, I mean the taste in men's
haircuts over these past six or seven years?
والله تغير إيه.
Well, yes, it has changed.
شلون؟ يعني هي القصات ما كانت سابقا؟
How? I mean, these styles weren't around before?
لا شلون بدي أقول لك... كل سنة سنة بيطلع شيء جديد، كل سنة سنة
بيطلع شيء جديد.
No, how can I say it... every year or so something new comes
out, every year or so something new comes out.
في شيء هون قصة للضيعة لجويق خاصة فيها مثلا؟ أو قريبة يعني
مثلا أهل عفرين بيقصوا نفس الشيء؟
Is there a specific haircut for the village, for Jweq in
particular, for example? Or something similar, I mean, do
the people of Afrin get the same haircut?
لا ما في، ما في.
No, there isn't, there isn't.
خلينا نسأل هالزلمة هاد، مبسوط من الحلاقة هي اللي عم يحلق لك
إياها الزلمة؟
Let's ask this man. Are you happy with this haircut the man
is giving you?
إيه الله يعطيه العافية معلم.
Yes, may God give him health, a master.
عاجبك؟ ما قصك ما ضربك شيء ضربة هيك؟
Do you like it? Did he cut you or nick you or anything?
لا لا لا ما في هالحكي لا معلم الله يعطيه العافية.
No, no, no, there's none of that. No, a master, may God give
him health.
مجربه سابقا؟
Have you tried him before?
إيه هي ثالث مرة بحلق عنده أنا.
Yes, this is the third time I get a haircut from him.
ثالث مرة؟
The third time?
إيه الله يعطيه العافية.
Yes, may God give him health.
إنت قديش بتجي لهون؟
How often do you come here?
أنا بشكل دائم أنا هون أنا عازف أورغ، فالفرقة موجودة هون
بالضيعة هون.
I am here permanently. I'm a keyboard player, and the band
is located here in the village.
لا أنا أقصد كل قديش بتحلق عنده؟
No, I meant how often do you get a haircut from him?
كل أسبوع عشر أيام، أسبوع عشر أيام تقريبا بتحنجر عادي، الشعر
يعني على العشرين خمسة وعشرين يوم.
Every week or ten days, week or ten days approximately, a
normal shaping. The hair, I mean, every twenty or twenty-
five days.
كويس.
Good.
إيه سيدي نعيما.
Yes sir, may it be blessed (Naeeman).
الله ينعم عليك ويبارك فيك يا طيب.
May God bless you and bless your life, good man.
الله يكرمك، السلام عليكم. شكرا إلك.
May God honor you, peace be upon you. Thank you.
وعليكم السلام، على راسي، أهلا وسهلا بحضرتك.
And upon you be peace, on my head, welcome to you.
مرحبا عمو.
Hello, uncle.
شلونك؟
How are you?
شو اسمك إنت؟
What is your name?
شو اسمك؟
بنتك؟
Your daughter?
لا بنت ابني.
No, my son's daughter.
بنت ابنك؟ يا أهلا وسهلا، السلام عليكم.
Your son's daughter? Welcome, peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, and the mercy of God and His
blessings.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا أهلا وسهلا.
May God give you health, welcome.
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
فؤاد بكر.
Fouad Bakr.
فؤاد بكر. من جويق؟
Fouad Bakr. From Jweq?
من جويق.
From Jweq.
يا أهلا وسهلا فيك.
Welcome.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
قد ايش صار لك فاتح الدكان؟
How long have you had the shop open?
صار لي 28 سنة.
It's been 28 years.
28 سنة بنفس هذا المكان؟
28 years in this same place?
نفس المكان.
The same place.
ما غيرت الصنعة؟
You didn't change your profession?
لا ما غيرت الصنعة.
No, I didn't change my profession.
طيب احكي لي هالأيام شلون وضع الناس باعتبارك إنت يعني الناس
تشتري من عندك وتبيع، يعني تشتري من عندك.
Alright, tell me, how is the people's situation these days,
considering that you... I mean, people buy from you and
sell, I mean, buy from you.
والله الناس بيجوا بالزمن يعني أنا فاتح المحل، بيجوا بياخذوا
أغراض، وعم الحمد لله عم ماشي أمورنا وعم ماشي أمور الزباين.
Well, people come... over the time I've had the shop open,
they come and buy goods, and thank God, our matters are
going well, and the customers' matters are going well.
وعم يمشي الحال يعني الأمور هيك.
And things are going alright, I mean, things are like that.
شلون القوة الشرائية للناس؟ معهم مصاري عم يشتروا؟
How is the purchasing power of the people? Do they have
money, are they buying?
والله هالوضع الناس تعبانين، هالوضع ما عندهم مصاري.
Well, in this situation, people are tired. In this
situation, they don't have money.
بس الأول كان الشغل أحسن من هيك.
But before, work was better than this.
أحسن مو هيك؟ هلا إنت شو بتبيع؟
Better, right? Now, what do you sell?
والله بنبيع أغراض، مثل سكر، شاي...
Well, we sell goods, like sugar, tea...
سمانة يعني كل شيء؟
Groceries, meaning everything?
سمانة يعني، منظفات، شغلات البيوت يعني، شغلات النظافات،
سمانة، منظفات، ما منظفات هيك.
Groceries, I mean. Detergents, household stuff, I mean
cleaning supplies, groceries, detergents and such.
الأسعار شلون اليوم هون؟
How are the prices today here?
والله هلق غالي الأسعار.
Well, right now the prices are high.
غالي مو هيك؟
High, right?
غالي جدا.
Very high.
في شيء هون يعني شغل الضيعة بينباع مثلا لبن، حليب، جبنة، كذا،
باعتبارها بلد زراعي، زيت، زيتون...
Is there anything here, I mean, village-made products sold,
like yogurt, milk, cheese, and so on, considering it's an
agricultural town? Oil, olives...
زيتون... من هون، إيه بتنباع كل شيء. لبن، ما لبن، حليب، زيت،
زيتون، عطون، يعني الشغلات الـ...
Olives... from here, yes, everything is sold. Yogurt and
such, milk, oil, olives, Attun (cured black olives), I mean
the things...
أنت بتبيع عندك هون بالمحل؟
Do you sell them here in your shop?
والله أحيانا... أحيانا نجيب لبن وما لبن، أحيانا.
Well, sometimes... sometimes we bring yogurt and such,
sometimes.
طيب كم محل في بالضيعة هون؟
Alright, how many shops are there in the village here?
في بيجي 10 محلات.
There are around 10 shops.
10 محلات؟ تقريبا.
10 shops? Approximately.
تقريبا.
Approximately.
الله يرزقكم يا رب، الله يعطيك العافية، شكرا إلك، السلام
عليكم.
May God provide for you. May God give you health. Thank you.
Peace be upon you.
الله يوفقكم، أهلا مية سلامة، شرفتونا.
May God grant you success. Welcome, a hundred greetings. You
honored us.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
ممكن أحكي معكم هيك شوي دردشة شوي معكم؟
Can I talk to you a bit, just a little chat with you?
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
حضرتك فاتحة محل؟
Have you opened a shop?
لا والله.
No, honestly.
تفضلي لهون شوي ليش خجلتي؟ تعي تعي تعي ليكي أنا واقف هون لو
سمحتي.
Please come here a bit, why are you shy? Come, come, come,
look, I'm standing here, please.
الاسم الكريم؟
Your good name?
جميلة عثمان.
Jamila Othman.
أهلا وسهلا فيكي. زبونة جاية تشتري من هون؟
Welcome. A customer coming to buy from here?
إيه.
Yes.
الأخت هون؟
The sister here?
مدينة دادو.
Madina Dado.
يا أهلا وسهلا كمان من هون؟
Welcome. Also from here?
الله يسلمك. إيه.
May God keep you safe. Yes.
وقفي هون شوي خلينا نحكي شوي لو سمحتي.
Stand here a bit, let's talk a little, please.
هذا محل بيع ألبسة في غيره هون؟
This is a clothing store. Are there others here?
لا والله ما في غير هالمحل.
No, honestly, there is no other store.
بس هذا المحل؟
Just this store?
إيه مبلى.
Yes, definitely.
من زمان ولا هلا بس ما في؟
Since a long time or just now there are none?
لا من زمان هون.
No, it's been here for a long time.
من زمان.
For a long time.
إيه شو ببيع هون؟
Yes. What does it sell here?
أغراض، يعني كنزات، بناطيل، هيك شيء.
Items, I mean sweaters, pants, things like that.
ولادي، نسائي...
Children's, women's...
ولادي، كل شيء فيه.
Children's, it has everything.
بتاع كله؟
Sells everything?
إيه مبلى.
Yes, definitely.
يعني ما بتحتاجوا تنزلوا على عفرين؟
So you don't need to go down to Afrin?
ننزل بس قليل.
We go down, but rarely.
قليل. عموما الكبارية هون شو بيلبسوا؟
Rarely. Generally, what do the older people wear here?
بناطيل، كنزات، شباب بيلبسوا بناطيل كنزات.
Pants, sweaters. Young men wear pants and sweaters.
عم أحكي عن النساء.
I am talking about women.
نساء، فساتين يعني.
Women, dresses, I mean.
فساتين، لأن الرجال الكبار بيلبسوا شروال.
Dresses, because the older men wear baggy trousers
(Shirwal).
إيه. بس النسوان بيلبسوا فساتين، هيك شغلات.
Yes. But women wear dresses, things like that.
فساتين.
Dresses.
إيه مبلى.
Yes, definitely.
شلون الأسعار هون؟
How are the prices here?
الحمد لله لا منيحا.
Thank God, no, they are good.
والله مو زيادة. كثير غالي. كثير غالي صاير.
Honestly, not so much. Very expensive. It's gotten very
expensive.
أغلى من عفرين؟
More expensive than Afrin?
أغلى من عفرين.
More expensive than Afrin.
لا عفرين أغلى من هون.
No, Afrin is more expensive than here.
هون أرخص؟
Here is cheaper?
هون أرخص.
Here is cheaper.
الله يعينكم والله يعطيكم العافية يا رب والله يرزقكم. السلام
عليكم، شكرا لكم.
May God help you, and may God give you health, and may God
provide for you. Peace be upon you, thank you.
الله يسلمك أهلاً مية سلامة.
May God keep you safe. Welcome, a hundred greetings.
شرفتونا.
You honored us.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
تحسن الظروف الاقتصادية والاستقرار اللي عم تعيشه جويق بالفترة
الأخيرة
The improvement in economic conditions and the stability
that Jweq has been experiencing lately,
إضافة إلى الحاجة إلى فرص عمل للناس اللي عاطلين عن العمل من
فترة طويلة بسبب الظروف الاقتصادية والاجتماعية الأخيرة،
in addition to the need for job opportunities for people who
have been unemployed for a long time due to recent economic
and social conditions,
خلت أحد أبناء هالقرية يفتح ورشة للخياطة.
prompted one of the sons of this village to open a sewing
workshop.
رح ندخل معكم لداخل هالورشة نتعرف عليها ونتعرف أيضا على فرص
العمل اللي موفرتها،
We will go with you inside this workshop to learn about it,
and also to learn about the job opportunities it provides,
وعلى طبيعة إنتاجها ووين بتصرفه، تفضلوا معنا.
and the nature of its production and where it is
distributed. Please come with us.
يا رب. السلام عليكم.
Oh Lord. Peace be upon you.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله، أهلا وسهلا.
Thank God, welcome.
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
جوان، من جويق.
Jiwan, from Jweq.
أهلا وسهلا فيك.
Welcome.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
صاحب الورشة؟
The owner of the workshop?
أنا صاحب الورشة.
I am the owner of the workshop.
احكيلي عن الورشة؟
Tell me about the workshop.
والله نحن بنشتغل مصانعة، بنجيب شغل من برا وعم نجيبه عالورشة
وكل صانع بيشتغل...
Well, we work on a manufacturing basis. We bring work from
outside and bring it to the workshop, and every worker
works...
يعني أنتم معناها هي البضاعة مو إلكن؟
So you mean these goods are not yours?
لا مو إحنا، هدول جابوها من عفرين.
No, not us, they brought these from Afrin.
من عفرين؟ من شركة ريان؟
From Afrin? From the Rayan company?
إيه شركة ريان.
Yes, Rayan company.
بتجيبوها بتصنعوها لحسابهم؟
You bring them and manufacture them for their account?
للمصانعة.
For manufacturing.
للمصانعة وبتاخذوا أجرتها؟
For manufacturing, and you take the wage for it?
إيه أجرتي. أنا بشتغل مصانعة.
Yes, my wage. I work in manufacturing.
كم فرصة عمل هون؟ يعني كم شغّيل؟
How many job opportunities are here? I mean, how many
workers?
هدول هنه، تقريبا شي 10.
These are them, approximately about 10.
10، بيشتغلوا كم ساعة؟
10. How many hours do they work?
تقريبا 9 ساعات.
Approximately 9 hours.
9 ساعات كل نهار. في ورشة، في جويق تاني ولا بس هاي؟
9 hours every day. Is there another workshop in Jweq, or
just this one?
لا بس هاي.
No, just this one.
كم بياخد العامل هون؟
How much does a worker earn here?
والله حسب العامل، في منهم صغار بياخدوا 35، في منهم 50،
تقريبا...
Well, it depends on the worker. Some of them are young and
take 35, some of them 50, approximately...
50 شو؟
50 what?
50 ألف.
50 thousand.
بالجمعة؟
Per week?
بالجمعة. بالأسبوعية.
Per week. As a weekly wage.
تمام، إنتاجكم شلون؟
Alright, how is your production?
حسب الأسبوع.
Depending on the week.
حسب الأسبوع، في أسبوع 1000 قطعة، في 1200 قطعة، تقريبا هيك
يعني.
Depending on the week. Some weeks 1000 pieces, some 1200
pieces, approximately like that, I mean.
تمام، موفقين يا رب.
Alright, wishing you success.
Tamam. Bas entu bima inno bitkunu entu ya'ni bitsarfuha aw
btsawquha? La, sharike hiye.
Okay. But do you... do you sell or market them yourself? Is
it a company?
La la, nahna bas mnishitghel masna'.
No, no, we just work as a factory.
Hiye btejiblekun l-kmash?
Do they bring you the fabric?
Ewa, huwe saheb l-shighel, nahna bas ssan'a, kheyata, bas
kheyata.
Yes, the business owner does, we just do the manufacturing,
the sewing, only the sewing.
Taswiq 'alekun?
Is the marketing on you?
La, mo 'aleina. Bas kheyata.
No, it's not on us. Just sewing.
Entu bas bitkhaytu?
You just sew?
Bas kheyata.
Just sewing.
Ya'ni hala' l-yom saraha hal-warshe hay,
So, honestly, today, does this workshop
bit'ayesh hal-'ashra aw khamstashar shakhis yalli 'am
byishtighlu hon?
provide a living for the ten or fifteen people working here?
Bala.
Yes.
Byi'ishu hon?
They make a living here?
E, b-hay shaghle.
Yes, with this job.
Kil shakhis ilu 'ayle min wara?
Does each person have a family behind them?
Kil shakhis fi 'ayle min wara.
Each person has a family behind them.
O 'ummalakun min wein?
And where are your workers from?
Killon min d-de'a. Killon min hal-de'a.
All of them are from the village. All of them are from this
village.
Ahli Jweq?
The people of Jweq?
Killon min Jweq.
All of them are from Jweq.
Fi shi min l-muhajerin hon?
Are there any displaced people here?
La, ma fi. Killon ahli Jweq.
No, there aren't. All of them are the people of Jweq.
Had l-makan shu kan hon sabiqan?
What was this place previously?
Hada kan awwali ma'sara.
This used to be an olive press.
Ma'saret zetun?
An olive press?
Ma'saret zetun, ma'saret 'adim hada.
An olive press, an old press.
Ewa. Entu jitu ta'amaltu, o...
I see. You came and operated it, and...
Ewa, o dallelna l-yom.
Yes, and we stayed until today.
Ya sidi Allah yirzi'ak ya rab w yiftah 'alek.
My man, may God bless you and open doors for you.
W nshuf sh-shabab kaman.
Let's see the guys too.
E, biddi shuf sh-shabab. Biddi ehki ma' hal-shabb.
Yes, I want to see the guys. I want to talk to this young
man.
Salam 'alekum.
Peace be upon you.
'Alekum s-salam w rahmatullah.
Peace be upon you and the mercy of God.
Allah ya'tik l-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afik ya rab.
May God give you health too.
Nita'arraf 'alek.
Let's get to know you.
Ismi Muhammad wallah.
My name is Muhammad.
Ahlan w sahlan.
Welcome.
Hala' enta shu ayy marhale 'am tishtighel hon?
Now, what stage are you working on here?
Wallah hadol bisammuhun jyab sa'a.
Well, these are called watch pockets.
Jyab sa'a?
Watch pockets?
E.
Yes.
Enta bitkhayet jyab s-sa'a?
You sew the watch pockets?
E.
Yes.
Sh'ad sarlak b-hal mihne?
How long have you been in this profession?
Wallah sar li bil alfein w tlati taqriban.
I've been in it since around 2003.
Min l-alfein w tlati?
Since 2003?
E.
Yes.
Shtaghalt hon w shtaghalt b-Afrin, wein shtaghalt?
Have you worked here and in Afrin, where have you worked?
Kint awwal shi ishtighel b-Halab.
I first used to work in Aleppo.
Abl s-sawra?
Before the revolution?
Ewa.
Yes.
W ba'dein jitu la-hon?
And then you came here?
Ba'dein ijina la-hon. Nazahna la-hon.
Then we came here. We were displaced here.
Shlon shayef s-shighel b-hal warshe?
How do you see the work in this workshop?
Wallah l-hamdulillah. Mashi l-hal l-hamdulillah.
By God, thank God. It's going well, thank God.
L-hamdulillah.
Thank God.
Ma fakart shi nhar tiftah warshe la-halak?
Haven't you thought of opening a workshop for yourself one
day?
Wallah ma fi imkaniye.
I don't have the means.
Mitzawwej?
Are you married?
E.
Yes.
Shu 'andak awlad?
How many children do you have?
Wallah 'andi wahid, w nshallah wahid 'a-tariq.
I have one, and hopefully, one on the way.
Allah yikhallihun ya rab.
May God protect them.
Allah ysalmak.
May God keep you safe.
Nshallah l-ajir lli 'am takhdu munasib?
Hopefully, the wage you are getting is suitable?
Wallah l-hamdulillah. Ahsan min balakih.
Yes, thank God. Better than nothing.
'Andak ared kaman 'ayesh minha?
Do you also have land you make a living from?
Wallah e l-hamdulillah. Fi.
Yes, thank God. I have.
L-hamdulillah.
Thank God.
Shi miyyet shajaret zetun.
About a hundred olive trees.
Ni'met Allah.
A blessing from God.
L-hamdulillah.
Thank God.
Allah yirzi'kun.
May God bless you.
Tislam ya ghali.
Thank you, dear.
Shukran elak.
Thank you.
Tislam.
Thanks.
Salam 'alekum.
Peace be upon you.
Allah ya'tikun l-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Matar w 'am tir'a.
It's raining and you are herding.
Allah ya'tik l-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Shlonak?
How are you?
Allah yihayyik.
May God greet you.
Ahlan fik, ya hala.
Welcome to you.
Min d-de'a min hon?
Are you from the village here?
Wallah saraha la' ana.
Honestly, no.
Ya ahla w sahla fik.
You are very welcome.
Had wadi Dargir mo hek?
This is Wadi Dargir, isn't it?
Wallah ma ba'ref ana hal qita'at ma ba'rifa.
Well, I don't know, I don't know these areas.
Ma bta'rifa. Ma nak min hon?
You don't know it. You are not from here?
Lakan min wein?
No.
Then where are you from?
Ana min rif Halab j-janubi, nazih hon.
I am from the southern countryside of Aleppo, displaced
here.
Ahlan w sahlan fik.
You are very welcome.
'Andak kam ghaname?
How many sheep do you have?
Wallahi 'adadon b-zabit, akhi l-yom ya'ni ta'dad, ta'dad bi-
zabit ma b'arif.
Honestly, their exact number, brother, today, like a count,
an exact count, I don't know.
Taqribi?
Approximately?
Ya'ni hawali tis'in yumkin, tmanin... ma ba'rif.
I mean, maybe around ninety, eighty... I don't know.
Inshallah. Gharib inno ma bta'rif l-ghanemat, akhi imshi
shway.
Hopefully. It's strange that you don't know the sheep,
brother, walk a little.
Ana ra'i, ra'i.
I am a shepherd, a shepherd.
Enta ra'i!
You are a shepherd!
Ra'i, ra'i.
A shepherd, a shepherd.
Aywa. Ra'i la-kil d-de'a walla bas hal ghanamat?
Oh, I see. A shepherd for the whole village or just these
sheep?
La, zalama hada 'andu ghanam w ana asrah fiyyon.
No, a man has these sheep and I herd them.
Aywa, aywa. Had sh-shabb ibnak had?
I see, I see. Is this young boy your son?
Ibni, e.
My son, yes.
Masha'Allah. Allah yikhallih.
As God willed. May God keep him safe.
Allah ysallmak.
May God keep you safe.
Shlonak?
How are you?
L-hamdulillah.
Thank God.
Nt'arraf 'alek?
Let's get to know you?
'Abd l-Malik.
Abd Al-Malik.
Ahlein ya 'Abd l-Malik.
Welcome, Abd Al-Malik.
Hada shu ismu ya 'Abd l-Malik, illi lashufak.
What is this called, Abd Al-Malik? Tell me, let's see.
Ghaname.
A sheep.
Ghaname, hada l-marya' walla hada l-marya'?
A sheep. Is this the lead sheep or is this the lead sheep?
Hada.
This one.
Hada l-marya', w hada?
This is the lead sheep, and this one?
Jahish.
A goat.
Ahaa, w hada l-jaras?
Aha, and this bell?
Marya'.
Lead sheep.
Marya', jaras l-marya' kaman.
Lead sheep, the bell of the lead sheep too.
Ya'ni fi marya' kabish, w fi marya' teys?
So there is a ram lead sheep, and a goat lead sheep?
E.
Yes.
Fi tnein?
There are two?
E.
Yes.
Ya salam. Ya salam.
Oh wow. Wow.
Hala' iza baddak tqilli, ya'ni yawmiyyet ra'i.
Now if you were to tell me, like, the daily routine of a
shepherd.
R-ra'i min eymat byitla' s-subih 'a-r-ra'iye?
When does the shepherd go out to herd in the morning?
Wallah, b-hal waqt eish, b-sh-shatwiye ma ybakkir.
Well, at this time, in winter, he doesn't go early.
Ya'ni?
Meaning?
Hasab n-nada, hasab ya'ni ta'rif enta...
Depends on the dew, depends, you know...
Ya'ni s-sa'a sh'ad?
I mean, what time?
Yijuz tis'a, yijuz 'ashra, hasab l-ya'ni, l-ghanam hasab ma
tar'a.
Maybe nine, maybe ten, depending, the sheep depend on what
they graze.
W b-s-seyf?
And in the summer?
B-s-seyf liman b-d-dasht, ya'ni yqulu d-dasht u m-l-hasid.
In the summer, when it's in the fields, they say the fields
and the harvest.
E.
Yes.
Ma tehsed l-hassadat akhi wa tasrah l-ghanam.
When the harvesters finish harvesting, brother, you let the
sheep graze.
Eyy sa'a ya'ni s-subih bitla'?
What time in the morning does he go out?
Ya'ni b-l-hasid s-subih ma byinda, 'reft 'aley shlon, b-hal
hasid b-hal sh'ir, ra'i yidman akhi u b-hal hasdan tasrah
l-ghanam.
In the harvest, they don't get covered in dew in the
morning, you know what I mean, in this harvest, in this
barley, a shepherd secures the area, brother, and in these
harvested lands, the sheep graze.
W eymat btirja' l-masa?
And when do you return in the evening?
Byiji z-zuhur
We return at noon.
Ywarrid, ghanam ta'tash b-s-seyf, yhallib akhi z-zuhur, w
tasrah l-'asriyat, w tridd thallib l-maghrib, w tridd.
He takes them to water, sheep get thirsty in the summer, he
milks them, brother, at noon, and they graze in the
afternoon, and then milks them again at sunset, and returns.
Tihlub martein?
You milk them twice?
E. Hala' b-sh-shiti sh'ad tihlub?
Yes. Now in the winter, how much do you milk?
Halbe, hala' ma fi, bas s-subih.
One milking, now there isn't much, just in the morning.
S-subih bas?
Just in the morning?
Bas s-subih.
Just in the morning.
Min s-subih la-s-subih?
From morning to morning?
S-subih nhar talyan minkawwez t-talyan bil leil, wa s-subih
mniflit ha khayo.
In the morning, during the day, the lambs, we pen the lambs
at night, and in the morning we let them out, my brother.
Sh'ad tahlub l-ghaname?
How much does a sheep milk?
Wallah hasab, hasab darrt n-na'je. Fi na'je thalib nos kilo,
fi na'je tahlib kilo, fi na'je thallib rubi' kilo, hasab
ya'ni.
It depends, it depends on the ewe's udder. There's a ewe
that gives half a kilo, there's a ewe that gives a kilo,
there's a ewe that gives a quarter of a kilo, it just
depends.
W l-ma'iz?
And the goats?
L-ma'iz i hallib.
The goats give milk.
Addeish?
How much?
Fi ma'iz, b-hasab zata kilu mo mitil ba'du, fi 'anze thalib
nos kilo, fi 'anze thalib kilewein, fi 'anze thalib kilo.
There are goats, depending on each one, they aren't all the
same. There's a goat that gives half a kilo, there's a goat
that gives two kilos, there's a goat that gives a kilo.
L-yom 'am tsawwu jibne aw ma sar waqt j-jibne?
Today, are you making cheese, or is it not the season for
cheese yet?
Lissa mo waqt j-jibne.
It's not the time for cheese yet.
Ma sar waqt j-jibne.
It's not the time for cheese.
La, lissa. Hala' ghaban ya'ni, 'a-l-akil ta'rif inta.
No, not yet. Right now they are just eating, you know.
Had mumayaz had, shu had?
This one is special, what is it?
Had kabish... had ismu aswad agrah.
This is a ram... this is called black agrah (bald).
Aswad agrah?
Black agrah?
E, agharr.
Yes, agharr (white-faced).
Agharr?
Ah, w had?
Yes, agharr.
Ah, and this one?
Teys.
A billy goat.
Hada shami?
Is this a Shami (Damascene) breed?
E.
Yes.
Shami, mo hek? Mbayyen min anfu.
Shami, right? It's obvious from its nose.
E.
Yes.
Had akhal.
This one is akhal (black-eyed).
Had akhal?
This one is akhal?
Hada e, anhu l-akhal?
This one, yes, which one is the akhal?
Had akhal.
This one is akhal.
Had?
This one?
E, li-anno 'yunu hawaleytoun aswad.
Yes, because around its eyes it's black.
Aswad e.
Black, yes.
E, aswad akhal. Hada...
Yes, black akhal. This one...
abrash abyad.
is abrash abyad (white-spotted).
Hada abrash abyad?
This is abrash abyad?
E, w had arkham.
Yes, and this one is arkham (gray-white).
Hada arkham.
This one is arkham.
Shu ya'ni arkham?
What does arkham mean?
Ah, arkham azraq e.
Ah, blue arkham, yes.
Qata'at, ta'ref bil ghanam.
You're an expert, you know about sheep.
Allah ya'tik l-'afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afik.
Shukran elak.
Thank you.
Ahlein fik.
Welcome.
Salam 'alekum.
Peace be upon you.
'Alekum s-salam.
Peace be upon you too.
Sani' l-mawas u s-sakakin l-'am Mustafa Kocher Abu Ahmed.
The knife and blade maker, Uncle Mustafa Kocher Abu Ahmed.
Shakhsiye mumayaze w muhimme ktir b-Jweq.
A very special and important figure in Jweq.
Ma'rufe la-inno mihnitu aydan ktir muhimme la-ahali Jweq w
la-ahl l-mantiqa 'umuman.
He is well-known because his profession is also very
important for the people of Jweq and the people of the
region in general.
Rah nkun ma'kun b-hal faqra z-zghire, nt'arraf 'a-hal mihne
w nt'arraf 'a-l-'am Abu Ahmed.
We will be with you in this short segment, to get to know
this profession and to get to know Uncle Abu Ahmed.
W nshuf mada ahamiyyeta l-yom, b-hal zarf r-rahin la-ahali
Jweq.
And to see how important it is today, in these current
circumstances for the people of Jweq.
Tabi'una.
Follow us.
Salam 'alekum.
Peace be upon you.
'Alekum s-salam wa rahmatullah.
Peace be upon you and the mercy of God.
Shlonak?
How are you?
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Shlon sahtak?
How is your health?
Ahlan wa sahlan, ahlan b-l-ustaz, ahlan wa sahlan, ahlan wa
sahlan.
Welcome, welcome sir, welcome, welcome.
Allah yi'afik.
May God give you health.
Biddi ubruk janbak hek shway la-at'arraf 'alek w ta'arraf
'a-mihintak.
I want to sit next to you for a bit to get to know you and
your profession.
Biddi shaghle hek ubruk 'aleha janbak.
I need something to sit on next to you.
Jiblu kirsi la-l-ustaz.
Bring a chair for the sir.
E, 'tini ha law samaht.
Yes, give me this please.
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Awwal shi btit'arraf 'alek?
First of all, can we get to know you?
Mustafa Ahmed Sido, min Jweq.
Mustafa Ahmed Sido, from Jweq.
Ahlan wa sahlan. Ma'ruf b-Mustafa Kocher.
Welcome. Known as Mustafa Kocher.
E, laqab, e.
Yes, a nickname, yes.
Ya'ni entu min beyt Kocher hon?
So you are from the Kocher family here?
E, e. Laqab hada, e.
Yes, yes. It's a nickname, yes.
Ya ahlein wa sahlein.
You are very welcome.
L-l-'ashayer awwali.
For the tribes previously.
Na'am.
Yes.
Hala' hay l-mihne lli 'am tishtighel fiha enta l-an. Shu
tusamma?
Now, this profession that you are currently working in. What
is it called?
Mihnit mawas, sunu' mawas, skakin.
The profession of pocketknives, making pocketknives, knives.
Sunu' mawas u skakin.
Making pocketknives and knives.
E.
Yes.
Eymat sarlak b-hal mihne?
How long have you been in this profession?
Sali shi tlatin sine taqriban.
I've been doing this for almost thirty years.
Hon b-Jweq?
Here in Jweq?
E min Jweq, kint saken b-Afrin, kint ishtighel b-Afrin, sar
li arba' khamis sanawat jay 'a-d-de'a.
Yes, from Jweq, I used to live in Afrin, I used to work in
Afrin. I've been back in the village for four or five years.
Bqa rji'na 'a mihnitna. Bidna nishtighel shughilna ya'ni,
kil min bishtighel shughlu w bi'ilu.
So we went back to our profession. We have to do our work,
you know, everyone does their job to feed their family.
Sabiqan ma kan b-Jweq fi hal mihne hon?
Previously, wasn't there this profession here in Jweq?
Kan fi b-Jweq, kan fi imam jami' Jweq, min shi arba'in sine
w ba'id, khamsin sine w ba'id,
There was in Jweq, there was the imam of the Jweq mosque,
from forty years ago and later, fifty years ago and later,
kanu yishtighlu, yimkin dallu shi 'ashir khamstashar sine,
ishrin sine, yijuz aktar kaman, kanu zghar.
they used to work, maybe they continued for ten, fifteen,
twenty years, maybe even more, they were young.
Kanu yishtighlu skakin, skakin Jweq illon shuhra bil-
mantiqa, bil-Afrin.
They used to make knives, Jweq knives are famous in the
region, in Afrin.
Shu shuhrton, ihkili 'annon?
What's their fame? Tell me about them.
Skakin Jweq, ya'ni 'amaliyyat aktar, w kan imam jami' yitqin
shughlu ya'ni.
Jweq knives, I mean, they are more practical, and the mosque
imam used to perfect his work, you know.
Ya'ni masalan bimyazu inno hinne haddat, matinat,
byistamirru ktir.
Meaning, for example, they are distinguished by being sharp,
durable, and they last long.
Tab'an, hadd w sqaytu kwayse w shughul m'almiye ya'ni.
Of course, sharp and its tempering is good, and masterly
work, you know.
W rijjal dayyen w kwayyes w yishtighel shi ya'ni kwayyes.
And he was a religious and good man and he did a, you know,
good job.
Hala' enta kint fatih mahal b-Afrin qabl ma tkun hon
b-Afrin?
Now, did you have a shop open in Afrin before you were here
in Afrin?
Kint fatih mahal b-Afrin...
I had a shop open in Afrin...
janb beyti, wa ashtighel a'ayyish wlati.
next to my house, and I would work to feed my children.
M-l-mihne bi-z-zat walla kan 'andak wazife tanye?
From the profession itself or did you have another job?
Kint mwasaf janb wazifti. Ba'd dawami ashtighel l-l-masa la
nos l-leil asawi skakin,
I was an employee alongside my job. After my shift, I would
work until the evening, until midnight, making knives,
ayyam aswaq Afrin, suq Afrin, Jinderes, Sheikh Hadid, Rajo.
Aruh abi'on u aji.
on market days in Afrin, Afrin market, Jinderis, Sheikh
Hadid, Rajo. I would go sell them and come back.
Awqat ma aruh abi'on fi makani ya'ni.
Sometimes I wouldn't go sell them, just at my place, you
know.
Ya'ni idafe la-shighlak btishtighel b-hal mihne. Su'al,
l-yom hal mihne bi-t'ayyish?
So in addition to your work, you work in this profession. A
question, today, does this profession make a living?
L-yom ya'ni...
Today, you know...
ghala m'ishe, ya'ni...
the high cost of living, you know...
am nishtighel ma bi... ma btitla' m'ishe.
we are working but it doesn't... it doesn't make a living.
Ma b-ti... ma b-tghatti m'ishe.
It doesn't... it doesn't cover the living expenses.
Fhimt 'alek, fhimt 'alek, fhimt 'alek.
I understand you, I understand you, I understand you.
Ihkili awwal shi shu ahamiyyet hay l-mihne la-ahl l-mantiqa
haliyan?
First of all, tell me what is the importance of this
profession for the people of the region currently?
Nihna k-mantiqa zira'iye, ya'ni l-muzari' ikan ykun 'andu
karim, ykun 'andu zeytun, 'andu rimman, shaghle.
We are an agricultural region, you know, a farmer might have
a vineyard, he might have olives, he has pomegranates,
something.
Biddu yiqta' 'ude, biddu... yuqtul dud s-sajaret z-zeytun.
Byiqa'wer mahal d-dude mahal ma fi dude.
He needs to cut a branch, he needs to... kill the worm of
the olive tree. He hollows out the place of the worm where
the worm is.
Biqa'wer mahalla shway b-buz s-sikkine, w bijib 'ude,
braffi'a hek u binaddifa w biduqqa l-l-'ude b-hal matrah
buqtul d-dude.
He hollows out its place a bit with the tip of the knife,
and brings a stick, thins it out like this and cleans it,
and pokes the stick in that spot and kills the worm.
Iza ma qatal d-dude, d-dude btiqtul z-zeytune.
If he doesn't kill the worm, the worm kills the olive tree.
Hada bi-n-nisbe l-l-muzari', w bi-n-nisbe masalan la mrubbi
l-haywanat lli 'andu ghanam u hek?
This is for the farmer, what about, for example, the animal
breeder who has sheep and so on?
L-haywanat biddu... yidbahluh shaghle, ya'ni ghaname murdat
shway...
For the animals, he needs... to slaughter something, I mean,
if a sheep gets a little sick...
ahsan ma tmut. Yruh 'aleha yidbaha ibi'a kaza, ya'ni...
better than it dying. He goes to it, slaughters it, sells
it, so on, you know...
Ya'ni fina nqul inno kil fallah aw kil mrabbi haywanat 'andu
sikkin fi jebtu?
So we can say that every farmer or every animal breeder has
a knife in his pocket?
E. Bi-sti'mal m-manzili.
Yes. For household use.
E, mitil ma tfaddalt. E, na'am.
Yes, as you said. Yes.
Tayeb... eish anwa' s-skakin?
Well... what are the types of knives?
Anwa' s-skakin khayo, fi 'andak... mus dabb...
The types of knives, brother, you have... a folding
pocketknife...
'adi.
standard.
Hada lissa ma ktamal.
This one is not completed yet.
Mus dabb.
A folding pocketknife.
E, e, bindabb e, byindabb hek e.
Yes, yes, it folds, yes, it folds like this, yes.
Wa fi 'andak... mus taqqat.
And you have... a click pocketknife.
Hada alu taqqat hada. Byinhat b-j-jeb e.
This one has clicks. It can be put in the pocket, yes.
... min hên bi heşşekil hada...
... from here in this shape...
ma xeyyo nehna mitil ma mita'llmîn nişteğil am nişteğil
beqa...
Well brother, we work just the way we learned...
kil wahid beqa bifaddil şuğlo ala... ala ğêro,
Everyone prefers his work over... over others',
w bitlebbes imma bi xaşab, aw taqên fûlaz reqîq,
and it is covered either with wood, these are two thin steel
layers,
w ba'dên bîcî telbîs xaşab aw...
and then comes a wood covering or...
bîkalêt aw baqa aw şağle, w ba'dên bitrekkeb bi heşşekil
hada.
bakelite or plastic or something, and then it's assembled in
this shape.
Hada... hada şû hada mûs tqati'?
This... what is this, a folding pocket knife?
Hada mûs tqati', êh.
This is a folding pocket knife, yes.
Hada mûs tqati' ma byindabb illa tşidd il-halaqa teba'o.
This is a folding pocket knife that doesn't close unless you
pull its ring.
Hada la şû byista'mal?
What is this used for?
Hada yusta'mal la kil iş-şağlat... mişan ma yîcî ala îdak w
ycarrih îdak...
This is used for everything... so it doesn't close on your
hand and cut it...
La êş ma kan byinşiğil.
It can be used for whatever you want.
Tamam... ğêr hêk?
Alright... what else?
Êh. Sakakîn matbax, w taslîhat w şağlat... ya'nî êş ma
bîcîna ma mindaşşir...
Yes. Kitchen knives, repairs, and things... I mean, whatever
comes to us, we don't turn it away...
Hay manaşîr... wahid inkasar minşaro... qulna mintaqa
zira'iyye la tu'axiznî...
These are saws... someone's saw broke... we said this is an
agricultural area, excuse me...
Wahid inkasar minşaro, nişşiğillo... mihattîn jambna.
Someone's saw broke, we fix it for him... we keep them next
to us.
Ninşurlo yaho ala qadd minşaro w nrekkiblo yaho, w naxud
icritna.
We saw it to the size of his saw, attach it for him, and
take our wage.
Tamam. Hallaq hat sakakîn matbax...
Alright. Now these kitchen knives...
illî btista'mil set il-bêt, ya'nî fî şî la taqtî' il-xudar w
il-fawakih,
that housewives use, I mean, there is something for cutting
vegetables and fruits,
w fî şî la l-lahme, w fî şî la şî tanî...
and there is something for meat, and there is something for
other things...
Êş hiyye anwa'on? Fî kbîr w fî sğîr w...
What are their types? There's big and there's small and...
Êh... w fî sîx ma'aş...
Yes... and there's a kebab skewer...
W fî sîx ma'aş.
And there's a kebab skewer.
Êh, êh, êh, êh, êh, hażôl êh. Neḥna majalna la twaxiznî
adyaq min hêk şwayye...
Yes, yes, yes, yes, yes, these, yes. Our field, excuse me,
is a bit narrower than this...
Is-sîx ma'aş biddo idde akbar w kaza... ya'nî byîcî tûlo şî
xamsîn santî aw sittîn santî...
The kebab skewer needs bigger tools and so on... I mean, its
length is about 50 cm or 60 cm...
La taqtî' il-lahim...
For cutting meat...
La taqtî' il-lahim... farim lahim... ma kan fî makînat,
ya'nî taqtî' yadawî.
For cutting meat... mincing meat... there were no machines,
I mean, manual cutting.
Hada haliyyan ma swayna, ma ştağalna b-haş-şağle... walakin
taslîh.
We haven't made this currently, we haven't worked on this
thing... but we do repairs.
Sann, kaza, tağyîr maske, mnsallih.
Sharpening, whatever, changing the handle, we repair.
Biddî is'alak su'al... ya'nî smi'it inno ilak şuhra hôn inte
fi-l mantiqa.
I want to ask you a question... I mean, I heard that you
have a reputation here in the area.
Ehh, tab'an, fî şuhra, fî, fî, fî, fî şuhra. Li-anno şuğlî
ya'nî şway... aytab min şuğl ğêrî.
Ehh, of course, there is a reputation, there is, there is,
there is, there is a reputation. Because my work, I mean, is
a bit... better than others'.
Ya'nî şway şuğlî aytab min şuğl ğêrî...
I mean, my work is a bit better than others'...
baqa ya'nî, akbar zbûnatî aktar şî, ya'nî aktar min ğêrî
byîcû zbûnat la andî.
So I mean, most of my customers, I mean, more than others,
customers come to me.
Tamam, byîcû min ğêr day'a.
Right, they come from other villages.
Byîcû min ğêr day'a...
They come from other villages...
In-naslat min êş hażôl masnû'at?
What are these blades made of?
In-naslat, mincîb rasurat taba' abwab dakakîn imkassara...
The blades, we bring broken springs of shop doors...
bkun bûzon imkassar ma byilzamon. Nehna minştrîhon mincî
minqisson, minhammîhon...
Their tips are broken and they don't need them. We buy them,
cut them, heat them...
Ya'nî huwwe fûlaz? Fûlaz şû huwwe?
I mean, is it steel? What kind of steel is it?
Huwwe fûlaz... walakin ba'd ma byinşiğil fî, biddna nqassî.
Kil m'allim, ya'nî sahîb san'a biddo yiştiğil ala ma'rifto.
It is steel... but after it's worked on, we have to harden
it. Every master, I mean, a craftsman, has to work according
to his knowledge.
Ya'nî ana ma'riftî lazim iza, ba'd ma ştağalt fî, aqassî
şway mişan yithammal hadd sann zyade, ma yitallam bisur'a,
I mean, my knowledge is that I must, after working on it,
harden it a bit so it can withstand extra sharpening, and
not become blunt quickly,
Ya'nî yiqta' zyade.
I mean, it cuts more.
Hallaq nehna şifna qabl şway, inte kîf kint am tiqta' nasle
la sikkîn,
Now, we saw a little while ago how you were cutting a blade
for a knife,
w kîf qassêta, a'taqid hôn wara'î.
and how you cut it, I think it's here behind me.
Hôn fî zêt mahrûq, şû fî hôn?
There's burnt oil here, what's here?
Zêt tab'an. Huwwe tabrîd, ya'nî minqassî bit-tabrîd, kil ma
barad bisur'a bitqassa aktar.
Oil, of course. It's for cooling, I mean, we harden it by
cooling, the faster it cools, the harder it gets.
Byibrud bisur'a?
It cools down quickly?
Êh.
Yes.
Bi-zêt il-mahrûq byibrud bisur'a?
Does it cool down quickly in burnt oil?
Bi-zêt... in kan mahrûq aw ğêr mahrûq...
In oil... whether it's burnt or not burnt...
Tayyib, in-nasle illî sana'ta wênha xallîna nşûfha?
Alright, where is the blade you made? Let's see it.
Biddha tirekkab alêha maske?
Yeah...
Will a handle be attached to it?
Êh na'am, in-nasle hay hiyye.
Yes indeed, this is the blade.
Biddha sann a-ş-çarx, kaza, tazbît şway a-ş-çarx, w ba'dên
mnrekkibla il-maske.
It needs sharpening on the grinder, this and that, a bit of
adjusting on the grinder, and then we attach the handle.
Xallîna nşûf şû am tişteğil fîha şway ma'lîş?
Let's see what you're working on with it a bit, is that
okay?
Êh ma'lîş. Hayy ma'nata... hay mna'îfa... hallaq kint biddî
rekkiba, ahan, hayy afnaha.
Yes, no problem. This means... we leave this... now I wanted
to attach it, aha, we left it.
Tab'an il-idde taba'ak hiyye malzame, w hiyye il-kûr, w
hiyye il... hada şû bitsammî?
Of course, your tools are a vise, and a forge, and the...
what do you call this?
Mawqid nar.
A fire stove.
W kûr minfax hawa, w muwallide la tawlîd il-kahraba.
And an air blower forge, and a generator to generate
electricity.
W malzame, w çakûç, w sindiyan, w mabared... w qatta'at w
şağlat... eyy na'am.
And a vise, a hammer, an anvil, files... cutters and
things... yes indeed.
Hada huwwe is-sindiyan? Bas lil-ilim ya'nî.
Is this the anvil? Just to know, I mean.
Êwa na'am.
Exactly, yes.
Tifaddal.
Go ahead.
Yallah yâ rabb. Mnişteğil bi-hay...
Come on, oh Lord. We work with this...
Tayyib Ammî Abû Ahmad Allâh ya'tîk il-afye, nehna rah
nitirkak am tişteğil,
Well, Uncle Abu Ahmad, may God give you health, we will
leave you to work,
hada namûzac şuğlak wadih kwanne. Allâh ya'tîk il-afye.
this is a sample of your work, it is clearly here. May God
give you health.
Biddî işkurak, tazzabnak ma'na nehna.
I want to thank you, we bothered you with us.
Ahlan w sahlan.
You are welcome.
Lakn t'arrafna ala mihne ya'nî il-yôm muhimme ktîr sarit
liş-şa'b is-Sûrî b-kull asaf.
But we got to know a profession that today, unfortunately,
has become very important for the Syrian people.
Ahlan w sahlan bîkon, w biş-şa'b is-Sûrî killiyyato,
killiyyatna ixwe, w minşni', w mntsa'ad ba'dna...
Welcome to you all, and to the whole Syrian people, we are
all brothers, and we make things, and we help each other...
w mra'î bi-l-as'ar kaman, w kil şî. Ya'nî il-wahid ahsan ma
yhutt ujar sayyara yirûh a-l-balad, w ysinn maqass taba'
qass ğanam, qass şa'ar ğanam, sûf ğanam, w ysinn mwas w
sakakîno, nehna mniştiğil-lon hôn w bi-arxas min ğêr matrah.
and we are considerate with the prices too, and everything.
I mean, instead of paying for a car fare to go to the city,
and sharpening a sheep-shearing scissors, shearing sheep
hair, sheep wool, and sharpening his razors and knives, we
do it for them here and cheaper than anywhere else.
Allâh ya'tîk il-afye.
May God give you health.
Şukran îlak.
You're welcome.
Thank you.
Hayyak Allâh, ma' as-salame.
May God greet you, goodbye.
Il-acwa' il-yôm a-aks acwa' il-cawle il-ûla b-Cwêq.
The atmosphere today is opposite to the atmosphere of the
first tour in Jweq.
Acwa' il-yôm matra w barde haqîqatan, w kan mutawaqqa' tsîr
asife,
The atmosphere today is rainy and cold indeed, and it was
expected there would be a storm,
w asife talciyye, walakin baqiya l-caw matir w barid.
and a snowstorm, but the weather remained rainy and cold.
Ruğm haş-şî, w ruğm inno il-cawle il-ûla kanit acwa'ha
şamis...
Despite this, and despite the fact that the first tour's
atmosphere was sunny...
lakin il-acwa' hôn ktîr camîle bi-acwa' iş-şita.
but the atmosphere here is very beautiful in the winter
vibes.
Is-sabab, huwwe il-cibal il-muhîta b-Cwêq, w illî mazrû'a
biz-zêtûn w il-aşcar fawakih,
The reason is the mountains surrounding Jweq, which are
planted with olive and fruit trees,
w aydan it-tabî'a it-tadarîsiyye la-Cwêq w illî hiyye byût
haqîqatan mrakkabe w m'ammara bi sufûh il-hidab.
and also the topographical nature of Jweq, which is really
houses stacked and built on the slopes of the hills.
Fa-t-tabî'a ktîr hilwe. Nehna maşyîn min it-tarîq il-qadim
min Dargîr...
So the nature is very beautiful. We are walking from the
road coming from Dargir...
w il-muhazî la Cwêq min it-taraf ic-cinûbî. Ya'nî nehna il-
an cinûb Cwêq, a-yamînna...
and parallel to Jweq from the southern side. I mean, we are
now south of Jweq, on our right...
tişahdû aşcar il-lôz il-mismira il-an, il-mizhira, lahzû il-
cibal il-camîle ktîr, il-mxattata biz-zêtûn.
you see the almond trees that are fruitful now, blossoming,
notice the very beautiful mountains, lined with olives.
Il-matar am yinzil qalîlan qalîlan.
The rain is falling little by little.
Mumti'. Tab'an Cwêq intişarha ic-cuğrafî kbîr xallîna nqûl,
is-sabab anno il-byût illî fîha,
Enjoyable. Of course, Jweq's geographical spread is large,
let's say, the reason is that the houses in it,
ila ard diyar was'a, ya'nî kil bêt la taqill masahito an
xamsmîye la saba'mîye lal alif mitir mrabba'.
have spacious courtyards, I mean, every house's area is not
less than 500 to 700 to 1000 square meters.
Lihêk fa-minşûf intişar ila ufuqî, ma fî intişar amûdî,
ya'nî ma fî abniye tabaqiyye illa fî ma nadar.
That's why we see its horizontal spread, there is no
vertical spread, I mean there are no multi-story buildings
except rarely.
W ğaliban, mitl ma na şayfîn a-yisarna, il-an, ğaliban haydi
ard id-diyar tustaxdam l-zira'at...
And mostly, as we are seeing on our left, now, mostly these
courtyards are used for growing...
l-xudarawat, l-zira'at il-fûl, zira'at il-baqdûnis, il-
basal, il-ficil, ya'nî bima ma'na axar...
vegetables, growing fava beans, growing parsley, onions,
radishes, I mean, in other words...
iktifa' iż-żatî... iż-żatî b-had-day'a.
self-sufficiency... self-sufficiency in this village.
Rah nlahiz hallaq a-yamînna ba'd şway... kîf yizhar il-wadî
binkişif, min xalf...
We will notice now on our right in a little bit... how the
valley appears and reveals itself, from behind...
il-byût il-mabniyye ala sifho il-cinûbî.
the houses built on its southern slope.
Manzar ktîr camîl, w xassatan...
A very beautiful view, and especially...
ma' bida'... ya'nî mawsam ir-rabî', fasl ir-rabî', w bid'
zuhûr il-haşa'iş fî asfal il-wadî.
with the beginning... I mean the spring season, the season
of spring, and the beginning of the appearance of grass at
the bottom of the valley.
Lahzû qaddêş il-manzar camîl ala yamînna il-an!
Notice how beautiful the view is on our right now!
Ktîr hilû. Hatta l-kuhûf il-qadîme illî sakanha il-insan...
mbayne w wadiha.
Very beautiful. Even the ancient caves that humans
inhabited... are apparent and clear.
Hay di hiyye il-mazallat illî hakêna anha...
These are the umbrellas we talked about...
İl-an şekla camîl, mutanazir.
Now their shape is beautiful, symmetrical.
Ruğm l-matar, lakin... il-ağnam w il-ma'iz am tira il-an,
li-anno l-matar mû qasîf.
Despite the rain, but... the sheep and goats are grazing
now, because the rain is not heavy.
Ir-ru'at bîtali'ûhon la-l-haywanat l-tira b-had-il-waqit.
The shepherds take the animals out to graze at this time.
Lahzû il-manzar il-camîl ciddan a-s-safh iş-şimalî mn il-
qarye, kîf il-byût şekla camîl,
Notice the very beautiful view on the northern slope of the
village, how beautiful the houses are,
mabniyye b-şekil mrakkab... fôq ba'da. Manzar ktîr hilû.
built in a stacked way... on top of each other. A very
beautiful view.
Rah inzil ma'kon şwayye, bi-tticah il-wadî min hôn, ruğm il-
wu'ûre w is-su'ûbe,
I will go down with you a little, towards the valley from
here, despite the ruggedness and difficulty,
bas l-na'tî fikra an camal hal-qarye. Hada t-tarîq biy'addî
ila il-wadî. Tarîq wa'ir qalîlan lakn-no camîl.
just to give an idea of the beauty of this village. This
road leads to the valley. A slightly rugged road but it is
beautiful.
Il-an nehna taqrîban...
Now we are almost...
sirna fî qalb il-wadî, lahzû...
in the heart of the valley, notice...
A-l-yamîn w a-l-yasar... il-wadî illî kan yicrî fî... macra
ma'î min nabi' ma' fî wasat il-qarye.
On the right and left... the valley where there used to
flow... a water stream from a water spring in the middle of
the village.
Il-an...
Now...
...مزروع بالقمح ومزروع بالشعير وبعض الأشجار.
...planted with wheat, barley, and some trees.
وهون قاسم القرية إلى قسمين.
And here, it divides the village into two parts.
المكان اللي نحن واقفين فيه الآن تماماً هو عبارة عن جسر وتحته
معبر مائي.
The exact place where we are standing right now is a bridge
with a water crossing underneath.
رح نختم هالجولة القصيرة بالسيارة بزيارة قصيرة للحي الشرقي
الشمالي من القرية.
We will conclude this short car tour with a brief visit to
the northeastern neighborhood of the village.
ويبدو أنه حي حديث قليلاً بالمقارنة مع باقي حارات جُوَيْق.
And it seems to be a somewhat modern neighborhood compared
to the rest of the alleys in Jweik.
واضح، هذا بيت عتيق أو عريق في القرية.
It's clear, this is an old or ancient house in the village.
شجرة كبيرة ضخمة، أعتقد شجرة بلوط، في قلب أحد البيوت، مغطية
كل البيت.
A large, massive tree, I think an oak tree, in the middle of
one of the houses, covering the whole house.
فيلا حديثة عم تتجاور الحديث مع نمط البناء التقليدي القديم
بهالقرية بشكل كتير جميل.
A modern villa, the modern is neighboring the old
traditional building style in this village in a very
beautiful way.
كتير حلو منظر اللوز المزهر.
The sight of the blooming almond trees is very beautiful.
الزهر الأحمر على أبيض، الوردي، كتير جميل.
The red and white flowers, the pink ones, it's very
beautiful.
هذا الطريق بيلتف حول جُوَيْق من الجهة الشمالية الشرقية
وبيرجع بيطلع لقلبها.
This road wraps around Jweik from the northeastern side and
goes back up into its center.
رح نختم معكم هالحلقة بلقاء مع أحد عازفي البزق المشهورين
بهالقرية.
We will conclude this episode with you by meeting one of the
famous buzuq players in this village.
واللي بيعزف الفلكلور الغنائي لهالمنطقة بالعموم،
And who generally plays the singing folklore of this region,
ورح يكون إن شاء الله ختام مميز.
and God willing, it will be a special conclusion.
متل ما وعدناكم الختام رح يكون بالعزف على البزق.
As we promised you, the conclusion will be playing the
buzuq.
لكن رياض، أخونا رياض غريب من جُوَيْق،
But Riyad, our brother Riyad Gharib from Jweik,
أصر إنه يكون العزف بهذا الجو الماطر في الطبيعة.
insisted that the playing be in this rainy weather in
nature.
عم يقول إنه بيعطيه إلهام أكتر لحتى يعزف شي من فلكلور وتراث
القرية.
He says it gives him more inspiration to play something from
the village's folklore and heritage.
رياض شو رح تعزف اليوم؟
Riyad, what will you play today?
غنية علي تجو.
A song by Ali Tajo.
علي تجو.
Ali Tajo.
علي تجو. غنية "آني شفانا".
Ali Tajo. The song "Ane Şivan e".
يعني أمي، راعي.
It means "my mother, a shepherd".
أمك راعي؟
Your mother is a shepherd?
يعني راعي، بيعطي بنته لراعي، وهي ما بترضى.
It's about a shepherd, someone gives his daughter to a
shepherd, and she doesn't agree.
أبوها بده يعطيها لراعي وهي ما بدها.
Her father wants to give her to a shepherd and she doesn't
want to.
أبوها بده يعطيها لراعي وهي ما بدها؟
Her father wants to give her to a shepherd and she doesn't
want to?
أبوها ما بدو، هي بدها تاخد الراعي.
Her father doesn't want to, she wants to marry the shepherd.
أبوها ما بدو وهي بدها تاخد الراعي؟
Her father doesn't want to, and she wants to marry the
shepherd?
هو الراعي ما بدها، هي ما بدها، أبوها ما بدو الراعي بس بنته
بدها الراعي.
He doesn't want the shepherd, she doesn't want to, her
father doesn't want the shepherd but his daughter wants the
shepherd.
تمام، البنت بدها الراعي.
Alright, the daughter wants the shepherd.
تفضل.
Yes.
Go ahead.
Anê şivan e, bi xwedê şivan e.
Mother, he is a shepherd, by God, he is a shepherd.
Lê anê şivan e, lê anê bi xwedê şivan e.
Oh mother, he is a shepherd, oh mother, by God, he is a
shepherd.
أعزائي المشاهدين، لهون بتكون انتهت جولتنا الثانية بقرية
جُوَيْق بريف عفرين الغربي.
Dear viewers, here our second tour in the village of Jweik
in the western countryside of Afrin comes to an end.
بهالجولة سُعدنا معكم بالتعرف على بعض المهن والحرف التراثية
والمستحدثة في جُوَيْق.
In this tour, we were happy to join you in learning about
some traditional and newly introduced professions and crafts
in Jweik.
وعلى أنماط الحياة المختلفة وأهمها تربية الحيوانات.
And about the different lifestyles, the most important of
which is animal breeding.
وأيضاً تعرفنا على وضع الناس الاقتصادي والاجتماعي.
We also learned about the economic and social situation of
the people.
سنكون معكم في الأسبوع القادم في جولة جديدة من منطقة سورية
أخرى حبيبة.
We will be with you next week on a new tour from another
beloved Syrian region.
لمتابعة برنامجنا تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة، وأيضاً
موقعنا على الإنترنت halabtodaytv.net.
To follow our program, follow the channel's Facebook page,
and also our website halabtodaytv.net.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.
[موسيقى]
[Music]