Arabic
In the first episode of the Tours program about the village
of Ba'danli, we talked about Ba'danli's history,
architectural styles, social dimension, and the nature of
the population.
Arabic
In this second episode, we will talk about Ba'danli, the
bazaar, professions, crafts, customs, and traditions.
Arabic
Stay tuned.
Ba'danli is a Syrian village in the Afrin region, northwest
of Aleppo, located 80 kilometers away from the city of
Aleppo.
Arabic
It was liberated from SDF control on the fifteenth of March
2018.
Arabic
It has a water pumping unit for the village, a clinic, a
municipality, a bakery, a mosque, and a vegetable market.
Arabic
Ba'danli is famous for its electrical battery manufacturing
plants in Afrin and the region in general.
Arabic
The relationship between its families is characterized by
respect, love, and coexistence, and they are known for their
tolerance and generosity.
Arabic
Their weddings are held collectively, and everyone
participates, putting an end to grudges and animosities.
Arabic
They are also distinguished by their own dialect, called
"Ba'diniyah" or "Ba'dinikiyah," which is easily
distinguished from other neighboring villages.
Arabic
It has a large number of university degree holders in
various specializations, especially engineers, lawyers, and
doctors.
Arabic
It is distinguished by its beautiful nature and the
cleanliness of its streets.
Arabic
A bazaar is held there every Thursday, where people from
neighboring villages come to shop for their needs from the
street vendors gathered in the bazaar.
Arabic
Ba'danli is an important center in the area located between
the sub-districts of Rajo and Maabatli in the Afrin region.
Arabic
It is also a village famous for its commercial activity,
especially the trade of agricultural crops.
Arabic
Every Thursday, a bazaar is held in the village, where
people from neighboring villages come to Ba'danli to shop
for their needs from street vendors who come here to sell
their goods.
Arabic
We will be with you in this segment on a short tour inside
the market, which is about to end today due to early high
temperatures.
Arabic
May God give you health, sister.
May God give you health.
Arabic
Are you from here?
Yes.
Arabic
From Ba'danli?
No.
Arabic
Then where?
From Homs.
Arabic
Welcome. Are you buying or selling?
We are buying.
Arabic
You are buying? How are the prices?
Amazing.
Arabic
How so?
Amazing, I mean good, thank God.
Arabic
Good?
Yes.
Arabic
Good. Now, normally, do you buy your goods on bazaar day,
Thursday, or do you buy your goods from the market any day
of the week?
Arabic
Well..
Which one is cheaper?
Arabic
Well, it's the same thing.
I know the bazaar is a bit cheaper.
Arabic
It's the same thing, really.
The same thing. Does this apply to clothes, food, and
vegetables, or what?
Arabic
Really the same.. the same thing, whether it's vegetables or
clothes.
Arabic
The same thing.
May God provide for you, may God give you health.
Arabic
May God give you health.
Welcome.
Arabic
Why are you packing up early?
Well, there's no one left.
Arabic
When did you come here?
The bazaar has emptied. At five o'clock.
Arabic
Tell me, what are you selling here?
Accessories, yeah.
Arabic
You were here at five?
Yes, we leave home at five o'clock, we leave early.
Arabic
Where did you come from?
From Afrin.
Arabic
Yes.
What other bazaars do you go to besides Ba'danli?
Arabic
Well, various places.
Where?
Arabic
Now you have Rajo, there is Jindires, there is Deir Sawwan.
A village every day.
Arabic
Where is the strongest bazaar with economic activity,
buying, and selling?
Arabic
Honestly, it's Jindires.
Jindires.
Arabic
Yes.
Okay, what distinguishes the Ba'danli bazaar?
Arabic
What do you mean?
For example, it finishes early, people buy a specific type
of the goods you have.
Arabic
By God brother, right now what's selling, uncle, is all
cleaning products.
Arabic
Mostly on cleaning products?
Yes, everyone is rushing for cleaning products and cleaning
materials.
Arabic
Other than that?
Groceries. Now groceries are essential items. Everything is
working out.
Arabic
How much did you sell today?
Well, I don't know, maybe around 300 thousand.
Arabic
300 thousand?
Yeah, the market..
Arabic
May God provide for you, may God provide for you.
May God keep you safe.
Arabic
Peace be upon you.
And upon you be peace, may God protect you.
Arabic
Peace be upon you.
And upon you be peace and the mercy of God, welcome.
Arabic
How are you?
Praise be to God Almighty, my greetings to you.
Arabic
Where are you from?
I am from Atarib, from Al-Abzamo.
Arabic
Welcome.
May God keep you.
Arabic
You are a stall vendor, meaning clothes?
New clothes.
Arabic
New.
Yes.
Arabic
How is the market here?
Well, the market, I mean the situation.. I mean, generally,
the situation is weak. There are no sales.. these sales,
because people are looking for their daily sustenance. I
mean, sales are weak, significantly low.
Arabic
Is it in the whole area, or just in Ba'danli?
Now, as for me, I go to two markets a week; I have the
Ba'danli market and the Rajo market.
Arabic
Now, the Ba'danli market is better and preferable to the
Rajo market.
Arabic
Why?
Population density and the surrounding villages, I mean, the
convergence of all the villages, they head to the Ba'danli
market.
Arabic
This is the most thing, I mean.. I mean, the Ba'danli area
or the town of Ba'danli has.. has a presence on the ground.
I mean, really, it has a good strategic location.
Arabic
May God provide for you.
May God keep you, our teacher.
Arabic
Peace be upon you.
My greetings, welcome, may God give you health.
Arabic
Peace be upon you.
Peace and the mercy of God.
Arabic
Hello, brother.
Welcome.
Arabic
How are you?
Welcome.
Arabic
Mallow seller?
Yes indeed, go ahead.
Arabic
I want to step in between you.
Go ahead, brother.
Arabic
Mallow seller?
Yes.
Arabic
Sold out completely?
Praise be to God.
Arabic
Where did you get your load, your goods, from?
Well, we got it from Rajo.
Arabic
From Rajo?
Yes.
Arabic
How much mallow did you get?
Well, today, 325 kilos.
Arabic
The kilo?
And I pluck it, I sell leaves, I sell a kilo for 1,500, and
dried, a kilo is 7,500.
Arabic
7,500.
7,500 for dried.
Arabic
How many.. how many green kilos make a dried kilo?
The green, 5 kilos yield approximately 1 kilo and 300 grams
dried.
Arabic
And with its stems, 100 kilos yield.. meaning for every 100
kilos, it yields 25 kilos of leaves. I mean, you have to
divide the 100 kilos by 25 kilos.
Arabic
Mashallah, now this.. is this the dried one?
This is the dried one, yes.
Arabic
And this is the one you are plucking?
Yeah. This is the dried one and this one we pluck, we
prepare it, I mean we pluck it like this and sell the kilo
for 1,500.
Arabic
Is this blossomed?
This is, I mean, this is the second harvest.
Arabic
I see.
The first harvest is gone, now the second harvest must
inevitably blossom a little.
Arabic
Where are you from?
From Ba'danli.
Arabic
A resident of Ba'danli?
Yes, a resident of Ba'danli, welcome.
Arabic
Welcome, how long have you been working in this field?
I've been in this business for about eight years now.
Arabic
Eight years?
Yes. Well.. now it's not my profession, but my profession is
car batteries.
Arabic
Ah.
But since I sell car batteries, but there's no work right
now. We are working with mallow now, I mean I've been in
this business for eight years.
Arabic
In the bazaar.. only in your bazaar or do you also move
around?
Arabic
No, I come on a day on, day off basis, I come here. I don't
work in other bazaars.
Arabic
No, you don't work in other bazaars?
No, I don't work in other bazaars, I barely manage to keep
up here, I have a lot of orders here, you know.
Arabic
Tell me about the Ba'danli bazaar, what makes it special?
Like what, you mean?
Arabic
The people.. what is the people of Ba'danli's purchasing
preference?
Arabic
In purchasing, right now the most distinctive thing is
vegetables, and such. Most of them, I mean the pressure is
on vegetables, and mallow, meaning it sells; with me, thank
God, if I bring it, it sells.
Arabic
Is there a specific item among.. for instance, foods,
vegetables that they like more, buy more?
Arabic
Walnuts, sumac.
Are you also from Ba'danli?
Arabic
No, I am from Homs.
Welcome.
Arabic
And to you.
The market, most of all right now, it's the walnut season,
and sumac is what the people of Ba'danli work with the most.
And dried figs, now is its season.
Arabic
Are there dried figs here?
There are figs now, but from now on it will start. Before it
was sumac, now it's walnuts. I mean, in a few days the figs
will start, the dried figs.
Arabic
Are there fig pressing factories here?
No, there aren't any here; it all goes to Idlib. Merchants
from Idlib come to buy from here and take it to Idlib.
Arabic
Sir, to your health and enjoyment, and may God grant you
success.
Arabic
May God honor you, thank you.
May God give you health, nice to meet you.
Arabic
Welcome, may God honor you, may God honor you, you've
honored us.
Arabic
Thank you, thank you.
Peace be upon you.
Arabic
And upon you be peace.
How are you?
Arabic
Hello, uncle.
Hello.
Arabic
Welcome, welcome.
May I know your name? Your noble name?
Arabic
Abu Ibish.
Abu Ibish, welcome Uncle Abu Ibish.
Arabic
And you, uncle?
Muhammad Jamil Hanan.
Arabic
Welcome.
Welcome to you.
Arabic
From Ba'danli?
Welcome to you.
Arabic
How old are you?
I am 93.
Arabic
How much is that?
93.
Arabic
90?
90, 93.
Arabic
And you, how old are you?
93 years old.
Arabic
93? Mashallah, mashallah.
93 years and you are here?
Arabic
Yes indeed.
Welcome, uncle.
Arabic
Is this a shirwal?
Yes indeed.
Arabic
And this is a shirwal. This shirt you're wearing, what is
it?
Arabic
This is a shirt?
What is it then?
Arabic
It does the job.
And this, what do you call it? What do you call this, uncle?
Arabic
A Marlot? That's right.
That's right?
Arabic
That's right.
Welcome, uncle.
Arabic
Welcome to you.
How is this village?
Arabic
Ba'danli?
Ba'danli.
شلونك كويسة؟
How are you? Are you well?
كويسة.
I am well.
إيش بتحبي فيها؟
What do you like about it?
أكثر شي بتحبه ببعدنلي شو هو؟
What is the thing you like most about Badinli?
أكثر شي بتحبه ببعدنلي إيش هو؟
Xalo, bi Kurmancî... qise televîzyonê da. Bêje ez
televîzyonê hez dikim.
Uncle, in Kurmanji... talk on the television. Say 'I like
the television.'
إيش يا عمي؟
What is it, uncle?
قالوا لي شوي تحكوا كويس.
They told me to speak a little nicely.
طيب، إنتي احكيلي، إنتي احكيلي.
Okay, you tell me, you tell me.
أنا ما بحسن.
I can't.
إي طولي بالك، طولي بالك.
Take it easy, take it easy.
عم أسألك سؤال، وعم أسألهم سؤال، أكثر شي بتحبوه ببعدنلي إيش
هو؟
I'm asking you a question, and asking them a question, what
is the thing you like most about Badinli?
إنتي شو بتحبي؟
What do you like?
أنا عيب ما بطلع.
It is shameful for me, I won't appear on camera.
ليش عيب؟ ليش؟ هذا المحل إلكن؟
Why is it shameful? Why? Is this shop yours?
إي.
Yes.
شلون الشغل اليوم بالبازار؟ في حركة؟
How is work today at the bazaar? Is there any movement?
في شي حركة.
There is some movement.
اليوم البازار أحسن؟ طيب يلا.
Is the bazaar better today? Okay then.
خد عمي. اليوم بازار، كنت في البازار؟
Here you go, uncle. Today is the bazaar, were you at the
bazaar?
مرقته وشقيت.
I passed by and walked through.
ورحت شقيت. يلا الله يقويك يا رب، الله يعطيك العافية.
And you went and walked through. May God give you strength,
may God give you health.
شكرا يا عمو. أهلين عمي.
Thank you, uncle. Welcome, uncle.
السلام عليكم. أهلا وسهلا، حياك الله.
Peace be upon you. Welcome, may God greet you.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام، أهلا وسهلا.
Peace be upon you too, welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
الحمد لله.
Praise be to God.
نتعرف عليكي؟
Can we get to know you?
زينب حسين.
Zainab Hussein.
أهلا وسهلا فيكي. من بعدنلي إنتي؟
Welcome. Are you from Badinli?
إي، ساكنة هون ومن بعدنلي.
Yes, I live here and I am from Badinli.
أصلك من هون؟
Are you originally from here?
إي أصلي من هون.
Yes, I am originally from here.
إيش عندك أولاد؟
What children do you have?
خمس أولاد، ثلاث بنات وصبيين.
Five children, three girls and two boys.
ما شاء الله، الله يخليهم. شو بيشتغل زوجك؟
Mashallah, may God protect them. What does your husband do
for a living?
كهربجي، تمديدات صحية.
An electrician and plumber.
تمديدات صحية. هلق بسألك سؤال، هاد اللباس اللي لابستيه، هاد
زيكم هاد؟
A plumber. Now I will ask you a question, this clothing you
are wearing, is this your traditional dress?
إي زينا، وعايشين هون. الجلابية زي عربي.
Yes, it is our dress, and we live here. The jalabiya is an
Arab dress.
نحن عنا بنلبس بناطيل وبلوزات، وهلق تعودنا شوي عالجلابيات.
We usually wear pants and blouses, but now we've gotten a
bit used to the jalabiyas.
هاد... توقفي هيك شوي لو سمحتي، هاد شو هاد الحطة على راسك؟
هاد كردي هاد؟
This... can you stand like this for a moment please, what is
this headpiece on your head? Is this Kurdish?
هاد كردي إي.
Yes, this is Kurdish.
هاد شو بيسموه؟
What do they call this?
اسمه يعني... بالكردي Şoşik.
Its name... in Kurdish is şoşik.
Şoşik. وبالعربي؟
Şoşik. And in Arabic?
ما بعرف شو اسمه بالعربي، إيشارب.
I don't know its name in Arabic, it's a headscarf.
إيشارب، يا عيني عليكي. إنتي دارسة؟
A headscarf, exactly. Did you go to school?
إي للتامن.
Yes, up to the eighth grade.
للتامن. احكي لي هون عن وضع المرأة في بعدنلي، شلون يعني وضع
المرأة هون؟
Up to the eighth grade. Tell me about the status of women
here in Badinli, how is the status of women here?
والله الحمد لله وضع المرأة منيحة هون، مثلها مثل الرجل.
Well, praise be to God, the status of women is good here,
she is equal to the man.
شلون؟ احكي لي.
How so? Tell me.
يعني مثلي، بربي الأولاد وبقعد عالدكان.
Well, like me, I raise the children and sit at the shop.
ببيع أغراض مثلاً، مثلي مثل جوزي.
I sell goods, for example, just like my husband.
تدرسي وبتشتغلي وبتتوظفي وبتربي أولاد.
You teach, you work, you get employed, and you raise
children.
في حدا قالي، همس بإذني، قالي المرأة ببعدنلي آخدة حقوقها أكتر
من الرجال، مزبوط هالحكي؟
Someone told me, whispered in my ear, saying that women in
Badinli have taken more rights than men. Is this true?
لا، شو مزبوط؟ الرجال بيضلو رجال.
No, how is that true? Men will always be men.
يعني مانكن مختلفين، إذا أخدتي حقك أكتر منه يعني؟
So you don't disagree, if you took more of your rights than
him?
لا عنا ما في هالعادة. الأمور يعني في تساوي.
No, we don't have that custom. Things are, I mean, there is
equality.
تساوي. إذا المرأة بتقدر بتشتغل مع جوزها.
Equality.
Equality. If a woman is able to, she works with her husband.
يعني بتساعده بالدكان. مثلا مثلي، إذا بخلص شغل البيت.
I mean, she helps him in the shop. For example, like me,
when I finish the housework.
برجع عالدكان ببيع مثلي مثله.
I return to the shop and sell just like him.
احكي لي أطيب الأكلات اللي بتحبيها ببعدنلي، ولا بتطبخيها
إنتي؟
Tell me the most delicious dishes you like in Badinli, or
the ones you cook?
إيوا. ملوخية، في محشي، في Kutayî. هي أكلة زمان.
Yeah. Molokhia, there is stuffed vegetables, and there is
kutayî. That is an old dish.
شو اسمها؟
What is its name?
Kutayî.
شو يعني Kutayî؟
What does kutayî mean?
هي برغل مسلوق ولحمة. بيسلقوه بعدين بيحطوا له لحمة.
It's boiled bulgur and meat. They boil it, then they add
meat to it.
هي اسمها حنطية؟
Is that called wheat porridge?
ما بعرف إيش اسمها بالعربي، نحن منقلها Kutayî.
I don't know what it's called in Arabic, we call it kutayî.
المحشي تبعك بالبرغل ولا بالرز؟
Is your stuffed vegetables made with bulgur or rice?
لا بالرز.
No, with rice.
بالرز. بتحبوا الحد هون؟
With rice. Do you like spicy food here?
لا والله أنا ما بجيبها عالبيت، ما بنحب نأكله.
No, I swear I don't bring it to the house, we don't like to
eat it.
بتساووا كبة نية؟
Do you make raw kibbeh?
إي بنساوي كبة نية.
Yes, we make raw kibbeh.
حدة؟
Spicy?
لا ما بحب الحد.
No, I don't like spicy food.
بس الملوخية يعني ما هي أكلة خاصة في بعدنلي؟
But Molokhia is not really a special dish to Badinli, is it?
لا ما هي أكلة خاصة، من زمان ما كانوا عم ياكلوا شغل ضيعة.
No, it's not a special dish. In the past, they wouldn't eat
village-made food.
إي هلا صار اختلاط، عم ياكلوها كمان.
But now there's mixing, so they eat it too.
وهلا على الغلا ما عم ناكلها، هالسنة ما بدنا نجيبها.
And now, because of the high prices, we don't eat it. This
year we don't want to buy it.
ما رح تجيبوها؟
You won't buy it?
إي هالسنة ما بدنا نشتري، ما بدنا نجيبها، الكيس صار بـ 8
آلاف.
Yeah, this year we don't want to buy it, we won't get it. A
bag now costs 8,000.
8 آلاف؟ لكا يعني في غلا؟
8,000? So there is high inflation?
في غلا إي. في غلا كتير.
Yes, there are high prices. Very high prices.
السنة الماضية كان بألف، جبت 5 كياس. إي هالسنة ما بقدر أجيب.
Last year it was for a thousand, I bought 5 bags. Yeah, this
year I can't afford to buy it.
الله يعينكم. والله يعطيك العافية وشكرا إلك.
May God help you. May God give you health, and thank you.
تسلموا.
Thank you.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
Peace be upon you too.
تشتهر قرية بعدنلي بأنها مركز لتصنيع البطاريات الكهربائية على
مستوى عفرين.
The village of Badinli is famous for being a center for
manufacturing electrical batteries at the Afrin level.
لا بل على مستوى سوريا بالأكمل.
In fact, at the level of all of Syria.
وقد ازدهرت هذه الصناعة أثناء سنوات الثورة بشكل خاص.
This industry has particularly flourished during the years
of the revolution.
للإضاءة على هذه الصناعة يسرنا أن نكون في زيارة قصيرة إلى
معمل الأهرام لتصنيع البطاريات الكهربائية.
To shed light on this industry, we are pleased to pay a
short visit to the Al-Ahram factory for the manufacture of
electrical batteries.
تابعونا.
Stay tuned.
يا رب. السلام عليكم.
Oh Lord. Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
Peace be upon you too.
مرحبا.
Hello.
أهلا وسهلا.
Welcome.
شلونك؟
How are you?
نتعرف عليك؟
Praise be to God.
Can we get to know you?
حسن أبو محمد.
Hassan Abu Mohammed.
يا أهلا وسهلا فيك. صاحب هالمعمل؟
Welcome to you. Are you the owner of this factory?
لا، أنا عامل فيه.
No, I am a worker here.
أهلا وسهلا فيك. احكي لي هالمعمل هاد؟
Welcome. Tell me about this factory?
هالمعمل عم نصنع البطاريات لكافة القياسات.
In this factory, we manufacture batteries of all sizes.
من جميع القياسات من الطاقة للسيارات الزراعية للسياحية، كافة
أنواع البطاريات بهالمعمل.
Of all sizes, from power batteries to agricultural and
tourist car batteries, all types of batteries are in this
factory.
نعم. يعني كم نوع؟
Yes. I mean, how many types?
حوالي شي 6، 7 أنواع.
About 6 or 7 types.
7 أنواع. شو الاستطاعات تبع البطاريات؟
7 types. What are the capacities of the batteries?
في عنا 240 أمبير، في 180، في 110، 130، 165.
We have 240 amps, there is 180, there is 110, 130, 165.
ما شاء الله، كل هدول؟
Mashallah, all of these?
إيوا. في 110 وحتى 70 و60 أمبير.
Yes. There is 110 and even 70 and 60 amps.
ما شاء الله، الله يعطيكم العافية. قديش عمر هالمعمل هاد؟
Mashallah, may God give you strength. How old is this
factory?
عمر هالمعمل من حوالي شي 7، 8 سنين.
The age of this factory is about 7 or 8 years.
7، 8 سنين. يعني أثناء الثورة اشتغل المعمل؟
7, 8 years. So the factory started during the revolution?
إيوا، أثناء الثورة كان بحلب، انتقل لهون عالضيعة.
Yes, during the revolution it was in Aleppo, then it moved
here to the village.
طيب، شو هو السر اللي عم يخلي إنو بعدنلي فيها كتير معامل
تصنيع بطاريات بشكل خاص؟ يعني ليش بعدنلي بشكل خاص؟
Okay, what is the secret that makes Badinli have so many
battery manufacturing factories in particular? I mean, why
Badinli specifically?
إيوا. كان في عنا المعلم الأساسي اسمه مصطفى إبراهيم.
Well. We had the main master, his name was Mustafa Ibrahim.
هو صاحب معمل الشرق، الله يرحمه.
He was the owner of the Al-Sharq factory, may God have mercy
on him.
ويعني كلياتنا تخرجنا من تحت إيده. من تحت إيد المصطفى
إبراهيم.
And, you know, we all graduated from under his hands. From
under the hands of Mustafa Ibrahim.
من كم سنة يعني؟
Since how many years, exactly?
هو من حوالي من سنة الـ 70.
It is since around the year 1970.
إيوا.
The 70s.
Yes.
وصارت هالصناعة عنكم هون؟
And this industry started with you here?
وصارت الصناعة عم تتطور خاصة بهالضيعة.
And the industry has been developing, especially in this
village.
طيب هلا تحكي لي شوي عن مراحل الصناعة تبع البطاريات؟
Okay, now can you tell me a little bit about the
manufacturing stages of the batteries?
مرحلة صناعة البطاريات، هدول البلاكات عم نلحمهم.
The manufacturing stage of the batteries, we weld these
plates.
هلا البلاك يعني شو البلاك يعني؟
Now, a plate, what does a plate mean?
هي بلاك مصنوعة من الرصاص، وهي الأصفر كمان رصاص مطحون.
This is a plate made of lead, and this yellow one is also
crushed lead.
هذا أنتو بتصنعوه؟
Do you manufacture this?
إيوا، هي نحن بنصنعوه هون بالمعمل.
Yes, we manufacture it here in the factory.
يعني هاي الخلية الأساسية؟
So this is the basic cell?
هي خلية أساسية للبطارية.
This is the basic cell for the battery.
طيب تفضل فرجينا شلون عم يشتغل؟
Okay, please go ahead and show us how it works.
كل بطارية كم خلية بيكون فيها؟ كم بلاك؟
How many cells does each battery have? How many plates?
هي فيها... هي 240، فيها 186 بلاكة.
It has... this is a 240, it has 186 plates.
هلا هي خلية جاهزة؟
Now is this a ready cell?
إيوا، هي بطارية 110.
Yes, this is a 110 battery.
هاد شو اسمه هاد؟
What is this called?
هي صندوق، صندوق البطارية.
This is a box, the battery box.
طيب، شو بتحط فيها هلا؟
Okay, what do you put in it now?
فينا بالعكس توقف؟ نشوفك الكاميرا؟
Could you stand the other way around? So the camera can see
you?
هي المرحلة التانية خلصت؟
So this second stage is finished?
إيوا.
Yes.
لوين بدنا ناخدها؟
Where are we taking it?
عالكبس.
To the press.
شرف.
Go ahead.
هذا مكبس؟
Is this a press?
هي مكبس.
This is a press.
شو بتحط لها؟
What are you putting on it?
هي الغطا.
This is the cover.
هلا هذا قطب وهذا قطب مو هيك؟
Now this is a terminal, and this is a terminal, right?
موجب وسالب.
Positive and negative.
إي.
Yes.
طيب هلا هي تكبسوها، بيركب الغطاء عليها هون.
Okay, now you press it, the cover fits on it here.
طيب بتحطولها هيدي السائلة، وين بتحطوا الأسيد؟
Okay, you put this liquid in it, where do you put the acid?
أسيد بعد ما نكبس، بنلحم من هون الرؤوس.
The acid, after we press it, we weld the heads from here.
وبناخدها على غرفه الشحن، بنعبيها أسيد، وعالشحن.
And we take it to the charging room, we fill it with acid,
and onto the charger.
هالورشة بتشغل كم واحد، كم عامل؟
How many people does this workshop employ, how many workers?
والله كنا... لازم على الأقل شيء بيكون شي 12 عامل.
Well, we were... at least there should be about 12 workers.
إيوا.
12 workers.
Yes.
ورديتين ولا وردية؟
Two shifts or one shift?
لا وردية وحدة.
No, one shift.
إيوا.
12 workers?
Yes.
بيعيشوا منها؟
Do they make a living from it?
بيعيشوا منها.
They make a living from it.
طيب الله يعطيكم العافية والله يرزقكم ويفتح عليكم يا رب، شكرا
إلك.
Okay, may God give you strength, provide for you, and open
doors for you, thank you.
الله يعافيك الله يسلمك.
May God give you health, may God bless you.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام أهلا وسهلا.
Peace be upon you too, welcome.
العادات والتقاليد في قرية بعدنلي هي عادات وتقاليد عشيرة
الشيخان الكردية.
The customs and traditions in the village of Badinli are the
customs and traditions of the Kurdish Sheikhan tribe.
التي ينتمي إليها كل سكان القرية.
To which all the residents of the village belong.
بما فيها من الشهامة والرجولة والكرم.
Including magnanimity, manhood, and generosity.
نحن الآن أمام مضافة العشيرة في القرية.
We are now in front of the tribe's guesthouse in the
village.
والتي يعود تاريخها إلى أكثر من 241 عاماً.
Which dates back to more than 241 years.
سنكون معكم في زيارة لهذه المضافة لنتعرف على العم خليل عزت
خليل.
We will be with you on a visit to this guesthouse to meet
Uncle Khalil Izzat Khalil.
وعلى ضيوفه ونتكلم عن عادات العشيرة والقرية.
And his guests, and we will talk about the customs of the
tribe and the village.
تابعونا.
Stay tuned.
يا رب. السلام عليكم.
Oh Lord. Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله.
Peace be upon you and the mercy of God.
مرحبا عمو. شلونك؟ ارتاح، شرف. سلمت عليك؟
Hello uncle. How are you? Relax, have a seat. Did I greet
you?
أهلا وسهلا، يعطيك العافية.
Welcome, may God give you health.
Yallah ya semek, selam aleykum.
By the fish, peace be upon you.
Aleykum selam, ehlen wa sehlen. Heyakellah, selam aleykum.
Peace be upon you too, welcome. May God greet you, peace be
upon you.
Ehlen wa sehlen.
Welcome.
Şlonak? Elhemdulillah ala kulli hal. Ehlen wa sehlen,
şereftek.
How are you? Praise be to God in any case. Welcome, you have
honored us.
Ehlen Amo Xelîl, şlonak?
Welcome Uncle Khalil, how are you?
Elhemdulillah, ehlen wa sehlen fîkun û bi kewadir îza'et
Heleb el-yom.
Praise be to God, welcome to you and to the staff of Aleppo
Radio today.
Heyakellah fîk û bi hal-wicûh t-teyyibe.
May God greet you and these good faces.
Amo, ez zanim ku tu wecîhê gund î li vir, û maşallah ji
eşîra Kora Ehmed ku beşek e ji eşîra Şêxan.
Uncle, I know you are the notable of the village here, and
mashallah from the Kora Ahmed tribe, which is a branch of
the Sheikhan tribe.
Malbata Kora Ehmed ku zeameta eşîra Şêxan e.
The Kora Ahmed family, which is the leadership of the
Sheikhan tribe.
Te ji min re behs kir ku bavê te jî endamê parlamena Sûriyê
bû û tu jî endamê meclîsa parêzgehê bûyî li Helebê, ji 77'an
ta 84'an.
You mentioned to me that your father was a member of the
Syrian parliament and you yourself were a provincial council
member in Aleppo, from '77 to '84.
Ji min re hinekî behsa vî gundî bike, edet û teqalîdên wî,
bi çi tê naskirin?
Tell me a bit about this village, its customs and
traditions, what is it known for?
Edet û teqalîdên vî gundî; ew ji bazirganî û çandiniyê hez
dikin.
The customs and traditions of this village; they love trade
and agriculture.
Nexweya (mêrxasiya) wan heye, kerema wan heye, wêrekiya wan
heye.
They have chivalry, they have generosity, they have courage.
Yanî di nav xwe de rêza hev digirin, nakokî di nav vî gundî
de nînin.
Meaning, they respect each other, there are no conflicts in
this village.
Eger hinek nakokiyên biçûk jî hebin, em yekser dighêjinê û
çareser dikin, em nahêlin kes bibihîze.
Even if there are some minor conflicts, we immediately step
in and solve them, we don't let anyone hear about it.
Tebîeta mirovan li vir gelek lêborîn e bi hev re?
Is the nature of the people here very tolerant with each
other?
Gelek, gelek lêborîn e.
Very, very tolerant.
Bi vê lêborîniyê ew li tevahiya çiyayê (Kurmênc) tên
naskirin.
With this tolerance, they are known throughout the entire
(Kurd) mountain.
Li vir, meşyexet (rêberiya) Şêxan... ev hemû gundên herêma
Raco ku ser bi eşîra Şêxan ve ne, ev e meşyexeta wan?
Here, the leadership of Sheikhan... all these villages of
the Rajo region that belong to the Sheikhan tribe, is this
their leadership seat?
Ev meşyexet e, û ev oda ku em lê rûniştine oda eşîrê ye. Oda
eşîra Şêxan e, deriyê wê her dem vekirî bû.
This is the leadership seat, and this room we are sitting in
is the tribe's room. It's the room of the Sheikhan tribe,
its door was always open.
Heta bi şev jî eger yek bihatana, bavê min sibehê hevalekî
me hişyar dikir û digot herin binêrin ka mêvan hene an na.
Even at night if someone came, my father would wake up a
friend of ours in the morning and say, go and see if there
are guests or not.
Me nedizanî ew kî ne, lê heger mêvan hebûna me ji wan re
xwarin tanî, dixwarin û diçûn.
We didn't know who they were, but if there were guests we
would bring them food, they would eat and leave.
Temenê wê zêdetirî 200 salî ye?
Is it more than 200 years old?
Zêdetirî 200 salî ye.
It is more than 200 years old.
Ji min re behsa pêwendiya xelkê gundê Bêdîna bi gundên
derdorê û bi Erebên nêzîkî we re bike.
Tell me about the relationship of the people of Ba'dinli
village with the surrounding villages and with the Arabs
near you.
Welleh hemû Erebên nêzîkî me, em bi hev re gelek bi tehemul
in...
Well, all the Arabs near us, we are very tolerant with each
other...
Em hemû bi hev re, eşîra Dumilî, Korkan, Hemşelek, anku hemû
gundên nêzîkî me, pêwendiya me bi wan re hebû.
We were all together, the Dumili tribe, Kurkan, Hemshelek,
meaning all the villages close to us, we had relationships
with them.
Lê bi Ereban re, pêwendiya me bi Dar Izza re hebû, di
bazirganiyê de, heta cotkarên wan jî dihatin cem me
diçandin.
But with the Arabs, we had a relationship with Dar Izza, in
trade, even their farmers would come to us and plant.
Bi Ezazê re, bi Til Rifetê re, ev pêwendiya me bi wan re bû.
Û yekser bazara me ya mezin li Helebê bû.
With Azaz, with Tel Rifaat, this was our relationship with
them. And of course, our major market was in Aleppo.
Lê têkiliya we bi wan re çawa bû? Taybetmendiya têkiliya we
çawa bû?
But how was your relationship with them? What was the
characteristic of your relationship?
Têkiliyek gelek, gelek baş bû. Tu cudahî di navbera Ereb,
Kurd û tiştên din de nebû.
It was a very, very good relationship. There was no
difference between Arab, Kurd, and other things.
Tu dakevî bazara Halê, tacirê Ezazî, tacirê Til Rifetî,
Helebî, Dar Izza, digotin ev Kurd e û ev Ereb e, ev tune bû.
If you went down to the wholesale market, the Azazi
merchant, the Tel Rifaat merchant, the Aleppian, the Dar
Izzian, saying this is a Kurd and this is an Arab, that
didn't exist.
Di dema berê de, sê rojan bû. Çi taybetmendiya dawetên berê
bû?
In the old days, it was for three days. What was the
characteristic of old weddings?
Dawetên berê, dihatin û radizan û mesrefên wan gelek dibûn,
sê rojan radizan.
The old weddings, they would come and sleep over and their
expenses were a lot, they would sleep over for three days.
Her malekê malbatek tehemul dikir, yanî her malekê mêvanek
hildigirt.
Each house would host a family, meaning each house would
take in a guest.
Û malbata xwediyê dawetê hemû mesrefên van mêvanan dida.
And the family of the wedding host would pay all the
expenses of these guests.
Hevkarî hebû di navbera xelkê gund de û xwediyê dawetê.
There was cooperation between the village people and the
wedding host.
Li gorî ku min bihîstiye, vexwendina xelkê ji bo dawetê bi
şandina diyariyan dihat kirin. Rast e?
According to what I've heard, inviting people to the wedding
was done by sending gifts. Is that right?
Bêguman. Hîn jî ev heye lê niha bûne kart (qert).
Definitely. This still exists but now they have become
cards.
Çawa bûn ew diyarî?
What were those gifts like?
Diyarî carna menşefe (pêşgîr) bû, yan tebsiye (tepsî) bû,
yan teqimek fîncan bû...
The gift was sometimes a towel, or a serving tray, or a set
of coffee cups...
Yan perçeyek qumaş bû ji bo rûspiyên mezin, qumaşekî baş
pêşkêşî wan dikirin. Ev bûn diyarî.
Or it was a piece of fabric for the major notables, they
would present them with good fabric. These were the gifts.
Apê min, em hinekî bi apê min re biaxivin.
My uncle, let's talk a bit with my uncle over here.
Dixwazim hinekî alîkariya min bikî di wergerê de, apê Xelîl.
I want you to help me a bit with the translation, Uncle
Khalil.
Navê pîroz?
Your noble name?
Mihemed.
Mohammed.
Ya ehlen, ji ku derê?
Welcome, where are you from?
Kurka Jêrîn.
Kurkan Tahtani.
Ehlen wa sehlen, tu cîranê Bêdîna yî.
Welcome, you are a neighbor to Ba'dinli.
Li gorî ku min fêm kir, yekî ji min re got tu zavayê
Bêdînayê yî jî. Bêdîna... erê?
As I understood, someone told me you are also a son-in-law
of Ba'dinli. Ba'dinli... yes?
Erê, min ji Bêdîna aniye.
Yes, I married from Ba'dinli.
Zavayê Bêdîna ye, û herwiha ji kurê xwe re jî keçek ji
Bêdîna aniye, wisa ye?
He is a son-in-law of Ba'dinli, and he also brought a girl
from Ba'dinli for his son, is that so?
Min ji kurê xwe re ji Bêdîna aniye.
I brought a bride from Ba'dinli for my son.
Nexwe tu ji xelkê Bêdîna hez dikî?
So you like the people of Ba'dinli?
Helbet min ji Bêdîna hez kir ku min... Mirovên min in.
Of course I liked Ba'dinli since I... They are my people.
Ez bi te re me, tu ji Bêdîna hez dikî?
I'm with you, do you like Ba'dinli?
Bêdîna? Helbet hez dikim.
Ba'dinli? Of course I like them.
Di erebî de dibêjin; eger te ji kilê hez kir, dûvika wê jî
bîne.
In Arabic they say; if you liked the eyeliner, bring its
tail as well.
Tu zewicî berî tiştekî ji Bêdîna û dema ku te çîrok eciband,
te ji kurê xwe re jî anî, ma ev rast e?
You married from Ba'dinli first, and when you liked the
story, you brought one for your son too, is this true?
Eger min hez nekira, min nedida û nedistan, yanî min jê hez
kir ku min anî.
If I didn't like them, I wouldn't have given or taken from
them, meaning I liked them so I brought her.
Çi tiştê şêrîn (baş) di Bêdîna de heye?
What is the sweet (good) thing in Ba'dinli?
Çi şêrîn e li Bêdîna? Zimanê wan xweş e.
What is sweet in Ba'dinli? Their tongue (speech) is sweet.
Tenê zimanê wan?
Only their tongue?
Ebeden.
Never (only that).
Bi boneya ziman, xelkê Bêdîna zaravayê wan ê taybet heye,
xweş e.
Speaking of the tongue, the people of Ba'dinli have their
own special dialect, it's nice.
Dibêjin zaravayekî Bêdînî yê taybet heye ku wan ji gundên
din cuda dike. Çi ye ew taybetmendî?
They say there is a special Ba'dinli dialect that
distinguishes them from other villages. What is that
characteristic?
Wek ku min berê ji te re got, zaravayekî hêsan e, em hin
tîpan dişkînin û em lez dikin tê de.
As I told you before, it's a simple dialect, we break some
letters and we speed up through it.
Weke zebeş em dibêjin cebeş. An kundir, em dibêjin kindir.
Like for "zebeş" (watermelon) we say "cebeş". Or "kundir"
(squash), we say "kindir".
An gund, em dibêjin gind. Hêsankirin û lezkirin e.
Or "gund" (village), we say "gind". It is simplification and
acceleration.
Ev e zaravayê ku tê cudakirin. Eger te ev her du peyv got,
dibêjin tu ji Bêdîna yî.
This is the dialect that is distinguished. If you say these
two words, they say you are from Ba'dinli.
Bila em herin ba apê min ê wir û ez ê vegerim cem te.
Let's go to my uncle over there and I'll come back to you.
Selam aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Aleykum selam, ehlen wa sehlen.
Peace be upon you too, welcome.
Çawa yî? Tu bi erebî dizanî? Têdigihîjî?
How are you? Do you know Arabic? Do you understand?
Ez nizam erebî.
I don't know Arabic.
Bi çi karî dikî?
What work do you do?
Şivanî.
Shepherding.
Û çi din?
And what else?
Tiştên din... ji vir û wir, di zeytûnan de, û wisa, nizam.
Other things... from here and there, in the olives, and so
on, I don't know.
Elhemdulillah, elhemdulillah. Ji min re behsa bîranînên xwe
bike di dema şivantiyê de li vî gundî.
Praise be to God, praise be to God. Tell me about your
memories from your time shepherding in this village.
Temenê te çend e?
How old are you?
Temenê min... 47.
My age... 47.
Mewalîdê 47 (Ji dayikbûyê 1947)?
Born in '47 (1947)?
Erê.
Yes.
Mewalîdê 47, anku temenê te 73 sal e. Temenê dirêj inşallah.
Born in '47, so your age is 73 years. A long life, God
willing.
Ji min re behsa bîranînên xwe yên şivantiyê li vî gundî
bike.
Tell me about your memories of shepherding in this village.
Gundê me baş e. Elhemdulillah.
Our village is good. Praise be to God.
Tu sibehê derdikevî heta êvarî?
Do you go out in the morning until evening?
Na, nîvro ez vedigerim.
No, I return at noon.
Çend serî pezê te hene?
How many heads of sheep do you have?
Yanî carna berê 20, 22, 23, 40 bûn... lê niha 10 mane.
Well, sometimes before there were 20, 22, 23, 40... but now
10 are left.
Deh mane?
Ten are left?
Deh mane.
Ten are left.
Elhemdulillah, Xwedê tenduristiyê bide te.
Praise be to God, may God give you health.
Ez ê vegerim cem apê Xelîl.
I'll go back to Uncle Khalil.
Apê Xelîl, pirsek tê bîra min. Li gorî ku min xwendiye, li
vir dîrok hatiye çêkirin.
Uncle Khalil, a question comes to mind. According to what
I've read, history was made here.
Min bihîst ku Emîn El-Hafiz, serokê Sûriyê yê berê, li vî
gundî mamostetî dikir di sala 42'an de.
I heard that Amin al-Hafiz, the former Syrian president,
used to teach in this village in the year '42.
Ji min re hinekî qala wan bîranînan bike, her wiha behsa
bavê xwe bike ku di salên 30 û 40'an de endamê Partiya Gel
bû.
Tell me a bit about those memories, and also talk about your
father who was a member of the People's Party in the 30s and
40s.
Pirsgirêka Emîn El-Hafiz, ez nikarim ji te re şîrove bikim
ji ber ku ez negihîştimê, lê min bihîstiye.
The matter of Amin al-Hafiz, I can't explain it to you
because I wasn't around for it, but I have heard about it.
Lê te ew li Qesra Komarî dît?
But you saw him at the Republican Palace?
Ez çûm û min pêşwaziya wî kir ji ber ku ew mamosteyê me bû,
û hevalê bavê min bû.
I went and greeted him because he was our teacher, and he
was my father's friend.
Du salan li vî gundî mamoste bû.
He was a teacher in this village for two years.
Ji ber ku ew di sala 42'an de bû, ez di sala 44'an de ji
dayik bûme. Lê ez bi bavê xwe re çûm serdana wî.
Because he was here in '42, I was born in '44. But I went
with my father to visit him.
Em çûn ba wî û wî pêşwaziyeke gelek, gelek baş li me kir.
We went to him and he gave us a very, very good reception.
Ew daket ji qesrê, bavê min bi 20 metreyan li derveyî qesrê
pêşwazî kir.
He came down from the palace, he welcomed my father 20
meters outside the palace.
Bavê min, dema di Meclîsa Gel de bû, ew meclîsa wî wextî
hikûmeteke sivîl û demokrasî bû.
My father, when he was in the People's Assembly, that
assembly at the time was a civilian and democratic
government.
Wan endamên Meclîsa Gel hildibijartin, û ew Meclîsa Gel diçû
Serokkomar hildibijart.
They would elect the members of the People's Assembly, and
that People's Assembly would go and elect the President.
Li wir du kutle (blok) hebûn, Kutleya Niştimanî û Kutleya
Gel. Bavê min ji Partiya Gel bû.
There were two blocs there, the National Bloc and the
People's Bloc. My father was from the People's Party.
Yên ku hatin hilbijartin, Şukrî El-Quwatlî hilbijartin.
The ones who were elected, they elected Shukri al-Quwatli.
Û Şukrî El-Quwatlî di sala 58'an de Sûriye radestî Misrê kir
da ku bibe yekgirtî.
And Shukri al-Quwatli in the year '58 handed Syria over to
Egypt so that it would become united.
Û Komara Erebî ya Yekbûyî (UAR) çêbû û Ebdulnasir hat.
And the United Arab Republic (UAR) was formed and Abdel
Nasser came.
هون مضافته، كان مضافته هون؟
Here is his guest house, his guest house was here?
كعضو مجلس نواب سوري، برلمان سوري...
As a member of the Syrian parliament, Syrian parliament...
في ذلك الوقت في الخمسينات كانت هون مضافته.
At that time in the 50s, his guest house was here.
كان هون مضافته، كان يجي يروح عالمجلس.
His guest house was here, he used to go to the parliament.
بس خلص الجلسة يجي لهون.
When the session finished, he would come here.
ويجوا الشعب يقدموا له مطاليب للحكومة...
And the people would come and present their demands to him
for the government...
كان ياخذها عالشام ينفذها.
He would take them to Damascus to execute them.
الله يعطيك العافية عمي خليل.
May God give you health, Uncle Khalil.
أهلين وسهلين.
Welcome.
الله يعطيكم العافية جميعاً، شرفنا بزيارتكم.
May God give you all health, we are honored by your visit.
أهلاً وسهلاً.
Welcome.
حياكم الله.
May God bless you.
أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم إنتوا وإذاعة حلب اليوم، على راسي وعلى
عيني.
You are very welcome, you and Aleppo Today TV, you are more
than welcome.
حياك الله.
May God bless you.
وأهلاً وسهلاً والمضافة مضافتكم.
Welcome, and the guest house is yours.
يا رب.
Oh Lord.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
مرحباً يا حجة.
Hello, Hajjah.
شلونك؟
How are you?
مرحباً.
Hello.
نتعرف عليكي؟
Can we get to know you?
نعيمة أصلان.
Naima Aslan.
أم إيش؟
Mother of who?
أم عبد المنعم.
Mother of Abdul Moneim.
أهلين خالة أم عبدو.
Welcome, Auntie Umm Abdo.
هلق نحن شفنا وماشيين في السيارة على الطريق ببعدنلي شفنا
هالتنانير...
Now, we saw, while driving in the car on the road in Baadli,
we saw these tandoors...
وإنتِ عندهم، إنتِ بتصنعيهم؟
And you are next to them. Do you make them?
إي.
Yes.
حضرتك من وين قبل كل شي؟
Where are you from, first of all?
من كفر بطيخ، نازحة لهون.
From Kafr Batikh, displaced here.
طيب. احكيلي شلون بتصنعوا هدول؟
Alright. Tell me, how do you make these?
بنجيب رمل أسود وتراب أحمر و...
We bring black sand, red soil, and...
منين بتجيبوا الرمل الأسود؟
Where do you get the black sand from?
من كوركان.
From Korkan.
كوركان، ضيعة قريبة من هون؟
Korkan, a village close to here?
إي.
Yes.
والأحمر، الأحمر من وين من هون؟
And the red, where do you get the red from? Around here?
من بين هالشجر، منهزه ونجيبه.
From between these trees, we sift it and bring it.
نعم.
Yes.
ونجبلهن و...
And we mix them, and...
إي.
Yes.
بنطينه كل دور لحاله وبنديره.
We apply mud to each layer separately and turn it.
بتحطي بس تراب أسود وتراب أحمر ولا معهن شي تاني؟
Do you only put black soil and red soil, or is there
something else with them?
لا، بس هني، وعم قلك شوالات يعني، بننسلهن وبنحطهن.
No, just them. And as I'm telling you, bags, we unravel them
and put them in.
شوالات قنب؟
Jute bags?
خيش، إي قنب.
Burlap, yes, jute.
شوالات ضرب أحمر...
Bags with red lines...
وتبن؟
And hay?
إي وتبن إي.
Yes, and hay, yes.
أنا كأنه شايفة تبن.
I seem to see hay.
إي في تبن إي.
Yes, there is hay, yes.
يعني تراب أسود وتراب أحمر وقنب...
So, black soil, red soil, and jute...
إي.
Yes.
وتبن.
And hay.
إي.
Yes.
بنعبي التبن، بندقه مع بعضه وبنطينه ومنديره.
We fill the hay, pound it together, mix it into mud, and
turn it.
إي. بتساويه بشكل لبن ولا بتساويه بشكل طين وبتديريه بهادا
الشكل؟
Yes. Do you make it in the shape of bricks, or do you make
it in the shape of mud and turn it like this?
شكل طين وبديره، متل إذا كان واحد بده يدير قبة، تبعية زمان
قديم.
In the shape of mud and I turn it, like if someone wants to
build a dome, from the old times.
أيوة.
I see.
إي ومعه معه بكبه هيك شوي شوي لحتى يزبط.
Yes, and little by little I mold it until it's right.
تمام. بس بعد ما سويتيه بهادا الشكل، شقد بطول لحتى ينشف؟
Perfect. But after you make it in this shape, how long does
it take to dry?
يومين تلاتة بيبس، بس يعني كانت الشمس قوية، بيومين بيبس،
تلاتة.
Two or three days and it dries. If the sun is strong, it
dries in two days, or three.
وهادا بيتحمل يعني هادا تنور بينخبز الخبز هون بصير العجين
جواته؟
And this can withstand... I mean, this is a tandoor, the
bread is baked here, the dough goes inside?
إي، إي في قلبه.
Yes.
Yes, yes, inside it.
بيتحمل النار؟
Does it withstand the fire?
لكان شلون!
Of course!
طيب ما بينحطله هادا آجر من جوا؟ أو فخار؟
Well, doesn't it have bricks put inside? Or pottery?
لا لا ما بنحطله شي خالص.
No, no, we don't put anything at all.
بس بنعمله عين، حجار... وطين...
We just make an opening for it, stones... and mud...
وين عين الحجار بتحطوها؟ فرجيني وين؟
Where do you put the stone opening? Show me where?
تحت منه.
Underneath it.
من تحت؟
From underneath?
منعليها على الأرض.
We raise it above the ground.
أيوة.
I see.
أرضية يعني.
A base, I mean.
إي.
Yes.
بنسويله هيك مثلا نص متر، وبنسويله عين وبنصير نخبز عليه.
We make it like this, for example, half a meter, and we make
an opening for it, and we start baking on it.
طيب هادا لما بتبيعيه...
Well, when you sell this...
بتبيعيه، شلون بشيلوه؟ هادا بيتحرك؟
When you sell it, how do they move it? Does this move?
إي بيتحرك.
Yes, it moves.
طيب فرجيني شلون بالله، فرجيني لو سمحت.
Well, show me how, please. Show me, please.
هوبي.
Hup.
بس هيك نشدها لورا ونحط تحتها حجر.
We just pull it back like this and put a stone under it.
ما بيفرط؟
It doesn't fall apart?
لا ما بيفرط، ماكن كتير ما بيفرط.
No, it doesn't fall apart. It's very solid, it doesn't fall
apart.
ماكن.
Solid.
وبيتحمل نار.
It endures, of course.
And it withstands fire.
طيب وقت وقت الخبز والعجين عليه هون من جوا وقت وضع العجين، ما
بيلزق يعني تراب، ما بيلزق بالعجين؟
Well, during baking and putting dough on it here from the
inside, when placing the dough, doesn't it stick... I mean,
the dirt, doesn't it stick to the dough?
لا ما بيلزق هلق بس...
No, it doesn't stick. Now just...
أول خبزة... بيطلع منه هيك آثار تراب.
With the first baking... some traces of dirt come off it.
بعد الخبزة التانية ما بيطلع منه شي بطول.
Yes.
After the second baking, nothing comes off it at all.
أسألك الحجة في المخيمات عم يشتغلوا منهم؟
Let me ask you, Hajjah, are they using them in the camps?
إي.
Yes.
اشتروا، مو عم يشتغلوا، اجوا من المخيمات لهون أخدوا.
Where?
They bought them, they are not making them. They came from
the camps here and took them.
ممم.
Mmm.
شقد سعر الواحد؟
How much is the price of one?
إذا مو سر؟
If it's not a secret?
عشرين، تمنطعش، حسب بقى...
Twenty, eighteen, it depends...
وقت اللي بعرف الآدمي درويش براعيه، ووقت اللي بعرفه حاله
منيح، بعشرين.
When I know the person is poor, I give them a discount, and
when I know they are well-off, for twenty.
تمام. تمام ما شاء الله عليكي، تمام.
Perfect. Perfect, may God bless you, perfect.
كم واحد صار مشتغلة؟ شقد صار لك عم تشتغلي بهالمهنة، من ايمتى
تعرفتي عليها؟
How many have you made? How long have you been working in
this profession? Since when did you learn it?
من زمان، مرت عمي علمتني إياها وصرت أشتغلها.
A long time ago, my mother-in-law taught it to me and I
started working in it.
حماتك؟
Your mother-in-law?
بكفر بطيخ؟
Yes.
In Kafr Batikh?
أيوة.
Yes.
أوه... وتعلمتي إنتِ.
Oh... and you learned it.
كفر بطيخ نجيب رمل من خان السبل، رمل أسود، ونعمل كمان
بالضيعة... يعني عملت بلايا كمان بالضيعة وبعتهن.
In Kafr Batikh, we used to bring sand from Khan al-Subul,
black sand, and we also made them in the village... I mean,
I made a lot of them in the village and sold them.
ما شاء الله عليكي.
May God bless you.
بس قبل الثورة يعني...
But before the revolution, I mean...
عملتي.
You made them.
إي.
Yes.
وهلق صار لك هون، شقد صار لك هون؟
And now you've been here, how long have you been here?
صار لنا شي تسع تشهر.
We have been here for about nine months.
تسع شهور وعم تشتغلي بهالصنعة هيدي؟
Nine months, and you've been working in this craft?
والله فتح عليكي؟
Yes.
And God has opened doors for you?
الحمد لله رب العالمين، مننا بجي عشرين تنور بعتهن.
Praise be to the Lord of the Worlds, I sold about twenty
tandoors here.
الحمد لله، نعمة.
Thank God, a blessing.
الحمد لله.
Thank God.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
وألف شكر إلك. والله يرزقك.
And a thousand thanks to you. And may God provide for you.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God keep you safe.
May God give you health.
شكراً إلكن.
Thank you.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
مع السلامة أهلاً وسهلاً فيكم.
Goodbye, you are welcome.
انتهت جولتنا الثانية في قرية بعدنلي، ولم ينتهي بحثنا عن
الجمال في هذه القرية الجميلة لا بل الرائعة.
Our second tour in the village of Baadli has ended, but our
search for beauty in this beautiful, rather wonderful,
village has not ended.
سنكون معكم في الأسابيع القادمة في جولات جديدة من مناطق سورية
أخرى حبيبة.
We will be with you in the coming weeks in new tours from
other beloved Syrian regions.
لمتابعة برنامجنا تابعوا صفحة الفيس الخاصة بالقناة وأيضاً
موقعنا على الانترنت، حلب تودي تي في دوت نت.
To follow our program, follow the channel's Facebook page
and also our website, halabtodaytv.net.
السلام عليكم ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace be upon you, and the mercy of God and His blessings.