Tiştê wan yê bav û kalada, bi sed sala damayî ye, ji mera
pêşkêş dikin.
They are presenting us with things from their ancestors,
remaining for hundreds of years.
Emê destpêkê bi hevra nasbikin. Merheba ji wera.
Let's first get to know each other. Hello to you.
Merheba ser seran.
Hello, you are welcome.
Em wa nasbikin?
Can we get to know you?
Navê min Mistefa ye.
My name is Mustafa.
Serçavê min.
You are welcome (lit: on my eyes).
Ez ji gundê Remezan a me.
I am from the village of Ramazana.
Emê ji wera tiştê xwe yê ku sed sala damayî ji wera
xeberdin.
We will tell you about our things that have remained for a
hundred years.
Heka be yara dê bêjim berî ku aş bikevin, ev bi desta pê ar
diherdin.
If I were to tell the friend, before mills appeared, with
this, they ground flour by hand.
Yanî berî aşabû?
Meaning this was before mills?
Berî aşa bû.
It was before mills.
Navê wî çiye?
What is its name?
Navê wî... destar... destar e. Aşê desta ye.
Its name is... destar (quern)... it is a destar. It is a
hand mill.
Bi desta bû. Aş berî aşê ku aletê derkevin, eva bi desta bû.
It was by hand. The mill, before the mills with machines
came out, this was by hand.
Çiqas sal daye?
How old is it?
Pir kevne em nizanin çiqas sal e.
It is very old, we don't know how many years.
Em salê nîkanin tehdîd kin.
We cannot determine the year.
We çawa dikir? Ka ji mera bêje.
How did you do it? Tell us.
Me îştedam nekir.
I haven't used it (personally).
Hê?
Huh?
Me îştedam nekir. O dar dikeve viderê kû... o...
I haven't used it. Look, the wood (handle) goes in here
where... look...
Eyb nîe sobetê bê, ar dê da... hewa hano... tîtik tê da dan.
There is no shame in saying it, the flour gave... look
here... grains are put inside.
O, hano dar dikeve viderê... aletê xwe hene. Hano. Dikeve
viderê.
Look, here the wood goes in here... it has its own tools.
Here. It goes in here.
Yanî berî destar... berî...
Meaning before the destar... before...
Berî destar a ye, berî giya ye.
It is before the destar, it is before everything.
Destpêkê ev bûn?
In the beginning, were these the ones?
Destpêkê ev bûn.
In the beginning, these were the ones.
Piştî vî çi bûn destar?
What came after this destar?
Piştî wî bûn aşê avê. Hewa aşê, î î erde.
After that came the water mills. Look at the mill, the one
on the ground.
Piştî wî bûn aşê, tenê her avê digerin, ne motor der
tinnebûn.
After that came the mills, they only turned by water, there
were no motors or anything.
Piştî aşê avê?
After the water mill?
Paşê motor der derketin, aşê hedîsî çêbûn.
Later motors appeared, modern mills were made.
U destar kengî bûn?
And when were the hand mills?
Destar, lez o, destar jî... çi kevnda dane.
The hand mill, well, the hand mill too... gave in the old
times.
Destar ez bawer dikim ji berî aşan bû.
I believe the hand mill was before the (water) mills.
Berî aşa bî lê.
It was before the mills, yes.
Destar ji berî aşa bû.
The hand mill was before the mills.
Destpêkê ji berî aşa bî lê? Hewa yî berî aşê avê ye. Paşê bî
destar.
Was the beginning before the mills? Look, this one is before
the water mill. Then came the hand mill.
Paşê bûn aşê avê. Paşê, aşê din hedîs e bi dar û dang
derketin.
Then came the water mills. Then, the other modern mills with
huge noises came out.
Jiber ku av jî derdora me pir bû, behsa aşa dikirin.
Because water was plentiful in our area, they talked about
mills.
A, aşê ber vê avî ye, vê çemî ra aş hebûn.
Yes, the mill by this water, along this river there were
mills.
Aşê ser avê. Wek enefî kehrabê nuko ser ewe tîne ne?
Mills on the water. Like the electricity turbine now brings
it on top, right?
Ê aşa jî eyn wî tûnî bî. Lê dixist, avê perê avê lê dixist,
aş digeriya.
The mill was exactly that way too. It hit, the water hit the
blades of the water (wheel), the mill turned.
U soxî? We kengî bikar dianî?
And the mortar (sox)? When did you use it?
Soxî jî, berî ku va delî melîbna derkevin, bi mehra... ê
hano bigre... hano, berkutan e...
The mortar too, before these threshers and things came out,
with the mallet... holding it here... here, it is a pounding
stone...
Bi vî ra dê kutan. Didu... peya bûn o... ê pê dikutan.
With this, they would pound. Two... men were there... who
pounded with it.
Genimê xwe, bilxurê xwe... berê delîb der tinnne bûn.
Their wheat, their bulgur... before threshers existed.
Digihiştê?
Did it suffice?
Egîşta me lê.
It sufficed for us, yes.
We çi digot? Demê we dikuta we digot çi?
What did you say? When you were pounding, what did you say?
Didiyo dikutan... yek weş e bo hano xurt e hano bila
werin... werin ber destê ya ha.
Two were pounding... one is nice, look here it's strong, let
them come... come to the hand here.
Yek ji mobeyna herdida rûdinişt.
One sat between the two.
Î, î rûniştî mobeyna herdu digo "su çi çi".
The one, the one sitting between the two said "su chi chi"
(rhythmic sound).
"Su çi çi", me'na "su çi çi" ew no... wehşê xwe dibe, wan
têne.
"Su chi chi", the meaning of "su chi chi" is that... he
takes his breath/energy, bringing them.
Yek lêdixê, yek radike.
One hits, one lifts.
Ku aletê me digot tînyorim, hewa hano... tîm tê ba dan... O,
hano dor dikeve viderê... aletê xwan e.
If the tool, we said tînyorim (specific part?), look here...
the pestle hits the grain... Look, here the wood goes in
here... these are their tools.
Dikeve viderê. Hewa, berî destar a ne, berî giya.
It enters here. Look, these are before the hand mill, before
everything.
Destpêkê hew bûn.
In the beginning, these were the ones.
Piştî wî bûn destar.
After that came the hand mill.
Piştî wî bûn aşê avê. Hewa aşê î erde.
After that came the water mills. Look at the mill on the
ground.
Piştî wî bûn aşê her avê digerin ne motor der tinnne bûn.
After that came the mills turning only by water, there were
no motors.
Lê dixî dê... "Su çi çi". Lê xî dê... "Su çi çi".
You hit it... "Su chi chi". Hit it... "Su chi chi".
Kalê me digot tînyorim, hewa o, ji wan harda pirterr radibê.
Xêre tîm dan dikê.
Our elder said tînyorim, look at that, it rises higher than
those two. The pestles hit each other.
Radbîniya wî dida hekrê daye. Ne dipiya daye.
The rhythm is in the waist. Not in the feet.
Yanî didiyo dikutan yek jî li kêlekê digot "su çi çi".
Meaning two pounded and one on the side said "su chi chi".
Êwa.
Exactly.
Temam, ka spas ji wera, ka cinda kerem kin vegerin.
Okay, thank you to you, please kindly return.
Ka em nêkê ji dayikê jî bipirsin.
Let's ask the mother (elder woman) a bit too.
Dayê merheba ji wera jî.
Mother, hello to you too.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Sax be dayê.
Be healthy, mother.
Te jî sax be.
You be healthy too.
We jî berê dikutan?
Did you also pound in the past?
Ee, em çûçik bûn me nizanî, bes xudanê dêkê me, bavkê me,
dikutan.
Yes, we were small, we didn't know, but the owners of our
mothers, our fathers, pounded.
Ê bes vaye ez dibêm...
Ah, but this is what I say...
Digo "Hum hum dan e. Dan kutan e. Dan bilxur e, sox kevir
e."
Saying "Hum hum it is 'dan' (grain). It is pounding 'dan'.
'Dan' is bulgur, the mortar is stone."
Hano.
Like that.
Telkû der... telkû gundî bîst, telder didu bîst...
The pestle... the villager heard, the pestle was heard by
two...
Nê... milvî gundî nebîstî.
No... this villager hasn't heard.
Elfrîdê bavkê xo ra çûm çûçik bûm, ez qîçik bûm.
I went with my father Elfrid, I was small, I was a little
girl.
U hevşûra kirin me, şîvê çaxê did bîrê min du ye.
And they made us work together, the time of supper is in my
memory.
Ê na tê bîra te? Diyo te wana dikutan?
Ah, don't you remember? Did you see them pounding?
Lêêê! Erê no... destê te ji... didu zana wij dikuta, û yekê
çêdikir ber.
Nooo! Yes no... your hand from... two wise ones pounded it
too, and one fixed it in front.
Hano çêdikirin ber, yane lvî gundî.
Fixing it in front like this, meaning in this village.
U digotin...
And they said...
Digotin "Su çi çi". Erê. Digotin "Su çi çi". Wayî kî bê "Su
çi çi" va dihesiya ne.
They said "Su chi chi". Yes. They said "Su chi chi". The one
who says "Su chi chi", they were getting tired/breathing.
Hewa va dihesî.
Like that, he gets tired.
Digo "Hum hum dan e, dan kutan e, dan bilxur e, sox kevir
e."
Saying "Hum hum it is 'dan', it is pounding 'dan', 'dan' is
bulgur, the mortar is stone."
Ka em dîsa kanê bêje, çawa...
Let's again, where, say it, how...
Ka jinda kerem ke, kerem ke vê.
Please kindly, kindly do this.
Ewane wese.
Those are nice.
Ha we bêjin ne? Li te bêjin.
You say it like that, right? You say it.
No, ez ê bibêjim.
No, I will say it.
Tu bêje.
You say it.
U hewcê tûmîq lêxin.
And hit the pestle down there.
Temam.
Hit it.
Okay.
Ka min hew jî bêjin, tu jî bêje. Destpêkê tu bêje.
Let them also say it, you say it too. First, you say it.
Dê bibêjin. Hum hum dan e.
They shall say. Hum hum it is 'dan'.
Hum hum dan e.
Hum hum it is 'dan'.
Dan kutan e.
It is pounding 'dan'.
Dan bilxur e.
'Dan' is bulgur.
Sox kevir e.
The mortar is stone.
Hum hum dan e.
Hum hum it is 'dan'.
Dan kutan e.
It is pounding 'dan'.
Dan bilxur e.
'Dan' is bulgur.
Sox kevir e.
The mortar is stone.
Hum hum dan e.
Hum hum it is 'dan'.
Dan kutan e.
It is pounding 'dan'.
Dan bilxur e.
'Dan' is bulgur.
Sox kevir e.
The mortar is stone.
Hum hum dan e.
Hum hum it is 'dan'.
Dan kutan e.
It is pounding 'dan'.
Dan bilxur e.
'Dan' is bulgur.
Sox kevir e.
The mortar is stone.
Hum hum dan e.
Hum hum it is 'dan'.
Spas ji wera.
Thank you to you.
Spas.
Thanks.
Spas ji wera.
Thank you to you.
Dayê bivê rengî bû.
Mother, it was in this manner.
E.
Yes.
We dema xwe jî derbas dikir, wextê xwe jî derbas dikir.
You passed your time too, you spent your time.
Wî demê jî ne dihesîn di gunda?
Did they not get tired in the villages at that time?
Ê demkê çi bihesin? Îşta karê malê bû û wisa em...
Oh, for a time, why get tired? Look, it was housework and so
we...
Dayê we çi dikir?
Mother, what did you do?
Me diçûn karê, dê hatin malê xwe.
We would go to work, would come to our home.
Em keçik çi karî bikin qurban?
We girls, what work could we do, my dear?
We çi kar dikir?
What work did you do?
Çi kar dikir... me pez didoşin, me zêtûn berhev dikirin, me
şexre dikişandin, me ceh ceh dikutan, îşta me çi kar... çi
kar hebî me hew dikir.
What work did we do... we milked sheep, we gathered olives,
we pulled the harrow/plough, we pounded barley, look
whatever work... whatever work there was, we did it.
Em diftilîn gundê Remezan a. Heva Remezan a ye.
We wandered in the village of Ramazana. This is Ramazana.
Nanê xwe dikirin heban e.
They put their bread in sacks (heban).
Ne dixwarin, ne didan cîrana. Dî dinan pîşo mîvana.
They didn't eat it, nor gave it to neighbors. They kept it
before the guests.
Wa spas dayê. No îne nanê xwe bidin me.
Thank you mother. Now bring your bread and give it to us.
Inşallah.
God willing.
Spas ji wera jî.
Thank you to you too.
Saet xweş.
Have a good time (lit: happy hour).
Jiyana berê pir xweş bû?
Was life in the past very good?
Jiyana berê pir xweş bû.
Life in the past was very good.
Jiyana rast... jiyana gundîtî pir xweş bû berê.
True life... village life was very good in the past.
Pir xweş bû.
It was very good.
Bê heye no, hew jiyana hîne xweş e.
Surely now, that life is still good.
Hîn xweş e û hîn jî heye welhemdu lillah û hîvî ye jiber
çêtir bê inşallah.
It is still good and it still exists, praise be to God, and
the hope is that it becomes better, God willing.
Ê mala we ava be, spas ji wera jî.
May your home be prosperous, thank you to you too.
We te jî ava, ser xweşî. Spas ji wera jî.
Yours be prosperous too, cheers. Thank you to you too.
Saet xweş.
Have a good time.
Spas ji wera jî jibo xatirê we.
Thank you to you too, for your sake.
Saet ta xweş, oxir be, gula gula.
Have a good time, bon voyage, flowers flowers (with joy).
U ser serê û çavê me.
And upon our heads and our eyes (you are welcome).
Spas dikim, saet a ta xweş.
I thank you, have a good time.
Xwedê ji te razî be û oxir be.
May God be pleased with you and bon voyage.
Di demên berê da jî bo ku gel xwarinên xwe peyda bike, mirov
gelek amûr afirandine.
In past times as well, in order for the people to find their
food, humans created many tools.
Yek ji wan amûran sox e.
One of those tools is the 'sox' (mortar).
Ku ji bo çêkirina sevara xwarina zivistanê... bi kar tînin.
Which they use for making 'sevar' (bulgur), the food of
winter.