Belê temaşvanên hêja, naha jî em derbasî ma'sereya tirî bûn
e.
Yes dear viewers, now we have moved on to the grape molasses
press.
Li gundê Omerxê em digeriyan, naha jî em gihîştine
ma'sereyê. Naha jî emê bibînin...
We were touring the village of Omerx, and now we have
reached the molasses press. Now we will see...
Rojbaş ji we re.
Good day to you.
Ehlen we sehlen, rojtinê we ronahî, ehlen we sehlen, mîlatê
serêm, ser serî me, ser çavê me.
Welcome, may your day be bright, welcome, guests on my head,
on our heads, on our eyes.
Wey spas, em destpêkê te nas bikin?
Oh thanks, can we get to know you first?
Ehlen we sehlen, navê min Dawûd e.
Welcome, my name is Dawud.
Oy serçavê min apê Dawûd.
You are welcome Uncle Dawud.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Xwedê te bihêle, dest û pêyên te sax bin.
May God keep you, may your hands and feet be healthy.
Îro em mêvanê gundê we ne, em derbas bûn, emê hinekî vî karî
bikin.
Today we are guests in your village, we passed by, we will
do a little bit of this work.
Mîlatê serêm, emê hemû vî tiştî kar dikin. Mîlatê selamê.
Guests on my head, we all do this work. Guests of peace.
Em hatin dema te dîtibû Ûmer a... em hatin... ma'sere te
bîra me anî.
We came when you saw Umer... we came... you reminded us of
the molasses press.
Te got ma'sereya tirî li vira heye.
You said there is a grape molasses press here.
Ma'sereya dimsê.
Molasses press.
Me jî meraq kir, îro em derbasî cem we bûn.
We were curious too, so today we came to visit you.
Ê ehlen we sehlen, rojtinê we ronahî.
Well welcome, may your day be bright.
Em hinekî behs bikin, ev ma'sere ji kevn da li ciye, yan
berê da ma'sere din hebûn?
Let's talk a little, has this press been here since old
times, or were there other presses before?
Ji berê da ma'seret ji tehtan çêkirî bûn, ji tehtan çêkirî
bûn, dijivlandin, belengaz dijivlandin.
Since old times presses were made of rock, made of rock,
they used to press, poor people used to press.
Ê şade... şade ne hewno bûn.
And the basins... the basins were not like this.
Ji şevê dikirin ke'kûr, didan ser hevdû... diguvastin.
At night they would make piles, put them on top of each
other... and press them.
Ê paşê, piştyî wî, hew derketin.
Then, after that, these came out.
Hewno rind bûn, meşîn yanî.
These were good, machines essentially.
Ê piştyî wî, me hedîs kir, me heva çêkir, vayî ev.
And after that, we modernized it, we made this one, here it
is.
Ev jî rind e, meqbûl e, rind e.
This is also good, acceptable, good.
Ew navê xwe çine?
What is the name of that?
Ew nav... yek jimar e?
That name... is it a single number?
Şade, şadeyê kefen evok.
Basin, that is an old basin.
Şadeyê kevin?
Old basin?
Şadeyê kevin... heva a ecem çêkirî, hedîs, ser deqê zeytê,
piston e.
Old basin... this one is newly made, modern, on the
principle of oil (presses), it is a piston.
Ê rind e.
It is good.
Awa ew axa din çi ye?
And what is that other earth?
Heva jî carûş e, bedelî tê pêlênê, tê bilind go...
This is the crushing floor, instead of stomping on it, it
comes up high...
Li carûşê dikeve.
It falls into the crushing floor.
Ji wî sehî tire, ji wî çêtire, ji lingan.
It is cleaner than that, better than that, than feet.
Belê, nah em dîtin gelek gund, tizanî? Hine ew ma'sereyê
kevn hene.
Yes, we have seen many villages, you know? Some have those
old presses.
Hene, erê no millet tînin hene, erê.
They exist, yes now people bring them, they exist, yes.
Hine li ser tehta çêkirine, ew...
Some are made on rocks, those...
xestinê dikelînin, ew hinek pêl didin.
I mean they boil it, some stomp on it.
Ê...
Yeah...
Yanî hine ew gelek gund... yanî em yek çûn ji gundê Elindorê
bi rastî yanî...
I mean some, many villages... I mean we went to one in the
village of Alindor actually...
Hene, hene, heta noka hene.
There are, there are, until now there are.
Rojbaş bû em çûn gundê Elindorê, ew diyon e.
It was good day we went to Alindor village, they saw it.
Hene, hene.
There are, there are.
Gelek gund jî hene yanî.
There are many villages too, actually.
Em diçûn Dîdanê... Dîdan pêşiya me xerab bû, diviya wê derê.
We used to go to Dîdan... Dîdan was destroyed before us, it
went there.
Kîderê ye evok?
Where is this place?
Dîdan, şerqî Ezazê dikeve, hûdûdê Tirkiyê.
Dîdan, it falls east of Azaz, the Turkish border.
Gund e?
Is it a village?
Gund e, gund e. Hewa cihê dimse, şeş heft ma'sere, mentîqe
eyrfîn... teqîben î dimse xweş tiriya xweş ji wê derê dihat.
It's a village, a village. That was the place of molasses,
six or seven presses, Afrin region... approximately the good
molasses and good grapes came from there.
Ê piştyî ev hewas çêbû, şûnda req bûn.
And after this situation happened, then they became
comfortable.
Ê me se kir, em kelxwe bexêrin.
We looked, we are grateful to our elders.
Ê mirovîş xora çêkir, û da hebab tên, da nîvan tên, xeyo
gund tên, îşta hemî derbas dikin da.
And man made it for himself, and friends come, neighbors
come, brothers from the village come, so everyone passes
through here.
Naha ev ma'sere ya te tenê ye?
Now is this press only yours?
Ê ya min tenê ye erê.
Yes, it is only mine.
Ha, û gund jî hemî tiriyê xwe tînin cem te?
Ah, and does the whole village bring their grapes to you?
Li gund... li gund tirî tine cem kesekî li gundê me.
In the village... in the village no one has grapes in our
village.
Gundiyê te tirî tinen?
Your villagers don't have grapes?
Gundiyê me tirî tinen... hene, îşî, ê pênc mêwa, sed mêwa,
boş mesela yanî.
Our villagers don't have grapes... there are, like, five
vines, a hundred vines, empty really.
Ê ji kîjan gunda tên cem te?
So from which villages do they come to you?
Ji her gunda tên... tên mesela ji Bêrganê da bigire, Dêrs...
They come from every village... they come for example
starting from Bêrgan, Dêrs...
Dêr Siwanê?
Dêr Siwan?
Ê nav çiya wan... Şehba tên...
Yes inside the mountains... they come from Şehba...
Belê dem... eynî waha...
Yes time... exactly like that...
Yanî wî gundan ma'sere tinen hene?
I mean don't those villages have presses?
Nah, wek Bêrganê ma'sere wan jî ez zanim heye.
No, like Bêrgan, I know they have presses too.
Na a Bêrganê tine ye.
No, the one in Bêrgan doesn't exist.
Tine ye?
Doesn't exist?
Tine ye na.
Doesn't exist, no.
Kîjan gundan hene?
Which villages have them?
Ê welle dibêjin yek li Qestelê heye, li Kuderê heye, ez
nizanim bidebet, bes wina çêra dibêjin.
Well they say there is one in Qestel, one in Kuder, I don't
know exactly, but that's what they say.
Ew ma'sere lora nemane?
Those presses haven't remained there?
Hew ma'sered kevin, wana ji texta çêkirine, nemane...
Those old presses, the ones they made from rocks, haven't
remained...
Çiyê noka işta yekî vî çîmento û dar çêdikin, şade, dar, ana
yekî woyî... anaha ye.
What is now, like someone makes this with cement and wood,
basin, wood, like someone like this... it is like this.
Naha ew kîjan tirî dibe dims?
Now which grape becomes molasses?
Tiriyê dukulganê kevin, dimsê xwe jî gîç e, tir e.
The old Dukulgan grape, its molasses is thick, it is dense.
Ê... hew ê tîr dibe. Esmer dibe.
Yeah... that one becomes dense. It becomes dark.
Kîjan a?
Which one?
Ê Zehlawî, amber dibe.
The Zahlawi, it becomes amber.
Ê voyî Frensî, hewa kele pir dixwaze, hew jî paşê diftile,
çiqas tu bikelînî, ser mize dînê ye, ê Frensî.
The French one, this one needs a lot of boiling, that one
also turns later, no matter how much you boil it, it depends
on its nature, the French one.
Dimsê rind, êz ê dukulganê kevin e.
The good molasses, I (say) is the old Dukulgan.
Hewa dimsê gund e rind e?
Is the village molasses good?
Hewa, temî wî, hemîya dikin dims.
That one, its taste, they make all of them into molasses.
Hewa, hewa ji berê da dibê ê dims e.
That one, that one since the past they say it is for
molasses.
Ê bes noka em çi dikin, da voyî Zehlawî, voyî Frensî, ê xera
dibê netê firuton, gî dibê dims.
Black molasses.
Ê bes noka em çi dikin, da voyî Zehlawî, voyî Frensî, ê xera
dibê netê firuton, gî dibê dims.
But now what we do, the Zahlawi, the French, people say it
doesn't sell, all of it becomes molasses.
Hawa farîqî lonî gine esmer dibe.
That one, the difference in color is a bit darker.
Tizanî berê, li piyan didan, hinek jî dikin tûr?
You know before, they used to stomp with feet, do some also
use bags?
Ê dikin tûr jî yanî.
Yes they use bags too.
Ew gelek tiştî mirovî...
That is a very human thing...
Yasî ti... temam gundiyara ew netê gifiştin, dikirin tûr
pêlê didan e.
Wait... okay for the villagers that couldn't be pressed,
they put in bags and stomped on it.
Ê woyî pêlê didan, di pêlênê ne sahiye.
And those who stomped, in shoes, it's not clean.
Yê hayê dirnoqê gindan e pîs e, yê hayê dirnoqê xwe dirêj
e... na sahiye.
There are the villagers' fingernails which are dirty maybe,
there are those with long nails... it's not clean.
Ê havo noka seke, me hana kirî, me'ne pêlênan tûzme, lepis
destî gîndiyo da...
But this now look, we did it like this, meaning boots for
footwear, gloves on the villagers' hands...
Yanî ma'ne sahiye yanî, pak bûn yanî. Havo çimkî dims e,
merov dixwe, milet dixwe yanî.
I mean it is clean, pure. Because this is molasses, people
eat it, the nation eats it.
Ê nah rojê çend seatan kar diket?
So now how many hours a day does it work?
Welle sibe saet heştan em di şuxulin, hesebi ini zehme,
hesebi tirê yanî.
Well, in the morning at eight o'clock we work, depending on
the crowd, depending on the grapes.
Ba'z heta heştan, ba'z heta dawudiyo dere.
Sometimes until eight, sometimes until late.
Ba'z jî îkindi xelas dibe.
Sometimes it finishes in the afternoon.
Te bîra men... demê zarok... rojê kî betiya xavara çim...
You reminded me... when I was a child... the day I went for
a nap...
Cema gund hebu... yek nizanibû haya sibe ya man...
There was one near the village... one didn't know until
morning remained...
Bi heftan diman, bi heftan. Bi heftan ser ma'serê diman.
They stayed for weeks, for weeks. They stayed for weeks at
the press.
Ê noka na, her roj diçin tiriyê xwe danîn, dibirin ser vê
ma'serê...
But not now, every day they go put their grapes, take them
to this press...
Û dema dora kêş da, diçû çêdikir.
And when whose turn it was, they went and made it.
Ê xoşgîniya tizanî herî baş têda çi bû? Gund bi hev ra bû
alîkar.
And the pleasantness, you know what was best in it? The
village helped each other.
Dema tirî kê danî, ew gund jî ver bû alîkar, ew dimsa
çêdikir.
When someone put down grapes, that village also came to
help, they made that molasses.
Bi hevdira harî dikirin.
They helped each other.
Çûnke çûçik bûn, bofkê min... rezê mel vider no hebûn...
Because we were small, my father... there were no vineyards
around here...
Bi şilîf, bi kerê me dikişan ser vê ma'serok me î çûçik li
viderê hebûn, gunê kolîma da...
With sacks, with donkeys we pulled to this press, we had a
small one here, in the corner of the alley...
Bi kerê, bi şilîfa me danî, boş dikir, dijivlandin, bi hefta
emkê timî... tirlok tera bijivlînin... çêkin bi dims kin.
With donkeys, with sacks we put it, emptied it, pressed it,
for weeks we would... constantly... press it enough... make
it into molasses.
Zehmetî hebu?
Was there difficulty?
Zehmet e, pir zehmet bî. Hevo noka serî e.
It is difficult, it was very difficult. This now is fast.
Ruyê deha ter lewaren. Bîznê Xwedê... berka dibê, dibê dims
û dibê dikeve teneko, ruyê dergo.
The means of living are plentiful in the area. By God's
permission... it becomes a blessing, becomes molasses and
falls into tins, the face of the harvest.
Nah ma'serê da, gerek jin jî hebin ha? Ez dibînim jin tinen
e.
Now in the press, there should be women too, right? I see
there are no women.
Na jin mennû ye viderê.
No women are forbidden here.
Jin nikarin kar nakin?
Women can't do the work?
Ê karî gino tinen.
There is no heavy work.
Gî biye mêra?
It has all become for men?
Gî biye îşta yê mêra îşta.
It has all become men's business now.
Û li vê şiyê jî dikelînin?
And in this place do they also boil it?
Li ji viderê li carûş dikeve, li viderê şade dikeve.
From here it falls into the crushing floor, here it falls
into the basin.
Li viderê tê jur...
Here it comes up...
Ji jor da re hule qetandine.
From up there it's the side of separating.
Ji wuderê qetî bu, solê dibê.
From there it separated, it becomes clear.
Safî şunda, orta ye dimse, li hula do jî dikelî se hula.
After clarifying, it's the middle of molasses, on the other
side it boils in three places.
Ew çiqasî berxwe de, heya dikeli?
How long does it take, until it boils?
Welle teqrîben barxwe dide teqrîben di saet nîvo, sê saeto
barxwe dide.
Well approximately it takes about two and a half hours,
three hours it takes.
Heya dikeli? Tîr dibe.
Until it boils? It becomes thick.
Heta dibê dims, teqrîben sê saeto barxwe dide.
Until it becomes molasses, it takes approximately three
hours.
Sê saeto barxwe dide.
It takes three hours.
Timî agir vêketî ye?
Is the fire constantly lit?
Timî orîginde jî me kine.
It is always a big fire.
Tiştê min dikin...
The things we do...
Piştî bû dims, em boş vê soleno dikin.
After it becomes molasses, we empty it into these coolers.
Ma'ne sor bibe.
So that it becomes cold.
Ba'dî sor bu şunda jî, em dikin teneko.
After it becomes cold, we put it in tins.
Çûnke bigermî teneko keve, xo didê, zingar digre, te'mê
dimsê xerab digere.
Because if it goes into the tin hot, it expands, it rusts,
the taste of the molasses goes bad.
Û xwediyê kî bê tê dibe?
And whoever the owner is takes it?
Ê xodanî ginde, ê kî be meselen, wara qemoz miştek ser
teneko digre, meselen...
Yes the owner from the village, whoever it is for example,
come puts a mark on the tin, for example...
Havo zime te ye, havo ê filanî ye, havo ê filanî ye, herkes
zimê xo dibe.
This is your property, this is so-and-so's, this is so-and-
so's, everyone takes their property.
Naha dims bi çiye, buhayê erzan e?
Now what is the molasses price, is it cheap?
Welle keka haliya noka, bi şeş nîvan farq difroşim. Yanî
yekî heye di teneka, sê teneka, bi şeş nîvan difroşe.
Well brother currently now, I sell with a difference of six
and a half. Meaning someone has a tin, three tins, sells for
six and a half.
Tenekê? Şeş hezar û pêncsidî?
A tin? Six thousand five hundred?
Erê, şeş hezar pêncsid.
Yes, six thousand five hundred.
Ê çiqasî têda heye?
And how much is in it?
Darda kîlo.
Twelve kilos.
Donzdeh?
Twelve?
Wa keka ticara jî işta porîkî misadayê, ma'ne hew jî
îstîfade bibînin hew jî...
Yes.
Wa keka ticara jî işta porîkî misadayê, ma'ne hew jî
îstîfade bibînin hew jî...
Well brother, also a bit of allowance for the traders, so
they can also benefit, they also...
Mala te ava be.
May your home be prosperous.
Serê te sax be.
May your head be healthy.