Dîlawî, dîlawî, dîlawî, dîlawî, dîlawî, dîlawî, dîlawî,
dîlawî, dîlawî wî wî.
My heart, my heart, my heart, my heart, my heart, my heart,
my heart, my heart, oh my heart.
Hemedê Mela wî, Êrebê Mela wî, Baqilê Mela wî, lo wî, lo
wî...
Oh Hemed of Mela, oh Ereb of Mela, oh Baqil of Mela, oh my,
oh my...
Yarê wele serê sibê da, serê me ra dibe bingun e, mezinan
digerî.
Oh dear, by God, in the morning, a fog rises over us,
looking for the elders.
Balzinê xweda qeran têkî devê kunda xayîntê.
The bracelet of God, putting destruction into the mouths of
the treacherous owls.
Gulcanê xwudê nêyo difkire, bîvara ketin serdarê xewê.
Gulcan, may God not let her think, the strangers have fallen
upon the commander of sleep.
Tê mîvan, me tê nebîna, nizanim cinawir e, nizanim benî-adem
e, welle nêwîrim rakim ji xewê.
You are a guest, do not look at me, I do not know if it is a
beast, I do not know if it is a human, by God I dare not
wake up from sleep.
Dema berfî dare, Balzinê xweda jêr va benî-adem e, jor va
cinawir e, çol e, gava gava kêm dikin nêwîrê rake ji xewê.
When the snow hits the tree, the Bracelet of God [implies a
person] is human from the waist down, a beast from the waist
up, it is the wild, step by step they decrease, not daring
to wake from sleep.
Dîlawî, dîlawî, dîlawî, dîlawî, Êrebê Mela wî, Hemedê Mela
wî, feqîretê Mela wî, lo wî, lo wî, lo wî.
My heart, my heart, my heart, my heart, oh Ereb of Mela, oh
Hemed of Mela, oh the poverty of Mela, oh my, oh my, oh my.
De gelî senemê, dê rabe ser Bozê kekê senemê, siwarê Dephê
kekê, kerê borketiyo radike ji erdê.
Come on idol [beloved], rise upon the Grey Horse of the
brother of the idol, the rider of Deph, brother, lifting the
grey donkey/foal from the ground.
Gotê rabe lo Keko, dê rabe lo... lo Bozo dê rabe, çiqas
muxenet e, xwedê dayê serê me wa vê salê.
She said rise, oh Brother, rise... oh Grey Horse rise, how
treacherous they are, God has brought them upon us this
year.
Em bîvar e, ketine serdarê xewê, tû mîvan me tê nebîna, vê
sibê kesê Balzinê xudim qeran têkî devê kunda, mîvan û xurmê
kizna xayîntê.
We are strangers, fallen upon the commander of sleep, you
are a guest, do not look at us, this morning may the
Bracelet of God put destruction in the mouths of owls, the
guest and the treacherous date palms.
Ez nizanim benî-adem e, nizarim cinawir e, çol e, welle
nêwîrim rakim ji xewê.
I do not know if it is a human, I do not know if it is a
beast, it is the wild, by God I dare not wake up from sleep.
Dîwarê o caxûna Bozê kekê, Senemê Gulcanê xudê nêyo difkire.
The walls, oh the times of the brother's Grey Horse, Senem
and Gulcan, may God not let them think.
Dengî ban kir go Senem lê, lê, lê, lê... lê xayînkê, lê, lê,
sêrbidîmanê, lê, lê, qederreşê, lê, lê.
A voice called out saying: Senem, oh, oh, oh... oh traitor,
oh, oh, mysterious appearance, oh, oh, black-fated one, oh,
oh.
Lê Senem, hezar yek navê xwedê xeberdana te xeberê giran e,
cinawirê çolê, benî-adem e, Erebê berê bûk e, xwarinê wî
gilûgiyayê çolê ye.
Oh Senem, a thousand and one names of God, your words are
heavy words, the beast of the wild is a human, Ereb is
facing the bride, his food is the grass of the wild.
Vexwarina wî şîrê mî ye. Xwedê zane gava qewacê Ehmed Begê
hatî, xutkirî şetû û delavê Mûsilê lingikê tîrê ye.
His drink is sheep's milk. God knows when the army of Ahmed
Beg came, crossing the rivers and fords of Mosul, the leg of
the arrow.
Bi şeva nîvê şevê vî ketî bingun e, kekê Bozê siwar e Dephê
ye, kes nedî binguna ketî serdarê xewê ye.
At night, in the middle of the night, a fog fell upon him,
the brother of the Grey Horse is the rider of Deph, no one
saw the fog fallen upon the commander of sleep.
Şalê Ehmed Begê hewa şandibû hatina, wî hatina xêrê be.
The shawl of Ahmed Beg, sent into the air regarding the
arrival, may his arrival be a blessing.
Dîlawî... Êrebê Mela wî, lo wî... Hemedê Mela wî, lo wî, lo
wî.
My heart... oh Ereb of Mela... oh Hemed of Mela, oh my, oh
my.
Yarê Senemê dê rabe, dûr Ereb Hemedî ro digere, temaqî
şinabê rake ji xewê.
Oh dear Senem rise, far away Ereb Hemed is searching for the
sun, do not wake the greedy one from sleep.
Ji wextê ke şûva Ereb Hemedî serê xwe radike ji xewê.
From the time that the shepherd Ereb Hemed lifts his head
from sleep.
Çavê xwe qîm û berê deşta 'Anê, mistide, ger deng neke
quleyê dê xayîn hatê.
He sets his eyes and face towards the plain of 'Anê (Ana),
watchful, if he makes no sound, the tower of the traitor has
come.
Senemê dengî ban kir go dîlawî, Êrebê Mela wî, Baqilê Mela
wî.
Senem called out with a voice saying: my heart, oh Ereb of
Mela, oh Baqil of Mela.
Erebê mi yarim, xwedê zane te xutkirî şetû û delavê Mûsilê
lingikê tîrê ye.
Ereb is my beloved, God knows you have crossed the rivers
and fords of Mosul, the leg of the arrow.
Li şeva nîvê şevê tu ketî bingun e, kekê Bozê siwar e Dephê
ye, te kes nedî binguna, tu ketî serdarê xewê ye.
At night, in the middle of the night, you fell into a fog,
the brother of the Grey Horse is the rider of Deph, no one
saw the fog, you fell upon the commander of sleep.
Şalê hatina, te hatina xêrê be.
The shawl of arrival, may your arrival be blessed.
Dîlawî... Êrebê Mela wî, lo wî... Hemedê Mela wî, lo wî, lo
wî.
My heart... oh Ereb of Mela... oh Hemed of Mela, oh my, oh
my.
Mela xwedê bişewitîne mala bavê Ereb Hemedî li dest sêstira
girîn û kare teşhûra bike.
Mela, may God burn the house of Ereb Hemed's father, holding
three-stringed instruments, weeping and making lamentations.
Lê lê Senem derdê mi va mek bera, medhê kûne û weşbira
xeberdan, xezeba minî jêde bişewite.
Oh Senem, do not bring up my pain, praising the tent and
eloquent speech, my wrath burns excessively.
Heger xeberê min arê biku ne wek ev e, destê xwedawî kunya
berû... daîre, bû cêbê, vê xet û mektûbê derdixîne dide dest
Senemê.
If my word, the fire of the tent is not like this, the hand
of God... the circle, it became a pocket, he takes out this
script and letter and gives it to Senem.
Senemê dare ser Bozê kekê, Senemê siwarê Dephê ye.
Senem is upon the brother's Grey Horse, Senem is the rider
of Deph.
Gotê rabe Bozo, dê rabe Keko, dê rabe qederreşo, dê rabe
kupê namûsê, dê rabe.
She said rise Grey Horse, rise Brother, rise black-fated
one, rise vessel of honor, rise.
Xeberdana Ereb Hemedî xeber dide arê bikûne mekefe.
The speech of Ereb Hemed speaks, the fire of the tent does
not suffice.
Weri serê vê sibê tikê, vê xet û mektûbê ji xayînka xwaro
bixwîne.
Come in the morning, read this script and letter from the
traitorous one down there.
Bozo radibe mektûbê dest digre, zerfê diser ra didirîne, vê
xet û mektûbê derdixîne.
The Grey Horse rises, takes the letter, tears the envelope
from it, takes out this script and letter.
Bise jiya şewitandinê, îşareta herbê ye.
Look at the burning, it is the sign of war.
Wa xetayê mişkinê bi kil e û bi hene û bi xwîn e.
That script of musk is with kohl, and with henna, and with
blood.
Xeta sivda ya mişkinî navê ferzê çûla bûka xerîba, dergista
hekkarî xaka sidiq, serekê neh hezar malî Ehmed Beg e.
The white script of musk, the name of the duty of the
wilderness of strange brides, the engaged of Hakkari, the
land of truth, the leader of nine thousand households is
Ahmed Beg.
Bozo pismam pismam e, te sadiq û hekkarî derketin deşta
'Anê, çûla Wuber e.
The Grey Horse is a cousin to a cousin, your loyal ones and
Hakkari came out to the plain of 'Anê, the wilderness of
Wuber.
Mela xwedê bişewitîne mala Kakuyê fele gewrê mûş e.
Mela, may God burn the house of Kakuy, the grey trap of the
mouse.
Mûş e teyar axa, wasê rûs e, şevîn li bin kune, îskan baş e,
Mela qelengê mi wa dibirre.
It is a mouse, Tayyar Agha, the Russian vessel, spending the
night under the tent, settlement is good, Mela cuts my dowry
like this.
Ê kê sibeda dest û lingê mi têkî henekê, mi xirab bike aşîra
deşta Mûş e.
The one who, in the morning, puts henna on my hands and
feet, destroys me, is the tribe of the plain of Muş.
Dîlawî... Êrebê Mela wî, lo wî... Hemedê Mela wî, lo wî, lo
wî.
My heart... oh Ereb of Mela... oh Hemed of Mela, oh my, oh
my.
Ape Mihemed dengê te sax be.
Uncle Mihemed, health to your voice.
Sizax be, xwedê ji te razî be.
Health to you, may God be pleased with you.
Ev çîrok li kû çêbûye?
Where did this story take place?
Ev çîrok me go li Kurdistana Bakur çêbû.
As we said, this story took place in Northern Kurdistan.
Belê, zatan te di stranê de xûya kir.
Yes, you already clarified it in the song.
Li Vilayeta Rihayê. Li Vilayeta Rihayê çêbû.
In the Province of Riha (Urfa). It happened in the Province
of Riha.
Ewa... kalê mi digot...
That... my grandfather used to say...
Kalê te dengbêj bû?
Was your grandfather a bard (dengbêj)?
Belê. Kalê mi dengbêj bû, dengbêjekî mekin bû.
Yes. My grandfather was a bard, he was a strong bard.
Navê xwe çi bû?
What was his name?
Navê xwe Mihemedê Xidir bû. Navê min bi navê wî ye. Ez
Mihemedê Xidir im. Navê min bi navê kalê min e.
His name was Mihemed, son of Xidir. My name is his name. I
am Mihemed, son of Xidir. My name is my grandfather's name.
Ser çavê min.
Upon my eyes (You are welcome/Respected).
Sax be, xwedê ji te razî be.
Be healthy, may God be pleased with you.
Ê dengbêjiya xwe li kû dike? Li ber dîlana dike?
So where do you perform your bard songs? Do you do it at
weddings?
Na. Bavê mi jî dengbêj bû, û kalê mi jî dengbêj bû, û ez jî
bi xwe dengbêj im.
No. My father was also a bard, and my grandfather was also a
bard, and I myself am a bard.
Ama em wek xelqê, em neçûn me kaset tijî nekirin.
But we, unlike others, we didn't go and fill cassettes.
Em li ser bîdera, ew di gunda axa li oda... yanî bibî
baxşîşekî me nedan. Wa tiştna li cem me tûnne ye.
We [sang] on the threshing floors, or in the villages in the
Agha's guest rooms... meaning, we didn't give/take tips.
Those things don't exist with us.
Bes na em bibînin gund zanî ku ez dengbêj im. Şevê zivistanê
dirêj bûn, em diçûn mal li Helebê.
But no, if we saw the village knew I was a bard. The winter
nights were long, we used to go to the house in Aleppo.
Ez diçûm gund, gund dor me kom dibû, digot bavê Îsmaîl
hatiye, ka ji me ra strana bibêje.
I would go to the village, the village would gather around
me, saying "Ismail's father has come, come sing songs for
us."
Û me distira. Saetek, du saet, sê saet, bes heta sibe me
distira.
And we would sing. One hour, two hours, three hours, just
until morning we would sing.
Zarokên te fêr bûn?
Did your children learn?
Na. Kê çêbû?
No. Who became [a singer]?
Te zarokê xwe jî fêr kirin? Zarokê te jî zanin?
Did you teach your children too? Do your children know how
[to sing]?
Na, zarokê mi elhemdulila yek tiştkî nizanin. Na welle.
Nizanin.
No, my children, praise be to God, don't know a single
thing. No, by God. They don't know.
Û ne birayê te?
And not your brothers?
Em çar bira ne, birayê mi jî nizanin. Bes ez di nav da
dengbêj derketim.
We are four brothers, my brothers don't know either. Only I
turned out to be a bard among them.
Ji xeynî vê stranê, te yên din jî hene? Tu yên din jî
dizanî? Stranê sivik?
Besides this song, do you have others? Do you know others?
Light songs?
Welle me pir çênekirine, bes ê kalê mi çêkirine hene. Li ser
vî gundî... li ser vî gundî... yanî yak sêra e sivik yanî
gotin.
Well, we didn't make many, but there are ones my grandfather
made. About this village... about this village... meaning,
they said a light poem/song.
Te ew dizanî?
Do you know those?
Belê.
Yes.
De yeke ji me ra bêje. Li dawiya bernameyê, wekî din tu çi
dikî di gund da?
Then sing one for us. At the end of the program [we will
hear it], otherwise what do you do in the village?
Welle di gunda ez karekî nakim.
Well, in the villages I don't do any work.
Tu tişta nanivîsînî?
You don't write anything?
Law nivîsandin... me berê, belê... de yek tiştekî hêja em
dinivîsînin.
Oh boy, writing... we used to, yes... well, if it's
something worthy, we write it.
Ê ne hêja?
And if not worthy?
Ê ne hêja em nanivîsînin... em dinivîsînin yanî.
If not worthy we don't write... I mean we write [sometimes].
Yek... bagur tarîxa, tiştekî rind yek bike em dinivîsînin.
One... looking at history, if someone does something good,
we write it.
Wek îro em bîn agha welat hat vir, emê binivîsînin: Agha
welat filan tarîxê, filan wextê, filan rojê hat. Emê
binivîsînin.
Like today, let's say the Agha of the land came here, we
will write: The Agha of the land came on such date, such
time, such day. We will write it.
Ewa nivîsî yanî tîda xelas.
That is the writing, meaning that's it.
Yanî tiştê di gund da tu dinivîsînî?
Meaning you write the things [happening] in the village?
Yanî çi di gund da çêbe tu dinivîsînî?
Meaning whatever happens in the village, you write it?
Belê.
Yes.
Belê, di gund da ya zewacek e, ya yek dimire, ya yek... işde
hat.
Yes, in the village either it's a marriage, or someone dies,
or someone... well, comes.
Çend zarokê te hene?
How many children do you have?
Welle ji min heftî û sê ne, sê heftî û çar e ma.
Well, from me [I have] seven, three [girls], and four are
remaining [boys].
Xwedê giya bihêle.
May God preserve them all.
Belê. Ez... xelq darê eskeriyê tê şûnva dizewice, ez çûm
eskeriyê hatim çar zarokê min hebûn.
Yes. I... people go to the military and marry after coming
back, I went to the military and came back having four
children.
Maşallah.
Mashallah (God willed it).
Tu çend salî çûyî eskeriyê? Kîjan salê tu çûyî eskeriyê?
At what age did you go to the military? Which year did you
go to the military?
Ez heqê heftî û yeka bûm çûm a. Me xu salekê tecîl kir,
heftî û duya çûm.
I was due for [the year] seventy-one when I went. I deferred
for a year, I went in seventy-two.
Heftî û duya.
Seventy-two.
Belê.
Yes.
Wê demê te çend sal eskerî kirin?
At that time, how many years did you do military service?
Sê sal û neh meh û çardeh roj.
Three years, nine months, and fourteen days.
Sê sal û neh meh û çardeh roj min eskerî kirin.
I did three years, nine months, and fourteen days of
military service.
Belê. Yanî mi jibîr nekiriye. Heta reqemêd eskeriyê der
filan mi jibîr nekirine.
Yes. Meaning I haven't forgotten. Even the military numbers
and such, I haven't forgotten them.
De Apê Mihemed di gund da kesên din dengbêj hebûn? Ji bilî
bavê te tenê?
So Uncle Mihemed, were there other bards in the village?
Besides just your father?
Na. Ne li vî gundî û ne li wî... Li wî gundî, li Şingêlê
mazim bûm.
No. Neither in this village nor in that... In that village,
I was living in Şingêl.
Li Şingêlê. Asil em ji vî gundî wextê ku kalê me hatî, ji
Mûşê hat, hat vî gundî.
In Şingêl. Originally, we are from this village, when our
grandfather came, he came from Muş, he came to this village.
Li virê... li pişta vir, berê heftî salî bavê min ji vir çû
mîdanek beze.
Here... behind here, seventy years ago my father went from
here to claim a field/land.
Ji virê barkir, çû mîdanek beze.
He moved from here, went to claim a field.
Li mîdanek beze di pêncî û çara, em hatin Şingêlê rûniştin.
In the claimed field in fifty-four (1954), we came and
settled in Şingêl.
Sala pêncî û çara?
The year fifty-four?
Li gundê Şingêlê. Li Şingêlê em rûniştin, belê.
In the village of Şingêl. We settled in Şingêl, yes.
Piştî wê hûn kengî derbasî vir bûn?
After that, when did you move here?
Li Şingêlê bavê min li wirê... çû rehma xwedê.
In Şingêl, my father there... went to God's mercy (passed
away).
Rehma xwedê lê be.
May God's mercy be upon him.
Şêst û neha me barkir ez çûm Helebê.
In sixty-nine we moved, I went to Aleppo.
Di şêst û neha me barkir ez çûm Helebê. Di şêst û heyşta da
ez zewicîm.
In sixty-nine we moved, I went to Aleppo. In sixty-eight I
got married.
Di şêst û heyşta ez zewicîm, şêst û neha ez çûm Helebê.
In sixty-eight I got married, in sixty-nine I went to
Aleppo.
Li du hezar, ez hatim vî gundî. Ez nesax ketim, lawikê min
18 salî bû rehmetî bû, ez dû gundo nesax ketim.
In two thousand (2000), I came to this village. I fell ill,
my son was 18 years old when he passed away, I fell ill due
to [grief/events] in the village.
Ez çûm cem doxtor, gotin nexweşiya nayê rindê, yanî...
I went to the doctor, they said the illness won't get
better, meaning...
Songa [sonra] em hatin doxtorekî go werin li gund rûnên, pir
dirêj nekin. Em hatin gund û em çêbûn elhemdulila.
Afterwards we came to a doctor who said come settle in the
village, don't prolong it. We came to the village and we got
better, praise be to God.
Ne wek wî gotî bû. Em çêbûn.
It wasn't as he had said. We got better.
Li gund da xûzayiya axa xweşe, bayê tê xweşe.
In the village, the nature of the land is good, the wind
coming is good.
Belê, tebî.
Yes, naturally.
Ew wele wek bajar e yanî.
It is indeed like the city (meaning implies it's better than
the city).
Belê.
Yes.
Em hinekî werin ser dengbêjiyê. Tu kîjan stranan dibêjî? Tu
kîjan stranan dizanî?
Let's come back a bit to the bard singing. Which songs do
you sing? Which songs do you know?
Welle stran, ez Dewrêş jî dibêjim, ez Delîl jî dibêjim, ez
Eyşo Îbê jî dibêjim.
Well songs, I sing Dewrêş [Evdî] too, I sing Delîl [Edûlê?]
too, I sing Eyşo Îbê too.
Ez ji pîşê Hekkarî da jî dibêjim.
I sing from the front of Hakkari too.
Ji Salih Begê şeş-penc a torina mala Surmelî Memed Paşa
Berazî, delemame dege xwedanê kela bazî tê da pîrro tê.
About Salih Beg the Six-Fingered, the grandson of the house
of Surmeli Memed Pasha of the Berazî [tribe], the tragic
one, the owner of the Castle of Bazî, therein the bridge
comes.
Ez pîrro tê, pîrro cebelî jî dibêjim. Û ez Mihemed Emîn jî
dibêjim. Û ez Erebê Salih Begê jî dibêjim.
I sing "The Bridge Comes", "The Mountain Bridge" too. And I
sing "Mihemed Emîn" too. And I sing "Ereb of Salih Beg" too.
Û ez Memê Alan jî dibêjim. Û ez Memê Ewan jî dibêjim.
And I sing "Memê Alan" too. And I sing "Memê Ewan" too.
Û efendime söyleyim... yanî pirrok e, ma ne di fikrê min
daye yanî.
And let me say... meaning there are many, well they aren't
[all] in my mind [right now].
Yanî ew dengbêjiya berê tu hemû tişta dibêjî?
Meaning you sing all the things of the old bard tradition?
Hesenê Elî Begê jî dibêjim.
I sing "Hesen of Elî Beg" too.
Guraşê... Guraşê Mîrzo jî dibêjim.
"Guraş"... I sing "Guraş of Mîrzo" too.
Bavê te ev hemû stran digotin?
Did your father sing all these songs?
Ê pir... yê pir, ez ji bavê xwe hîn bûm.
The many... the majority, I learned from my father.
Ya te hinek jê guhdarkirin, te ji hinekên din jî fêr bû?
Or did you listen to some, did you learn from others too?
Welle yê pir ez ji bavê xwe hîn bûm.
By God, the majority I learned from my father.
Wek însanekî derê dibistanê, bi xwendina di elimê, paşê hemû
kitêba kanê bixwîne.
Like a person going to school, learning through reading,
afterwards they can read all books.
Ê... Ewa berê xwendina wî heye.
So... He has that reading background.
Ax, hemû kitêb... çi kitêb destkeve dikare bixwîne. Çi
pirtûk destkeve dikare bixwîne, yanî.
Ah, all books... whatever book comes to hand, he can read.
Whatever booklet comes to hand, he can read, meaning.
Ê min jî wusa bû. Ez ji bavê xwe elimîm, yanî estranan...
Well, mine was like that too. I learned from my father,
meaning the songs...
Lê lê bîra, weha li singê lê lê bîra.
Oh Bîra, like this on the chest, oh Bîra.
Cûrra min şan a we xwenzîra, cûrra min şan a we xwenzîra.
My Curre rifle is aimed at you boars, my Curre rifle is
aimed at you boars.
Gundê Bîkê bi mij e, lau gundê Bîkê bi mij e.
The village of Bîkê is foggy, oh the village of Bîkê is
foggy.
Germê kê qije qije, germê kê qije qije.
The heat is sizzling, the heat is sizzling.
Xatê tivangê wîne, lê bavî te çûkê bikuje.
Xatê bring the rifle, so your father can kill the game.
Bavî te çûkê bikuje.
So your father can kill the game.
Korta Hêro bi newal e, korta Hêro bi newal e.
The hollow of Hêro is a valley, the hollow of Hêro is a
valley.
Xerbî yî nale nale, xerbî yî nale nale.
The west wind is howling, the west wind is howling.
Cûrra tivang ne li mal e, lau teras tivang ne li mal e.
The Curre rifle is not at home, oh rascal, the rifle is not
at home.
Erdê Pêşnê bece ye, erdê Pêşnê bece ye.
The land of Pêşnê is marshy, the land of Pêşnê is marshy.
Tivangeke çerpe ne ye, tivangeke çerpe ne ye.
It is not a clattering rifle, it is not a clattering rifle.
Mêx kêrî tê nekeye, mêx kêrî tê nekeye.
The nail knife does not penetrate it, the nail knife does
not penetrate it.
Cûrra tivang tenê ye, lau teras tivang tenê ye.
The Curre rifle is unique, oh rascal, the rifle is unique.
Dilê min aqê tew na kê, dilê min aqê tew na kê.
My heart does not find peace, my heart does not find peace.
Berfê dayî û vena kê, berfê dayî û vena kê.
Snow has fallen and it does not melt, snow has fallen and it
does not melt.
Silha cûrê bidava kê, silha cûrê bidava kê.
Use the Curre weapon for the cause, use the Curre weapon for
the cause.
Cûrûyî îna nake, terasî îna nake.
The Curre does not refuse, the rascal does not refuse.
Tila Tîlo li tîlekê, tila Tîlo li tîlekê.
Tilo's finger is on the trigger, Tilo's finger is on the
trigger.
Çûrma da ber kulekê, çûrma da ber kulekê.
I put my Curre at the embrasure, I put my Curre at the
embrasure.
Tivang diza xelkê, lau tivang diza xelkê.
The rifle is the thief of strangers, oh the rifle is the
thief of strangers.