Temaşevanên hêja, dema we xweş be. Bernameya Ax û Welat îro
dîsa em li Çiyayê Kurmênc in, li gundê Jelemê.
Dear viewers, have a good time. In today's episode of "Soil
and Country", we are again in the Mountain of Kurds (Kurd-
Dagh), in the village of Jeleme.
Em hatin karkirda katin, wera karê xwedê kin, hinar, wextê
hinarê ye.
We came to visit the workers, to do their work with them;
pomegranates, it is pomegranate season.
Em hatin bernameyekî ji bû hinarê çêkin. Lê ka ba hev ra
temaşe kin.
We came to make a program about pomegranates. Please, let's
watch together.
Merheba ji were.
Hello to you.
Ahla û sehla.
Welcome.
Saeta we xweş.
Good day to you (May your time be happy).
Bi xêr hatî. Ê te jî xweş be.
You are welcome. May yours be happy too.
Saeta we xweş.
Good day to you.
Ahla û sehla, hûn çûn e, hûn rahet in? Ahla û sehla baba.
Welcome, how have you been, are you comfortable? Welcome,
dear (father).
Dilê we ra zîbe.
Bless your heart.
Elhemdillah ji vî royî ra, me qeneta ronahî dît, em bi
ronahiyê ketin.
Praise be to God for this day, we saw the conduit of light
(electricity), we entered the light.
Hûn saet çenda sibe tê?
What time do you come in the morning?
Em sibe saet şeşan tê, em saet çaran berdidin.
We come at six in the morning, we leave at four.
Şeşê sibê heta saet çaran?
Six in the morning until four o'clock?
Erê wela.
Yes, indeed.
Merheba şaro.
Hello, uncle.
Ahla û sehla.
Welcome.
Sibe xweş.
Good morning.
Ahla û sehla.
Welcome.
Saeta te xweş.
Good day to you.
Ê te jî, ê we jî xweş be. Ahla û sehla ji were.
Yours too, may yours be happy too. Welcome to you.
Emrê vê darê çiqas aye?
How old is this tree?
Wela emrê vê darê... otuz iki sal e.
Well, the age of this tree... is thirty-two years.
Sî û du sal e?
Thirty-two years?
Erê, sî û du sal e.
Yes, thirty-two years.
Te çandiyê, bavkê te çandiyê?
Did you plant it, or did your father plant it?
Wela hema... min bi destê xwe çandiye.
Well, actually... I planted it with my own hands.
Min bi destê xwe çandiye. Min bi destê xwe şivik çandine.
I planted it with my own hands. I planted sticks (cuttings)
with my own hands.
Ne şitil in?
They aren't seedlings?
Ne şitil in. Şivik in, min sing... min şivik jê qut kirine û
min çandine, ne şitil in.
Not seedlings. They are sticks, I cut the sticks from it and
planted them, they aren't seedlings.
Min sing kutane erdê, min çandine.
I pounded stakes into the ground, I planted them.
Ewa şaxê gindê... ewa gindê me şiqnê şitlê gindê me jê
kirine, û me qut kirine, me kirine sing, çovik hanekî, û me
kutane erdê.
Those branches from the village... from our village, we cut
the sprouts of the seedlings from our village, we cut them,
made them into stakes, sticks like this, and pounded them
into the ground.
Me dikirine şerbeta...
We put them in the mud/slurry...
Me kirine erdê, me çandiye û hema... dar naha şuxulî mezin
bûne. Temam.
We put them in the ground, we planted them and just... now
the trees have worked and grown big. Okay.
Emrê... nuka bûye sî û du sal min çandiyê.
Age... now it has been thirty-two years since I planted it.
Wû qutkê me, emal û, em bar dikin... meselî hestew sal bi
sal em bar dikin.
And our harvesting, labor and, we load them... for example,
year by year we harvest/load them.
Ê ewilî em jê dikin, ê din em tovlî jê dikin. Manê bê hal
xêr e, manê gi barvra xara nebe.
We pick the first ones, then we pick the others
collectively. Because otherwise, it's good, so they don't
all spoil together.
Gava te wergî nekir, te nûfa jê nekir, nûfê din... gi barvra
jê kî, gi xara dibe. No lehiqînî.
If you don't do it like that, if you don't pick this batch,
the other batch... if you pick them all at once, they all
spoil. You won't catch up.
Emal tinen e, der tinen e... yanê emal hene em bar dikin, no
lehiqînî, xara dibe.
There are no workers, no place... meaning if there are
workers we harvest/load, otherwise you can't catch up, it
spoils.
Hinara ji kîjan mehê da tê?
From which month do pomegranates come?
Hinar... çilo mehê da tê... hinar divê... va mehê da em bar
dikin. Dimêhê... dihêda.
Pomegranates... in which month they come... pomegranates
must... in this month we harvest. In the month... in the
tenth (October).
Mehê dihêda?
In the tenth month?
Mehê dihêda em bar dikin. Temam.
In the tenth month we harvest. Okay.
Saeta te xweş.
Good day to you.
Ahla û sehla bira.
Welcome, brother.
Merheba ştera.
Hello to you.
Saabî, ahla û sehla.
Saabi, welcome.
Çawayî halê te?
How are you doing?
Ahla û sehla, halê we çawaye?
Welcome, how are you doing?
Dilê te ra zîbe.
Bless your heart.
Ser serê me, ser çavê me, ahla û sehla ji were.
You are very welcome (On our head, on our eyes), welcome to
you.
Wey hinar saet çenda tê?
So, what time do the pomegranates come?
Bi xwedê adeten saet şeş û şunda em tê, şeş û nîv, heft,
sibe, em derdikevin.
By God, usually at six onwards we come, six-thirty, seven,
in the morning, we go out.
Yanî teqrîben barê me heta du û du û nîv, gerekê... yanî em
çiqas zû... yanî sarê bikin ji me ra çêtir e.
So approximately our load is until two or two-thirty,
necessary... meaning the earlier... meaning if we start in
the cool (morning), it is better for us.
Yanî em dibin darin xanê, sûkê. Manî... yirmîş namîne, yanî
li derê.
So we take them to the house, to the market. Meaning... no
fruit remains, meaning outside.
Yanî heta saet duduya?
So until two o'clock?
Heta saet duduya yanî em diqelînin, em xelas dikin.
Until two o'clock, meaning we finish up, we complete it.
Hûn çiqas karker bavra tê?
How many workers come together with you?
Teqrîben... yanî em bêne ededê emalê me yanî... wela em
bixwe, bixwe bixwe ne, ez im, birayê min Ebdû, mesela birayê
min Ciwan...
Approximately... I mean if we come to the number of our
workers... well, it is just us, ourselves, it's me, my
brother Abdu, for example my brother Ciwan...
ê diya min e, ê bavê min e... Em bixwe bixwe ne, karê xweş
xara dikin.
...and my mother, and my father... It is just us, we do the
work nicely ourselves.
Xweşî, elxol Helebî roştî me. Diva mehê hinarê da, em
têne... ore destpêka bavkê xwe dikin. Dêk bavkê xwe dikin,
em bavkê xwe ra dikin dikin.
Happiness, we left the Aleppo situation (or similar
context). In this month of pomegranates, we come... there we
help our father. We help our mother and father, we do it
with our father.
Saeta te xweş.
Good day to you.
Saeta te jî xweş, ahla û sehla.
Good day to you too, welcome.
Nuxa... em dixwazin tu çikî li ser hinarê nas kin. Û
temaşevanên hêja, milet jî nas ke. Hinar... ji kijan mehê da
destpêdibe? Kulîlkê gindor çwa destpêdibe?
Now... we want you to introduce a bit about the
pomegranates. And for the dear viewers, let the people know
too. Pomegranates... from which month do they start? How
does the flower cycle start?
Bixwe kulîlkê xwe di azadê da... yanî mesela di meha azarê
da... şekl vedibe.
The flowers themselves in March... meaning for example in
the month of March... the shape opens up.
Bixwe dar... hêşînahî pê tê mesela. Be'dê hêşînahî tê yanî
bixwe... kulîlkê xwe çêdibin.
The tree itself... greenery comes to it for example. After
the greenery comes, meaning... its flowers are formed.
Dibe kulîlk?
It becomes a flower?
Erê bixwe dibe kulîlk. Û paşê bixwe hinar destpêk çêdibe
heta nîv meha şeş, yanî di meha şeşê da, heftê da, hinar
xwe... belî dike.
Yes, it becomes a flower. And then the pomegranate starts
forming until the middle of the sixth month, meaning in the
sixth month, the seventh, the pomegranate... shows itself.
Hinar xwe... yanî ma... yanî dar belî dike enû hinarî xwe pê
hat.
The pomegranate... meaning... the tree shows that its
pomegranates have arrived.
Mezin dibe?
It gets big?
Erê.
Yes.
Her darek çiqasî... yanî çiqasî hinar digre?
Each tree how much... meaning how many pomegranates does it
hold?
Bixwedê şekl am... yanî teqrîben darê me mezin e. Darê me
emrê xwe mezin e, emrê xwe sî û du sal in. Bavê min sî û du
sal in çandiye.
By God, generally... meaning approximately our trees are
big. Our trees are old in age, their age is thirty-two
years. My father planted them thirty-two years ago.
Sî û du sal in ev darana çandine?
These trees have been planted for thirty-two years?
Erê.
Yes.
Ê... û... çiqas hinar digre her darek? Yanî...
So... and... how many pomegranates does each tree hold?
Meaning...
Dar heye... heta nî, maşela nîho... bîst filînî digre, sî
filînî digre. Heye çel filînî digre.
There are trees... up to, Mashallah now... it holds twenty
crates, holds thirty crates. There are some holding forty
crates.
Filîn çiqasî dikişîne?
How much does a crate hold/weigh?
Filîn bixwe heye pênc hinar tê heye. Pênc hinar heye, çar
hinar heye.
The crate itself, sometimes five pomegranates fit. There are
five pomegranates, four pomegranates.
Heye em du qora çêdikin, lezaq dikin ser hevra. Heyş bin,
heyş liser dikevine ser. Yanî hinarî wekî vî mesela... çar
dikevine filînê.
Sometimes we make two layers, we tape them on top of each
other. If it's eight, eight go on top. Meaning a pomegranate
like this for example... four fit in a crate.
Çar?
Four?
Çar dikevine.
Four fit.
No no, eva şîrîn e, le tan e?
No no, is this sweet, or...?
Eva bixwe lefanî şîrîn e.
This one itself is sweet Lefani.
Ê tirş kani ye?
Where is the sour one?
Lefanî şîrîn e, heye hiş... tirş heye. Di nav da heye tirş
heye, vayî sipî heye, vayî sipî heye, vayî sipî heye.
Lefani is sweet, there are... there are sour ones. Inside
there are sour ones, there are white ones, there are white
ones.
Bixwe şekl am, hinarî... hinarî tirş girs nabe.
Generally, pomegranates... sour pomegranates don't get big.
Hinarê girs?
Big pomegranates?
Hinarê girs, ê... ê tirş, şîrîn... ê şîrîn, girs dibe.
Big pomegranates, the... the sour, sweet... the sweet one
gets big.
Girs dibe. Û ê...?
It gets big. And the...?
Û ê tirş, girs nabe.
And the sour one doesn't get big.
Xêr e?
Why (Is it good)?
Bixwe adeta xwe wergî ye. Yanî darek bixwe... yanî darê
hinarê tirş, girs nabe hinarê xwe.
That is just its nature. Meaning a tree itself... meaning
the sour pomegranate tree, its pomegranate doesn't get big.
Bixwe darê hinarê bes du noc ne?
Are there only two types of pomegranate trees?
No. Bixwe sehke ka, em werin ken sinfê vayî sipî... bixwe em
sinfê gind... him tirşî heye û şîrîn jî heye.
No. Look, if we come to the category of the white ones... we
categorize... there is both sour and sweet.
Heye?
Is there?
Erê. Û vîr dibên eslûrî heye. Eslûrî darê hene hinarê xwe
hûrik in. Em vîr dibên cam xu teqrîben em jê xora dibêjin
sedefî mesela.
Yes. And here they say there is "Esluri" (Usfuri). Esluri
trees have small pomegranates. We call it here approximately
"Sedefi" for example.
Bixwe darê... yanî esfûrî vîr dibên. Hûrik in. Hinarê xwe
hûr in. Girs nabe.
The tree itself... meaning they call it Esfuri here. They
are small. Its pomegranates are small. It doesn't get big.
Bixwe... hinarê şekl am, ê ga girs bibe, ev mala... mîna
darê hinarê lefanî şîrîn. Vê dibên...
Generally... the pomegranate that gets big, this family...
like the sweet Lefani pomegranate tree. They call this...
Çend nocê xwe hene?
How many types does it have?
Hinar bixwe yanî... sinfê vî... bixwe em teqrîben cem me
bixwe ga, ê me sinfoke. Sinfoke.
Pomegranates themselves... this category... approximately
with us, ours is a category. A category.
Lefanî şîrîn e heye.
There is sweet Lefani.
Erê.
Yes.
Bes xêrî cem we hene dî?
But do you have others besides it?
Erê. Cûz cem me vayî dibên... dar... ket fransî. Rengê xwe
sor e seke hanû ye. Va rengê heye.
Yes. A part with us they call... tree... fell French. Its
color is red, look like this. This color exists.
Tirş heye û şîrîn heye.
There are sour ones and sweet ones.
Dar heye ku dibe tirş û dibe şîrîn heye?
Is there a tree that becomes sour and becomes sweet?
Na na, ne wek dor e kî do.
No no, it's not like the turn [of the tree] from yesterday.
Belkî nefs... mesela te dît çînî... mesela em bêjin te bi
dorra şan da...
Maybe the same... for example you saw the picking... for
example let's say you gave it by turn...
Yan bi dora wî wergî derdikeve. Mesela tirş heye û şîrîn
heye.
Or by its turn, the yield comes out like that. For example,
there are sour ones and sweet ones.
Bes em bêjin nefs sinfê gişk welle gişk tirş derkewitin, na.
But let's say the same class, that all of them come out
sour, no.
Avdanê gund çûye?
Is the village irrigation gone?
Me berye cerî av dida.
We used to irrigate with flowing water before.
Me motor di şixulandin, me ra motorê me hebûn.
We were operating motors, we had our own motors.
Motorê me, bîrê me 3 înç av in.
Our motors, our wells have 3 inches of water.
Av derdikeve, me bi erqê av dida berdidê, dora me, darê me
şitil çêdikirin...
The water comes out, we used to irrigate via channels by
releasing it, our turn, we used to prepare saplings...
Belkî waye diyim... me şitil av dida. Cerî, me vê re digot
cerî mesela.
Maybe I saw it like this... we watered the saplings.
Flowing, we called this flowing [irrigation] for example.
Yanî avê... ewa. Paşê pey ra hedîs derket.
Meaning the water... yes. Then later the modern [method]
came out.
Me rabû bava min, jima ra, me hedîs kirî, xartûm, tenqîd.
We stood up, my father, for us, we bought the modern one,
hose, drip irrigation.
Neha tenqîd in, erê.
Now they are drip irrigation, yes.
Me xetas kirîn û me berda şûna vî.
We bought submersibles [pumps] and we released it instead of
this.
Ser va ezmê mazotê dera de çi bû çi tiştî hana, mesrefê me
zêde bû.
Due to this diesel crisis that came out and things like
that, our expenses increased.
Me rabû kirne cerî. Em nehatin riya hedîs av didin. Riya
cerî, tenqîdê.
We started doing flowing irrigation. We didn't come to water
via the modern way. The flowing way, [instead of] drip.
Saeta te xweş.
Have a good time.
Ehlen wa sehlen ji were.
You are most welcome.
Tu çawa yî?
How are you?
Hemdillah, tu çawa yî?
Praise God, how are you?
Saeta te xweş.
Have a good time.
Elhemdillah.
Praise be to God.
Tu çi karî dikî li vira?
What work are you doing here?
Işê hinarê dikim.
I am doing pomegranate work.
Dikî flîna?
I am putting them in Styrofoam crates.
Winê çawa dikin? Mezin dikin bin, hûrik dikin ser?
How are you doing it? Putting big ones on the bottom, small
ones on top?
Eh lê, emê hûrik dikine bin, mezin dikine ser. Tiştê jûyî
mestirş em dikine, me neyê gafdarroke.
Yes indeed, we put the small ones on the bottom, the big
ones on top. The thing is separate... we don't have a
supervisor [watching strictly].
Winê mezin dikin ser?
You put the big ones on top?
Ee, em dikin ser.
Yes, we put them on top.
Win çiqas li vir î, tu çiqas xilaz dikî bi tenê?
How long have you been here, how much do you finish alone?
Rojê... avayî sedî dikim.
Daily... I do a hundred of these.
Sedî?
A hundred?
Ee.
Yes.
Sibe de heta êvarê nîvro tu dixebitî?
From morning until evening or noon you work?
Heta nîvro em dixebitin.
We work until noon.
Win sedî xilaz dikin vana?
You finish a hundred of these?
Ee sedî dikim.
Yes, I do a hundred.
Tu bi tenê dixebitî?
Do you work alone?
Ee tenê xwe, keça min bi tenê ye.
Yes just myself, my daughter is alone [with me].
Keça te... ew qişka ew tenê ye?
Your daughter... that little one is alone?
Ee qişka tenê ye.
Yes, the little one is alone.
Temaşevanên hêja, wek we dît çawa ev karker bûn, çawa ev
karker hatin sibe, saet şeşan de ketin karê xwe.
Dear viewers, as you saw how these workers were, how these
workers came in the morning, at six o'clock they started
their work.
Hatin hinar berhev kirin. Kar û barê vê gundî gelem e.
They came and gathered pomegranates. The work and business
of this village is mostly this.
Xwediyê vê zeviyê, ew jî li kêlek min e. Em spasî dikin,
saeta te xweş.
The owner of this field, he is also by my side. We thank
you, have a good time.
Saeta te jî xweş.
Have a good time as well.
Tu bi xêr hatî.
You are welcome.
Ê hazir a, ê giştka xweş, û milletê Kurd pav da saeta xwe
xweş.
Those present, everyone is good, and the Kurdish nation all
together, have a good time.
Ê we jî xweş.
Yours as well.
Ewa rû... we karê xwe dawî kir?
Those faces... did you finish your work?
Me karê xwe noka me temam kir. Me giştk sefandin, me dogre
kirin.
We have now finished our work. We sorted everything, we
straightened [packed] them.
Me evana, me henek hene virdibêjin 'et lezaq', evana heşt
hinar in.
We have these, we have some they call 'et lezaq'
[adhesive/sticker grade], these are eight pomegranates [per
row/layer].
Me çêkirin, û me pênc hinar kirinê, û me çar hinar jî
kirinê.
We made them, and we put five pomegranates [size], and we
put four pomegranates [size] too.
Û me hûr jî kirinê, me giştk dogre sefandin, dogre çêkirin.
And we did the small ones too, we sorted everything
correctly, prepared them correctly.
Me negebin her sûkê em bifroşin.
So that in every market we can sell them.
Em ji destpêkê de werin... no... hinar.
Let's come from the beginning... now... pomegranates.
Dorê gund da, çend cûre hene?
Around the village, how many types are there?
Cûret hinar a pir in. Cûret hinar a pir in.
The types of pomegranates are many. The types of
pomegranates are many.
Tu gişka zanî?
Do you know all of them?
Ez giştka zanim, bes eger giştka eger bibêm se... pir in.
I know all of them, but if I were to say all of them... they
are many.
Mirov, zira navkê.
Man, just the names.
Hinar, Lefanî şîrîn heye. Lefanî tirş heye. Hinarê tirş
heye. Hinarê qalik sor heye. Hinarê vê dendik heye.
Pomegranates, there is Sweet Lefanî. There is Sour Lefanî.
There is Sour pomegranate. There is Red Peel pomegranate.
There is Pomegranate of this seed [specific seed type].
Hinarê... îçî genda, lûnê xwe sor heye. Enwaet hinar a pir
in.
Pomegranates... inside the fruit, its color is red. The
types of pomegranates are many.
Yanî enwaet hinar a, kani bibêm dora heft heşt nûa heye.
Meaning the types of pomegranates, if I say, there are
around seven or eight types.
Gelo li cemedê ver hene?
Are they present in the frost/cold areas?
Li cem... erê.
In the... yes.
Li Cuma wa?
In the Jume [region]?
Li mentiqa Efrînê pavda hene.
In the Afrin region, they are everywhere.
Lê nuxêre, li hevderna giştk ji mentiqa Efrînê, hev mentiqa,
ji mentiqa Efrînê me nuyatina çandine.
But mostly, everywhere in the Afrin region, all regions,
from the Afrin region we have brought and planted them.
Li gûdera hevderna hene, bes baxçe na da hene, gi... yanî
digehin da hene. Baxçe jî hene, sefandine...
Everywhere else they exist, but they are in the orchards...
meaning where they ripen. Orchards also exist, sorted...
Mesela ji nûekî hez kiriye, ji du nûa hez kiriye û çandiye.
For example, he liked one type, he liked two types and
planted them.
Avdanê gund çawa ye?
How is the village irrigation?
Avdanê gund... bi bîrê jî em av didin. Em bi bîrê jî, em
berdidin, em av didin.
Village irrigation... we water with wells too. With wells
too, we release [flood irrigate], we water.
Û em av didin, bi tenqîdê jî tê avdan.
And we water, it is watered by drip irrigation too.
Hassebî însan reqbeta xwe çi tûne ye.
According to what the person's desire is.
Însan dixwaze heger yekê tenqîd ke, ji ardê xwe dike tenqîd
ke, hinarê xwe bi tenqîdê av dide.
A person wants, if one wants to do drip irrigation, he does
drip irrigation for his land, he waters his pomegranates
with drip irrigation.
Û hegerê wekê bi cerî av de, yanî bi bîrê av de.
And if one waters with flowing water, meaning waters with
the well.
Avê berdidê devik devik, avê berdidê qor, wa qorê hinarê av
dida.
He releases the water mouthful by mouthful [gate by gate],
releases the water in rows, that row of pomegranates is
watered.
Win heftê çend caran av didin?
How many times a week do you water?
Hassebî erd. Erd heye heftê carekê dixwaze. Her pênc ro
carekê dixwaze.
Depending on the soil. There is soil that wants it once a
week. Wants it once every five days.
Û erd heye her deh ro, heta deh du ro, netîce erdê tewrî
rind... yanî çi qasî dirêj key her deh û pênc ro hinar kêm
were avdan.
And there is soil every ten days, up to twelve days, the
result is the best soil... meaning however long you extend
it, every fifteen days the pomegranate [if] watered less [is
okay].
Ji pênc ro da heta deh û pênc ro, hinar kêm ilmê wara avdan.
From five days to fifteen days, pomegranates... that is the
science of their watering.
War avdan?
Their watering?
Mm.
Win çend meha av didin?
How many months do you water?
Em teqrîben pênc meha av didin.
We water for approximately five months.
Pênc meha?
Five months?
Mm.
Ez dibînim erdê Cûmê... erdê xwe avî ye.
I see the Jume soil... its soil is irrigated/wet.
Erê xwe ardê xwe avî ye, û ard li cem me ardê mentiqa kî pir
rind e, ardê sor heye li cem me, ardê gewr heye.
Yes its soil is irrigated, and the land with us is a very
good region, there is red soil with us, there is grey soil.
Ard li cem me li mentiqê bi du nûa heye.
The land with us in the region is of two types.
Va ardê Cûmê, ardê xwe ê sor, hinar têda mesela rind dibin.
This Jume land, its soil that is red, pomegranates in it,
for example, become good.
Û heta deh, deh û pênc ro av didin, hinarê xwe zêde rind
dibe û d'nejih e.
And [even if] watered up to ten, fifteen days, its
pomegranate becomes very good and succeeds.
Ardê gewr bese, hinarê xwe ne wekî ardê sor e.
As for grey soil, its pomegranate is not like the red soil.
Ardê sor, quweta xwe pir e, mawadê xwe pir e, quwetlî ye.
Red soil, its strength is great, its minerals/substances are
great, it is strong.
Ardê gewr hew jî quwetlî ye rind e, lê bes ne wekî ardê sor.
Grey soil is also strong and good, but just not like the red
soil.
Hinarê wî jî d'nejih e û rind dibe ê ardê gewr jî rind dibe.
Its pomegranate also succeeds and becomes good, the grey
soil one also becomes good.
Hew jî her çend ro, pênc ro heta nî dehe ro di vê fetrê de
kî ilmê wara avdan.
That too, every few days, five days up to ten days, in this
period is the science of their watering.
Yanî zêde nabe.
Meaning it shouldn't be more.
Yanî ser dehe ro nikan e bêle.
Meaning over ten days, you cannot leave it.
No, darê hinarê...
Now, the pomegranate tree...
Bi xwe şitil tînin tê?
Do you bring saplings for it?
Darê hinarê bi du nûa tê çandin.
The pomegranate tree is planted in two ways.
Heye em şitil tînin têne, em diçînin.
Sometimes we bring saplings, we plant them.
Û heye em singa dikutin erdê, çûva qut dikin, dikine çûv
wekî bostekê, em qut dikin, û em di erdê da diçînin.
And sometimes we hammer stakes [cuttings] into the ground,
we cut sticks, make sticks like a hand-span, we cut them,
and we plant them in the ground.
Dibe dar?
It becomes a tree?
Dibe dar.
It becomes a tree.
Emrê darê heta çiqas diçe?
How long does the age of the tree go [last]?
...heta pêncî salî heye, yanî dirêj dike heta pêncî salî
dirêj dike.
...it lives up to fifty years, meaning it lasts, it lasts up
to fifty years.
Piştî pêncî salî?
After fifty years?
Piştî pêncî salî, ew dara çi dibe, hasebî xizmetî wî merî,
eger xizmet rind lê kiribe, wê bijî. Eger xizmet rind lê
nekiribe, dar ditixe, çikî gûndê wekî lîfê anaçê dibe, wekî
pembe hana ditixe.
After fifty years, whatever that tree becomes depends on the
person's care. If they cared for it well, it will live. If
they didn't care for it well, the tree decays, it becomes
like a loofah sponge inside, it decays like cotton.
Wi hildikin?
Do they pull it out?
Em hildikin.
We pull it out.
Jê acer didin?
Do you replant/renew it?
Acer didin, merîkî gî... bixwaze ser va acer didin,
biçînin...
We replant it, if a person wants... on top of this, they
replant, they plant...
...awekî hilke, hewa herreyê, yeke tiştî din biçîne, ê
biçîne.
...pull that one out, [unclear word: let it go/remove it],
plant something else, they will plant it.
Dara hinarê li mentîqê me ya Efrînê, çiqas heye? Çiqas dar
hene?
How prevalent is the pomegranate tree in our Afrin region?
How many trees are there?
Welle teqrîben li mentîqê Efrînê hinar, teqrîben nîzîkî
gereke pênc mîlyon dar hebe.
Well, approximately in the Afrin region, pomegranates, there
must be approximately close to five million trees.
Pênc mîlyon dar?
Five million trees?
Erê.
Yes.
Ji ku dere heta ku dere ye yanî?
From where to where does it span?
Ji Dêr Belûtê bigire, hidûdî me yê xerbî de, ji Dêr Belûtê
da bigire heta dere digihî Aqîbê, Meydanê, heta dere digihî
Dêr Siwanê.
Start from Deir Ballout, on our western border, start from
Deir Ballout until it reaches Aqiba, Maydan, until it
reaches Dêr Siwan.
Yanî tu çayî, kirmiz li gî dera heye?
Meaning wherever you go, is it red everywhere?
Li gî dera hinar hene.
There are pomegranates everywhere.
Bes bêtir li vira heye?
But is there more here?
Pir... hinarê pir, li Celemê, li Îskê, li Xezawiyê, li
Şadêrê, li Bircê, li Basûtê, hewa hinar... û li Kurzêlê...
hinar pir li vê gûndayê ye.
Lots... lots of pomegranates are in Jalame, Iska, Ghazawiye,
Shadere, Burj, Basoute, those pomegranates... and in
Kurzêl... pomegranates are abundant in these villages.
Pir li vê gûndayê... ji zeytûnê pir tire?
Abundant in these villages... is it more than olives?
Pir ji zeytûnê pir tire.
Much more than olives.
Zeytûnê pir naçîne?
Don't they plant olives much?
Zeytûn mentîqê me, va mentîqê... ji Dêr Belûtê da heta niha
dere digihî Kurzêlê, zeytûn lê kêmin.
Olives in our area, this area... from Deir Ballout until it
reaches Kurzêl, olives are scarce there.
Giştik hinar, pir e, ardî deştê, ardî avî, gî dibe hinar.
It's all pomegranates, mostly, the plain land, the irrigated
land, it all becomes pomegranates.
Gî dibe hinar?
It all becomes pomegranates?
Erê.
Yes.
Yanî ardî xwe ji wî den çêtire?
Meaning its land is better than that [for olives]?
Ardî hinarê bixo, ardî avî ye. Ardî avî jî... hinar jêre
çêtire diçînin.
The pomegranate land itself is irrigated/watery land. And
irrigated land... pomegranates are better suited for
planting there.
Diçînin.
They plant [them].
Jê kartire? Ji zeytûnê?
Yes.
Is it more profitable? Than olives?
Jê kartire, zeytûnê pir kartire. Zeytûn salekê digire, yekî
nagire. Hinar sal bi sal digire.
More profitable, much more profitable than olives. Olives
yield one year and not the next. Pomegranates yield year
after year.
Sal bi sal digire.
Yields year after year.
Yanî salê çiqas, win kîlo difiroşin?
Yes.
So how much per year, [how much] do you sell a kilo for?
Hasebî sûkê. Eger sûk beha be se, hinar heta nî... bîst û
pênc wereqa... ji sî heta bîst û pênc wereqa tê firotan.
Kîlo.
It depends on the market. If the market is expensive [high
demand], pomegranates sell up to... twenty-five pounds...
from thirty down to twenty-five pounds. A kilo.
Û... deh wereqa da tê firotan heta sî û pênc wereqa.
And... it sells from ten pounds up to thirty-five pounds.
Hasebî anwae û hasebî girsbûnê, û hasebî hûrbûnê hinarê.
Depending on the types, and depending on the size
(largeness), and depending on the smallness of the
pomegranate.
Win dibin ku dere difiroşin?
Where do you take it to sell?
Em dibin, dibin sûq el-hal. Sûq el-hal, ya Efrîn, ya Heleb.
We take it, we take it to the wholesale market. The
wholesale market, either Afrin or Aleppo.
Ya Efrîn, ya Heleb.
Either Afrin or Aleppo.
Win difiroşin, ticor hene?
Yes.
You sell it, are there merchants?
Ticor hene, tên dikirin, "şahîn" vir dixin. Ra dikin û dibin
derve.
There are merchants, they come and buy, they load "Shahin"
trucks [large cargo trucks]. They load them and take them
abroad/outside.
Hawna dibin ku dere hawna?
Where do they take those?
Hawna dibin, dibin... hasebî rexbetî wana. Qisemek ji wana
heye dibe Libnanê. Qisemek ji wana heye dibe Iraqê. Qisemek
ji wana heye dibe Tirkiyê. Qismek heye dibe Şamê. Qismek
heye dibe Dêrazorê. Hasebî... haseb rexbetî şahîn.
They take them, take them... depending on their desire. Some
of them take it to Lebanon. Some of them take it to Iraq.
Some of them take it to Turkey. Some take it to Damascus.
Some take it to Deir ez-Zor. Depending... depending on the
truck's/merchant's desire.
Li wura tune ne? Li wura tune ne hinar?
Are there none there? Are there no pomegranates there?
Li mentîqê wana hinar hene, kêmin.
In their regions, there are pomegranates, [but] they are
scarce.
Li mentîqê me hinar pir in, ra dikin, dibin ê... wa mentîqê,
eger heta hinar jî lê hebin, têra wa mentîqê tûne, derbas
dikin. Meselen dişînin Urdinê. Di Urdinê re derbas dibe
dihere dûr dibe.
Scarce.
Li mentîqê me hinar pir in, ra dikin, dibin ê... wa mentîqê,
eger heta hinar jî lê hebin, têra wa mentîqê tûne, derbas
dikin. Meselen dişînin Urdinê. Di Urdinê re derbas dibe
dihere dûr dibe.
In our region, pomegranates are abundant, they load them and
take them... to those regions, even if they have
pomegranates, it's not enough for those regions, so they let
them pass through. For example, they send to Jordan. Through
Jordan, it passes and goes further.
Tab, noha me got... noha em dan pişiya ten ha... ev o hinarê
çiye ev o?
Okay, now we said... now we came before you... what is this
pomegranate?
Vana hinarê... va hinarê hewa lefan e. Hinarê lefan bixo, ne
şîrîn e, ne tirş e. Mabeynê şîrîn û tirş da ye, vêra dibên
lefan.
These pomegranates... this pomegranate is "lefan" (tangy).
The lefan pomegranate itself is neither sweet nor sour. It
is between sweet and sour, they call this lefan.
Bixo çend nûe hene? Ê tirş û...
How many types are there essentially? The sour and...
Hinarê tirş, hinarê tirş heye, û lefanî tirş heye. Hinarê
tirş heye û lefanî tirş heye.
Sour pomegranate, there is sour pomegranate, and there is
sour-lefan. There is sour pomegranate and sour-lefan.
Hewa lefanî şîrîn vêra dibên. Hewa... vêra dibên lefanî
şîrîn.
This one, they call sweet-lefan. This... they call this
sweet-lefan.
Şîrîn.
Sweet.
Bivoyî ra dibên, lefanî tirş. Lefanî tirş, hewa yanî tirşbûn
vêra heye, yanî ne... zêde, zêde ne tirş e. Ev o vêra dibên
lefanî tirş.
For this one, they say sour-lefan. Sour-lefan, meaning it
has sourness, meaning not... excessively, it is not
excessively sour. This one, they call sour-lefan.
Ev o vêra dibên hinarê lefanî tirş, hewa ev jî nûe kî, xeyrî
lefanî şîrîn e.
This one, they call sour-lefan pomegranate, this is also a
type, different from sweet-lefan.
Bivoyî ra dibên?
What do they call this one?
Hinarê tirş. Ê tirş yanî hewa wekî lîmonê dibe. Yanî vêra
dibên hinarê lîmonî, tirş e. Ev o jî tirş e, ê... vo hinarê
bixo, ê... jwona hûrtir dibe, bes hinarê xwo î mekîne, tirş
e.
Sour pomegranate. The sour one becomes like a lemon. Meaning
they call it lemon pomegranate, it is sour. This one is also
sour, uh... this pomegranate itself... is usually smaller
than those, but it is a solid pomegranate, it is sour.
Û vayî sor?
And the red one?
Vayî sor, vêra dibên hinarê Fransî.
The red one, they call it French pomegranate.
Fransî? Xêr nav lê kirine Fransî yanî?
French? Why did they name it French?
Welle nav lê kirine... hewna va li mentîqê me nav lê kirine.
Well, they named it... just like that in our area, they
named it.
Ji Fransa hatiye?
Did it come from France?
Belesil (bi esil), navê xwo hinarê sor e. Hinarê sor, bi
navê xwo bi Kurmancî ye. Bes welakin, li va derê, car kî li
mentîqê nav lê kirine, enû hinarê Fransî. Bes navê xwo
hinarê sor e.
Originally, its name is Red Pomegranate. Red Pomegranate,
its name is in Kurmanji. But however, here, at some point in
the region they named it French pomegranate. But its name is
Red Pomegranate.
Hinarê qalik sor.
Red.
Red-peel Pomegranate.
Şîrîn e lê tirş e?
Is it sweet or sour?
Ev o nûe kî heye jî şîrîn e, û nûe kî jê heye lefan e, û nûe
kî jê heye tirş e.
There is a type of this that is sweet, and a type of it is
lefan (tangy), and a type of it is sour.
Tirş e.
It is sour.
Nûe î tirş heye, û nûe î şîrîn heye, û nûe î lefan heye. Sê
nûe ne. Ev o jî. Sê nûe ji voyî hene.
There is a sour type, and a sweet type, and a lefan type.
They are three types. This one too. There are three types of
this one.
Û dimsê hinarê çawa çêdikin?
And how do you make pomegranate molasses?
A dimsê hinarê... emê hinarê berî gî o...
Ah, pomegranate molasses... first, all the pomegranates...
Ev o dimsê hinarê ye?
Is this pomegranate molasses?
Hevo dimsê hinarê ye. Berî gî o, emê hinarê bi tanekin.
Yes.
This is pomegranate molasses. First of all, we beat the
pomegranates [with sticks].
Haa.
I see.
Emê hinarê bi tanekin, ji tanebûnê, emê hinarê biguvşin. Emê
biguvşin, bi hecqînin, emê avê gîndê derxînin.
We beat the pomegranates, after beating, we squeeze the
pomegranates. We squeeze them, crush them, we extract the
juice out of them.
Me av çêkir, bi şûnda, emê avê gîndê dînin ser êgir, emê
têkin ne berûşê, bisafînin. Emê bisafînin, bi süzekê, emê
têkin ne berûşê, û emê bikelînin.
Once we made the juice, afterwards, we put the juice on the
fire, we put it in the cauldron, we filter it. We filter it
with a strainer, we put it in the cauldron, and we boil it.
O wan tişta li mal çêdikin lê maasara kî xûye heye?
Ah, do you make these things at home or is there a specific
factory?
Na, em li mal çêdikin. Her kes malê xwo çêdike.
No, we make it at home. Everyone makes it at their own home.
Emê çêke, emê dînin ser êgir, emê bikelînin, heta ni... dibe
wekî dims tîr dibe, çîçikî, yanî rind dibe. Wî çaxê emê êgir
vemirînin, wê sar bibe. Emê rakin têkin ne ya golone, ya
qetremîza, û emê têkin ne şûşê, emê paşê jî bifiroşin.
We make it, we put it on the fire, we boil it, until... it
becomes like molasses, it thickens a bit, meaning it becomes
good. At that time we turn off the fire, it will cool down.
We pick it up and put it in either a gallon jug or jars, and
we put it in bottles, and then we sell it.
Win bi çi difiroşin vî?
How much do you sell this for?
Vî, dimsê hinarê, heger rind pak be û paqij be se, dused
pêncî heta bi sêsidî kîlo tê firotan. Kîlo.
This, pomegranate molasses, if it is really good and clean,
it sells for two hundred fifty up to three hundred per kilo.
A kilo.
Yanî şûşek bi dused pêncî ye?
So a bottle is two hundred fifty?
Şûşek bi dused pêncî.
A bottle for two hundred fifty.
Kîlok têdaye?
Is there a kilo in it?
Kîlok têdaye.
There is a kilo in it.
Ee avo fêdê xwo çiye fêdê? Meriv jibo çi?
Uh, what is the benefit of this? What does one use it for?
Fêdê dimsê hinarê, heger safî ji hinarê tirş be se, heger
safî ji hinarê tirş be se, fêdê xwo li dil heye.
The benefit of pomegranate molasses, if it is purely from
sour pomegranates, if it is purely from sour pomegranates,
its benefit is for the heart.
Dil. Ee... nexweşiya dil quwetli dike. Nexweşiya dil, bi
însên ra zeîf... yanî pê çêdibe. Pê fêdê jê dibîne. Lî ew
xêra madê xwo... ewê tiştî şuhûmat dihelîne. Dihelîne.
For the heart.
Dil. Ee... nexweşiya dil quwetli dike. Nexweşiya dil, bi
însên ra zeîf... yanî pê çêdibe. Pê fêdê jê dibîne. Lî ew
xêra madê xwo... ewê tiştî şuhûmat dihelîne. Dihelîne.
Heart. Uh... it strengthens heart disease [strengthens the
heart against disease]. Heart disease, if weak in a
person... meaning they get better with it. They see benefit
from it. Besides that, its substance... that thing dissolves
fats (cholesterol). It dissolves them.
Û hinar jî weye?
And the pomegranate [fruit] is the same?
Hinar jî weye.
The pomegranate is the same.
Bes dims pêtir. Eger dims ji hinarê tirş safî be.
But molasses is more so. If the molasses is purely from sour
pomegranates.
Ê bas heger muxtela... yanî gî tevlihev dibin, ê şîrîn û ê
lefan û ê tirş gî tevlihev dibin se, xeyrî gava hinar safî,
ê tirş be.
But if it's mixed... meaning all are mixed together, the
sweet and the lefan and the sour are all mixed together, it
is different than when the pomegranate is pure, the sour
one.
Neha avo çiye avo?
Now what is this one?
Hewa tevlihev di ye. Hinarê lefan e jî, û ê şîrîn e jî. Me
tevlihev, me çêkiriye.
This one is mixed. It's lefan pomegranates, and sweet ones.
We mixed it, we made it.
Tamê xwo çawa tê?
How is its taste?
Avo tamê xwo pir xweş e. Hinekî xwa jêre be vexwe, seh ke çi
tamê xwo heye.
Its taste is very good. Take a little for yourself,
eat/drink it, see what taste it has.
Xweş e.
It's good.
Ne?
No? [Isn't it?]
Naha dibên dikin salata jî ne?
Now they say they put it in salad too, right?
Voyî dikine salata, dikine nav goşt, dikine nav zeytûna,
hasebî rexbetî însên. Hasebî rexbetî însên, heya vedixwe...
heya dike şûrûb vedixwe. Çawa dilê xwo xwest, wergî dike
dimsê hinarê...
They put this in salads, they put it in meat, they put it in
olives, depending on the person's desire. Depending on the
person's desire, some drink it... some make syrup and drink
it. However their heart desires, that's how they use
pomegranate molasses...
Yanî merov... yanî gerek însan birû li xwdê vexe yanî.
Meaning one... meaning a person must really consume it, by
God.
Gerek e dimsê hinarê her merîk vexe û îstîmal ke, ma'ne
salata, û ma'ne nav zeytûna, û ma'ne bi şerab ke vexe, fêdê
xwo nefeet pir e. Hem xweş e, hem derman e, hem lezetî xwo,
tamê xwo pir xweş e. Xaseten eger têkeve nav goşt, têkeve
şîva, pir xweş dibe.
It is necessary that every person eats and uses pomegranate
molasses, meaning for salads, and meaning in olives, and
meaning to make as a drink and consume, its benefit, the
utility is great. It is both good, and it is a cure, and its
delight, its taste is very good. Especially if it goes into
meat, goes into dinner, it becomes very good.
Em te spasî dikin. Em hêvîştin dawiya bernameya xwo.
Xwesteka we hene?
We thank you. We have reached the end of our program. Do you
have any requests?
Xwestekê me, silavê min ji her merîkî Kurd ra heye, û silavê
min ji qanatî Ronahî ra jî heye, û her merîk dengî me
dibîse, giştik silavê min ji giya ra hene, û saetê giya jî
xweş.
My request, I have greetings for every Kurdish person, and I
have greetings for the Ronahî channel as well, and every
person who hears our voice, all of them, my greetings to
all, and may everyone have a good time.
Te jî xweş. Em dixwazin tiştekî giştik bibîsin.
You have a good time too. We want to hear something general
[a song].
(Singing) Erê nema dilî milyan ey...
(Singing) Oh, there is no comfort/patience left for the
hearts...
(Singing) Erê nema dilî milyan ey...
(Singing) Oh, there is no comfort left for the hearts...
(Singing) Erê Alî Beg derket qesra rengîn, birca belek,
dayîra giran ey.
(Singing) Oh, Ali Beg came out of the colorful palace, the
speckled tower, the grand circle.
(Singing) Rûnişt li ser kursiyê sê-çuk û çar-lingan ey.
(Singing) He sat on the chair with three legs and four legs.
(Singing) Li hember... li hember behra 'umyan ey.
(Singing) Facing... facing the ocean of the blind (or deep
ocean).
(Singing) Erê ne balê Xwedê, sûk û çarşiyê bajorê muxribê
ye. Balê Xwedê xarzê dimeşin derin malê xalo nayî, ne birazî
dimeşin derin malê apan ey.
(Singing) Oh, by God's attention, the markets and bazaars of
the western city. By God's attention, the nephews (sister's
sons) walk going to the maternal uncle's house, and the
nephews (brother's sons) walk going to the paternal uncle's
house.
Saet xweş.
Good health [Well sung].
(Singing) Erê ne çavê Alî Begê li êkêt li xwarz û li
biraziyan ey.
(Singing) Oh, Ali Beg's eye did not fall upon the nephews
(sister's side) nor the nephews (brother's side).
(Singing) Erê newî çaxê deng lê kir li erdê beran ey.
(Singing) Oh, at that time he called out to the barren/wild
land.
(Singing) Erê go lawo keko mebire, her yekî sê-çar êxsîr ke
eyalê jinan ey.
(Singing) Oh, he said, son, brother, don't take [them],
everyone capture three or four women as captives.
(Singing) Erê bima her sê bira tenê, ewladikî ji ewlada li
şûnê me bibê siltan ey. Heger em serê xwe dînin axa gora
kelaka bimirin.
(Singing) Oh, let only the three brothers remain, so one
child of the children may become Sultan in our place. If we
lay our heads on the soil of the grave and die on our sides.
(Singing) Erê miletê me yê Kurda, wê perîşan bikeve, wê
bimîne mîna pezekî lal o, vê şivan ey.
(Singing) Oh, our Kurdish nation, it will fall into misery,
it will remain like a mute flock of sheep, oh shepherd.
(Singing) Erê... newî çaxê erdê beran ten, cem Alî Begê
rûniştin, beramberî kirin şêwr û mişêwrê xo. Gotin emê
berdin qesra rengîn, birca belek, dayîra giran ey. Emê li xo
kin, kin cê dewrîşan ey.
(Singing) Oh... at that time the barren land became narrow,
they sat with Ali Beg, they held their council and
consultation opposite each other. They said we will abandon
the colorful palace, the speckled tower, the grand circle.
We will dress ourselves in the clothes of dervishes.
[Music]