Belê temaşevanên hêja, îcarê jî em li gundê Çema ne.
Yes dear viewers, this time we are in the village of Chama.
Gundê Çema girêdayî navçeya Şera ye.
The village of Chama belongs to the district of Shara.
Rojavayê gund çemek derbas dibe.
A river passes through the west of the village.
Gelo ev navê gund ji wî çemî hatiye, yan jî ji derek din
hatiye?
Did the name of this village come from that river, or did it
come from somewhere else?
Ka vê hefteyê em derbasî gundê Çema bibin, em bi hev ra nas
bikin.
Let us enter the village of Chama this week, and let's get
to know it together.
Apê Hec Qedrî merheba ji te ra.
Uncle Hec Qedrî, hello to you.
Merheba, ehlen.
Hello, welcome.
Ehlen û merheba, ji hatina we ra, ji qenala Ronahî ra.
Welcome and hello, to your arrival, to Ronahi channel.
Û ewê me şehîdên me hene, û ji birîndaran ra şîfayê
dixwazim.
And we have our martyrs, and I wish healing for the wounded.
Û ji temaşevanan ra jî, hazir û giyan ra, hurmet û selamê me
hene.
And to the viewers, those present and all souls, we offer
our respect and greetings.
Spas ji te ra apê Hec Qedrî.
Thank you, Uncle Hec Qedrî.
Gundê we Çema, nav ji ku hatiye?
Your village Chama, where did the name come from?
Navê Çema, berê kevn e.
The name Chama, it is old.
Ji avên şimalî me dertên, geliyê Sîmanê, av e, av çem e yanî
xwedê.
From the waters that come out north of us, the Siman valley,
it is water, water is a river ("çem") basically.
Rojavayî me Efrîn e, çemê Efrîn e.
To our west is Afrin, the Afrin river.
Hema navê wî ji vê hatiye, ev navê minin lê daniye.
So its name came from this, this is the name they gave it.
Û dîroka xwe jî kevn e, dîrokê xwe, em nizanin çiqas sal da,
yanî hatiye avakirin.
And its history is old, its history, we don't know in which
year, meaning, it was built.
Ew cîyên dîrokî jî bawerim hene?
I believe there are historical sites as well?
Cîyên dîrokî kevn hene.
There are old historical sites.
Wekî Xirabê Sîman heye, Xirabê Çartaqê heye, hemna şikeftên
kevn in.
Like the Ruins of Siman, the Ruins of Chartaq, they are all
old caves.
Di gund da, ew pêş şikeft hene.
Inside the village, there are those front caves.
Şikeftên kevn in. Hemna.
They are old caves. All of them.
Berê însan têda dijiyan, dewarê xwe dikirnê, îşte yanî
heyat, jiyan têda derbas dikirin yanî.
Humans used to live in them, kept their animals there, well,
meaning life, they spent their lives in them.
Erê, şikeft bûn.
Yes, they were caves.
Gundê we Çema çend malbat in?
How many families are in your village, Chama?
Gundê Çema, şeş malbat tê hene.
The village of Chama, there are six families in it.
Bes yanî çar, hemna Mala Elî Şêr in, dibên.
But four, they are all the House of Ali Sher, they say.
Noka qicik mezin nizane Mala Elî Şêr.
Now the small and big [young and old] don't know the House
of Ali Sher [by that name].
Dibên hema Mala Îbê, hema Mala Misê, hema Mala Hemê.
They say just House of Ibi, just House of Misi, just House
of Hami.
Hema Mala Me'mê û Ne'sê ye, hema Mala Ûsê ye, Hespisîyo ye.
Just House of Ma'mi and Na'si, just House of Usi, Hespisiyo.
Ev malbatna hene di gund da yanî.
These families exist in the village.
Erê.
Yes.
Wekî dên berî... dên, bar, wextê şên bûye, ava bûye ev
gunda...
Like they say before... they say, back when it was
populated, when this village was built...
Yanî malbatên, sê malbat hebûn, paşê xîlaf ketî mabeyna wan
û wana, ew sê malbatna bar kirin.
Meaning families, there were three families, then a conflict
occurred between them, and those three families moved away.
Mala Qelqê, Mala Hemîkê, Mala Hûrê bûn.
They were the House of Qelqi, House of Hemiki, House of
Huri.
Û di gund da jiyan kirine, got teqrîben du sed, sê sed mal
heye Çema.
And they lived in the village, saying there were
approximately two hundred, three hundred households in
Chama.
Gundekî kevn e, dîroka xwe kevn e.
It is an old village, its history is old.
Yanî em nagihîjin dîroka gund.
Meaning we cannot reach [don't recall] the history of the
village.
Kevn e?
It is old?
Kevn e, erê.
It is old, yes.
Miletê we derketî, derve jî hene?
Have your people gone out, are there any outside/abroad?
Miletê me derketine, wekî Efrînê, wekî Helebê...
Our people have gone out, like to Afrin, like to Aleppo...
Derketine Helebê, derketine Şamê, derketine Efrînê,
derketine bajarra yanî.
They went to Aleppo, went to Damascus, went to Afrin, went
to the cities.
Erê. Pir derketine.
Yes. Many have left.
Paşê di vê ezmê da, hinek şûnda vegerîne hatine yanî.
Then during this crisis, some have returned back.
Wextê di vê ezmê da vegerîne hatin, wekî hefteyê malî di
gund da girtin.
When they returned during this crisis, they occupied about
seventy houses in the village.
Di vê ezmê da. Enk ji der va hatine yanî.
During this crisis. Those who came from outside.
Erê.
Yes.
Gund, dîroka xwe kevn e.
The village, its history is old.
Û Kurd in. Û ji Kurdistana kevn e.
And they are Kurds. And it is from ancient Kurdistan.
Kurdistana jî dîroka xwe...
Kurdistan's history as well...
Dîroka xwe şeş hezar sal vir da ye. Ji gura Îbrahîm
Aleyhîselam da.
Its history is six thousand years back. Since the time of
Abraham, peace be upon him.
Kurd hene.
Kurds exist.
Heta nîmek, wextê Îbrahîm Aleyhîselam çêkirin agir...
Even, when they made the fire for Abraham, peace be upon
him...
Tefsîrê Ibn Kesîr, dibê bi îşaretê siwarekî Kurd, Îbrahîm
Aleyhîselam çêkirine agir, navê wî jî Heyzen bû.
The Tafsir of Ibn Kathir says that with the signal of a
Kurdish horseman, they made the fire for Abraham, peace be
upon him, and his name was Hayzan.
Wa siwarî. Navê xwe Heyzen bû.
That horseman. His name was Hayzan.
Hema Tefsîrê Ibn Kesîr, ji me ra beyan dike.
The Tafsir of Ibn Kathir declares this to us.
Kê, Kurd dîroka xwe kevn e, ji gura Îbrahîm Aleyhîselam da
Kurd hebûye.
Who, the Kurds, their history is old, since the time of
Abraham, peace be upon him, Kurds have existed.
Û jiyan kirî, dîroka xwe bernedaye, dîroka xwe bernedane,
welew dagirkerra hatiye Kurdistan dagirker kirine.
And they lived, they didn't give up their history, didn't
give up their history, even if occupiers came and occupied
Kurdistan.
Kurda zimanê xwe bernedaye, axa xwe bernedane.
The Kurds did not give up their language, did not give up
their land.
Welew xelkê lê hukim kirî, Kurd ser erdê xwe neçûye. Ser axa
xwe neçûye.
Even if people ruled over them, the Kurd did not leave his
ground. Did not leave his land.
Belê, nah wa bahs dikir, cîyên dîrokî di gundê we da hene,
efê Rûm e?
Yes, you were mentioning, there are historical places in
your village, are these Roman?
Tê dê bêje, berda Kurd livir nîn, li Kurdistanê?
You are saying, before that Kurds were not here, in
Kurdistan?
Rûm hatiye...
The Romans came...
Ereb hatiye, Tirk hatiye, yekî din hatiye.
Arabs came, Turks came, another one came.
Hemna cîyê xwe dane.
They all left their mark [places].
No, apê Hecî gundê we, wek gundê Çema, debara xwe bi çi
dikin?
Now, Uncle Hecî, your village, as the village of Chama, how
do they make their living?
Debara xwe, gundekî jûtarî ye.
Their livelihood, it is a farming village.
Erdê xwe hene, zeytûnê xwe hene. Reze xwe hene.
They have their lands, they have their olives. They have
their vineyards.
Ê... ewit xwe hene, têda îşte... genim diçînin, ce diçînin,
nûka diçînin, cihê diçînin, zeytûna xwe hene, reza xwe hene.
Uh... they have their things, in it they, well... plant
wheat, plant barley, plant chickpeas, plant lentils, they
have their olives, have their vineyards.
Pê dijîn.
They live by it.
Û firaniya ciwana waha, karê terzileqê zani dikin.
And the majority of the youth like that, they do vegetable
farming ("terzileq").
Hê... karê terzileqê, di gund da pir e.
Yeah... vegetable farming work, is abundant in the village.
Erê. Hin li Efrînê, hin li vir dikin.
Yes. Some do it in Afrin, some do it here.
Hinek li Heleb dikirin.
Some used to do it in Aleppo.
Erê. Karê terzileqê dikin.
Yes. They do vegetable farming.
Erê, ew kara heye.
Yes, that work exists.
Mala te ava be apê.
May your house be prosperous, Uncle.
Xwedê ji we razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Gundê Çema girêdayî navçeya Şera ya kantona Efrînê, 17
kîlometre li bajaroka Şera, û 20 kîlometre li bakurê bajarê
Efrînê dikeve.
The village of Chama belongs to the Shara district of the
Afrin canton, situated 17 kilometers from the town of Shara,
and 20 kilometers north of the city of Afrin.
Navê gundê Çema ji dewlemendiya deverê, bi av û çeman
hatiye.
The name of Chama village comes from the richness of the
area, with water and rivers.
Cihê gund kevnare, û gelek şikeft têda hene.
The location of the village is ancient, and there are many
caves in it.
Tê texmîn kirin ku di wan şikeftan da, gel di demên borî da
jiyan dikirin.
It is estimated that in those caves, people lived in past
times.
Derdora 200 xanî di gund da heye, û nêzî 2000 kes di gund
dijîn.
There are around 200 houses in the village, and close to
2000 people live in the village.
Malbata Elî Şan, yekemîn malbat di gundê Çema da niştecîh
bûye.
The family of Ali Shan was the first family to settle in the
village of Chama.
Di gel van malbatan, gelek malbatên din jî hatine li vir
niştecîh bûne.
Along with these families, many other families also came and
settled here.
Du dibistan li gund hene, ku di şoreşa Kurdistanê da şehîd
bûne, bi navê wan hatine û ekînin.
There are two schools in the village, named after those who
were martyred in the Kurdistan revolution, and they are
active.
Her wiha komîngeha gund bi navê şehîd Kawa hatiye
binavkirin.
Likewise, the village commune has been named after Martyr
Kawa.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, naha jî em ji gundê Çema derketin, me
berê xwedê geliyê Sîmanê, av ji vir derdikeve.
Yes dear viewers, now we have left the village of Chama, we
headed towards the Siman Valley, water comes out from here.
Sê gund avê xwe ji vir dibin: Gundê Çema, gundê Qerqîna,
gundê Ba'rava.
Three villages take their water from here: Chama village,
Qerqina village, Ba'rava village.
Naha dayik bi me ra derbas vir bûn, em spasya wan dikin, em
ê bi hevra dayika nas bikin.
Now the mothers have come here with us, we thank them, we
will get to know the mothers together.
Berê çawa dihatin av ji vir dibirin.
[To learn] How they used to come and take water from here in
the past.
Em destpêkê wa nas bikin.
Let's get to know them first.
Navê min Şaziye ye.
My name is Shaziye.
Ser çava.
You are welcome [Literally: On my eyes].
Ehlen we sehlen. Navê min Fatme ye.
Welcome. My name is Fatme.
Ser çavê min dayê. Dayê em navê te jî zanibin?
You are welcome, mother. Mother, may we know your name too?
Ehlen we sehlen. Navê min Fatme ye.
Welcome. My name is Fatme.
Ser çava. Bûn du Fatme?
You are welcome. Are there two Fatmes?
Erê.
Yes.
Ê... dayika me inşallah. Em ji destpêkê cem te destpê bikin.
Uh... our mothers, God willing. Let's start with you first.
Berî em werin walgund bahs dikir, digot berê me dihat av ji
vir dibir.
Before we came, the villagers were discussing, saying "we
used to come and take water from here in the past."
Em dihatin bi dewêr, bi kuna, kunê lastîkî me dihat av ji vê
kaniyê dibir. Av li gund tunebû.
We used to come with animals, with waterskins, rubber
waterskins, we used to come and carry water from this
spring. There was no water in the village.
Paşê bîr çêbûn, ava şîrketê hat.
Later wells were made, the company [government/network]
water came.
Ê noka neyn vira, noka vir laxû bûye, neyn vira.
So now we don't come here, now here is canceled [abandoned],
we don't come here.
Ê dayê, berî vê bi çend salan we dihat av ji vir dibir?
So mother, how many years ago did you come to take water
from here?
Ê wele emrê min noka 47 sal in, yanê ya dixe heqîzek, ya
gişta me dibir. Em dihatin me dibir.
Well, my age is 47 years now, meaning since I was a
child/young girl, we all carried it. We used to come and
carry it.
Ê bû teqrîben sê sal hen ji vir nabin.
It has been approximately three years that they don't carry
from here.
Ji vir nabin.
They don't carry from here.
Hm.
Ava hikûmetê heye, û bîr lê xistine, her malekê bîrek xwe
heye.
There is government water, and they dug wells, every house
has its own well.
We çawa av ji vir dibir, yanê nika zehmet jî hebu? Gund tadî
li jor e, û ev jî gelî ye...
How did you carry water from here, I mean was there hardship
too? The village is way up there, and this is a valley...
Zehmet e... em bi lingan dihatin. Bi lingan dihatin, bi
kuna, bi kera, bi dewêr dihatin dibirin.
It is hard... we used to come on foot. We came on foot, with
waterskins, with donkeys, with animals we came and carried
it.
Dibin da diketin.
They would fall under [the load].
Lê, bi kunê lastîkî, li keran dikirin dihatin dibirin, yanê,
ew min bi xwe hat, ber, ya giştê me bir.
But, with rubber waterskins, we loaded them on donkeys and
came to carry, meaning, I myself came, carried, all of us
carried.
Yanê bi denê davêtin ser pişta xwe?
So they used to carry the cans on their backs?
Na, bi davêr dibir, erê.
No, they carried it with a strap/rope, yes.
Teneke hebûn, li ser kerê radigirtin û kindir û lastîk hebûn
li ser radigirtin, pê dibirin.
There were tin cans, they secured them on donkeys, and there
were ropes and rubber bands to hold them, that’s how they
carried it.
Heye na pir gundê me heye ne, û sa dikin, yanê heye na diçin
kaniyê û çawa dawêr dibin, xweşikbûna gunda heye na?
Is our village still full [lively], like, do they still go
to the spring and carry straps? Is the beauty of the village
still there?
Wele na, berê bîst sî sal heye, yanê belkî ser sî salî ra,
yanê noka nehingî lê.
Oh no, that was twenty or thirty years ago, maybe even over
thirty years, now it is not like that at all.
Eba bavê di navbera bo Qerqîna û vana, yanê gundî me
elhemdulelah noka nayên birin.
Here between Qerqîna and the others, thank God, our village
doesn't get carried away [empty out] now.
Ê rojê bi çend cara dihatin av dibir?
How many times a day did they come to fetch water?
Ê de haseb mal hebu kulfet bibû, mal hebu kulfetî hindik
bibû, haseb mala.
Well, it depended, some houses had large families, some
houses had small families, it depended on the household.
Mal hebu du cara dihatin, sê cara dihatin, mal hebu neqlekê
dihatin. Haseb kulfet, haseb mala.
Some households came twice, three times, some came once.
According to the family size, according to the house.
Jin bi tenê dihatin, lê mêr jî dihatin?
Did only women come, or did men come too?
Ê kib (keç) hev diketin. No jin bi hev ra dihatin, qîz, jin,
bûk, meriv bi hev ra dihatin.
Well, the girls gathered together. No, women came together;
girls, women, brides, relatives came together.
Yanê kaniya me bareşên bû. Tim şênayî bû, milet pir bû, tirs
tune bû, dihatin bi hev ra.
I mean, our spring was very crowded. It was always lively,
there were many people, there was no fear, they came
together.
Ne bi tenê, erê ban hev dikirin, cîran ban hev dikirin, bi
hev ra dihatin.
Not alone, yes, they called each other, neighbors called
each other, and they came together.
Ez dixwazim hinekî sê pirs bikim. Ne de dê her cîkî av hebe,
gere baxçe hebin.
I want to ask you a bit too. Wherever there is water, there
must be orchards.
Lê, baxçe hebûn yara min, hêjîr hebûn, sêv hebûn, mişmiş
hebûn, hirmîk hebûn, gûz hebûn.
Yes, there were orchards my dear, there were figs, apples,
apricots, pears, walnuts.
Kesî nediqarfa, pir wutan jî tune bû.
No one forbade it [picking fruit], and there wasn't much
strictness either.
Yanê em biçûna karê xwe me bikira, em dihatin li vî derî xwe
dişûştin.
Meaning, if we went to do our work, we would come and wash
ourselves at this place.
Em ji karê xwe me... ew kiriye, me palê çiniye, me dikir,
emê Batana, Gêlê, Qerqîna, Berava, Çema, gi li vî derî kom
dibûn.
When we finished our work... harvested, did the labor, those
from Batan, Gêl, Qerqîna, Berava, Çema, everyone gathered
here.
Wekî xakbiraka.
Like a gathering of land-siblings [a very close community
gathering].
Yanê wekî dawetê.
Like a wedding.
Êwa. Me bot, serê kincê xwe li vir dişûştin, av bierdana...
Yes. We brought things, washed our clothes here, let the
water run...
Yanê mala mirov digotin Henîfe, tu çûyî mişemehere...
Meaning, at home they would say, "Hanife, you went to..."
Henîfe kî ye?
Who is Hanife?
Henîfe dêyika min e. Henîfa Gulê. Dêyika min e.
Hanife is my mother. Hanife of Gule. She is my mother.
Mm. Ê kincê xwe bi şûştana, paşê jî seletokê xwe çêkirana,
bixwarana, vexwarana, hilkişîna biçûna.
Mm. Yes, they would wash their clothes, then make their
salads, eat, drink, pack up and go.
Êwa. Yanê hanokî bû, haskirin hebû, merlaqê hebû. Yanê
tefrîq tune bû.
Yes. Meaning, it was like that, there was love, there was
humanity. There was no division.
Te got darê gûza, darê fêkiya hebûn.
You said there were walnut trees, fruit trees.
Êwa. Eletûl emê li vî derî li gelê bûn.
Yes. We were always here in the valley with the people.
Carê gamnêtan a ruyê neqlekê gela, me nika xew kira, hingî
gelî xweş bû, şên bû.
Sometimes... [unclear phrase, possibly regarding
napping/resting]... the valley was beautiful and lively
then.
Eynî çem darik e, û dar û berê xwe heye, baxçe ne.
The river is bordered by trees, it has its trees and
produce, they are orchards.
Dar berê xwe pir e, baxçe ne. Êwa.
The trees have lots of produce, they are orchards. Yes.
Û pitek a me hebû li vî derî, digot werin, werin, kî çi jî
bixwe, wî nêt. Kefşîdan kî wî nêt.
And we had an aunt/elder here, she would say "Come, come,"
whoever eats whatever, let them. Even the cobblers, let
them.
Yara min hingî cavteng bû jî. Digot werin, werin, hil darê
ranîn, li darê dinêrin.
My dear, back then it was tight/strict too. She said "Come,
come," they climbed the trees, looked into the trees.
Hama em qicik in, emê kê binêrin.
But we are small, whom shall we look at.
Êwa. Wa digo.
Yes. She said that.
Ê, dadê, tu çend salî ye?
So, mother, how old are you?
Emrê min, belkî heftê û didu, heftê û sê... heftê û heft
hene. Heftê û heft.
My age, maybe seventy-two, seventy-three... seventy-seven
exist. Seventy-seven.
Xwedê bide te dadê.
May God give you [long life], mother.
Ê dadê, ew xweşikbûna berê çiqas xweş bûn. Dem, berê milet
bi hev diket, dihat.
So mother, that beauty of the past was so nice. The times,
before when the people gathered and came together.
Berê îstonata hebû, iştavtar dibên, berê yanê haskirin hebû.
In the past there was stability, they call it gathering,
back then there was love.
Berê yanê gi wekî xakbiraka bûn. Ha.
In the past, everyone was like land-siblings [kin]. Yeah.
Yanê arvanî yekî nema bû, rûkê diroy sê ro ar ji hev deyn
dikirin, bilxur deyn dikirin.
Meaning, if someone ran out of flour, for two or three days
they borrowed flour from each other, borrowed bulgur.
Didan hev. Berê kanî yarim, noka tune bavê te birçî.
They gave to each other. Where is the past, my dear? Now
there isn't any, even if your father is hungry.
Îşta hanokî ye. Te kê bêje çi yarim.
That's how it is. What can you say to whom, my dear.
Ma pir tengî dît, ma tengî jî dît û ma ferehlixê jî dît.
We saw a lot of hardship, we saw hardship and we saw relief.
Û dîsa xirabûna tengiya tewra paşîn e. Xirabûna tewra paşîn
e yarim.
And again, the badness of hardship is at the very end. The
worst destruction is at the end, my dear.
Ha.
Yeah.
Ê dadê, te behsa dayika xwe kir. Ew jinê vira dihatin kî bûn
di gunda?
So mother, you mentioned your mother. Those women who came
here, who were they in the village?
Jinê dihatin, jinê d' abka bûn, jinê d' braka bûn, jinê d'
cîrana bûn.
The women who came, they were women with water pitchers,
women with containers, neighbor women.
Tu navê wan bêje, belkî...
Say their names, maybe...
Hemî rehmetî jî bûne.
They have all passed away too.
Ê hawno gi rehmetî bûn.
So they are all deceased.
Amojna Hûr bû, Xac bû... ê em bêjin Ayşo me bû, xaltiya vê.
There was Aunt Hur, Xac... uh, let's say our Aysho, her
aunt.
Ê em bibêjin tişta gi bûn, Zeynû bû, havno gi dihatin. Navê
berê ne havno, ka navê noka hene, havno nav?
Uh, let's say they were all there, Zeynu was there, they all
came. The names of the past are not like these, are there
names like those now?
Hine hene, hine...
Some exist, some...
Hine. Tişta, wa nav naîn, pê nav dikin.
Some. Those things, those names don't come back, they don't
name people that.
Wa navê berê, Ayş û Gul û hîna, halê pê nav dikin.
Those old names, Aysh and Gul and such, they still name
people that sometimes.
Êwa. Îşta hanokî bû, te kê bêje çi yarim.
Yes. It was like that, what can you say to whom, my dear.
Ka em hinekî ji dadê bipirsim.
Let me ask mother [the other woman] a bit.
Dadê?
Mother?
Heee...
Yeaah...
Em nuh li ber avê jî rûniştine, dengê avê jî tê me.
We are sitting by the water now, the sound of the water is
coming to us.
Lê.
Yes.
Çi tîne bîra te, dema nav vî dengê avê tê te?
What does it remind you of, when this sound of water comes
to you?
Dengê avê tê min, tişta em dihatin ber, xweş bû, rind bû,
noka hindik e av ko, hewa wa hindik e hene noka.
The sound of the water comes to me, the things we used to
come for, it was nice, it was good, now the water is scant,
the weather/atmosphere is scant like this now.
Yanê tib seata binêrî tib demê nahesî vira?
Meaning if you look at the hours [pass time here], you don't
feel the time passing?
Lê? No, no. Xweş bû, rind bû, işta em ser aveyê daxl, ser
genim şûştina daxl...
Huh? No, no. It was nice, it was good, like when we [washed]
the grain, washing the wheat...
Çi çêbûye? Gojmero bêje.
What happened? Let the guy say it.
Gohê me, ez art û daxl, firîk bûn. Brokê me hat ber, em
dibêjin kargez a ye jor e.
Our ears... I [remember] flour and grain, it was green wheat
(firîk). A flood came to us, we call it the upper "kargez"
[likely a local term for a type of flood or water surge].
Wanî dewarê xwe berda wi derê... û ra bû, pir tenok çêbû,
baranek hat, baranek hat, hana diser va çinarara, çiqas gi
çinar bûn.
They let their cattle down there... and it rose, a great
mist/darkness happened, a rain came, a rain came, it went
over these plane trees, however many plane trees there were.
Û hev ga, xwe bi ser ket çû, ra lehê tengê Qerqîna bi ser
av... darê ma.
And an ox, fell over and went, the flood went towards the
Qerqîna gorge over the water... [past] our trees.
Yanê ga bi avê da çû?
So the ox went away in the water?
Bi avê da çû. Brokê me hat gu kanî ga, me gu goneh wutiye.
It went away in the water. Our flood came, they asked "where
is the ox?", we said "it is gone/sin happened to it".
Rwa dîn, av dahat, der hat, rabû çûn sehkirin goyî li vî
derî mirî.
They saw the path, the water came down, came out, they went
and looked, the ox was dead there.
Yanê berê av pir bû?
So in the past there was a lot of water?
Pir bû. Av ne yanê wextê lêmişd hat. Ga, bes av pir bû, we
ne wekî noka bû, av ji vê pirtir bû.
It was a lot. The water, no, it was when the flood came. The
ox... but the water was plentiful, not like now, the water
was more than this.
Bes baş e lêmişd hat, çem pir in, av qalibîn ser hev de û ew
dem go çû.
But it's good that the flood came, the rivers are full, the
water piled up on top of each other and at that time the ox
went.
Ê berî bi çend salan e dayê, ev behsa te dikî?
So how many years ago was this, mother, this story you are
telling?
Ê berî vê bi çil salî da ye. Heye emrê sê, ay bîramî ma do.
Uh, this was forty years ago. There is the age of three...
oh my memory has left.
Bîramî dê... pêncî û heft sal in çiye şta, wî çaxê da.
My memory... fifty-seven years or whatever, in that time.
Wanê bi hev ga çû, bi lê da çû işta.
Like that, the ox went with it, went with the flood.
Ê berê wa dihat livira, zarok, serê wan dişûştin livira?
In the past, did they come here, children, did they wash
their heads/hair here?
Lê? Serê qîçkê xwe dişûştin, serê mêrkê xwe dişûştin.
Huh? They washed their little ones' heads, they washed their
husbands' heads.
Ê berê hemiya dihat milet livir serê xwe dişûştin?
So in the past everyone came, the people washed their heads
here?
Giya dişûşt. Were gi, kîkê avê bibar, gun... li vî derî
kelşê xwe bikirana, kincê xwe bişûştana.
Everyone washed. Come all, whoever carries water... here
they would do their washing, wash their clothes.
Digot werin, werin, kîkî war hala mal avê lênîn, av tune bî,
hildigrin dibin danin bi mal e.
Saying "come, come," whoever [unclear] put water on the
fire, there was no water [at home], they carry it and take
it to the house.
Walê kul derê, wavil ku derê dişûşt?
So where, where did they wash [items]?
Ê berrî, î hey, da na, diçûn baxçit xakî bûn, tune bûn, li
stlber vira ser kaniyê dişûştin.
Uh, the rugs, yeah, no, they went to the dirt orchards,
there weren't any [facilities], right here by the spring
they washed.
Giçî wî çinarê de, binî siya darê de serê xwe dişûştin.
Inside that plane tree, under the shade of the tree, they
washed their heads.
Ê darê da?
Inside the tree?
Are. Binî kokê xana hemamek bû.
Yes. Under its roots/trunk was like a bathhouse.
Ku em kanin herin bibînin?
Can we go see it?
Dadê tu behsa vê darê dikî?
Mother, are you talking about this tree?
Ê, hewa hingî gito, morê xwan hebna.
Yes, back then [unclear phrase, possibly referring to the
size or shape]...
Ê ev darê berê mezin bû?
So this tree was big in the past?
Bêêê, hono, hono gelek gew bû.
Wooow, like this, like this it was very huge/hollow.
Lê? Dar mezin bû lê, xosî hamamê, kûkê gendê xosî hamamekê
çêbûbû.
Huh? The tree was big, like a bathhouse, the village
tap/pipe was made like a bathhouse.
Lê?
Huh?
Yanê berê ev daro wusa mezin bû?
So in the past this tree was this big?
Lê, hana, ho, hooo, gelek gew bû. Hamam bû, aw wekî qopîl
l'vrabûbû.
Yes, like this, oh, ohhh, it was very hollow/wide. It was a
bathhouse, it was opened like a hole/cave here.
Yanê derî xwe l'vir bû?
So its door was here?
Arê. Û hundirê darê bû, dar jî hana fere bû, mezin bû.
Yes. And it was inside the tree, and the tree was wide like
this, it was big.
Li vî derî, ê kelşê xwe l'vro bikirana, serê qîçkê xwe
bişûştana.
Right here, uh, they would do their washing here, wash their
little ones' heads.
Hama ne av dibir, bi lastîka dibir.
But they carried water, carried it with rubber straps.
Îşta wanokî bû ezbenim.
That's how it was, my dear/sir.
Me dahat av ji vî derê dibir, bi lastîka, kewrkê me azdan
l'vir bû.
We used to come carry water from here, with rubber straps,
our shoulders were in pain here.
Me dahat li vî derî bilxur jî, ew daxl jî dişûşt, daxlî
bilxur, î zexîre.
We came here and washed the bulgur and that grain too, grain
for bulgur, for storage.
Li vî derî em dihatin l'vir, l'vir destê me ji vî derê
nediqetî.
At this place, we came here, here our hands never stopped
[working] from this place.
Wele kincê xwe jî dişûştin, serê xwe jî dişûştin, qîçkê xwe
jî dişûştin, işta korî me gi ra dibûn li vir, ra dibûn em
d'lvir kaniyê.
Oh, they washed their clothes too, washed their heads too,
washed their kids too, all our chores happened here,
happened here at the spring.
Av tune bû, li gund kûk av tune bû.
There was no water, there was no tap water in the village.
Bes bîrek me hebû, dûr bû, pas dibirn ser av didan.
We just had a well, it was far, they took it... [unclear]
gave water.
Livra gelek tim şên bû, işta milet pir bû, pas pir bû, em
tim li vir bûn, teyzî, malê bavkê mi jî pir bûn.
Here it was always very lively, the people were many,
[unclear] was many, we were always here, auntie, my father's
house was large too.
Em tim li vir bûn, baxçê me li vir in. Li vir dikirin, li
vir d'... karê xwe bikirin, êvarê ro çû em diçûn diçûn.
We were always here, our orchards are here. They did [work]
here, here... did their work, in the evening when the sun
set, we went, we went.
Mala te ava be.
May your house be prosperous [Thank you].
Saet xweş.
Good times [You're welcome].
Spas.
Thanks.
Saet xweş.
Good times.
Dîroş, avayî, guncemê Efrînê, yek û wek e gula, avê li
paşbendava Meydankê hatiye, ava kirin.
The scenery, buildings, and riverbend of Afrin, one and like
a flower, the water has come behind the Meydanki dam,
constructed.
Li bakurê gund, Kaniya Sîmon û Kaniya Keres dikevin.
To the north of the village, Simon's Spring and Keres Spring
are located.
Gundî baxçeyê xwe ji av didin. Û herwiha li başûr jî, xirab
Sîmon heye.
The villagers water their orchards. And also to the south,
there is the Simon ruin.
Ew jî şikeftek kevnar e. Weke cihê mirovan dihat bikar anîn.
That is an ancient cave. It was used as a place for humans.
Tê gotin cihê gund, wekî bajarekî kevnar bû. Û ev di serdema
berî Îslamê da bû.
It is said the village site was like an ancient city. And
this was in the pre-Islamic era.
Li rojhilatê gund, bîreke polê heye. Ew bîrek e, ava gelekî
kevnar e.
To the east of the village, there is a class/type of well.
That well, the water is very ancient.
Diben reqaneleke avê heye, ku ava wê ji çiyayê Parsê ya
Qestel Cindo tê.
They say there is a water canal, whose water comes from the
Pars Mountain or Qestel Cindo.
Û li ser wê qenalê, sê bîrên avê yên din jî hene.
And on that canal, there are three other water wells.
Di berê demêkê, ava wan bîran dihate bombeyê, ango
embarxaneya avê.
Once upon a time, the water from those wells came to the
pump, meaning the water reservoir.
Li gelek gundan ava vexwarinê belav dibû.
Drinking water was distributed to many villages.
Mîna Gabeleka, Omera, Berava, û Qerqîna.
Like Gabeleka, Omera, Berava, and Qerqîna.
Mamosta Ebdullah, merheba ji te re.
Teacher Abdullah, hello to you.
Merheba ser çava.
Hello, upon my eyes [you are welcome].
Îro em li gundê Çema ne. Em spasiya te dikin, tu jî bi me re
derbasî cihê dîrokî bî, ev şikeft ne.
Today we are in the village of Çema. We thank you for coming
with us to this historical place, these caves.
Tu karî behsa bikî, ev şikefta ji çiqas sal da çêbûye?
Can you talk about it, how many years ago was this cave
made?
Tamam. Eviya di bex... di di yale zanistê da, eviya navê xwe
ne şikeft e.
Okay. This in... in scientific terms, its name is not a
"cave".
Ji van re dibêjin Naûs. Şikeft, xozayî ye.
They call these "Naûs" [Necropolis/Rock-cut tomb]. A cave is
natural.
Ama eviya mirova bi destê xwe kolaye, çêkiriye.
But this one, humans dug it with their own hands, made it.
Modelekî wiha, li Kurdistanê pir hene.
There are many models like this in Kurdistan.
Bi taybetî...
Especially...
Li vî herêmî amade bêtirî 17 naûsên bi vî rengî hene.
In this region, there are more than 17 rock-cut tombs of
this kind ready.
Mirov dikare tê de rûniştinê jî, bo îqametê, ji bo tê de
rûnin.
One can sit inside them, for residence, to live in them.
Hinek jî bo miriyê xwe tê de veşêrin, yanî bo mezel bikar
anîne hatî çêkirin.
And some are to bury their dead inside, meaning they were
made to be used as graves.
Ev jî modelekî ku bi desta hatiye kolan.
This is also a model that has been dug by hand.
Ev ya tiştê li hundir da, wekî ku xuya dike, ev ya mîna
mezelekî bikar anîne.
This thing inside, as it appears, they used this one like a
grave.
Di hundirê wê de, wekî ku xuya dike, mîna sê ode ye.
Inside of it, as it appears, it is like [it has] three
rooms.
Li sîngê her odeyekî jî mîna qenterekî heye, di bin ra
tûrbek heye, li ortê jî lîwan heye.
At the chest of every room there is like an arch, underneath
there is a tomb, and in the middle, there is a hall.
Eynî mîna malên modern hatiye çêkirin.
It has been built exactly like modern houses.
Tûrbeyê tê de ji mîna tabûtên ji kevir hatine kolan.
The tombs inside have been dug out of rock like coffins.
Ev modela, eynî van modela li... wekî tûrbe bikar anîne li
Dîlokê.
These models, exactly these models at... they used as tombs
in Dîlok (Gaziantep).
Dîlokê kevin, yanî bakur û rojavayê bajarê Eyntabê, bi 10
kîlometre.
Old Dîlok, meaning north and west of the city of Antep, by
10 kilometers.
17 naûsên bi vî rengî li wî derî hene.
There are 17 rock-cut tombs of this kind in that place.
Ev gorên malmezinên wî welatî bûn.
These were the graves of the nobles of that country.
Ev modela bi xwe texmîn dibe ji merheleya berî zayînê ye,
dema Romane.
This model itself is estimated to be from the pre-Common
Era, the Roman period.
Texmîn aîdê memleketa Komagene ye, war tê naskirin.
It is estimated to belong to the Kingdom of Commagene, that
is how it is known.
Ê ev deriyê şikeftê ye.
And this is the door of the cave.
Tê de neqş heye neqş?
Are there carvings inside, carvings?
Ê eynî modelê Eyntabê ye, texmîn dikim belkî neqş hatibine
xerakirin, belkî hatibine dizîn.
It is exactly the Antep model, I estimate maybe the carvings
were destroyed, maybe they were stolen.
Bêhtir neqşên li ser dihatin çêkirin ji xuzayê Kurdistanê...
Mostly the carvings that were made on them were of the
nature of Kurdistan...
Rengê çîçekan li ser dihatin çêkirin, rengê berana heye,
rengê bizina...
Flower shapes were made on them, there are ram figures, goat
figures...
Belkî bizin zêde bikar anîne, di xuzayê Kurdistanê de bizin
pir hatiye kedîkirin, feyda bizinê pir hebûye.
Maybe they used goats more often; in the nature of
Kurdistan, the goat was domesticated a lot, the goat had
many benefits.
Ewa derî wekî... wekî tekerekî ye, grover e.
That door is like... like a wheel, it is round.
Belkî qub... wekî din jî qenalê avê jî pir e, bo av pê têne
girtin, li vê herêmê li vir alî şerawa pir hene.
Maybe... furthermore, there are many water canals, to catch
water with them, in this region here towards Sherawa there
are many.
Ê ev jî belkî eynî war be, ema li şikefta didery...
And this is maybe exactly like that, but in the cave with
two doors...
Yanî yek ji şikefta du derî?
You mean one of the caves has two doors?
Ê şikeftekî xuza ye. Ev ya bi desta hatine çêkirin.
It's a natural cave. This one was made by hand.
Ev qenala bi desta hatiye çêkirin.
This canal was made by hand.
Ê didery ê ku şopê mirova tê dîtin, hestiyê zarokekî tê de
hatiye dîtin, temenê wî berî 100 hezar sal e.
And the two-door one where traces of humans are found, the
bone of a child was found in it, its age is 100,000 years
ago.
Yanî ev ya ispat dike li ser erdê berî hemû herêmên dinê,
insan li Kurdistanê bela bûye.
Meaning, this proves that on earth, before all other regions
of the world, humans spread in Kurdistan.
Li Kurdistanê pêşketiye. Civakbûn li Kurdistanê hatiye
çêkirin.
They developed in Kurdistan. Socialization was created in
Kurdistan.
Komê kolan li Kurdistanê hatine çêkirin.
Groups of streets/settlements were created in Kurdistan.
Ji xwa belkî ji aliyê Rojhilatê Afrîqa derketiye lê pêşketin
çênebûye.
Originally, maybe they came out of East Africa, but
development did not happen [there].
Tenê pêşketin ji Efrînê ya destpêdike û heta nî Silêmaniyê,
insanê li vir çalak derketiye.
Development only starts from Afrin and up to Sulaymaniyah,
the human here emerged active.
Ji xwa ew şopê Efrînê û şopê li Silêmaniyê şikefta Şaneder,
ev ispat e li dinyayê teva da...
Indeed, those traces in Afrin and traces in Sulaymaniyah,
the Shanidar cave, this is proof in the whole world...
Zanîngehên dinyayê teva da li ser lêkolîn çêkirine.
Universities of the whole world have done research on it.
Yanî cihê mirovahiyê Kurdistan e, şaristanî ji Kurdistanê
derketiye, civakbûn ji Kurdistanê derketiye.
Meaning, the place of humanity is Kurdistan, civilization
emerged from Kurdistan, socialization emerged from
Kurdistan.
Belê.
Yes.
Mala te ava be, spas.
May your home be prosperous, thank you.
Spas ji bo we hemûyan.
Thanks to all of you.
Şînahîya gund û wara jîyana xwe bi çandinîyê, jê zevîyên
zeytûn û baxçeyên sebze û darên fêkîyan dikin.
The greenery of the village and their homeland, they sustain
their lives with agriculture, from olive fields and
vegetable gardens and fruit trees.
Berhemên wan li bazara Efrînê difroşin, û herwiha zevîyên
zozan jî diçînin.
They sell their products in the Afrin market, and they also
plant the highland fields.
Digel çandinîyê hinek malbat sewalan jî xwedî dikin, û
firotina berhemên wan debara malbata xwe ya jiyanî dikin.
Along with agriculture, some families also raise livestock,
and with the sale of their products, they make their
family's living.
Piştî şoreşa Rojava, çarkarên derûnî li gund vebûn û mezin û
biçûk, jin û mêr her kes têda kar dikin.
After the Rojava revolution, internal workshops opened in
the village, and young and old, women and men, everyone
works in them.
Û debara jîyana xwe pê dikin. Vê yekê hişt ku koçberî çênebe
û aramî di gund da hebe û derfetên kar ji xurt û keçên gund
re bibin.
And they make their living with it. This allowed migration
not to happen, peace to exist in the village, and job
opportunities to arise for the young men and women of the
village.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, îro jî em li gundê Çeman e. Em
derbasî ser ziyaretekê bûn.
Yes, dear viewers, today we are in the village of Çeman. We
have proceeded to a shrine.
Jinê gundê Çema jî hemî derbas bûn. Emê spasiya wan bikin.
All the women of Çeman village also came along. We will
thank them.
Dayîkek li kêlek mine, emê dîroka ziyaretê jê bipirsin. Dayê
merheba ji te re.
A mother (dayê) is by my side, we will ask her about the
history of the shrine. Mother, hello to you.
Ehlen we sehlen, bi xêr bi selamet.
Welcome, in safety and health.
Sax be dayê. Dayê em destpêkê te nas bikin.
Be healthy, mother. Mother, let us first get to know you.
Wele temenê weştekî... ez ji vî gundî me, ez xizavî gundî
me, elbet gundî me ezim bî me.
Well, your age [meaning hers] is something... I am from this
village, I am a native of this village, certainly I am a
villager, I am myself.
Ser çavê me dayê.
You are welcome (on our eyes), mother.
Ser çavê te xweş be, ev qurbanê çavê te bim. Tu ji wekî lawê
min î.
May upon your eyes be good, may I be a sacrifice for your
eyes. You are also like my son.
Ehlen we sehlen. Da were... ziyaretê me ziyareta qedîm e.
Welcome. Come now... our shrine is an ancient shrine.
Tu çend salî ye?
How old are you?
Umrê min ez di hêştê da me.
My age, I am in [my] eighties.
Tu hêştê salî ye?
You are eighty years old?
Ha, hêştê wele.
Yes, eighty, really.
Û ji berê de tê ber vê ziyaretê?
And you have been coming to this shrine since the past?
Ji berê de têm ber vê ziyaretê, em dewer şarjê dikin, em
dafê dixin.
I have been coming to this shrine since the past, we engage
in... [customs], we play the drum.
Yanî şe'b pir e, yanî...
Meaning the people [crowd] is large, meaning...
Navê ziyaretê we çiye?
What is the name of your shrine?
Navê ziyaretê me Şêx Mihemed e. Em qicikê xwe pê nav dikin.
The name of our shrine is Sheikh Mohammed. We name our
little ones after him.
Yanî her nîvê gund Şêx Mihemed e.
Meaning half the village is [named] Sheikh Mohammed.
Yanî hûn zarokên xwe jî pê nav dikin?
Meaning you name your children after him too?
Erê, zarokên xwe jî em pê nav dikin.
Yes, we name our children after him too.
Bi taybet yanî hûn kîjan rojê derbasî ziyaretê dibin?
Specifically, which day do you visit the shrine?
Em roja pêncşemê tên, ber.
We come on Thursday, before.
Bi taybet hewarê înê?
Specifically on the eve of Friday?
Hewarê înê.
The eve of Friday.
Çarşemê jî hûn tên?
Do you come on Wednesday too?
Çarşemê, ew tên cî... qastelê tên, ev noq...
On Wednesday, they come to the pl... come to the fountain,
this now...
Yanî milletê me yê Êzîdî, ez dayî, ew roja çarşemê derbasî
vir dibin?
Meaning our Ezidi people, I say, do they visit here on
Wednesday?
Roja çarşemê tên, ê me pêncşemê ye.
They come on Wednesday, ours is Thursday.
Û behsa çi dikin, li vir jî dema şevê ara dibe, şevê Newrozê
dibe jî, dîsa hûn tên vira?
And what is discussed, here too when it becomes the night of
the fire, the night of Newroz, do you come here again?
Dîsa em tên vira. Vira tav da dibe ar...
Again we come here. Here in the sunlight [open] becomes
fire...
Tekera ar dikin, şe'b tav da dafê dixin, hezar filmî
çêdikin.
They make a wheel of fire [bonfire], the people play the
drum in the open, they make a thousand films
[scenes/activities].
Agirê Newrozê jî pê dixin?
Do they light the Newroz fire too?
Çema pê dixin weleh.
They light it at the river/creek, by God.
Em berê... hêlek li vir da didan, em dihatin ber ziyaretê,
şta ro da îda... me gund derbas kir.
We used to... set up a swing here, we came to the shrine,
then on the holiday... we passed the village [celebrated].
Ê demê tu zarok bû, zarokên naha ştên?
And when you were a child, are the children of now like
that?
Zarokê noka... noka nayên wela, gum hadî, ha. Berê em
dihatin.
Children of now... now they don't come, really, it's lost,
yeah. Before we used to come.
Wela me dar li vir bû, qasîrî hana...
Really we had a tree here, a palace [huge] like this...
Di bin evê tav da koka xwe, qulibî, berfê lêkir, qulibî.
Under this sun [sky] its root, it toppled over, snow fell on
it, it toppled.
Dar?
A tree?
Erê, me çop darê merxê bû.
Yes, we had a juniper tree log/trunk.
Ev darê çi bû?
What tree was this?
Merxê.
Juniper.
Merxê?
Juniper?
Erê, vê darê merxê bû. Wê li vî derî bû, we li vî derî.
Yes, it was a juniper tree. It was at this place, right at
this place.
Li vira xwa sifra çêdikin heta derê hana.
Here they would set the table [spread food] up to that place
there.
Gund... sferik di hundir... ew dikirin, di ziyaretê da,
dikam rehmetî...
The village... [unclear] inside... they did that, in the
shrine, the late mother...
Ê şta me şorbe dikir, şîv dikirin, du dîr dinan, şe'b şêrîna
dikirî, fike dihatin. Tu kes ne dima.
And then we made soup, made dinner, put two pots, the people
bought sweets, fruits came. Nobody stayed behind.
Ê gund xeberdan hevdu, qicikê me l'kiban'o dihatin.
And the village told each other, our little ones came from
the huts/houses.
Ê şta wernî.
And so it was like that.
Dayê naha milletê naha hatî derdora me, hemî ji gundê we ne?
Mother, now the people who have gathered around us, are they
all from your village?
Yo wela, giş gundî me ne. Ê xerîb jî hene t'hemû.
No really, they are all our villagers. And there are
strangers too among them.
Yanî naha wek gundê Bera vê, gundê kîlek we ye...
Meaning now like the village of Bera, the village next to
you...
Ê cîranê me ne.
Yes, they are our neighbors.
Ewder... Omer Axa ye, Şera ye, ew jî tên vira?
That place... Omer Axa, Shera, do they come here too?
Ew giş dihatin vira.
They all used to come here.
Naha kes jê heye?
Is there anyone from them now?
Haa, noka nayên. Erê gum hadî.
Ah, now they don't come. Yes, it's lost.
Yanî wextê go ewê bikin, da ey batone, teklîf dikirin.
Meaning when they would do it, they would... [unclear], they
would organize/task.
Teklîf kirina gi dihatin ber ziyaretê.
When they organized, everyone came to the shrine.
Ê noka nakin, gum hadî.
And now they don't do it, it's lost.
Wextê baran lê nake, dahen digerin.
When rain doesn't fall, they would go around.
Dahen şarjê dikin, şîva dikin li vî derî.
They would perform rituals, make dinner at this place.
Wan ferexna naşûn, baran lê dike, bo avê tên dişûn.
They wouldn't wash the dishes, [until] rain falls, they come
to wash them with water.
Ka dayê, te got ev sersal e.
Look mother, you said this is New Year (Sersal).
Mm, sersal e.
Mm, it's New Year.
Dema baran nabare?
When rain doesn't fall?
Sersal e, erê.
It's New Year, yes.
Ka wê destpêkê ji me ra bêje, hûn çi dikin dema baran
nabare?
Tell us about that beginning, what do you do when rain
doesn't fall?
Wextê na barîne, şta dahen nav gunda digerin.
When it doesn't rain, then they would go around the
villages.
Ê zeytê kof dikin, bulxur kof dikin, avê...
And they pound/collect oil, pound/collect bulgur, water...
Mêr digerin bi taybet?
Do men go around specifically?
Mêr digerin, bi şev.
Men go around, at night.
Zarok jî digerin?
Do children go around too?
Zarok jî ver digerin, yanî di... torlox... xicxicoke.
Children also go around, meaning in... [unclear]...
scarecrows/costumes.
Erê xurt.
Young men?
Yes, young men.
Ê dahen avê çêdikin ser.
And they would pour water on [them].
Me'ne baran lê ke. Tên ber maşalla, baran tovilê lê dike li
viro.
Meaning let the rain fall. They come and mashallah, rain
pours down heavily here.
Yanî darda, li mala, deriyan dixin...
Meaning outside, at houses, they knock on doors...
Aaa, li hewş tişta dikin.
Aaa, they do things in the courtyard.
Riz didinê, pera didinê?
Do they give them rice, give them money?
Aaa, tên berxê dikirrin.
Aaa, they come and buy a lamb.
Ê şta...
And then...
Ewê rojê bi taybet rojê înê tên?
That day, do they come specifically on Friday?
Erê roje înê emkê werin ber. Ê ber roje pêncşemê êvarê înê.
Yes on Friday we would come before. Before Thursday, the eve
of Friday.
Wîn tên dewarekî xwe li vir serjê dikin?
You come and slaughter a livestock of yours here?
Serjê dikin, xwarinê dikin, gund g'te dixwe.
They slaughter, make food, the whole village eats.
Ê rasta dilê xwe. Solî jî dîsa hatin kirin, çêkirin.
And truly from their hearts. It was done again this year,
made.
Sersal wa çêkir?
Did you do the New Year?
Ê salê çûyîn baran baş barî. Îsal neqî baran pir nebarî.
Yes, last year the rain fell well. This year rain didn't
fall much.
Baran nebarî, dîsa wa nekir?
Rain didn't fall, did you not do it again?
Em noka di buharê dane.
We are in spring now.
Em noka di buharê dane, de şta wa dikin.
We are in spring now, so they do that.
Yanî her waxtkî baran bisekine wa dikin.
Meaning anytime the rain stops, they do that.
Efeji qenata xwe pê dikin, bawerî xwe pê tînin?
Do you have faith in this, do you believe in it?
Qeneta xwe em pê dikin, he.
We have faith in it, yes.
Welehîl... biderî ber... kim... canê salikê hatin biderî
gund.
By God... out before... [unclear]... like one year they came
outside the village.
Bidefê, dera gund... virjî, virjî da bû şe'b heta hano.
With drums, around the village... here too, here too was
people up to there.
Bes noka naye, gum hadî.
But now it doesn't come [happen], it's lost.
Yanî mala hek dewrekî şarjêke çêtine, çiye mlo wane ber
ziyareta qedîm e.
Meaning if a family performs a ritual well, what is it to
them, before the ancient shrine.
Ziyareta me navê xwe heye.
Our shrine has its name.
Dayê spas ji te ra.
Mother, thank you.
Mala te ava be. Ezê bi derbas bim. Spas.
May your home be prosperous. I will pass on. Thanks.
Bula bula.
Okay okay.
Dayê merheba ji were.
Mother, hello to you.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Merheba ji we gişara.
Hello to all of you.
Spas. Saeta we xweş?
Welcome.
Thanks. Are you well?
We jî xweş. Ser ser û ser çava hatine ma, tûna ma.
You [be] well too. Upon head and eyes [welcome] you came to
us, our home.
Sax be. Sax be dayê.
Be healthy. Be healthy mother.
Îro pêncşem e û we berê xwe daye ziyaretê.
Today is Thursday and you have turned towards the shrine.
Erê.
Yes.
Naha we şema'ê xwe jî, mûm jî vêxistine?
Now have you also lit your candles, wax?
Mm, hem dila.
Mm, thank God.
Avo xaltîka Manî ye. Noka ser lêkirina baranê, îçirrin bûye.
This is Aunt Mani. Now regarding the making of rain, there
was a tearing [custom].
Milletê têde ba'z miri hebin tên têda nimê dikin, îvarî îne
tên jinek darten têda rûdinên nimê dikin, di r'ketin.
The people in it, if some died, they come and pray in it,
Friday eve women come outside, sit in it, pray, and leave.
Nime xweşbûyî zeratê dikin.
It is not a cure, we are making a pilgrimage.
Ee, yek xalkê min ye emtê min me, ewî naha dikin, hîç manehê
li ser namîkin.
Yes, one is my uncle, one is my aunt, they are doing it now,
they leave no meaning/doubt upon it.
Bo cil jiyanî ye?
Is it for rheumatism/life pain?
Ee, cil jiyanî ne, xist... rêxistin e.
Yes, it is for rheumatism/life pain, it's... it's
organization/arrangement.
Hwkî yanî ye?
How is it?
Wele şîniyek bindanî ye. De miletê gund her kes tengiya xwe
ra tişto tîne te.
By God, it is a tied blue cloth. So, the people of the
village, everyone brings things for their distress.
Wero, çi dua dikir? Wero... wele kê ker erê ro?
Come, what prayer did she make? Come... who did it, yes
come?
Ê de hişta... ê em dua dikin, em jî jiyapaka xwe ra dikin
heta biserûkê xwe.
Uh, well... uh, we pray, we also do it for our own
purity/goodness up to the outcome.
Em jî giyarê yapakê... giyarê gotinê xwe dikin, duayê xwe
dikin, ji qîçkê xwe ra dikin.
We also [pray] for the sake of goodness... for the sake of
our words, we make our prayers, we do it for our children.
Ji xwe ra dikin. Erê.
We do it for ourselves. Yes.
De te jî mum vêxist, şem'a vêxist?
So you also lit a candle, lit a candle?
Bi ant kiriye, layê min bide me û rûk girtinê...
I made a vow, that [God] gives me my son and taking the face
[honoring]...
Ant kiriye bî, layê min bide rê înşalla, hekî cerê zîratê
vêxim.
I had made a vow, that if He gives my son to the path [of
life] God willing, that I will light the pilgrimage
jar/candle.
Berî layê min bi saetekê, ew hatim min ban xwedê kir, parçe
kirin zîratê.
An hour before [the news of] my son, I came and called upon
God, and did my part at the shrine.
Min got, dikan jî ekê şem'ê vêxim. Di vê rûniştî bûm, berdî
saetekê layê min xeberê layê min hat.
I said, I will light a candle at the shop too. I was sitting
right here, an hour later the news of my son came.
Aşo bûm... dima û rûkê... û noka xeber hat got derket, etî
berî da tê.
I was anxious... remaining and... and now the news came
saying he got out, he is on his way coming.
Kê lê te girtibû?
Who had held/arrested him?
Cêş hûrin cin e.
It is the Jaysh [Army]... spirits/enemies.
Cebit Nesra?
Jabhat al-Nusra?
Cebit Nesra.
Jabhat al-Nusra.
Em duaya dikin, rizgî wa bixêr e înşalla.
Did they release him now?
We are praying, God willing their sustenance/livelihood is
blessed.
Xwedê selametî giya bi derbas ke înşalla, xwedê hevalê giya
be.
May God grant safety to all to pass through God willing, may
God be the companion of all.
Em dua ji giya dikin, heval cîrana... xûbe serok bejî derê
ekê layê min înşalla, saeta wa giya xweş.
We pray for everyone, friends and neighbors... whether it's
the leader or outside, like my son God willing, may all
their hours be happy.
Ê ne ev dima hinek zarokî te hatibû girtin, Cembhet el
Nesra, naha berdan?
So wasn't this remaining child of yours who was captured by
Jabhat al-Nusra, released now?
Ee, dima û rûk.
Yes, the remainder and the face [child].
Bi vê munasabê wa rû înşalla, saeta wa xweş.
On this occasion, go then God willing, have a good time.
Înşalla, em na bibînin jiyanê.
God willing, we won't see [bad things] in life.
Tu birê da tê?
Is he on his way coming?
Ee, saet xweş. Xwedê xêra zîratê vêxim jêra înşalla.
Yes, thanks. I will light the charity of the shrine for him
God willing.
Tê navêxî?
Won't you light it?
Heke... mukeş bimîne.
If... if the coverage/opportunity remains.
Dayê, win hatine vir pêşem e?
Mother, you have come here, is it Thursday?
Wele maşalla... ciyê qena xweş me dît, min xoca kirbû, ciyê
kî elhemdula rehet bû.
By God, mashallah... we saw a very nice place, I had made a
wish, it was a place that, praise be to God, was
comfortable.
Ee, hûru dîsa em hatin me çerê xwe, em kê vêxînin.
Yes, and today we came again for our wandering, we will
light [candles].
Yanî bi taybet jin tên, mêr nayên?
Meaning, especially women come, men don't come?
Mêr nayên, jin tên.
Men don't come, women come.
He?
Huh?
Jin tên.
Women come.
Ee, jin... em pêncem pêncem em tên.
Yes, women... we come every Thursday.
Em kevirê pêva dizeliqînin, ştê ant dikin, antet xwe... aw
dikin, maşalla tê cî.
We stick stones onto it, we make vows, our vows... we do
that, mashallah it comes true.
Miradî şda, çi bit ê cî.
The wish for them, whatever it is, comes true.
Em den dikin, em mirad... qevrê xwe vêdixînin, miradê me
dibê.
We make noise [pray aloud], we... our wish... we light our
grave/place, our wish happens.
Elhemdula. Rind e.
Praise be to God. It is good.
Na evî ne derbasê çibin nîye?
Now, isn't there a passage for these things?
Dayê?
Mother [Give it]?
Ev jî dar e?
Is this also a tree [part of the ritual]?
Ev jî darê xwa ye, ee.
This is also God's tree, yes.
Paçka î miraza ye. Paçka tê girêde mirazê te dibê.
What tree is it?
It is the cloth of wishes. You tie a cloth, your wish comes
true.
Darê zan zelaqê ye.
It is the tree of sticking knowledge [Tree where things
stick].
Heke te girêda qebîl nake?
If you tie it, does it not accept?
Ta çi nider kir, maşalla dimaşe.
Whatever vow you made, mashallah it walks/proceeds.
Heke pêş ve hat ew?
If it came forward [accepted]?
Aa, berî me kevir pêva zeliqandin e.
Ah, before us, stones were stuck to it.
Kê mumaj we vêxê? Tê vêxê?
Who among you will light the candle? Will you light it?
Merheba rojbaş.
Hello, good day.
Ez hatime şem'ê vêxim ji bo mirazê xwe.
I have come to light a candle for my wish.
Mirazê ki xwe bixwazim û şem'ê vêxim.
To ask for a wish for myself and light the candle.
Û înşalla xwedê mirazê dilê me û giya bike û ê me jî bike.
And God willing, may God grant the heart's wish of all and
grant ours too.
Amîn înşalla.
Amen, God willing.
Binerên daka vejêr...
Look down here...
Temaşevanên hêja, bi hevre ka em temaşe bikin ka çawa
dakevin jêr jî.
Dear viewers, let us watch together how they go down as
well.
Hinekî zehmetî jî tê da heye.
There is some difficulty in it too.
Xwedê mirazê dilê we bike.
May God grant your heart's wish.
Selametî yê te jî bike ya reb. Saet xweş.
May He grant you safety too, oh Lord. Thanks.
Ziyaretgehek bi navê Şêx Mihemed tê naskirin li Jûrî gunda.
A shrine known by the name Sheikh Muhammad in the village of
Juri.
Ku xelkê gund û ê barên îdorê serdana wî dikin û muman
vêdixin.
Which the people of the village and those from the
surrounding areas visit and light candles.
Her wiha li ber xwedê digerin ku mirad û hêviyên wan pêk
bîne.
Likewise, they pray to God to fulfill their wishes and
hopes.
Naha li derdora ziyaretgehê bûye goristana gund.
Now, the area around the shrine has become the village
cemetery.
Di sibaha rojin cejnan da, dîsa xelkê gund serdana vê
ziyaretgehê dikin.
On the mornings of feast days, the village people visit this
shrine again.
Bombeya avê ku berê pênc gund ava xwe ji vê werdigirtin li
Jûrî gunda.
The water spring [pump], from which five villages used to
get their water, is in the village of Juri.
Lê niha tenê ji bo gundê Çemakê tê bikar anîn.
But now it is used only for the village of Chamake.
Dibistaneke seretayî di gunda heye, ku zarokên gund ta refa
şeşa têda dixwînin.
There is a primary school in the village, where the village
children study up to the sixth grade.
Û mizgeftek a dînî vê gunda heye.
And there is a religious mosque in this village.
Ku şîniyên gund nimêja xwe têda dikin.
Where the residents of the village perform their prayers.
De lalê, de lalê...
Oh dear, oh dear...
Ye de lalê, ye mencolê, mencolî ye de lalê...
Oh dear, oh Mencole [name/swaying one], Mencole oh dear...
Mencolê, mencolî ye de lalê.
Mencole, Mencole oh dear.
Li cûmê pembê çî ye de lalê.
The cotton in the riverbed, what is it, oh dear.
Ezozê qowîn çî ye de lalê.
The strong pain/love, what is it, oh dear.
Li kellesê şeker çî ye de lalê.
In the sugar bowl, what is the sugar, oh dear.
Mencol o bavî kal e de lalê.
Mencole, the father is old, oh dear.
Ser minda gole gole.
Upon me, it is lake after lake [deep water/trouble].
Av şîr o, av mertal o.
Water is milk, water is a shield.
Mencolê de lalê...
Mencole, oh dear...
Mencolê, mencolî ye...
Mencole, Mencole is...
Lê de yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar,
yar, yar, yar, yar î ne...
Oh love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love,
love, love, love, love, love, love...
Zalim kurbê her çar kabe xwe spî ne, sale wekî sal nehatî
berî zînê we...
The cruel one, victim, all four anklebones are white
[lucky/pure], a year like [this] year has not come before
the saddle...
Biserdikeet xûrde, ewîlekî me î çarde salî ne.
It falls upon [us] in small pieces, ours is a firstborn of
fourteen years.
Xo hal e hal e bal dike, xo ber dide berî ya mewşêrî ne.
Making herself into a state/condition, letting herself go
before the heavy/sweet load.
Siba û heya bê, barê pêşê nêrî xazêl diftiline.
Morning and the coming month/moon, the load in front of the
billy goat, the leaves are twirling.
De yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar, yar,
yar wa...
Oh love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love, love,
love, love, love...
Her bijî serê muxtar.
Long live the Mukhtar [Village Head].
Saet xweş, ehlen we sehlen bi hatina we.
Thanks, welcome to your arrival.
Spas, we dengê te sax be, her bijî serra.
Thanks, may your voice be healthy, long live the
leader/head.
Saet xweş, ehlen we sehlen bi hatina we.
Thanks, welcome to your arrival.
Ji gundiyê Çemara û elhemdula ji vê rûyê ra me heft tişto jî
dît.
From the villager of Chamara, and praise be to God, from
this face/aspect we saw seven things too.
Û noka emê werin, yanî ax û welat lividere li gundiyê Çema.
And now we will come, meaning the land and country here in
the village of Chema.
Emê awikî kevin, yek ji torasî kevin, ji bav û kala da, ji
me ra mayî.
We [will perform] an old melody/song, one from the old
heritage, from the forefathers, remaining for us.
Û taben yek winim biter bibim li çoyî kurmancî gi tina.
And naturally, one, if I may say, purely in Kurmanji, it's
all there.
Illa ji çema şerab paşê yek aw lêxistin, Awî Reşko.
Except from the river, wine afterwards, one melody played,
Awi Reshko [Blackish Melody].
Ev Awî Reşko, bi taybet na sitranê wî her kes zanê.
This Awi Reshko, especially now everyone knows his song.
Dema tu zarokê biçûk bibînê, ew kalekî bibînê, ew ê sitranê
zanê.
When you see a small child, [or] see an old man, he knows
that song.
Bes govend, ev kes nizanê.
But the dance, nobody knows this.
Em zanîn kes nizanê, bes...
We know that nobody knows [it], but...
Taybetmendiya we ev govend awa heye.
Your specialty/uniqueness is that this dance exists like
this.
Ê ev govend we çêkirî ye li wejder ve haniye?
So, did you create this dance or did you bring it from
outside?
Na wele, ev govenda ma çêkiriye.
No by God, we created this dance.
Ev govenda taben ma çêkiriye, ji taben wextê g...
Naturally, we created this dance, from naturally the time
when...
Kêça dikuje, g... bêderê li ba dike, g... ew dike.
He reaps the furrows [harvest], when... he winnows the
threshing floor, when... he does that.
Heva yanî însanî pintî bila hay ji xwe hebe, nehewce ye
merov tembe ke.
This means, let the stingy/lazy human be aware of himself,
it's not necessary to warn a person.
Bila bi xwa xozan e be. Yanî dêmek wê çaxê, meselen wextê tu
kêça dikujî, dêmek hevîr distirî, pozî xwe fiş dikî.
Let him be knowledgeable himself. Meaning at that time, for
example when you reap the furrows, meaning kneading dough,
you wipe/blow your nose [working hard].
Me'neta pintî bûn.
The meaning was being stingy/lazy.
Hema noka bila milet îga marî bila hay ji xwe ke.
Even now, let the people... let them be aware of themselves.
Ê min hoha ye.
Mine is like this.
Yanî ew govend hin kar têda heye, hin rexm hene?
Meaning, does that dance have work in it, or are there
figures/rhythms?
Serkêsî pintî, û hin jî kar dikin, çawa diçin zîraetiyê
taben, bêderê til ba dikî, ti pa'lê biçinî...
Based on the stingy person, and some also work, naturally
how they go to agriculture, winnowing the threshing floor,
reaping the harvest...
Ti... yanî geheye têda.
You... meaning it is all in it.
Û ehlen we sehlen, û emê noka ji wera...
And welcome, and we will now for you...
Na govend jin jî hazir in?
Now regarding the dance, are the women ready too?
Taben.
Naturally.
Û mêr jî hazir in? Ev timê wusa ye?
And are the men ready too? Is it always like this?
Eywa.
Yes.
Yanî çiqas şayî we çê bibin, divê jin çêbibin û vê govenda
jî heye.
Meaning however many celebrations you have, women must be
there and this dance exists too.
Li sahî gunda. Heye, va govenda heye, eletûl çiqas dewat
biba ev govenda li cem me heye.
In the village celebration. It exists, this dance exists,
always however many weddings there are, this dance exists
with us.
Tamam ka kerem kin.
Okay, please go ahead.
Bêrî. Tamam.
Come on. Okay.
Aman Rişkû te nakim.
Oh Rişkû, I won't give you up.
Ez qurbanê canê xakim.
I am a sacrifice for the soul of the earth.
Sor û sipî li xanê kim.
I will paint the house red and white.
Kevtera erzan nakim.
I won't sell the pigeon cheap.
Aman Rişkû te nakim.
Oh Rişkû, I won't give you up.
Rişkû dîn û te gêj e.
Rişkû is mad and you are dizzy.
Hindir serê te bûş e.
Inside your head is full.
Ken li cem te belaş e.
Laughter is free with you.
Aman Rişkû te nakim.
Oh Rişkû, I won't give you up.
Dema mera dibê gûvenda Rişkû, mera xem û xeyala wunda dike.
When one speaks of the Rişkû dance, one loses their grief
and worries.
Dema mera dibê gûvenda Rişkû, gundê Çema tê ber çavê mera.
When one speaks of the Rişkû dance, the village of Çema
comes before one's eyes.
Gundê Çema, bi xwezaya xwe, bi dilxweşiya xwe, bûye vîn
gerandin.
The village of Çema, with its nature, with its joy, has
become a passion for wandering.
Me jî wusa xatir ji Çema û ji we xwest.
We also bade farewell to Çema and to you in this way.