Lo lo lo lo lo firoto.
Oh, oh, oh, oh, oh you sold [me].
Erê migo nem lo xalo bima gorî ke to.
Yes I said, I won't remain oh uncle, may I be a sacrifice
for you.
Erê milo dibê Sêvo lo wikê wa şeqelqê delal cî ruknê
bermaso, dibê ber defkê bi hukm bike.
Yes, Sêvo says oh boy, that figure of the dear one is a
pillar at the table, he says rule at the entrance.
Erê migo kekê Zelîxanê, yar bi qurban Zelîxanê.
Yes I said, brother of Zelîxan, may the lover be a sacrifice
for Zelîxan.
Gere ne go milo xalo bima gorî ke to, Sêvo dibê lawikê minî
delal cî ruknê bermaso.
Indeed I said oh uncle may I be a sacrifice for you, Sêvo
says my dear boy is a pillar at the table.
Erê dibê milo pêda pêda bişewitiya gundê me yî xeracî, milo
wisî fesad to, lawiko co fesad to.
Yes he says, oh step by step may our village of Xeracî burn,
oh such mischief, oh boy the mischief went.
Gere migo di ber ra, di ber ra, di ber ra, di ber ra, di ber
ra.
Indeed I said passing by, passing by, passing by, passing
by, passing by.
Erê serê yara ser bidûman bi qurban a di ber ra.
Yes, the lover's head is misty, a sacrifice for the one
passing by.
Erê dinya fanî saet dinya xweş e şêrîn e, erê berê lo lawiko
yar bi qurban namîne şikesta ro.
Yes the world is transient, the hour of the world is
pleasant and sweet, yes before oh boy, the lover is a
sacrifice, the broken day will not remain.
Lawiko şikesta ro.
Oh boy, the broken day.
Erê dibê serê mi bi qurban a lo lawo, erê dibê weza nibim
dinya namîne ji min û te ra.
Yes he says may my head be a sacrifice oh boy, yes he says
if I am not here, the world will not remain for me and you.
Erê dibê dibê qapûzê xwa bimalo mewalê dinyê ra mekin, erê
dibê dinya ne bi zêr a ne bi per a.
Yes he says, says do not exchange your deeds oh householder
for the wealth of the world, yes he says the world is
neither by gold nor by money.
Erê dibê na dibê çima bi xêl û zêtûna ne bi meqesa.
Yes he says, no he says, why with veils and olives(?) not
with scissors.
Erê dibê serê mi bi qurban o, erê dibê çima tiştik mera
xilas nake.
Yes he says may my head be a sacrifice, yes he says why does
nothing save us.
Erê dibê ne bi lafa ne bi şûro, lawiko hay bi şûro.
Yes he says neither by words nor by sword, oh boy beware of
the sword.