Belê temaşevanên hêja, em derbasî cem dayika bûn. Destê
dayika sax be, wan jî xas tiştim taybet çêkirine.
Yes, dear viewers, we have moved on to the mothers. Bless
the mothers' hands, they have prepared very special things.
Neha jî dema leçer e, dema tirî ye. Neha jî emê bi hevre nas
bikin. Dayê merheba ji were.
Now is the time for preserves, the time for grapes. Now we
will get to know them together. Hello to you, mother.
Ehlem we sehlem. Qenatî Rûnahî raser ser çava, ser seran.
Welcome. Ronahi Channel is very welcome, upon our eyes, upon
our heads.
Destê we sax bin dayê.
Bless your hands, mother.
Sax bî.
Be well.
E naha jî we got dema leçer e, emê leçer çêbikin.
And now you said it is the time for preserves, we will make
preserves.
Erê. Hama daxwe dema tirî ye, tirê me heye, me asirandiye.
Yes. Indeed, it is the time for grapes, we have grapes, we
have pressed them.
Me kiriye ta'ek, me kiriye mîj, me kiriye dims, me kiriye
bastiq, kêsme. Hêşta daxwe dema tirî ye noka.
We made ta'ek, raisins, molasses, fruit leather, kesme. It
is still the grape season now.
Yanî çiş tiriye çêdibe, hûn hemî çêdikin.
So whatever can be made from grapes, you make it all.
Gi çêdibe, gi hemî tişt jê çêdibe. Mesela wek me got bastiq,
me got dims, me got mîj, me got kêsme, gi jê çêdibe.
It can all be made, everything can be made from it. For
example, as we said fruit leather, molasses, raisins, kesme,
it is all made from it.
Na, ev leçer cuda ye, ev cuda ye?
Now, is this preserve different, is this different?
Ee, leçer me hasirand û me rabi av... kils ket, me kefî
xwasar o girt.
Yes, the preserve, we pressed it and then water... lime was
added, we skimmed the foam off well.
Dused kel vê ketin, me tirî xwe boş nav kir.
It boiled two hundred times, we poured our grapes into it
abundantly.
Bi taybet kîjan tirî dibe leçer?
Specifically, which grape becomes preserve?
Gi tura, hey yalla. Bas î sûr nabe.
All kinds, oh my. Just the red one won't do.
Î sipî gi dibe. Şekirê 'am yanî gi dimeşe. Bes î sûr na
meşe.
The white one all works. Common sugar all works. Only the
red one doesn't work.
Bivî rengî çêdibe?
It becomes this color?
Erê bivî rengî de me... çêkirî me. Erê, ta'ek in evana.
Yes, this color we... we made it. Yes, these are ta'ek.
Ev jî şerbet e?
Is this syrup?
Ev jî şerbet e, me keland, hêşta me boş nav kir.
This is also syrup, we boiled it, then we poured it in
abundantly.
Sax bî, ehlem we sehlem, ser çava.
Bless your hands.
Be well, welcome, you are welcome.
Em hinekî ji vê jî bipirsin.
Let's ask this one a bit too.
Dayê jî le kerem ke.
Mother, please go ahead.
Ehlen we sehlen bhatina we, bi qenatî Rûnahî, ser serî me,
ser çavê me.
Welcome to your arrival, to Ronahi channel, upon our heads,
upon our eyes.
U dogî şte nuka mûnê... vistaniye, dogî leçer o... leçerî
kundira hewa.
And now the thing is the season... of the vegetable garden,
the season of preserves... this is pumpkin preserve.
Ev ya kundurom şirîn e?
Is this sweet pumpkin?
Erê, hewa leçerê kundira, me kundirê xwe qaşart, u me hûr
kir.
Yes, this is pumpkin preserve, we peeled our pumpkins, and
we chopped them.
Me şerbetê xwe da er, şekirê xwe kirê, u me keland.
We put our syrup on the fire, put our sugar in, and we
boiled it.
U ştewa evana bi leçer, ma'nî vistaniye, hesobî xoy
vistaniye em dikin.
And these things like preserve, meaning the garden, we do it
counting it as garden work.
Şten î vono hatin, ehlen we sehlen, berqahwê ramê dînin ê
bixon.
These things are coming, welcome, we serve it with coffee
and they eat.
Sax bî, wey sax bî.
Be well, oh be well.
Neha tetîd hemî, yanî neha em ber cî vistanê de çûn, nava
malatê male, hazir dikin.
Now preparation is all, meaning now we are going towards
winter, inside the family home, you prepare.
Hazretî xoy vistaniye şte em dîdinin. Leçerê, hat... ew
leçerk yê h'jîra, yê tirîye, yê kundirê drêj in, yê tup...
qişê, vê dibên kundirê qişê.
We see the preparations for the garden. Preserves, until...
that preserve of figs, of grapes, of long pumpkins, of
round... winter squash, they call this winter pumpkin.
Em gîyo çêdikin şte hazirê xwe dikin.
We make all of it, preparing our things.
Te çi hazir kirî?
What have you prepared?
Ehlen we sehlen ştaro. Wele min hêjîr 'eşkrin, mil mokînê
xist. Wekî 'ecwê çêkir, mi gûz kirnê.
Welcome to you. Well, I pressed figs, put them in the
machine. Made like paste, I put walnuts in them.
Henek bi gûz ilind, henek jî be... kuncî yo.
Some rolled in walnuts, some also in... sesame.
Yanî ev ne?
Meaning these?
Erê.
Yes.
Eva hêjîr e ne?
This is fig, right?
U gûz j'te tê xistî?
Yes.
And you put walnuts in it?
Erê.
Yes.
U tiştek din naye?
And nothing else comes in it?
Gûstê don.
Just walnuts.
Gûstê don? Ev te... rêdixin ber mêvane?
Just walnuts? This you... serve to guests?
Na sersî ye.
No, it is for New Year (Sersal).
Sersî ye. E ka ji destpêkê ji me re bêje te çawa çêdikir?
It's for New Year. So tell us from the beginning how you
made it?
Ewel şî ez... hêjîrê xwe 'eşk dikim. Ga 'eşk bî, el mokînê
dixim.
First thing I... I prepare my figs. When prepared, I put
them in the machine.
Ba'dî mil mokînê xist, wekî hevîr e, tiştê xwe dikim, ê
distirim. U ez çêdikim.
After putting in the machine, it's like dough, I do my
thing, I knead it. And I make it.
Bivî rengî çêdibe?
It becomes this color?
Erê.
Yes.
Ev jî yek din e?
Is this another one?
Ev jî bi kuncî yo ye.
This one is with sesame.
Erê.
Is it made with sesame?
Yes.
E dayê em tiştekî ji te bipirsin. Te bi xweş gundê 'Umer e?
So mother, let us ask you something. You yourself are from
the village of Omer?
Ez ji 'Umera me.
I am from Omer.
Tu bûka vî gundî mezin bûyî yan keçka vî gundî yî?
Did you grow up as a bride of this village or are you a
daughter of this village?
Erê.
Yes.
Gerek tu baş me nas bikî. Dema win keçik, diya we, li pêşiya
we çi kar dikirin? Win çi jê 'elimîn?
You need to inform us well. When you were a girl, your
mother, what work did they do before you? What did you learn
from them?
Dê me pale diçinin. Cotarî bûn.
Our mothers were reaping harvest. They were farmers.
Cû dajotin. Bidarê xwe çê dikirn, ardê... dexla me dibî, me
diçinî.
They drove the plow pair. They prepared their seeds, the
land... we had grain, we harvested.
Me diçinî, me şixre çê dikir. Me şixre çê dikir, danî şûn
bêderê didan.
We harvested, we made the threshing sled. We made the
threshing sled, then put it on the threshing floor.
Me danî dina, me cer-cerê xwe hebû. Cer-cerê me hesin têdaye
u cûr bu, text e.
We put it down, we had our thresher. Our thresher had iron
in it and it was a type, it is wood.
U heywan pê va girêdidan ê dizivirilandin. Fitelandin, dexlê
xwe... gi ba dikirn.
And they tied animals to it and spun it around. Spun it,
winnowed their grain... all of it.
Ê bikutan a, dexlê xwe el ba kiron a, dan ê me bişişta.
They would pound it, winnow their grain in the wind, wash
our grain.
Ê birana aş, me yê danî...
They would take it to the mill, we would...
Yanî berê karî we, berê pir bicefa têda bû.
Meaning formerly your work, formerly had a lot of hardship
in it.
Me pir bicefa dî. U kurê me hebûn u me kurê xwe dibirin,
buxar o. Me kincê wan dişuşt. Me ser tûma rê da.
We saw a lot of hardship. And we had sons and we took our
sons, to the spring. We washed their clothes. We laid them
on the bushes.
Wa li kuderê dişuşt? Av li kuderê hebû?
Where did you wash them? Where was there water?
Li kaniyê. Kaniyê vî sîmanê.
At the spring. The spring of this Siman.
Kaniyê vî sîmanê?
The spring of this Siman?
Erê, geliyê sîmanê. Geliyê sîmanê me rêdixist. Me qîçkê xwe
xwedî dikir. U me dabarê jî pale diçinî.
Yes, the Siman valley. In the Siman valley we spread them
out. We raised our little ones. And for livelihood we also
harvested.
E berê dinyê xweş bû, jiyana berê xweş bû yan ê neha?
So was the world better before, was life better before or
now?
Jiyan, ti ciwan bî jiyan xweş e. Ti ket, jiyan ne, jiyan
nabe.
Life, if you are young, life is good. If you get old, life
no, life is not good.
Yanî berê ji neha xweştir bû?
So before was better than now?
Xweş bû. Xweş bû.
It was good. It was good.
Enekî cefa hebû, bes xweş bû.
There was some hardship, but it was good.
Cefî me temam bû. Avî me tinebû vira, bîr tinebû, sehrînc
tinebûn, henîfe tinebû.
Our hardship was complete. We didn't have water here, no
well, no cisterns, no taps.
Em dıçûn bi dewar, me danî, avê xwe bi pişta radikirin. Kûze
bû.
We went with beasts of burden, we put it down, carried our
water on our backs. There were clay jars.
E tiştê dayikê we li pêşiya we çê dikirin, u neha çi hinda
bûye? Yanî çi wenda kir? We wek dayikê xwe ne dikir yanê?
And the things your mothers made before you, and now what is
lost? Meaning what is lost? You didn't do like your mothers?
Dayikê me xeyat bûn, dayikê me terzî bûn, dayikê me... her
tişt nikan ji pêncî.
Our mothers were tailors, our mothers were dressmakers, our
mothers... everything with their fingers.
Me'nî dikirn.
They did it.
Erê, cil çê dikirin. E hîryê xwe, miyê xwe banîna, gi teşiyê
biristana.
Did they make carpets?
Erê, cil çê dikirin. E hîryê xwe, miyê xwe banîna, gi teşiyê
biristana.
Yes, they made carpets. Bringing their wool, their sheep,
spinning it all on the spindle.
Wan miya, teşiyê biristana, bigulok kirana, cilê xwe, cilê
mihîrî çê dikirn. Her çonek ana dikirn.
Those sheep, spinning on the spindle, making into balls,
making their carpets, mohair carpets. They did every kind.
Her çî. Me wanaka wekî wan nekira.
Everything. We didn't do like them.
We nekir yanî. Jê ne 'elimîn?
You didn't do it. Didn't learn from it?
Me zanî, me ne ko wekî wan bikra. Teşta me nan dikir. Oooh
hoo.
We knew, we just didn't do it like them. In the trough we
made bread. Oh ho.
Şebab dihatin, nan derdidan, nanê sorê didan, nanê her nanek
ana.
The youth came, rolled out bread, gave red bread, every kind
of bread.
E noko ku ev nan, em nê dixun. Ev ne'met e. Tiştem na îş.
And now this bread, we don't eat it. It is a blessing. It's
not tasty.
Xwedê kemasiyê wanede, saeta we xweş. Mala we ava be.
May God give no lack, good health to you. May your home be
prosperous.