Na cîm derbaz bime... Rastî bawer bike ji zûda derbaz
nebûme... Hinekî ditirsim jî.
I won't go across... Honestly, believe me, I haven't crossed
in a long time... I'm a little scared too.
Tiştekî herî balkêş, zivistan e, sar e. Hinekî serma heye.
The most interesting thing is that it is winter, it is cold.
There is a bit of a chill.
Em ê niha derbazî cem çirvana bibin. De ka em baverin,
derbaz bin.
We will now go over to the boatmen. Come on, let's believe
and cross over.
Em despêkê te nas bikin?
Can we get to know you first?
Raşîd.
Rashid.
Ser çava Raşîd.
You are welcome, Rashid.
Tu çirvan î?
Are you a boatman?
Erê.
Yes.
Hûn çend kes in di gundê Qerqozaxê de masîgiriya dikin?
How many of you in the village of Qaraqozak do fishing?
Wallah em didu ne. Em ne li gund didu ne.
By God, there are two of us. We aren't two from the village
[specifically].
Wek din jî hene. Gundî der û dorê me jî hene.
There are others too. There are villagers around us as well.
Ji kû derê tên?
Where do they come from?
Ji şahrê tên, ji Efrînê tên, ha wina tên... Havînê ekseriya
xwe tên, biharê tên.
They come from the city, they come from Afrin, they come
like that... The majority come in the summer, they come in
the spring.
Bes em... daîm têdanin. Didu ji gund in.
But we... are always in it. Two are from the village.
Gundî der û dorê me jî hene, ew jî daîm têdanin.
There are villagers around us too, they are also always in
it.
Hewayê vê zivistanê zehmet e?
Is the weather this winter difficult?
Wallah zehmet e. Sar e, berf e, seqem e.
By God, it is difficult. It is cold, snowy, and frosty.
Îna berf li gundê we heye?
Is there snow in your village right now?
Berf jî heye.
There is snow too.
Yanî em îro di hundirê... em derbasî nava avê dibin û berf û
sar e.
So today inside the... we are crossing into the water while
it is snowy and cold.
Wallah berf...
By God, the snow...
Ji mêj ve me nedîbû. Berf axa zozanê sedî sed tê de dîtiye,
a vê carê tê de dibîne.
We hadn't seen it for a long time. The snow has definitely
covered the plateau soil completely, this time it is
witnessing it.
Yanî sih û heşt sal in vê carê berf tê.
Meaning, it's been thirty-eight years, and this time snow is
coming.
Mamoste çi cûre masî hene di vir de?
Sir, what kinds of fish are in here?
Masiyê Bûrî heye, Kerb heye, Karsîn heye.
There is Buri (Mullet), there is Carp, there is Karsin.
E... Beraq heye. Vêra dibêjin.
Uh... There is Beraq. That's what they call them here.
Em berê di Efrînê de jî hebûn.
We used to have them in Afrin in the past too.
Bes piştî vê avê şêbû şûnda... gî (hemû) bi nav bûn yanî.
But after this water became murky... they all got mixed
up/lost, basically.
Çar, pênc nûre (cûre) ancax mane.
Barely four or five types remain.
Mşext (Mişext/Mişe) heye?
Are there Mshekht (Locally specific fish/Carp)?
Mişext... Demîş nabe. Serma pir bû, salê serma pir bû, demîş
nabe.
Mshekht... They don't thrive/survive. The cold was severe,
the cold of the year was severe, they don't thrive.
Rojê çiqas kîlo berhev dikin? Çend kîlo?
How many kilos do you collect a day? How many kilos?
Wallah gava xweş be, serma tune be, seqem tune be, berf tune
be...
By God, when it is nice, no cold, no frost, no snow...
Ro heye deh kîlo, panzdeh kîlo, bîst kîlo, pênc kîlo...
There are days with ten kilos, fifteen kilos, twenty kilos,
five kilos...
Niha ev şeş roj e em vala têne.
Now, for these six days, we have been coming back empty.
Dabara we jî tê de tê?
Does your livelihood come from it too?
Dabara me jî tê de tê û rind jî tê.
Our livelihood comes from it, and it comes well.
Masî bi çiqasî difroşin?
For how much do you sell the fish?
Em masiyê hûr bi pêncsedî difroşin, û ê gir bi hezarî
difroşin.
We sell the small fish for five hundred, and the big ones
for a thousand.
Difroşin kû derê, vî masiyan?
Where do you sell these fish?
Wallah em difroşin... Şahrê, Efrîn, tên...
By God, we sell... The City, Afrin, they come...
Yani bi xwe tên ba we, li vir dibin?
Meaning they come to you themselves, taking them from here?
Bi xwe tên, telefon me dikin, em wa'de didinê...
They come themselves, they call us, we give them an
appointment...
Em ji mêj têdanin.
We have been in this [business] for a long time.
Çend sal heye?
How many years has it been?
Bûye... du-sê sal niha têda me. Hene...
It's been... I've been in it for two-three years now. There
are [others]...
Hene jî deh-panzdeh sal in têda hene, bîst sal, deh-heşt sal
tê hene.
There are also those who have been in it for ten-fifteen
years, twenty years, eighteen years.
Yanî despêkê sê de da hene.
Meaning they have been here since the beginning of the dam
[construction].
Hûn çend saetan di nav avê de dimînin?
How many hours do you stay in the water?
Du saet in.
It is two hours.
Tenê du saet hûn di nav avê de dimînin?
Only two hours you stay in the water?
Wallah gava ba tune be, karê me zû xelas dibe.
By God, when there is no wind, our work finishes quickly.
Gava ro heye, ba hebe... karê me dereng dimîne.
When there is sun, if there is wind... our work runs late.
Gelo ba heye?
Is there wind?
Îro ba heye, em dereng man îro.
Today there is wind, we stayed late today.
E... mihim ez dixwazim... deqê çêkim, em jê avê derkevin.
Uh... anyway I want to... fix the spot/net, so we can get
out of the water.
Av çiqa avê hebe, nohqa me maye.
However much water there is, our dive remains.
Nohqa me maye, em ê jê avê derkevin.
Our dive remains, [then] we will get out of the water.
Yekî sîwan... em jê avê derkevin.
A protected area... we will get out of the water.
Yekî sîwan em jê avê derkevin.
A protected area, we will get out of the water.
Û hene... kesên ku hene tên şebekê cer... Wa şebeka...
And there are... people who come with drag nets... Those
nets...
Tînin, tê de dixînin, difitilînin, dikişînin derva.
They bring them, put them in, twist them, and pull them out.
Dikişînin derva, masiyê sîsiyê, çorê jî, masî bizer (bi
zirar) tê.
They pull them out, the Sisi fish, the Chora too, the fish
comes damaged.
Bizer bar dide. Dikeve ber şebekê, derdikeve derva, giyan
xelas dibe.
It yields damage. It falls into the net, comes out, and its
life ends.
Yanî divê (gerek) wisa nekin?
Meaning they shouldn't do that?
Gerek wisa nebe.
It shouldn't be like that.
Bi nîspet (bi nesîbet) kêmbûn dibe.
Relatively, a decrease happens.
Bizer... gava derxist derva xera bû, kêmî mese jê hinekî
dibe.
Waste... when taken out it gets ruined, the quantity
decreases a little from it.
Yanî em du sal, sê sal e, hifaz dikin (diparêzin) ser vî...
avê... vê helîna.
I mean, for two years, three years, we have been protecting
this... water... this nesting ground.
Kêmiya (hejmar) zêde pirr nebe.
So the shortage doesn't become too great.
Ez rojê pênc kîlo digrim, ez ê deh-panzdeh kîlo bigrim, bîst
kîlo bigrim.
I catch five kilos a day, [if protected] I would catch ten-
fifteen kilos, twenty kilos.
Şebekê te çend metre ye?
How many meters is your net?
Şebekê min... pêncî heye, sed heye.
My net... there is fifty, there is a hundred.
Û qiyas in. Dav-heşt, ê hefte, sî û pênc, çil...
And they are sizes. Eight-mesh, seven-mesh, thirty-five,
forty...
A masî me yê ha vaye, di ber şebekê da ne. Ez ê dikişînim.
See, our fish are like this, they are in the net. I'm
pulling it.
Ê mezin pirtir kîjan in, hene di nava wan de?
Which are the bigger ones mostly, are there any among them?
Ê pir şekal in (biçûk in). Ê pir havna (havne) dişixûlin.
Most are small ones. Most of these ones work/are active.
Ê pir bûrî mara dişixûlin.
Most of the Buri fish work for us.
Ê bûrî mara dişixûlin.
The Buri fish work for us.
Ba ye, tama (tehma) bê têne... Bû me dûr avêt, xistilî ne.
It is wind, the taste of wind comes... The wind threw us
far, it is turbulent.
Ey quwat be, spas dikim.
May you have strength, thank you.
Sax be.
Be healthy.
Ka em hinekî vegerin.
Let's go back a little.
Hêjayî gotinê ye ku du gund bi heman navî hene.
It is worth mentioning that there are two villages with the
same name.
Qerqozaxa Biçûk ku bi navê Derwêş tê naskirin.
Little Qaraqozak, which is known by the name Dervish.
Û Qerqozaxa Mezin jî, an gundê...
And Big Qaraqozak as well, or the village of...