[Instrumental Music]
Temaşevanên hêja, îro em hatine gundê Hec Xelîl. Li navçeya
Raco.
Dear viewers, today we have come to the village of Hec
Xelîl. In the district of Raco.
Ev gunda berî vê bi 225 salî de ava bûye.
This village was built 225 years ago.
Ê darbesta vê gundî daniye navê xwe Ma'mûk bûye.
The one who laid the foundation of this village was named
Ma'mûk.
Lê ev gunda jî naha 250 mal e. Pir mal ba derbas vir bûn.
But this village now has 250 households. Many families have
passed through here.
Lê di sala 1914an de, ev şerê dijî Ermeniya çêbûye, malbatin
Ermenî jî derbas vir bûn.
But in the year 1914, when the war against the Armenians
happened, Armenian families also passed through here.
Lê di vê gundî da jî ziyaretek heye bi nav û deng e, vêra
dibêjin Ziyareta Mehmê Elî.
Also in this village, there is a famous shrine, they call it
the Shrine of Mehmê Elî.
Lê şazdeh (16) pakrewanên me jî ji vê gundî hene.
And we have sixteen martyrs from this village.
Lê ka em ba hev ra derbasî vê gundî bin, em çanda vê gundî
nas bikin.
But let us enter this village together, let us get to know
the culture of this village.
[Music]
Temaşevanên hêja, em derbasî gundê Hec Xelîl bûn. Em hatin
mala Sebrî Hibo.
Dear viewers, we entered the village of Hec Xelîl. We came
to the house of Sebrî Hibo.
Apê Sebrî jî kelek min e. Merheba.
Uncle Sebrî is also an elder of mine. Hello.
Merheba.
Hello.
Apê Sebrî, ev dîroka gundê we me got 225 sala de ava bûye.
Uncle Sebrî, regarding the history of your village, we said
it was founded 225 years ago.
Piştî malbatin din jî hatin vê gundî, destpêkê Ma'mûk bû?
After that other families came to this village, was it
Ma'mûk at the beginning?
Piştî wî malbatin din derbas bûn...
After him, did other families pass through...
Belê.
Yes.
Ka ji me re bêje malbat kî ne?
Tell us, who are the families?
Malbat sifte hemî Ma'mûk, lawê Hec Xelîl bû.
The family at the beginning was all Ma'mûk, the son of Hec
Xelîl.
Ji Dîlokê, ji Entabê... berî 225 salan teqrîben... hatine li
vî derî şên kirine.
From Dilok, from Antep... approximately 225 years ago...
they came and populated this place.
Cîk şên kirine, li wî derî... dirêj nekirin.
They populated a place, over there... they didn't stay long.
Hatine li vî gundî, navê xwe Sirtê Korê bû, li vî derî bicî
bûn, nav lê nan gundê Hec Xelîl.
They came to this village, its name was Sirtê Korê [Blind
Ridge], they settled here, and named it the village of Hec
Xelîl.
Ev çiyayê cemb we jî, werim Çiyayê Mîr e?
This mountain next to you as well, I believe is Mîr
Mountain?
Çiya jî di şîmalî gundê de haye, dibêjin Çiyayê Mîra, Mîrek
lê rûdiniştin.
The mountain is to the north of the village, they call it
the Mountain of the Mîrs, a Mîr used to reside there.
Leqebê xwe Çiyayê Mîr e.
Its title is Mîr Mountain.
Û şerqan... rûlat jî Çiyayê Bilêl e.
And to the east... east is the Bilêl Mountain.
Gundê ka ye kûr e... rojelatî me.
There is a village deep down... to our east.
Û rojava me jî gundê Raco ye.
And to our west is the village of Raco.
Başûrê me jî gundê Mûskê heye, Gûliya heye, Çeqelma heye...
To our south is the village of Mûskê, there is Gûliya, there
is Çeqelma...
Gundê me di navberê de ye.
Our village is in between.
Yanî ev gundê, li navçeya Raco ne? Tabeî navçeya Raco ne?
Meaning these villages are in the district of Raco?
Affiliated with the Raco district?
Na gundê we... Tabeî navçeya Raco ne.
No [regarding proximity]... They are affiliated with the
Raco district.
Heft heşt gund li dor me da ne.
There are seven or eight villages around us.
Gund mewqiyê xwe ev e.
This is the village's location.
Me got ser malbata. Çend malbat, yanî çend malbat di vî
gundî da ava bûn?
We spoke about the families. How many families, meaning how
many families were established in this village?
Malbat... mişter beyan kir, bi mere dibêjin Hec Xelîlî...
lawê Hec Xelîl Ma'mûk bû.
The families... the elder stated, they call us Hec Xelîlî...
Hec Xelîl's son was Ma'mûk.
Û jî sê aîle çêbûn.
And three families were formed from him.
Yek mala Bilê, vêra digotin Bilê Bavkê Reşo bû.
One was the house of Bilê, they called him Bilê, the father
of Reşo.
Yek mala Mehmed, bavkê Ehmed Bekû bû.
One was the house of Mehmed, the father of Ehmed Bekû.
Evna bûn sê aîle. Em jê pir bûn, bes cîranê me hene, bi mere
rûniştine.
These were the three families. We multiplied from them, but
we have neighbors, they settled with us.
Ji ku derê hatin?
Where did they come from?
Ewa... mala Hecû hene... me jinik da bû gundiyekî...
xwarziyê me ne.
Those... there is the Hecû family... we had given a woman to
a villager... they are our nephews.
Xalê Mamkê bêrî bû.
They were the maternal uncles of Ma'mûk previously.
Ji bo gundiya, îşek qewimî, hatin cem me rûniştin.
Regarding the villagers, a matter occurred, they came and
settled with us.
Û koçer bûn, Gûlîjêrin bûn.
And they were nomads, from Lower Gûlî.
Li Gûlîjêrin hatin cem me rûniştin.
From Lower Gûlî they came and settled with us.
Sêwî... sêwî ro sêwî me mezin kirin.
Orphans... as orphans we raised them.
Mehmûk ma'na wada xwedî kirin.
Ma'mûk fostered them in that way.
Wan bûn cîranê me.
They became our neighbors.
Paşê me li wan jî hilkir, me hat gundê Hec Xelîl şên kir,
cîh hatine cem me.
Then we accepted them too, we came and populated Hec Xelîl
village, they came to us.
Û berî me jî malek li wir hebû, digotin mala Tekû.
And before us, there was a house there, they called it the
Tekû house.
Tekû ne tatû. Noka kirine Tetû. Malek hebû mala Tekû.
Tekû, not Tatû. Now they've made it Tetû. There was a house,
the Tekû house.
Û mala Hecû, û mala Hec Xelîl va, bi hev ra ev gunda şên
kirin.
And the Hecû family, and this Hec Xelîl family, together
they populated this village.
Û du-dû ra aîlan hatin, dibêjin mala 'Erûys.
And later two families came, they call them the 'Erûys
family.
Du-dû ra hatin ew jî koçer in, mal milkê xwe tînan li gundê
me bûn mal.
Two came later, they are also nomads, brought their property
and became residents in our village.
Du-dû ra mala Kûsa hatin.
Later the Kûsa family came.
Du-dû ra mala Hecû hat... hewke... mala Ûsê hatin.
Later the Hecû family came... uh... the Ûsê family came.
Mala Girû hatin. Evna şaxçaliyên eslî xwe.
The Girû family came. These are branches of their own
origin.
Mala Elwîtê hatin. Ew jî eslê xwe şaxçaliyan e.
The Elwîtê family came. They are also branches of their
origin.
Û malin heye, mala Gunêş, mala Xecwînê, mala Misxarîbê...
mala Biliş hebûn.
And there are families, the Gunêş family, Xecwînê family,
Misxarîbê family... there were the Biliş family.
Evna aîlan îş gunda hatin gundê me.
These families came from the villages to our village.
Nava gundê we de Ermenî jî hene?
Are there Armenians inside your village as well?
Ermenî hişta malek e. Noka bûnê sê-çar mal.
Armenians, there is still one house remaining. Now they have
become three or four houses.
Navê xwe vêra digotin mala Miskûşko... Kûşkarî dikirin.
Their name, they called them the Miskûşko family... They
used to do shoemaking.
Mistefa Xerîb navê xwe yazmîş kiriye.
He wrote his name as Mustafa Xerîb.
Navê jina jî Meryem bû, ew jî Ermenî bû.
The wife's name was Meryem, she was also Armenian.
Û lawkê xwe bûn Cemîl, yek bûn Nûrî, yek bûn Şemsî.
And his sons were Cemîl, one was Nûrî, one was Şemsî.
Evna Cemîl miriye, du dima ne, Nûrî û Şemsî va mane.
Of these, Cemîl has died, two remain, Nûrî and Şemsî remain.
Û sê malên jî gundiyan çêbûne.
And three families of villagers have been formed.
Na na ev tişkî ser vê çayî jî ji me ra bêje, tişkî ser vê
çayî...
Now, tell us something about this well/spring too, something
about this well...
Çayê Mîrê... dibêjin berê hesin dan... hinek kumpanîk hebû
rûsî bû...
The Mîr's Well... they say formerly iron came out... there
was a company, it was Russian...
Şîrketek Rûsî hat, me'denê hesin li vî derî derxist, xendek
kolan salê pêncî û şeşa.
A Russian company came, extracted iron ore here, dug
trenches in the year fifty-six.
Hetanî pêncî û heşt-pêncî neha întîha kirin, xelas kirin,
hiştin, asarê xwe hene.
Until fifty-eight or fifty-nine they finished, completed it,
left it, their ruins are there.
Me'denê zêr li vî çoyî tê der...
Iron ore comes out of this mountain...
Berê Mîrî vê mentîqeyî, reîsî... merkezê xwe di vî çoyî da
cih hebû.
Formerly the Mîr of this region, the chief... had his center
in this mountain.
Yanî havîngeha xwe lê dikir.
Meaning he made his summer residence there.
Naha 20 sal ne, belkî belediya gundê we jî heye.
Now it's been 20 years, perhaps your village has a
municipality too.
Û belediyek jî ji hatiyî...
And a municipality has come...
Belediya gundê me girêdayî belga Raco ye.
Our village's municipality is connected to the town of Raco.
Ji sala sî û şeşa da girêdayî wî ye.
Since the year thirty-six it has been connected to it.
Ji sî û şeşa da, şeklî yanî belediye bû...
Since thirty-six, it was formally a municipality...
Yanî mudîr nahiye hatin, hewî mensibê reîs belediye dibir.
Meaning the district director came, he took the position of
mayor.
Û paşê belediye jî teqrîben ez wek ez zanim 25 sal e ne, di
gundê me da resmî çêbûye.
And then the municipality, approximately as far as I know,
it's been 25 years since it was officially established in
our village.
Û reîs belediye sifte Ehmed Fewzî Elî bû, e paşê jî Adem
Sîdo bû.
And the first mayor was Ahmed Fewzî Elî, and after that was
Adem Sîdo.
Em ga... yanî pismamê hev din.
We are... meaning cousins of each other.
Û va belediya jî mîzaniye ji jor ra derdikeve.
And this municipality, the budget comes out from above
[government].
Reîs belediye ji hatiye bû, li vî gundî serf dikir.
The mayor who had come spent it in this village.
Vê gundî ji jor ra gist serbest dikir.
He made this village completely free [developed] from above.
Rê, malê kê keta, digot mela lê keve.
Roads, if someone's house collapsed, he said let it be [we
will fix it].
Ba didane, digot mela ba dime. Fetl a gundî bîjî, avî bîjî.
They provided aid, he said let me give aid. The poor of the
village existed, the water existed.
Û gundê me fe'len gundekî nemûzeje di belga Raco da.
And our village is actually an exemplary village in the Raco
town area.
Yanî belediya xwe pir pak e, li pêş e, nîzamî ye, rehet e.
Meaning its municipality is very clean, advanced, organized,
comfortable.
Nana ziyareta... du ziyareta jî nav û deng e, Ziyareta Mehmê
Elî heye?
Now the shrine... two shrines are also famous, is there the
Shrine of Mehmê Elî?
Ziyareta Mehmê Elî heye. Yek dibêjin dabetekî Ûsmênî bû.
There is the Shrine of Mehmê Elî. Some say he was an Ottoman
officer.
Hinik jî dibêjin yekî Yezîdî bû.
Some also say he was a Yezidi.
Çarşem, roja xwe ye. 'Eyda Yezîdiya di Çarşemê da bû.
Wednesday is its day. The Yezidi holiday was on Wednesday.
Û ew jî dibêjin dabetekî Ûsmênî bû li vî derî mir.
And those also say he was an Ottoman officer who died here.
Û di kelêkê da Şêxmûs heye, ew jî ziyaretek e.
And on the side there is Şêxmûs, that is also a shrine.
Ew jî tirbe, ew jî tirbe ye.
That is also a tomb, that is also a tomb.
Vê belga Raco tev da miriyê xwe tînin vî derî, berê.
This whole Raco district used to bring their dead here to
bury, formerly.
Li her gundekî cîh miriya tinebû. Ê mentîqeyê giştkî bû.
No village had a place for the dead [cemetery]. It was for
the whole region.
Nav lê kirin Şêxmûs û Mehmed Elî.
They named it Şêxmûs and Mehmed Elî.
Ta spas dikim, saet xweş.
I thank you, have a good time.
Spas xweş.
You are welcome.
[Outro Music]
Em hatine vê hêla...
We have come to this side...
Emê li gundê Pirsaxê, li gel Apê Mihemed Elî bikin.
We will be in the village of Pirsax, with Uncle Mihemed Elî.
Li ser vê gundî...
About this village...
adet û teqalîdên vî gundî çine?
what are the customs and traditions of this village?
Urf û adetên xwe...
Its customs and habits...
Debara xwe bi çi dikin?
How do they make a living?
De Apê Mihemed Elî, hûn debara xwe bi çi dikin vira?
So, Uncle Mihemed Elî, how do you make a living here?
Xweşî li ser çavên min, ser çava.
You are very welcome, upon my eyes.
Va gunda, wek gundên Kurda ye, bi zîraetê...
This village, like [other] Kurdish villages, [relies] on
agriculture...
Ya kêmîş û pîvaz.
Or garlic and onions.
Lê vî gundî esas, piraniya xwe bi tîcaretê yani.
But this village, fundamentally, the majority of it [relied]
on trade.
Ji kevin da heta niha.
From old times until now.
Wek çi? Tîcareta çi dikin?
Like what? What trade do they do?
Mesela dema Fransa, Mutehedî Kumrî hebûn ji vî gundî bûn.
For example, during the French [mandate] era, there were
customs contractors from this village.
Dibe wer...
It might be...
Dema diçûn Helebê, Şamê, tîcaret dikirin.
When they went to Aleppo, Damascus, they did trade.
Yanî ev kar kirine.
Meaning, they did this work.
Tîcareta cimlê, tîcaret... her reng bi reng.
Wholesale trade, trade... of all various kinds.
Lê milkê gundê me yê pan û fereh tune ye.
But our village does not have vast and wide property.
Hanîfe Axa bî, milkê wî tenê hebû.
[Unless] it was Hanife Agha, only he had property.
Xêncî wî, kesê milkê wî 2000, 5000, 10000 zeytûnê wî tune
ye.
Other than him, there is no one who has property of 2,000,
5,000, or 10,000 olive trees.
Li ser vê esasê...
On this basis...
Kerem ke.
Go ahead.
Çîrokek li ser vî gundî heye.
There is a story about this village.
Misaîdekî vî gundî, yêkî kor hebû, Hafizê Kor jê re digotin.
There was an assistant [official] in this village, a blind
man, they called him the Blind Hafiz.
Heger tu yê esker bî...
If you were a soldier...
Wextê li ser hespê, sise sêtê tê waha cem wan.
When on a horse, three sets [of officers] come like this to
them.
Dibê, "Ez heyran..."
He says, "I admire..."
Rûkê de rû, nîvî wan...
Face to face, half of them...
Ew jî jê re xwarinê çêdikin.
They also prepare food for him.
Dibêje, "Ez heyran, gundê we çima waha di çelê da ye, di
kortê da ye?"
He says, "I admire, why is your village in a hole, in a
hollow like this?"
Dibêje, "Gundê me yê nizim e, rizqê me yê kêm e."
He says, "Our village is low, our luck/sustenance is low
[scarce]."
Hafizê Kor hebû.
The Blind Hafiz was there.
Yekî hinikî şûrnasker e.
He was someone a bit witty/knowledgeable.
Gotibû, "Emoxlî, min xerîb e, dibê tu ji kûyê, dibê ez ji
gundê Hec Xelîl im."
He said, "Cousin, I am a stranger, if you say where are you
from, say I am from Hec Xelîl village."
"Law welle dibê gundê Hec Xelîl gundekî rind e, ciyê wî
bilind e, rizqê wî rizqê kunc e."
"Oh my, they say Hec Xelîl village is a good village, its
location is high, its luck/sustenance is confined."
Law gotiye, "Hafiz, gundê Hec Xelîl gundekî rind e, min
naskir, ew bilind bûn naskir. Çima rizqê kunc e?"
The man said, "Hafiz, Hec Xelîl village is a good village, I
recognized that; that they were high up, I recognized. Why
is the luck/sustenance confined?"
Gotî, "Bira, ez biçim kesê wek Axayê Cûmê, milkê wî bin erqê
da tune ye."
He said, "Brother, let me say, there is no one like the Agha
of Juma whose property is under the sweat [of
laborers/feudalism]."
"Kesê wî 1000 dar, 10000 zeytûn tune ye. Ez dibînim xwarina
we pak e, kincê we xweşik e, xwarina we xweşik e, hûn jî têr
in."
"No one has 1,000 trees, 10,000 olives. I see your food is
clean, your clothes are beautiful, your food is beautiful,
and you are full."
Bira rastî ki va, nasnekirî mesel li ser tîcaretê ye.
Brother, truthfully this, unknown to him, the issue was
about trade.
Lê vî gundî ji kevin da, bingehî...
But in this village, from old times, fundamentally...
zanîbûn û me'rîfet...
knowledge and capability...
Li kûjan civakî dinyayê da zanîbûn hebe, fikir pêş dikeve.
In whichever society in the world there is knowledge,
thought progresses.
Pê ra civak jî pêş dikeve.
Along with it, society also progresses.
Mesela van gunda rengê vatanî ji kevin da, dema Fransa da,
pîra Çeqeso...
For example, these villages had a patriotic nature from old
times, during the French era, the bridge of Çeqeso...
Doda şoreş gerandin.
They conducted a revolution there.
Rengê vatanî birine.
They carried a patriotic nature.
Heya pirtiya Karkerê Kurdistan hat.
Until the Kurdistan Workers' Party came.
Dadihî ber refa, bersiv dan.
They gave answer [joined] immediately.
Muhendis li vî gundî hene, çûne...
There are engineers in this village, they went...
museqefên çûne, bi vî hesabî...
intellectuals who went [studied], in this regard...
Sibe bingehekî fikrî cem wî da heye.
Because there is an intellectual foundation among them.
Li vî gundî dema mekteb û camî hebû...
In this village, when there was a school and a mosque...
Şerqî me da heft, heşt gund roj gundê Qîsim, gundê Şêx da
dihatin mekteba me.
To our east, seven or eight villages, [from] Qîsim village,
Şêx village, used to come to our school.
Dihatin camiya gundê me.
They used to come to our village's mosque.
Heke zanîbûn hebe, fikir pêş dikeve.
If there is knowledge, thought progresses.
Dihatin dixwendin?
Did they come and study?
Dihatin dixwendin, dihatin fêr dibûn.
They came and studied, they came and learned.
Em gundê derdora we...
The villages surrounding you...
Heft gund da.
Seven villages.
Gura, gundê Holê, gundê Çençeliya...
Gura, Holê village, Çençeliya village...
bi mira xwendine.
they studied with us.
Gundê Şêx, gundê Qîsim dihatin vî gundî dixwendin, mekteb
tune bûn li wan gunda.
Şêx village, Qîsim village came to this village to study,
there were no schools in those villages.
Li Raju dûbistan tune bûn? Li Raju?
Were there no schools in Raju? In Raju?
Hebû, lê em jî nîzîk in. Em jî ji wa, ji Raju nîzîktir in.
There were, but we are also close. We are closer [to them]
than Raju.
Dihatin cem me.
They came to us.
Nexweşbêjim, av jî ji gundê we tune, av tune ye?
Unfortunately, there is no water in your village either, no
water?
Ji kevin da avê baranê.
From old times, [we rely on] rainwater.
Va mantiqê Raju, xusyetek wî heye, em herêm, mantiqê me
mantiqê hesin e.
This Raju area has a characteristic; our region, our area is
an iron area [ferrous soil/rock].
Derê hesin hebe, av kêm dibe.
Where there is iron, water becomes scarce.
Ee, em ş... li ser avê baranê.
Uh, we... [rely] on rainwater.
Av nehat, vê şoreşê Sûriyê da, em tenkerik mezin kirin.
[If] water didn't come, in this Syrian revolution, we
enlarged a tanker.
Xêncî nuhayî, avfînkê dikişînin.
Besides now, they are drawing water tankers.
Ji vî dera na, av heye, ema cama...
Not from here, there is water [elsewhere], but the people...
Tine, av tune. Çike zehmetî pir.
None, there is no water. Because it's very difficult.
Ne gundê we rewşenbîr e, di gundê we da doxtor e, di gundê
we...
Since your village is intellectual, there are doctors in
your village, in your village...
Neha dibêjin gundê we da hinek toxtor hene bêşade ne, wam
tune ne? Kî çîrokê wan bêje ji me ra.
Now they say in your village there are some doctors without
degrees, aren't there? Who can tell us their story.
Heval Dodo hebû, rehmetî bûn.
There was Heval Dodo, he is deceased.
Ji nuyha Bilbilê, ji nuyha Şera, ji nuyha Şiyê dihatin li
meydanê, dihatin pêşiya wî nexweşî giran derman dikirin.
From Bulbul district, from Shera district, from Shiye
district, they came to the square, they came before him and
he treated serious illnesses.
Pir nexweş çûbûn bajarê Beyrûtê û Helebê çênebûn, gundî
derman dikir û pir ser diket.
Many patients had gone to the cities of Beirut and Aleppo
and didn't get better; the villager treated them and was
very successful.
E çawa elimîbûn, toxtor e ev na?
How had they learned, is he a doctor or not?
Yek ji wan, nexweş bî dema Fransa, çû bin Libnanê bi
hûranekat.
One of them was sick during the French era, he went down to
Lebanon with [?].
Li wê derê, me got temam, derkî de ku fikir pêşkeve, zanebûn
çêdibe.
There, we said okay, once [you go] out so thought
progresses, knowledge is created.
Li wir kirin mumeril [mumaris] li ber destê doktor.
There they made him a practitioner under the supervision of
a doctor.
Hinikî, hûr û tiştin ji wan... hat vî derê mumarise kir.
A little, details and things from them... he came here and
practiced.
Neha deha qicik birîna mezin kirin.
Now, he treated [made big] ten small wounds.
Yek reîs belediye Siftah li wê gundî bû, Ehmed Fewzî.
A mayor, Siftah, was in that village, Ehmed Fewzî.
Na şahîn jî ketiyê, ew nebûye.
Now a certificate was also entered for him, [although] he
didn't have one.
E kû derê şahid katiye?
Where was the certificate entered?
Li Kurdistanê.
In Kurdistan.
Şoreşê da.
During the revolution.
Îna ew la nebûye.
Meaning, he didn't have it [before].
Neha deha qicik mezin kirin, bi xwendin dan li ser wî şewdê.
Now he treated ten small ones [children/people], they
certified him based on that witness/evidence.
Hewal, pîrek hat, qicikê xwe anîbû, çomî destê wê dikir...
Friend, a woman came, she had brought her child, she was
doing [gesturing] to his arm/hand...
Digot filan dermanî bide...
He said give such and such medicine...
Pîk hat. Yekî got ta na bin. Got na dibin.
The [bone/arm] came [set]. Someone said it won't happen. He
said no, it will happen.
Dirûndikî waha cem hebû yani. Ewa mîsalî vî pir in di vî
meselê da.
He had such honesty/integrity about him. Examples like this
are many in this matter.
Ca li hunermendiyê da jî ez dibêjim gundê we camêr e,
hunermendên xwe jî hene.
Well, in artistry too, I say your village is noble, it has
its artists too.
Hunermendê me û... dema kevin tune.
Our artists and... in old times there weren't any.
Ama di vî demê da, Semîr Eytan tênaskirin.
But in this time, Semîr Eytan is known.
Ew jî li Ewropayê ne, a?
He is also in Europe, right?
Li Belçîka, belê.
In Belgium, yes.
U Perwer tênaskirin.
And Perwer is known.
A, Perwer jî hin helbestvan e, hin hunermend e. Bi rastî...
Ah, Perwer is both a poet and an artist. Truly...
Belê, belê.
Yes, yes.
Belê.
Yes.
Yelek dengî wî jî xweş e.
He has a very good voice too.
Belê, xweş e, e.
Yes, it is good, yes.
Navê xwe Farûq e, kirî Perwer. Navê hunerî.
His name is Farûq, he made it Perwer. Artistic name.
Belê. Semîr Eytan navê xwe yê heqîqî ye.
Yes. Semîr Eytan is his real name.
Û helbestvanek jî ji gundê we heye, Nezîr Palo.
And there is a poet from your village too, Nezîr Palo.
Nezîr Palo. Ew jî li Ewropayê silavê me hemû ji wan ra hene.
Nezîr Palo. He is also in Europe, our greetings to all of
them.
Almanya.
Germany.
Şabekî hendesî ziraî birîbû, bi exlaq û edeb bû.
He was a young man who held an agricultural engineering
[degree], he was of morals and manners.
Heta dema çûye.
Until the time he left.
Dengî wî xweş e li welat... li Ewropa.
His voice/reputation is good in the country... in Europe.
Spas, saet xweş.
Thanks, have a good time.
Sax bim, serkeftin ji we ra.
Be healthy, success to you.
Navê te çi ye keça min?
What is your name my daughter?
Sîlva.
Silva.
Na Sîlva, te çend kevire ne ev na?
So Silva, how many stones are these?
Dozdeh.
Twelve.
Dozdeh kevir ne?
Twelve stones?
We çend kes in kî bilîzin?
Yeah.
How many people are you who will play?
Ehm, du ferîq in, her yek sise.
Um, two teams, each one is three.
Her yek sise.
Each one is three.
Na hûnê çi bikin?
Now what will you do?
Hê?
Us?
Huh?
Hûnê çawa bilîzin?
How will you play?
Emê şimkê bavêjin.
We will throw the slipper/ball.
Lêkî em birevin, hewê daf ser me kin.
Then we run away, they will chase [throw at] us.
E parekî hişt we, ew dibê moka wan?
If a part is left of you, that becomes their 'moka'
[score/turn]?
A.
Yeah.
Selmegeyo ket, dibê moka me.
[If] the 'selmege' fell, it becomes our 'moka'.
Selmege duxri kirin, em ser gindoka da dikin.
[If] they straighten the 'selmege', we put it on the
'gindoka' [round stones/ball?].
De kerem ke.
Go ahead.
Emê şûnda hatin vê ji derbasî malekî bûn, Cema Meta Zeynep.
We came back and passed by a house, the group of Aunt
Zeynep.
Meta Zeynep jî, vir dibêjin tixter.
Aunt Zeynep is also called a doctor here.
Ne xwendiye, berê tu zan... milet ne diçû bajara, tixter pir
kêm bûn.
She hasn't studied, before you know... the people didn't go
to the cities, doctors were very scarce.
E ji gunda tixter derdiketin.
So doctors emerged from the villages.
Meta Zeynep, merheba.
Aunt Zeynep, hello.
Ehlên.
Welcome.
Na dibên, bêtir dibêjin tu tixter e.
Now they say, mostly they say you are a doctor.
Tu çava pak dikî, tu çawa çava pak dikî?
You clean eyes, how do you clean eyes?
Çava, ezê pak bikim.
Eyes, I will clean them.
Yê gêlek têda be, ezê bikim gêle.
If there is a thorn/speck in it, I will make it [remove] the
thorn.
Yê qirş têda be, ezê qirş pê tînim der.
If there is a husk/straw in it, I bring the husk out with
it.
Yê hesin têda ye, ezê zimanê xwe li ser gerînim.
If there is iron/metal in it, I will roll my tongue over it.
Ezê bi derînim.
I will take it out.
Yanî çi, çi gemar ket çava, tu derdixî?
Meaning what, whatever dirt fell in the eye, you take it
out?
Çi gemar têda be, ezê derxim.
Whatever dirt is in it, I will take it out.
U çi bêjî, yekî werin cem min, siheta xwe jî bi min hene, ez
pî çavî gindovî paçî hûno fehre dikim û pî tînim der.
And whatever you say, [if] someone comes to me, they have
their health with me [trust me], I check/clean the round
part of that eye with a cloth like this and bring it out
with it.
Ezê wî çakim, hem yekî xwedê didarînim.
I cure him, I also fulfill a duty to God.
Jiber ku gundiyan hemûyî karê gunda dikin, cotkar in e.
Because the villagers all do village work, they are
ploughmen.
Yanî gemar dikeve, qirş dikeve, hesin dikeve, tên ba te.
Meaning dirt falls in, straw falls in, iron falls in [their
eyes], they come to you.
Wan waye.
That is how it is.
Tu çend sale vê karî dikî?
For how many years have you been doing this work?
Weleh, de 'emrê orto li heyştê de herre, ez vê karî dikim
yorim.
By God, let the middle age go past eighty, I have been doing
this work, my dear.
Ne hûro ye, ne doho ye.
It isn't [just] today, it isn't [just] yesterday.
Na tu çend salî bûyî?
Now, how old were you [when you started]?
Ez îna ku topa deh, dav du salî bûm, evan karî dikim nav
mileti me da.
I mean when I was ten... twelve years old, I have been doing
this work among our people.
Ez hatim vira jî, karê min dîsa ew bû.
I came here too, my work was that again.
Tu ji kû derê bûyî berê?
Where were you from before?
Ez Çençelî bûm.
I was from Çençeliya.
Ji gundê Çençeliya ye.
From the village of Çençeliya.
Ez Çençelî bûm, bavkê min Reşîdê... Êdo ye.
I was from Çençeliya, my father is Reşîdê... Êdo.
U bapîrê min, Hebeşê Êdo ye.
And my grandfather is Hebeşê Êdo.
Ez ji we derê bûm, paşê jî hatim vira...
I was from there, then I came here...
Vê rojê me vekara kir, û me paqij kir.
We cleared it this day, and we cleaned it.
Erê çend kes tên ba te?
So, how many people come to you?
Wele ekê bim... kes... rojê bazarê... a bibim yonî bîst
tên... ser bîsta ra tên.
Well, let me be... people... on market day... I'd say around
twenty come... over twenty come.
Û li vira jî dêm dar têne. Noka ez hatim gîştim mal, hir û
bazar e.
And here too, constantly people come. Now that I've reached
home, it's all noisy and busy like a market.
Hîn min parî nan nexwaribû, porê xwe dida makîna wetan.
I hadn't even eaten a bite of bread yet, I was giving my
hair to the machine [hair dryer/comb] of the homeland.
Û ma êwa jî rabû, min got destê xwe şûştin... û ma ew jî
kerî ye.
And that one got up too, I said I washed my hands... and
that is also numb/paralyzed.
Hem... vê qirnê, ay rîyo... hem ha kerî şişe.
Both... this hernia, oh my face... and this numbness is
swollen.
Û hem Îsparta kerî. Ez kê vê destê no jî bişûm, bi ava sar
ta, paşê jî destê bişûm...
And Isparta is numb. If I wash this hand too, with cold
water, and then wash the hand...
Û paşê ekê ecêb derynim. Her sê çarika jî hewa nêtînim der.
Û paçikê xwe jî ez çêdikim.
And then I will bring out wonders. Every three quarters I
bring out the air. And I fix my own cloth [headscarf].
Paçê min... li Recû ha qos e ne... Kî min re tîne? Wele li
Heleb tîne? Li Efrînê noka li rê li Be'dîna jî min re
dişînin.
My cloth... in Rajo is it like this... Who brings it to me?
Do they bring it from Aleppo? In Afrin now, on the road in
Be'dîna they send it to me.
Manê ez çavê vî rê peşanim.
Meaning, I am watching/showing the eye of this road.
Yanî tu li Recû kar dikî?
So, you work in Rajo?
Li Recû kar dikim. Ez na wa rim tita derê.
I work in Rajo. I don't go anywhere else.
Bes rojê bazarê. Bazarê Recû şemiyê... ekê dokavem sibê, û
heta nîvro...
Only on market day. Rajo's market is Saturday... I will set
up shop in the morning, and until noon...
Azan didê jî ez li malim. Ortê xelas dibê, min lecî pir
tê... nayê hindik tê.
When the call to prayer happens, I am at home. When the
middle is finished, I get a lot of urgency... not a little
comes.
Ne waye, dewarî ye. Millet feqîr e.
It's not like that, it's rotating. The people are poor.
Herekî çi qasî pere dide te?
How much money does each person give you?
Wele î heye dusedî dide, î heye sêsedî dide, î heye sedî
dide, î heye pêncî dide, î li duha jî ez nobim.
Well, there is one who gives two hundred, one who gives
three hundred, one who gives one hundred, one who gives
fifty, and regarding the prayer [duha], I won't say.
Deha feqara jî tên cem min, evê rûsê dikim, ez jê nobim.
Ten poor people also come to me, I do this face [favor], I
don't take from them.
Herekî çavê xwe deşîne te ba te?
Anyone whose eye hurts comes to you?
Gi kê, qulî kê çûha der, hewa didê.
Whoever, whatever hole/pain goes out, it gives air.
Yanî ez nobim, ez qut nakim, ez nobim wî... bes ez noka
dibêm... ewê dikanê min...
Meaning I don't say, I don't cut [a price], I don't tell
him... but I say now... that shop of mine...
Ser min temam bûye, zêde dibe.
It has finished on me, it is becoming too much.
Gi pênc be, ekê çil mehrî jî rûsekim ne pidim.
If it's five, I will handle forty dowries and not give up.
Gi bûye dused... ez deha mehrî rûsadikim... De heştî jî ma
rû didim min re kaka. Bes ê min e. Ekê çi bikim?
If it becomes two hundred... I handle ten dowries... Give me
eighty face too, brother. It is enough for me. What shall I
do?
Serikî min e. Wî jî gi qiçikî, yanî feqara, jinik feqara, kî
bêjî ware cem min... ekê berîka xwe darînim û pidim.
I have one head [I am alone]. And him too, if small, meaning
poor, a poor woman, whoever you say comes to me... I will
take out my pocket [money] and give to them.
Ez na berda haceta... yanî pêra me. Ekê çi bikim pêra?
I am not after the needs... meaning money. What will I do
with money?
Ne qiçkî me zewicî me, ne zewicî me... ne qiçkî me vî şîr mo
ne... ekê çi bikim?
I don't have small children to marry off, I am not
married... I don't have small children on milk... What will
I do?
Çend zarokê te hene?
How many children do you have?
Heft. Xwedê star bike. Sê qîzik û heft jî law in.
Seven. May God protect them. Three girls and seven are boys.
Temaşevanên hêja, li vî gundî heye, însanek ji vî gundî
heye...
Dear viewers, in this village there is, there is a person
from this village...
Her ro derê, ne raş, derê navçeya Recû tîne. Du kîlometre
heye. Navbera gundê Hec Xelîl û Recû va.
Every day he goes, not straight, he goes to Rajo district
and comes back. It is two kilometers. Between the village of
Hec Xelîl and Rajo.
Ew çavê wî nabînin. Bê çavê, nabîne, bes derê nanê xwe tîne
û tê.
His eyes do not see. Without eyes, he doesn't see, but he
goes, brings his bread, and comes back.
Apê Ehmed, qurbana gundî be, û Recû va du kîlometre ne. Tu
çawa de, her ro derê û tê?
Uncle Ahmed, may I be a sacrifice for the village, and Rajo
is two kilometers away. How do you go, going and coming
every day?
Du kîlometre ne erê. Ez bi saet pênc û pênc nîv va radibim
derim, û şeş nîv orna ro li malim.
Yes, it is two kilometers. I get up at five or five-thirty
and go, and by six-thirty, at sunrise, I am at home.
Tu çawa rêyê nas dikî?
How do you know/recognize the road?
Rêk, subhanallah, dayîna Xwedê mekin e. Ez gi gihîştimê kû
ez zanim li wirim. A pêl ku didim, ez zanim a pêl wir didim.
The road, glory be to God, God's giving is solid. Wherever I
reach, I know I am there. Where I step, I know I am stepping
there.
Rêk... pî çavê min e, sîkê min e. Noka ez dibînim.
The road... the foot is my eye, it is my guide. Now [it is
as if] I see.
Û tu derê wir, nanê dibin, alîkar, nanê te didin te?
And you go there, they take the bread, help, do they give
you your bread?
Erê, min aqindûr e (?).
Yes, I have a subscription (?).
Te nanê qindûr e?
You have bread by subscription?
Rast e. Ê millet hîs dikin, gi min, hew mi tê vedaye, hew mi
tê vedaye, dan ber soqê, nanê xwe tînim û têm. Bes.
Correct. The people sense it, when I... this one makes way
for me, that one makes way for me, they put me at the front
of the line, I get my bread and come. That's it.
Nah, tu çawa xelkê nasdikî? Wextê tu însanekî ber te, dibîne
tu nasdikî?
Now, how do you recognize people? When a person is before
you, do you see/recognize them?
Heval, dayîna Xwedê ji gî baştir e. Teysîrê Xwedê ji gî
baştir e. Ê min... el Tebqa bim, dişuxulîm... sî sal, çil
sal ê bûye...
Friend, God's giving is better than all. God's facilitation
is better than all. Me... I was in Tabqa, I was working...
thirty years, forty years have passed...
Noka ba zan e tên, dibên "Merheba". Ez dibêjim "Ehlen
filan".
Now they come knowingly, they say "Hello". I say "Welcome
so-and-so".
Tu nasdikî?
You recognize them?
Ez nasdikim, sê sed roj lê...
I recognize them, [even if] three hundred days [have
passed]...
Tu dengê wi ro nasdikî?
You recognize them by their voice?
Erê.
Yes.
Wek çawa te niha dengê min naskir?
Like how you recognized my voice just now?
Hêşta ma min... gultanoyî (?) me, ez ser televîzyon dîye.
Just now I... [referring to hearing him before], I have seen
[heard] on television.
Lê.
Yes.
Me dîye... Ez dibêjim ew Hiskerî ye yanî me dîye.
I have seen... I say this is Hiskerî [Host's name/nickname],
meaning I have seen him.
Ê wa.
That's right.
Cemê wanoy.
[Unclear, possibly "Together with them"].
Elhemdulillah, dayîna Xwedê pir mezin e.
Praise be to God, God's giving is very great.
Rast e. Te çend sal e nabînî?
That's right. How many years have you not been seeing?
Çil... çil derbas kir.
Forty... passed forty.
Çil sal ne berî te didî?
Forty years? Didn't you see before?
Lê, berê didîm. El Tebqa dişuxulîm.
Yes, I used to see. I was working in Tabqa.
Te çi kar dikir li Tebqa?
What work did you do in Tabqa?
Min tenekî, betûnê ra dikir.
I used to do tinsmithing, concrete work.
Mala te li wir bû?
Was your home there?
Erê.
Yes.
Û çil sal jî tu nabînî. Emrê te çiqas e?
And for forty years you haven't seen. How old are you?
Emrê min şêst û heft.
My age is sixty-seven.
Şêst û heft.
Sixty-seven.
Erê.
Yes.
Ê çawa, nexweşî bi te ra çêbû, yan...
So how, did an illness happen to you, or...
Tiştek nebû. Hîn weke berê maşallah. Bes nezer çû.
Nothing happened. Still like before, Mashallah. Just the
sight went.
Bes nezer. Maşallah siheta te jî baş e.
Just the sight. Mashallah your health is also good.
Erê, de çûyî seyî nizam (?).
Yes, [unclear phrase].
Mala te dûrî ne?
Is your house far?
Mala me na, nîzîk e, gihîşt e nîzîk e.
Our house, no, it is near, we have reached near.
Çawa tu zanî noka tu gihîştî mala?
How do you know now that you have reached home?
Law, ez zanim. Bêhna Xwedê, hana hesas, mirov dibê ot
gihîştê.
Man, I know. God's scent, a kind of sense, one says "there,
arrived".
Tu gihîştê na? Keremke derbas be ka.
You arrived, right? Please, enter, let's see.
Temaşevanên hêja, naha em gihîştin mala Apê Ehmed. Naha emê
derî vekin, wek nabîne bes, kilîtê vedike.
Dear viewers, we have now reached Uncle Ahmed's house. Now
we will open the door, although he doesn't see, he unlocks
the key.
Temaşevanên hêja, naha em derbasî mala Apê Ehmed bûn. Çayî
jî me re çêkiren. Naha emê çayî jî vexwin.
Dear viewers, we have now entered Uncle Ahmed's house. They
have made tea for us too. Now we will drink tea as well.
Lê mîvanên Apê Ehmed jî hatine. Lê bi rastî, naha emê jî
bipirsin, mîvanê xwe nasdike nasnake.
But Uncle Ahmed's guests have also come. But honestly, now
we will ask him if he recognizes his guests or not.
Çawa ez naskirim? Naha emê bipirsin ji mîvanê xwe jî nasdike
yan nasnake.
Just as he recognized me? Now we will ask if he recognizes
his guests or not.
Apê Ehmed, ev mîvanê hatine rûniştine, tu naskî kî ne?
Uncle Ahmed, these guests who have come and sat down, do you
know who they are?
Lê ez naskim, mîvanê me ne ez naskim.
Yes I know them, they are our guests, I know them.
Kî ne?
Who are they?
Merheba Elî Şewket. Bavê Şewket rûniştîye... cîranî me ye.
Hello Ali Şewket. Şewket's father is sitting... he is our
neighbor.
Te çawa naskir?
How did you recognize him?
Hisê gêndiro... Me berê hisê gêndî kirî.
The sense of the smell/aura... We sensed the smell/aura
before.
Te dengê wî bîst he nas kir?
Did you hear his voice then recognize him?
Te naha digot kêlek te du jin hene. Kî ne?
Mm.
You were just saying there are two women beside you. Who are
they?
E... hisê xwe bike ezê naskim.
Uh... let them make their sound/presence known, I will
recognize.
Ka hisê xwe bike.
Go ahead, make your sound.
[Indistinct sound/greeting]
A... Wehîda ye. Wehîda... dayika Semîr Elî ye, hunermendekî
me yê Kurda ye, ji mêj da jî, û dayika Semîr e.
Ah... It is Wehîda. Wehîda... she is Semîr Elî's mother, a
Kurdish artist of ours, from long ago too, and she is
Semîr's mother.
Û ê din?
And the other one?
Ê din jî...
The other one too...
[Woman speaks] Were Ahmed [indistinct]
[Woman speaks] Come Ahmed [indistinct]
Elhemdulillah, ehlen we sehlen cîran. Ew jî cîran e, pîka
izzetî Bilêl e... bavkê... bi dişehîda ye, û cîranê me ne,
hovo nîzîkî me ne.
Praise be to God, welcome neighbor. She is also a neighbor,
the daughter-in-law of Izzet Bilêl... father of... with the
martyrs, and they are our neighbors, they are close to us
right here.
Tu di wusa, tu vî bi vî rengî tu xelkê nas dikî?
You are like this, in this way you recognize people?
Ez gî nasdikim. Bes his ware, me nasdikim.
I recognize everyone. Just let the sound come, I recognize.
Weke kefn û hecer.
Like [telling apart] linen and stone.
Apê Ehmed, naha pêşî tu ji Tebqa vegere hato gundê xwe. E te
li gund çi kar kir?
Uncle Ahmed, now, before when you returned from Tabqa to
your village. What work did you do in the village?
Ez hatim gund rûniştim... min fikirîm, min got ezê çikarî
bikim? Zêdetirî dikanê li min na meşe.
I came to the village and sat... I thought, I said what work
shall I do? Nothing suits me better than a shop.
Min çû tiştî nîxwanî hot kir... dikanê... min şeqlek refa
kir.
I went and got building materials... for the shop... I built
some shelves.
Paşê min dest bi semon kir.
Then I started with goods [groceries].
Paşê min çû... kareba li gundê me tune bû.
Then I went... there was no electricity in our village.
Min çû hebek motor kirî anî, min li der da qurmiş kir.
I went and bought a motor [generator] and brought it, I set
it up outside.
Û me dikan şuxuland, û motor bi kareba, û du berad da min
hewandine. Min pênc mihora, ke zû zanî, dikan wekî dixwazê
dişuxulî.
And we operated the shop, and the motor with electricity,
and I put two refrigerators inside. I [worked] five seals
[times?], as one knows quickly, the shop operated as
desired.
E Apê Ehmed naha te... tenê didî?
So Uncle Ahmed now you... did you sell alone?
Min tenê didî.
I sold alone.
Te çawa tişt nas dikir?
How did you recognize things?
Ez gî nast... min gî nas dikir. Ez dişuxulîm... xelkê ecêbê
xwe li min hiltîna.
I recognized all... I recognized everything. I worked...
people were amazed by me.
Naha yek hat o cem te dikanê got "Ka paketekê bide min". Te
paket çawa nas dikir?
Now if someone came to you at the shop and said "Give me a
packet [of cigarettes]". How did you recognize the packet?
Min dest diavêtê... Eyn li cî gind (?) da, derxist û danî
ber da û pere jî... gi pênc sed e, sed e, dehan e, min e...
zêdebûn jî pêda û ê biçû.
I reached for it... Exactly in the place... took it out and
put it before him, and the money too... if it's five
hundred, a hundred, a ten, whatever... I gave the change too
and he would go.
E te pere çun... çun nas dikirin pere?
So the money... how did you recognize the money?
Çiko pere li cem min e... qol cem min nîn e. Yanî çiqul cem
min nîn.
Because money is with me [I know it]... there is no
fake/mistake with me. Meaning no mistake with me.
Pereyê naha lê berê?
Money now or before?
Ê berê.
The old ones.
Te li kîjan salê dikan vekir?
In which year did you open the shop?
Salê... heftê û sisyan ez hatim vira.
The year... seventy-three I came here.
Kareba tine bû wî çaxî?
Was there no electricity at that time?
Tine bû ya. Ne... motor bû ya.
There wasn't. No... it was a motor [generator].
Kîjan salê kareba çêbû li vira, elektrîk çêbû?
What year did electricity come here, was electricity made?
Welle nizanim kîjan salê bû... nizam... de bîst, bîst pênc
sal hene elem çêbûye.
Well I don't know which year it was... I don't know... maybe
twenty, twenty-five years ago it happened.
Apê Ehmed dibêjin dengê te jî xweş e. Nizanim... ev gund
dibêje. Çend kes ji gundê we hebûn, ji min ra gotin.
Uncle Ahmed, they say your voice is also good. I don't
know... this village says so. Several people from your
village were there, they told me.
Dibêje dengê te jî xweş e, tu jî strana dibêje?
They say your voice is good too, do you also sing songs?
E wele heme qurmişî dibine, yanî na riş e.
Well, they all become wrinkled [old], meaning it's not
smooth.
Te kîjan stranê dibêje?
Which songs do you sing?
E wele da... hûn zanin, ezê... ya jî... heme çend şora
çûbîlî yekî bibêjim.
Well... you know, I will... or... I will just say a few
words suitable for one.
Lê ne... belkî pir bin.
But not... maybe they are many.
Te guhdarî kê dikir? Te guhdarî kê dikir?
Who did you listen to? Who did you listen to?
Min guhdarî Cemîl Horo kirî, min Elî Tico kirî, min ê Bavê
Selah kirî...
I listened to Cemîl Horo, I listened to Elî Tico, I listened
to Bavê Selah...
Kilom jî pir in.
The songs are many.
E naha tê strana kê janî bêje? Tê dengbêjî, ev çîrokê kevne
tê bêje?
So now whose song will you sing? Will you sing bard style,
these old stories?
E... heke... kelamek hewa, kelamê Cemîl Horo ye, Xwedê rehma
xwe lê ke, ev hunermendekî kêm bû...
Uh... if... a song like this, it's a song of Cemîl Horo, may
God have mercy on him, he was a rare artist...
Û pir jî nav millet da eîşa, daistan, bi dengê xweş rind.
And he lived much among the people, epics, with a beautiful
good voice.
Havro jî çend şor ji kelamê wî ne.
Today, a few words are from his songs.
De keremke.
Please, go ahead.
Hmm... Mamo dilî melyane... Mamo dilî melyane... dilî
melyane, dilî melyane...
Hmm... Uncle, the heart is wounded/sad... Uncle, the heart
is wounded... the heart is wounded, the heart is wounded...
Mamo dilî melyane, lyane, lyane, lyane, lyane... dilî
melyane, lyane, lyane...
Uncle, the heart is wounded, wounded, wounded, wounded,
wounded... the heart is wounded, wounded, wounded...
Erê dibêta ser dilî mi xwinê da pêda kirî, kulikê ji kulê
lak lakê çar û sêr yan e...
Yes, upon my heart blood has appeared, a grief from the
griefs of storks of four and three sides...
Ta mor û çolê xozkî mi da berdan e wî...
Until the snakes and the desert, I wish I had let go of
him...
Dibêta bindirî mi xistî arî da baran e... nav çavê mi ra
dibê gelek mij û duman e, wêl wêl wêl wêl...
It says my threshing floor has been struck by fire giving
rain... before my eyes there is much fog and smoke, woe woe
woe woe...
Lê lê, lê lê, lê lê, lê lê, lê lê, lê lê.
Oh woe woe woe woe woe...
Oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my.
De way lê, lê, lê, lê, lê, lê, hoho way lê, lê, lê.
Oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my.
Gulo lo bira no, lo...
Oh Rose, oh brothers, oh...
Bajarê Muxribê bajarêkî mezin î pîr û pan e.
The City of Mughrib is a grand, ancient, and vast city.
Dibê li ser rûyê behr û erbyan e(?).
They say it is on the face of the Arab(?) Sea.
Dibê li ser rûyê behr û erbyan e.
Dibê bajarê Muxribê çêkirine li ser pozê heft û çiyan e, wîl
wîl wîl wîl heft û çiyan e.
They say the City of Mughrib was built on the peaks of seven
mountains, oh my, oh my, seven mountains.
Erê dibê... bajarê Muxribê çêkirine li ser pozê heft û çiyan
e.
Yes, they say... the City of Mughrib was built on the peaks
of seven mountains.
Dibê li ser sê sed û şêst û şeş deryan e, wî...
They say it is on three hundred and sixty-six seas, oh...
Her deriyekê li ser sê sed û şêst û şeş wîlayetan e.
Each gate opens to three hundred and sixty-six provinces.
Her wîlayetekê li ser sê sed û şêst û şeş mudiriyetan e.
Each province has three hundred and sixty-six directorates.
Her mudiriyetekê li ser sê sed û şêst û şeş mehellan e.
Each directorate has three hundred and sixty-six
neighborhoods.
Her mehellake sê sed û şêst û şeş camî têda girtine, minare
li ser bucî(?) têda vedan e, wî, wî...
Each neighborhood holds three hundred and sixty-six mosques,
minarets raised upon towers within them, oh my, oh my...
Erê dibê kûbserê minarê da zincîrê zêrî gulî cewherî berdan
e.
Yes, they say from the dome of the minaret, they let down
golden chains with jeweled braids.
Wey saet xweş, wey saet xweş.
May your time be happy (bless your voice).
Bi rastî spasî, dengê te gelek xweş e.
Truly, thank you, your voice is very beautiful.
Ew jî xweş. La işte em nizanin, nizanin, ne kilamçî me lê
işte...
Yours as well. Well, we don't know, we don't know, I'm not a
singer, but well...
Em şikir hûrbûkêf in, em rehet in, batinê we, bi her tiştî
me, em bi kêf in, em têr û tijî ne.
Thankfully we are joyful, we are comfortable, with your
presence(?), with everything, we are happy, we are full and
satisfied.
Hema saya kê da?
But thanks to whom?
Saya wanê canê xwe didin şehîdê Kurdistanê da em xweşiya
wana da em bi kêf in.
Thanks to those who give their lives, the martyrs of
Kurdistan, thanks to their goodness, we are happy.
Saya YPG û YPJ û... saya wi şê da em bi kêf in.
Thanks to the YPG and YPJ and... thanks to that thing, we
are happy.
Em... parastin. Kerameta me, şerefa me, namûsa me, gi te
parastin. Wana hewna me diparêzin.
We... defense. Our dignity, our honor, our virtue, all is
defended. They are defending us.
Welat, milletê welat diparêzin. Em gelek spas dikin, û em
serkeftinê jê ra dixwazin.
They defend the country, the people of the country. We thank
them very much, and we wish them victory.
Û em dibên saeta we xweş, û saeta we xweş, û saeta we xweş.
And we say may your time be happy, and may your time be
happy, and may your time be happy.
Temaşevanên hêja, em darbazi malekê bûn, mala Apê Arif.
Dear viewers, we have moved to a house, the house of Uncle
Arif.
Apê Arif jî livir xurcê çêdike.
Uncle Arif is making a saddlebag here.
Ka em jê bipirsin. Na, merheba ji te ra.
Let us ask him. Now, hello to you.
Merheba was.
Hello to you.
Apê Arif ka ji me ra bêje tu çi dikî, tu çi çêdikî?
Uncle Arif, tell us, what are you doing, what are you
making?
Law işte xurcê ji kerê ra çêdikim.
Well, I am making a saddlebag for a donkey.
Tu çewa çêdikî?
How do you make it?
Berê kartonçî hebûn çêdikirin, ew jî neman, em bi xwe
çêdikin.
Before there were cardboard-makers (saddlers) who made them,
they are gone too, so we make them ourselves.
Yani berê çarşiyê da difirûtan?
Meaning, they used to sell them in the market before?
Lê berê da difirûtan e.
Yes, before they used to sell them.
Kerton, xurc...
Saddles, saddlebags...
Xurc, keten û derg e... kartonçiyo çêdikir. Nok na nema ne,
em bi xwe çêdikin.
Saddlebags, linen and twine... the cardboard-maker used to
make them. Now they are gone, we make them ourselves.
E çi ma nemane? Heta niha hewceyi heye yani dewar heye?
Why are they gone? There is still a need now, meaning there
are still beasts of burden?
E kes nema ye, la reca berê hebû, tina li nok na.
Oh, no one is left, there was the generation of the past,
there isn't one now.
No, Apê Arif, no ev... ev nerm e, ev hişk e. Te çi kiriye ev
çi ye?
Now, Uncle Arif, this... this is soft, this is hard. What
have you done, what is this?
Ewa kilav me kiriye, me pûş kiriye.
We put a felt lining, we put straw.
Ev xurcê berê hemî hana bûn yan te...
Were all the saddlebags like this in the past or did you...
Ço?
What?
Yani xurc hemî gi hanane gi bi vî rengî çêdibin?
Meaning, are all saddlebags like this, are they all made
this way?
Lê gi hanakin. Xurc ev e. Ewa kertone kerê ye.
Yes, they are all like this. This is a saddlebag. That is a
donkey saddle.
Ew jî xurcê ser e.
And that is the saddlebag on top.
Ev jî ji bo tiştê xwe dikî nê?
And you do this for your own things, right?
Lê ji bo tiştê, ji bo wan tiştî xwe.
Yes, for things, for those things of mine.
Berê xelkê ji te ra dianî te çêdikir yan...
Before, did people bring them to you to make or...
Na weleh. Min çênedikir. Heger yekî bigota min xurcê bîne
min çêke, min çêçûle...
No, by God. I didn't make them. If someone told me to bring
a saddlebag to make, I would get annoyed...
Tifrim, min ranedikir xurcê tînim, min lêdinin û min têt.
I'd spit, I wouldn't accept bringing a saddlebag, I'd throw
it down and leave.
Te ev kirêt ji kê girt? Berê pişê te kesî joro çêkiribû?
From whom did you learn this craft? Did anyone do it before
you?
Min berê joro çênekiriye, bes mi li nêrî, mi pê elimîm.
I haven't done it before, I just watched and I learned.
Te li kê nêrî?
Whom did you watch?
Min li kertonçiyo nêrî.
I watched the saddle-maker.
Yani te li kertonçî... tu di be kes nema, yani zû da te li
nêriye?
So you watched the saddle-maker... you say no one is left,
so you watched him a long time ago?
Li mêj e, aqilê min de şuxla çêdikim. Kedanê dê û dîsa mi
çêdikin.
It's been a long time, I do the work from my memory. The
needs come up and I make them again.
Tu bêtir vî tiştî çi çêdikî?
What else do you make besides this?
He?
Huh?
Bêtirî xurcê û kertên va?
Besides these saddlebags and saddles?
Berê me ticoreta pêz dikir. Dewar me dikirî difirût. Me ga
dikirîn, me dewar... pez dikirî me ga dikirî.
Before, we traded in sheep. We bought and sold livestock. We
bought oxen, we... bought sheep, bought oxen.
Tu bi xwe jûtyar î?
Are you a farmer yourself?
Ez bi xwe jûtyar im bavo. Me bi dêmîr dajot, ne bi
dîrektorê.
I am a farmer myself, dear. We plowed with the iron (plow),
not with the tractor.
Temaşevanên hêja, livir jî ziyaretek heye, di navbera du
gundan da ye.
Dear viewers, here there is a shrine, it is between two
villages.
Gundê Kûra, gundê Heçqelîl livir.
The village of Kura and the village of Heçqelîl are here.
Livir jî ziyaretek pîroz e, ziyareta navê xwe Mehemed Elî
ye.
Here is a holy shrine, the shrine's name is Muhammad Ali.
Millet jî her hefteyêkê tê vira, ji her gundekî tê vira.
The people come here every week, they come here from every
village.
Roja çarşem û înê.
On Wednesdays and Fridays.
Livir jî millet tê livir, dewarên şerjê dike.
People come here and slaughter livestock (sacrifice).
Daxwazê wan çi ne, li ber Xwedê digerîn.
Whatever their wishes are, they ask God for them.
Lê kerem bikin, em dîroka vê ziyaretê nas bikin.
Please come, let us learn the history of this shrine.
Merheba ji te ra.
Hello to you.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Tu ji kîjan gundî yî?
Which village are you from?
Weleh ji Heçqelîl im ez.
By God, I am from Heçqelîl.
Yani her înê tê vira?
Meaning, do you come here every Friday?
Weleh çarşemê û înê. Hêj ta salê du car sê cara em têne
vira.
By God, Wednesdays and Fridays. Sometimes we come here two
or three times a year.
Hûn tên livir çi dikin?
What do you do when you come here?
Em tên işte em nexweş dibin, qîçik tên nobin, qîçiko pê nof
dikin. Ziyaret pir meqedes e.
We come, well, if we get sick, children come... we name
children after him. The shrine is very holy.
Zewr kê (Keramet) kî nîşan dabûn? E te nîşan dabû yani?
Were miracles shown? Did he show you any?
E min... dibûn. Bes hev (kurê min)... kurê min ma pê nof
kir.
For me... there were. My son... I named my son after him.
Û hev jî layî tî min e, ma pê nof kir, heft sala ma porê
ginde berda.
And he is my dear son, I named him, and for seven years I
let his hair grow.
Û qut kir, û tayî pera kir, hata similî...
Then I cut it, weighed it against money, up to...
Navê vî zatî çi ye?
What is the name of this person?
Weleh navê hew Mehemed Elî ye.
By God, his name is Muhammad Ali.
E navê vî Mehemed Elî ye.
Ah, his name is Muhammad Ali.
Û hev Mehemed Elî pir rind e. Û pir kîbar e.
And this Muhammad Ali is very good. And very noble.
Hew bir, sê birak in e. Hewa Mehemed Elî livir ketî. Û Şêx
Mûs livir e. Û Bilîlê Hebeş serî çiya ye.
He is a brother, they are three brothers. Muhammad Ali fell
here. And Sheikh Mus is here. And Bilal al-Habashi is on top
of the mountain.
Û xoka wî heye, Gilyaqîb. Gilyaqîb jî derê hana ye. Vêra
dibên Kêlşîr.
And he has a land/place, Gilyaqib. Gilyaqib is over there.
They call it Kelshir (Sword-Rock).
Jine (bi) şîrê xwe tîne da diçîm ber, bi şîr dibûn.
He brought his sword and went towards the rock, it split by
the sword.
Hew Kêlşîro jî, ya Gilyaqîb mirt.
That Kelshir, or Gilyaqib, died.
Ku dere dikeve va?
Where is that located?
Ew hamo li pozê zeytûna derê hana. Bin gundî û rî ye. Nêzîk
e.
It's all at the olive peak over there. Below the village and
the road. It's near.
Hewa tirba wa bû. Û qîçkî xwe bû. Û qîçik... dimêt. Li tirbê
da dêkî cîcîkî Gilyaqîbê dimêt. Vêra dibên Kêlşîr. Ekîd
enizim Gilyaqîb e, bes navê xwe Kêlşîr bû.
That was their grave. And his child was there. And the
child... was suckling. In the grave, the mother suckled
Gilyaqib's breast(?). They call it Kelshir. I don't know for
sure if it is Gilyaqib, but its name was Kelshir.
Ê ekîd xoka Mehemed Elî ye.
But for sure, this is the ground of Muhammad Ali.
İşte însan tê ce, bar, ma'nê qîçkê xwe nabin, ma'nê
nexweşiyê, ê kwîd bûyî, ê qiloqê xwe giran bûyîn, ê ma'nê
miroz o tên bar.
Well, people come here, for the sake of children they don't
have, for sickness, the paralyzed, those with heavy burdens,
those with wishes come here.
İşte pir rind e yani. Ziyaret... û kes newêre qişkî ginde ji
vir bibe mal. Newêrin bibin mal.
So, he is very good. The shrine... and no one dares to take
even a twig from here home. They don't dare take it home.
Lê tê awe. Yek sond xwe bi ziyareta Mehemed Elî, û îşî xwe
vir be, ya yêkê dîn bibe, ya yêkê kwîr bibe, ya yêkê seqet
bibe wa re sêre.
It happens. If someone swears by the shrine of Muhammad Ali,
and their business is crooked (dishonest), either they go
mad, or they go blind, or they become crippled, that's how
it is.
Yani kes li ceva gund wa bûye?
Meaning, has this happened to anyone in the village?
Erê wa bûne. Wa bûne bes berê vê pirî.
Yes, it has happened. It happened, but mostly in the past.
Û heta yani, pêncî sal ne elvî gundî me ez zanim.
And even those who are fifty years old in this village don't
know (as much), I know.
Û emrê min heftê û çar pênc sal in e. Dîsa mi navê ginde
bîstî.
And my age is seventy-four or five. I have heard their
names.
Û milletî me hew vira... sûrê girtin bar.
And our people here... received benefits from him.
Û şilyo jî îşela dimeşe.
And the rain also, God willing, comes.
Û sewqê gundî me gi...
And the livelihood of our village is all...
Temaşevanên hêja, li vê goristanê...
Dear viewers, in this cemetery...
Ev gora Şehîd Mehemed Elî ye.
This is the grave of Martyr Mehemed Ali.
Me lez xist heta verekê têna, em dê nerin, me lez ji vira
ye.
We hurried until this point, we won't stay, we are in a
hurry from here.
Tên li vir mes'h dikin, maç dikin...
They come here and wipe [for blessing], kiss it...
Û daxwaziya wan çiye?
And what is their request?
Qeneetê pê dikin, li ber Xwedê şidegerin.
They have faith in it, they seek it from God.
Daxwaziya te çiye tu hatiye vira?
What is your request for coming here?
Daxwaza me, tişta me qeneet... Serek Rebîûl Alem e.
Our request, the object of our faith... Is primarily the
Lord of the Worlds.
De tişta me qeneetê xwe pê kirî.
So the thing we have put our faith in.
De ji mêj da, ev asar a ji mêj da ye.
So from long ago, this relic is from long ago.
Ji Rebîûl Alem e de mûy.
It is from the Lord of the Worlds...
Erê kes nexweş e têtî...
Yes, if someone is sick, they come...
De hîşta bi me'na qick, miçko, hîşta qick tên dewa dikin.
So still, meaning small ones, tiny ones, still small ones
come and seek remedy.
Yani Xwedê bi rê ve dibe... Sileh, serê Rebîûl Alem e.
Meaning God guides [them]... Peace, by the head of the Lord
of the Worlds.
Pêxwas jî hişta...
Barefoot ones also still...
Ya zarok nabin?
Or those who don't have children?
Çimo, bi... hewah, berê kêm a zim bê...
Why, with... desire, before...
De hemû tişt hematin, tişto ji kîskê bîkê de hatin.
So all things came, things came from the bride's pocket.
Temaşevanên hêja, li vir jî em gihîştin dawiya bernameya
xwe.
Dear viewers, here too we have reached the end of our
program.
Li gundê Xaşxalîl me ro derbas kir.
We spent the day in the village of Khashkhalil.
Heta bernameyek din, hefteyek din...
Until another program, another week...
Hûn bimînin di xêr û xweşiyê da.
Stay in goodness and happiness.