Belê temaşevanên hêja, ji bernameya Ax û Welat îro em
berê... em derbasî gundekî bûn, gundek nîzî sînûr e.
Yes dear viewers, from the program Ax û Welat today we
headed... we passed into a village, a village near the
border.
Dema mera dibê sînûr, em hema bi sed salî şûnda va
vedigerine.
When one says border to us, we immediately go back a hundred
years.
Dema Sykes-Picot, ev gund neha li binxetê ye.
At the time of Sykes-Picot, this village is now below the
line [in Syria].
Ev gundê li serxetê û binxetê va, hemî merivê hev bûn. Diçûn
gel hevdu, dihatin.
This village at the above-line [Turkey] and below-line
[Syria], were all relatives of each other. They used to go
to each other, and come.
Lê ev gund jî neha ji hev cuda bûne, dema ev sînûra çêbûye.
But this village also separated from each other, when this
border was made.
Vê heftê jî emê derbasî gundê Şengêlê bibin, emê bi hev ra
gundê Şengêlê nas bikin.
This week we will pass into the village of Şengêlê, we will
get to know the village of Şengêlê together.
Mamoste Adil merheba te şêr e.
Teacher Adil, hello to you.
Merheba, ser serê me, ser çavê me, hûn bi xêr hatin.
Hello, upon our head, upon our eyes, you are welcome.
Sax bî.
Be healthy [Thanks].
Îro em derbasî gundê Şengêlê bûn, bi xwest em dîroka Şengêlê
jî nas bikin.
Today we passed into the village of Şengêlê, we wanted to
get to know the history of Şengêlê too.
Ê... navê Şengêlê ji ku hatiye?
Eh... where did the name Şengêlê come from?
Di serî da em bi xêr hatina we dikin, û bi xêr hatina
bernameya Ax û Welat, hebi evî me yê bi selam bî.
In the beginning we welcome you, and welcome the program Ax
û Welat, may our love be with greetings.
Ku rojekê kanalekî Kurdî were nav me, ji me ra şîrove bike
her gundek ji ku hatiye, eslê wî ji ku hatiye, dîroka wî çi
ye.
That one day a Kurdish channel comes among us, explains to
us where each village came from, where its origin came from,
what its history is.
Ê îro hûn jî hatin gundê me, wek Şengêlê, em jî kanin hinekî
li ser Şengêlê şîrove bikin.
Eh today you also came to our village, as Şengêlê, we can
also explain a little about Şengêlê.
Navê Şengêlê, mamoste... navê Şengêlê navekî pir kevne, wek
kalam ji me ra gotî, hin dibên ji darê hatiye.
The name of Şingêlê, teacher... the name of Şingêlê is a
very old name, as the elders told us, some say it came from
a tree.
Dara Şingêlê, darek mezin e, ew jî li binê gund e, li binê
banê ye.
The Şingêlê tree, it is a big tree, it is also at the bottom
of the village, at the bottom of the plateau.
Û hin jî dibên ji ewî hatiye, ji Şengalê hatiye.
And some say it came from that, it came from Şengal
[Sinjar].
Ortemanî navê vê da, em jî wene man e, em nizanin tam dîroka
vê çûye.
In the middle of this name, we are also left like that, we
don't know exactly how its history went.
Wek ji me ra gotine, hin dibên ji darê hatiye, hin jî dibên
ji Şengalê hatiye.
As they told us, some say it came from the tree, some say it
came from Şengal.
Tucarî navê gundê we nehatiye guhertin?
Has the name of your village ever been changed?
Tucarî navê gundê me nehatiye guhertin. Osmanlî jî derbas
bûn, vêderê bî zaten, navaxê Kurdistanê, neha biguherta.
The name of our village has never been changed. The Ottomans
also passed through, it was here anyway, inside Kurdistan,
they would have changed it by now.
Ereb jî hat vêderê, rejîm e, zaten wan jî neguhertin, navê
gund ji halê xwe ma.
Arabs also came here, the regime, anyway they didn't change
it either, the village name stayed as it was.
Ê nav gundê we nîzî sînûr e, te dît berî ev sînûr daketî,
dema Sykes-Picot...
Eh the name of your village is near the border, you saw
before this border fell, the time of Sykes-Picot...
Ev gund hemî merivê hev bûn, gundê serxet û binxetê va.
This village were all relatives of each other, the village
of the above-line and the below-line.
Ê ev gund jî dên, merivê wan hene?
Eh does this village also have... do they have relatives?
Rast e, se'î naha em dibên gundê serxetê binxetê, tucarî jî
em xet ji xura nahesibînin.
True, right now we say village of above-line and below-line,
[but] we never consider the line for ourselves.
Hema wir û vir em wek malekê ne. Wek malbatekê ne. Naha
meîrê me gundek li wir heye, piş sînûr, em dibên Dêl Osman.
Just there and here we are like one home. Like one family.
Now in front of us there is a village there, behind the
border, we call it Dêl Osman.
Ew jî merivê me ne, zaten diya me jî ji wir e, û Hesar hew
jî li vêderê, hew jî meîryê me ne.
They are also our relatives, anyway our mother is also from
there, and Hesar is also here, they are also in front of us.
Heta naçûndin û hatinî me jî heye. Ekar em tiştekî bibêjim,
sala hezar nehsed sî û heştan, dema Fransa têl verxistî...
Even now we have going and coming. If I say one thing, the
year 1938, when France laid down the wire...
Mirîd li vêderê hebûn, Hareketa Mirîdîn digotin.
There were Murids here, they called it the Murid Movement.
Wê demê em çûn cem merivê xwe. Me hoke bîst roj eman, piştre
em dîsa vegerîn ser axa xwe.
At that time we went to our relatives. We stayed about
twenty days, then we returned again to our land.
Zaten naha jî tucaran li ser axa xwe neçûne.
Anyway, even now they have never left their land.
Ê wê demê têl frens li vir bûn?
Eh at that time was the French wire here?
Tabî wê demê da Fransa hat, Hareketa Mirîdîn li vir bû.
Hareketa Mirîdîn jî mantiqê meydanê bî.
Of course at that time France came, the Murid Movement was
here. The Murid Movement was in the Meydan area.
Bilbil kû bî, vê gundana bî. Hat vê derê, tesîra xwe li ser
me jî çêkir.
Wherever Bilbil was, it was these villages. It came here, it
made its impact on us too.
Ê dema naha ev sînûra çêbûye, gund... gundê we li vir bû,
licihan de bû?
Eh when now this border was made, the village... was your
village here, where was it?
Dema sînûr çêbûyî, em li vir bûn.
When the border was made, we were here.
Ama gundekî din mezin hebû digotin Xoca. Ew jî li ser sînûr
bû. Zaten sînûr di nava berê gund ra hat.
But there was another big village called Xoca. It was also
on the border. Anyway the border came through the front of
the village.
Qismek li hîda çûn û qismek jî vê derê ketin. Gundekî pirî
mezin bû.
A part went to that side and a part fell to this side. It
was a very big village.
Mamoste Adil, te dît gelek gundê me li serxet û binxetê va,
te dît mîna geşta rebêjim, wek gundê cîranê we, wek Elî
Karo, wek gundê Ze're, em çûn wira...
Teacher Adil, you saw many of our villages on the above-line
and below-line, you saw like Gesta I say, like your neighbor
villages, like Elî Karo, like the village of Ze're, we went
there...
Tirba ê we gundiya hemî yek bûn.
The graves of you villagers were all one.
Dema ev têla daketî, wa gundê yê li dî din çarçîyo heye.
When this wire fell, the village on the other side has a
frame.
Ew tirbê wan jî li Elî Karo mane. Te dît hemî sê çar gund
tirbê wan yek bûn.
Those graves of theirs remained in Elî Karo. You saw all
three or four villages their graves were one.
Ê naha ji hev qut bûnê, ew jî... yanî fir gund li serxetê
mane, tirbê wan li vê alî mane.
Eh now they are cut from each other, they too... meaning
many villages remained above-line, their graves remained on
this side.
Ê li vê milî ketin, tirbê wan li wî alî mane. Cem we tiştek
wusa çêbûye?
Eh they fell on this side, their graves remained on that
side. Did something like that happen with you?
Raste eynî cem me jî çêbûye. Naha Hesar heye, Hesar ew jî li
bakur e, ber sînûr.
True, the same happened with us too. Now there is Hesar,
Hesar is also in the north, by the border.
Ew jî li binê xetê dikeve. Ew jî... naha ardê me li wir
mane, tirbê me jî li wê derê mane, di binxetê mane.
It also falls below the line [on the border line]. It
also... now our lands remained there, our graves also
remained there, they remained in the below-line.
Û milkê me jî li wir maye. Ê wan jî qismek li vê derê mane.
Piştî sînûr lêket.
And our property also remained there. And a part of theirs
remained here. After the border struck.
Hûn narin ser tirbên xwe? Tu caran naçin ser tirbên xwe?
You don't go to your graves? You never go to your graves?
Na, em narin... naha tin. Na ew tên deryê, ne em deryê tên.
We namîne naha.
No, we don't go... now [?]. Neither they come over, nor we
go over. It doesn't remain like that now.
Ê naha wek gundê we... debara xwe bi çi dikin?
Eh now like your village... with what do you make your
livelihood?
Gundekî nîzî sînûr e... Yanî ardê we bi aliyê din ketine?
It is a village near the border... Meaning did your lands
fall to the other side?
Tabî ardê me li wir jî ketine. Ê wan jî li vê derê ketine.
Eynî ew jî wane, çûn tirba li vir hene, li wir hene. Gund
mana parçe bûye.
Of course our lands fell there too. And theirs fell here.
It's the same for them, graves are here, are there. Our
village has been fragmented.
Milkê me jî li wir heye, ardê me li wir mane. Heta naha li
vê derê mane.
Our property is also there, our lands remained there. Until
now they remained here.
Ê wan jî li vê derê mane, hinekî wan namaye. Debara vî gundî
jî...
And theirs remained here, some of them didn't remain. The
livelihood of this village too...
Debar ji berê da, berê li ser pez hebû. Piranî ser pez bî.
Piştre rez derketin.
Livelihood from the past, in the past it was on sheep.
Mostly it was on sheep. Then vineyards came out.
Debara xwe li ser rezan bûn. Her tişt li rezan çêdibû, debar
ser wi bî. Piştre zeytûn derketin.
Their livelihood was on vineyards. Everything was produced
in vineyards, livelihood was on that. Then olives came out.
Û naha jî keres û zeytûn û be'îv û her tişt heye li vê derê.
And now cherries and olives and almonds and everything
exists here.
Mamoste Adil, kanî li ba we hene?
Teacher Adil, do you have springs?
Kanî cem me tunene. Faqat çi heye, bîr hene. Digotin Bîra
Jûr û Bîra Jêr.
We don't have springs. Only what is there, there are wells.
They called them the Upper Well and the Lower Well.
Yanî millet diçûyî, him wekî bîra, him wekî bîra av li wir
nemaba, diçûn bîrê din li wir nemaba, dihatin vê derê.
Meaning the people used to go, both like the well... both
like the well if water didn't remain there, they went to the
other well if it didn't remain there, they came here.
Debara xwe bi wê bî. Kanî tunene, li vê gundî av jî pir kêm
e yanî.
Their livelihood was with that. There are no springs, in
this village water is also very scarce actually.
Avê wa kêm e?
Your water is scarce?
Kêm e, av tuneyo. Tuneyo.
Scarce, there is no water. It doesn't exist.
Ê naha gundê we çend xane ne?
Eh now how many households is your village?
Gundê me xane naha dorî sed û deh û pênc mal in. Hema
destpêkê bi xwe sê çar mal bûn yanî.
Our village households now are around one hundred and
fifteen homes. But in the beginning itself it was three or
four homes actually.
Kîjan mal bûn?
Which homes were they?
Gund bi xwe çar malbat in. Malbata yekemîn Malbata Malyê
Atêş bî. Piştre jî Malyê Mehmujiq bî.
The village itself is four families. The first family was
the Family of Atêş House. Then it was the House of Mehmujiq.
Û Malyê Piçê jî hebin li vê derê. Û Ehmedê Geyîkê digotin.
And the House of Piçê were also here. And they called him
Ehmedê Geyîkê.
Hev jî gî, teben wek malekê bî yanî. Tucaran te ew neketî
pirsgirêk, di navbera wan da çênebû yanî.
All of these, naturally were like one home actually. Never
did... problems did not happen, it didn't happen between
them actually.
Mala we ava be. Spas.
May your house be prosperous. Thanks.
Ê weşî ava be, spas ji we ra jî. Bi sehet û wekî ya xweş,
serkeftin be.
Eh yours be prosperous too, thanks to you too. With health
and a good one, may there be success.
Gundê Şingêlê girêdayî navçeya Raco ya Kantona Efrînê, 20
kîlometre li bakurê rojavayê bajarê Raco, û 55 kîlometre li
bakurê bajarê Efrînê dikeve.
The village of Şingêlê is attached to the Raco district of
Afrin Canton, it falls 20 kilometers to the northwest of the
town of Raco, and 55 kilometers to the north of the city of
Afrin.
Gundê Şingêlê li ser sînûrê bakurê Kurdistanê tenê nîzî 500
metroyî ji sînûr va dûr e.
The village of Şingêlê is on the border of Northern
Kurdistan, it is only near 500 meters far from the border.
Ji ber vê yekê gund her tim rastî êrîş û kiryarên hovana yê
dewleta Tirk tê, dema ku diçin nav zeviyên xwe.
Because of this the village always faces attacks and savage
acts of the Turkish state, when they go into their fields.
Berê gund girêdayî navçeya Bilbilê bû, lê piştî ragihandina
Rêveberiya Xweser li Kantona Efrînê...
Previously the village was attached to the Bilbil district,
but after the declaration of the Autonomous Administration
in Afrin Canton...
Di destpêka 2014an da, gund bi navçeya Raco va hate girêdan.
In the beginning of 2014, the village was attached to the
Raco district.
Navê gundê Şingêlê ji navê Dara Şengalê ango Dara Benaştûkê
hatiye. Ji ber ku darek bi vê cureyê li gund heye.
The name of the village Şingêlê came from the name of the
Şengal Tree, meaning the Benaştûk Tree. Because a tree of
this type exists in the village.
Û tê gotin ku ev cure gelekî kêm e, û her wiha li herêma
Şengalê li başûrê Kurdistanê ev cureyê daran têne dîtin.
And it is said that this type is very rare, and also in the
Şengal region in Southern Kurdistan this type of trees is
found.
Gund li ser deverekê bi navê Bena Xopê ava bûye. Li başûr
Bena Rezî û gundê Bîkê. Li rojhilat Çiyayê Behîvê û gundê
Kûsa û Penereka.
The village is built on an area with the name Bena Xopê. To
the south is Bena Rezî and the village of Bîkê. To the east
is Mount Behîvê and the village of Kûsa and Penereka.
Li bakur reza Çiyayê Puskûlê, Geliyê Hecî, gundê Hesarê û
Dêl Osman li serxetê, û li rojavat gundê Çerçiya û Çiyayê
Reş e berxê, ku li serxetê dikeve.
To the north the vineyards of Mount Puskûlê, Valley of Hecî,
the village of Hesarê and Dêl Osman on the above-line, and
to the west the village of Çerçiya and Mount Reş e Berxê,
which falls on the above-line.
Du bîrên avê li nîzî sînûr hene, Bîra Jûr û Ya Jêr. Û ta
naha ava wan heye, lê mixabin ava gund bigiştî kêm e.
There are two water wells near the border, the Upper Well
and the Lower One. And until now they have water, but
unfortunately the village water in general is scarce.
Lewma gundî di peydakirina ava xwe da xwedî spêrin komkirina
ava baranê û di sehrîcan de.
Therefore the villagers in finding their water rely on
collecting rain water and in cisterns.
Belê, na em nîzî sînûr ne. Em ji gund derketin. Hema 500
metir mabeyna me û sînûr da ma.
Yes, now we are near the border. We left the village. Just
500 meters remained between us and the border.
Milletê gund jî derbas... bi mera derbas vir bûn, em spasîya
wan dikin.
The village people also passed... passed here with us, we
thank them.
Eh... hinikî xwestin ew jî bîranînê xwe... Dema çi berê di
bîranînê de vê gundana da çêdibûn, ew çi demê di berê da...
çawa sînûr daket...
Eh... they wanted a little bit their memories too... When
what used to happen in the past in the memories in these
villages, what time in the past... how the border fell...
Ena hinekî ji me ra behs bike.
Let him talk a little bit to us now.
Merheba ji were.
Hello to you.
Ehle merheba.
Hello welcome.
Apê Êco.
Uncle Êco.
Belê.
Yes.
Dema ev sînûra daketî... çawa bû? Te dît?
When this border fell... how was it? Did you see it?
Berî ku sînor were danîn, sînorê van têlên mînkiriî,
muqedesata we, hemî rojhilatê Kurdistanê... gund cîran bûn,
pirr guncî he bûn, sînor qet derbaz bûn, gund xera bûn?
Before the border was established, the border of these mined
wires, your sanctities, all of Eastern Kurdistan... were the
villages neighbors, were there many relations, was the
border crossed at all, were the villages destroyed?
Xera bûn.
They were destroyed.
Na wek gundê Şengêlê û ev gundê Serxetê va jî... sînor ket
navberê... we jî ji hevdû qut bûn, ji hevdû cida bûn.
Like the village of Şengêl and this village of Serxet... the
border came in between... you were cut off from each other,
separated from each other.
Cida bûn.
We were separated.
Tê bîra te dema sînor da kirin?
Do you remember when the border was established?
Dema sînor danîn, erê... axa, em man li ser eraziyê xwe, em
jî li vir bûn. Bavê me jî li vir li ser milkê xwe bûn.
When the border was established, yes... the land, we stayed
on our land, we were here too. My father and us were here on
our property.
Û sînor da ket, ya saxkirin.
And the border fell, it was established.
Ewan li wê bûn, em li vir bûn.
They were there, we were here.
Tê bîra te dema sînor çêbû ye? Ev têl danane?
Do you remember when the border was made? When these wires
were laid?
Yox ê têl dananê ne têbîra min e. Ez biçûk bûm.
No, the laying of the wires is not in my memory. I was
small.
Wê demê tu çend salî bûyî? Nêzî sînor, dema çawa çêdikirin,
çawa radikirin...
How old were you at that time? Near the border, when they
were making it, how they were erecting it...
O pîra... tebîra... ez biçûk bûm, heft salî, heşt salî, ez
heşt bûm ev ê hat.
Oh old man... memory... I was small, seven years old, eight
years old, I was eight when this came.
Ê dema bavê te, kalê te... kesên mezin bi emr... çi digotin?
Dema sînor da ket, çawa ew ji hev qut bûn?
So when your father, your grandfather... the elders... what
did they say? When the border fell, how were they cut off
from each other?
Wan digot çi hedîd hat danan, têl veniştin, yasax kirin. Rê
daxistin. Nedihiştin.
They said iron was placed, wires were planted, it was
forbidden. They closed the road. They didn't let us.
Em jî kurd bûn, em jî kurd, bavê me, em gi yek in. Em û
Kurmanc jî gi yek in.
We were Kurds too, we are Kurds, our father, we are all one.
We and the Kurmanj [Kurds across the border] are all one.
Erê haşîna hemî yek in, yanî hûn berê... berî sînor da keve?
Yes, basically everyone is one, meaning you were before...
before the border fell?
Em hemî mirovê hev in.
We are all relatives of each other.
Meriyê hev in?
Relatives of each other?
Le.
Yes.
Yanî hinde diçûn, gelek hevdu dihatin... di şahîya da... di
şînîya da... hinde dihatin, hinde diçûn.
Meaning some went, many came to each other... in weddings...
in funerals... some came, some went.
Rast e. Diçûn.
That's right. They went.
Têk diçûn dihatin. Sînor manî... çwanî... şûn da kûk yasax
kirin. Silah, bombe tianîn.
They went and came. The border remained... how was it...
later they forbade it completely. They brought weapons,
bombs.
Paşê bombe pêncûheşta, pêncûneha da xistibûne sînorê, vê
dewrê me paşê kişandin jûr da birin.
Then in '58, '59 they put bombs on the border, in this era
of ours later they pulled it [the border line] further up.
Na ev gundê yali dîn dikevin, navê gunda çine?
Now these villages that fall on the other side, what are the
names of the villages?
Dêlûs mînaye, Hesaraye, Çerçaye, Xozixlê aye... heta Texta
Koprê ta ro... giştî, em gi meriyê hev in.
Dêlûs remains, Hesar is there, Çerça is there, Xozixlê is
there... up to Texta Koprê... all of them, we are all
relatives of each other.
Gundê dîn ji ber xera bûn dema sînor da ket?
The other villages were destroyed because the border fell?
Xera bûn.
They were destroyed.
Tetî gelek gund xera bûn.
So many villages were destroyed.
Gundik xera bûn bes lê hêlê me.
Some villages were destroyed but they left us.
Lê hêlê?
They left?
Hê.
Yes.
Çûn ew milet bi kûde?
Where did that nation [people] go?
Wê derê dibên Qûca.
That place they call Qûca.
Ew miletê ku diçûn?
Those people who left?
Her yek derekê de çûn.
Everyone went to a place.
Yanî hinek vî alî da hatin?
Meaning some came to this side?
Hinek vî alî da jî hatin. Gundê me jî çûn, erê.
Some came to this side too. Our village went too, yes.
Pismamê me, xalê me, apê me, ew gi li wê rûniştin. Berê.
Our cousins, our maternal uncles, our paternal uncles, they
all settled there. Before.
Berê win wilo bûn?
Before you were like that?
Le, berê eslê xwe li wî gundî bûn paşê hatin Şingêlê.
Yes, before their origin was in that village, then they came
to Şingêl.
Vê demê da gund berê hebû yanî?
At that time the village existed before, meaning?
Li vir hebû.
It existed here.
Gund cihê bû?
Was the village separate?
Hatin vir. Manê eraziyê xwe çibûn wir, deştê, vêra dibên
Texta Koprê... meydanek vezî... gel ser navê Kolkî miqeykî
hata noker... çûn, vê xarin ser kirin.
They came here. Meaning their lands remained there, in the
plain, they call it Texta Koprê... a square... [unclear land
names]... they went, they ate it [took it] over.
Ê do tapoyê wa hene li milkê we berê li wî alî ketî?
So do you have deeds for your property that fell on that
side before?
Do tapoyê Osmanî hene.
There are Ottoman deeds.
Hene?
They exist?
Hene.
They exist.
Ne meşîn? Milkê we li wî alî yê din ketî ye?
Why don't you go? Your property has fallen on the other
side?
Heyle. O pîr me li vê hêle Şingêlê Hesaraye... O pîr me
rûnişt.
It's forbidden. Oh man, we sat on this side, Şingêl,
Hesar... Oh man, we settled.
Wê... poyî kirin...
That... they mined it...
Wê... bavê me hebir, apê me hewbir.
That... our father gave up, our uncle gave up.
Yanî ew e wa, bes pirr kes hene ji yanî... milkê wan dest
dewletê ketin, dewlet dest xwaro kirin.
Meaning that is that, but many people exist who... their
property fell into the hands of the state, the state
confiscated it.
E dewletê birin lê. Dewletê birin. Cehê me her kes meriyê
xwe bûn, teslîmî wa kirin.
The state took it, yes. The state took it. Our place,
everyone was their own relative, they surrendered to them.
E ne, eyna meriyê wa li wir jî hene?
So no, exactly, are there relatives of yours there too?
Hene.
There are.
Wan birin?
Did they take them?
Wan birin.
They took them.
Em gi yek in. Em gi Kurd in, gi yek in, gi meriyê hev in.
We are all one. We are all Kurds, we are all one, all
relatives of each other.
Wê gundê ber Hecîra giştî... ber sînor da... em gi meriyê
hev in.
That village towards Hecîra... towards the border... we are
all relatives of each other.
Hwin jinan ji hev nînin?
Do you not take wives from each other?
Na.
No.
Na?
No?
Na. Yasax kir, kû?
No. They forbade it, where?
Yanî berê we ji hev dizewicîn? Wa keşkê xwe didanê, wa keşkê
xwe didanî?
Meaning before you used to marry each other? They gave their
daughters, you gave your daughters?
Pirr danî, pirr danî, pirr danî.
Many gave, many gave, many gave.
Wa jî danî, wa jî danî.
They gave too, we gave too.
Noko jî hêşta... yasax... her kes ciyê xwe da ma.
Now also still... forbidden... everyone stayed in their
place.
Tetî gelek gund o no... tu diçî, tu dibînî, hinek vî alî
ketin, hinek vî alî ketin, ji hev qut bûn ne.
So many villages or not... you go, you see, some fell this
side, some fell that side, they were cut off from each
other, right.
Ji hev qut bûn ne. Qut bûn.
They were cut off from each other. They were cut off.
Bes em zanin bi telefonê em xeberdan dikin.
But we know, we speak by telephone.
Hene wek peywendî, hûn xeberdidin bi hevdura?
Is there like a connection, do you speak with each other?
Erê, tim.
Yes, always.
Dî derî vebin, telefonê hekîşto, cem hev hene, didin.
If the door opens, the telephone... we have them together,
we give.
Jarkî ba telefon na, derketan, telefonê dan.
Once there was no telephone, they came out, they gave
telephone [numbers].
Wê pasaport hebû zemanekî, pasaport ji çûn dihatin, xêr
pirro... hew jî dihatin, em jî diçûn.
There was a passport at one time, with passport they went
and came, very expensive... they came, we went.
Hat birîn.
It was cut off.
No hûn benda sînor in, sînor rabe... hûnê herin wek berê,
çawa diçûn ba hevdû dihatin?
Now you are waiting for the border, for the border to be
removed... will you go like before, how you used to go to
each other and come?
Sînor inşellah e rabe... û emê lê berê zêdetir herin werin.
Bêhna xwe dighîha.
The border, God willing, will be removed... and we will go
and come more than before. We will catch our breath.
Spas tero. Fermo kîş vî mîkrofonê bigre bipirsim.
Thank you, uncle. Please take this microphone, let me ask.
No... tu gundê we da...
Now... in your village...
Belê.
Yes.
Tetî, me behsa... pêşo behsa sînor û çawa milet ji hev qut
bûn û de... gelek gund bûn li ber sînor, milet jî zirar dîn.
You said, we discussed... before we discussed the border and
how the nation was cut off from each other and... there were
many villages near the border, the people also suffered
damage.
Zirar dîn e.
They suffered damage.
Yanî lingê wan di mayîna da ketin... kes, pir kes jî jiyana
xwe dest xwe dan.
Meaning their legs were lost in mines... people, many people
also lost their lives.
Yek jî tu yî yanî? Ez yek ji wan, em sê ne wilo.
One is you, meaning? I am one of them, we are three like
that.
Hwin sê kesin?
You are three people?
Ez û Xelîl Ehmed, û yek jî rehmetî bû. Li vê derê me zirar
dît.
Me and Xelîl Ehmed, and one was deceased. In this place we
suffered damage.
Milkê me li ser sînor e.
Our property is on the border.
Em hatin, nav milk... em lê derbaz jî neketin.
We came, inside the property... we didn't even cross over.
Me nezanî bû ew der... mayîn lê hatine çandin.
We didn't know that place... mines had been planted there.
Di nav milkê me da, mayîn hatibûn danîn. Em nezan bûn.
Inside our property, mines had been placed. We were unaware.
Çend salî dema te zirar dît? Lingê te çû?
How old [were you] when you suffered damage? Your leg went?
Sala heştê û heştê... pêncê meha şeşan bû.
The year eighty-eight... it was the fifth of the sixth
month.
Pêncê meha şeşan?
The fifth of the sixth month?
Belê.
Yes.
Hingê tu zewicî bûyî?
Were you married then?
Na, ez ezeb bûm.
No, I was single.
Tu ezeb bûyî?
You were single?
Belê.
Yes.
Bavê te ne li gel te bû?
Was your father not with you?
Bavê min li gel min bû.
My father was with me.
Hun diçûn wek karê xwe, diçûn...
You went for your work, you went...
Me pezê xwe diçêrand.
We were grazing our sheep.
Pezê xwe diçêrand?
Grazing your sheep?
Belê.
Yes.
Li nav eraziyê xwe, li nav milkê xwe?
Inside your land, inside your property?
Erazî ê me ye.
The land is ours.
Ew der nêzîkî sînor e?
Is that place near the border?
Nêzîkî sînor e, pêncî metro, sed metro dûr e.
It is near the border, fifty meters, one hundred meters
away.
Pêncî metro?
Fifty meters?
A.
Yeah.
Te nezanîbû mayîn lê hene?
Did you not know mines were there?
Me zanîbû hene, me nedizanî kîderê ne.
We knew they were there, we didn't know where.
Me dizanî hene, ew der mayînkirî ye, sînor e.
We knew they were there, that place is mined, it's the
border.
Bes em nezan bûn kîderê ne, şûna wan kîderê ye.
But we were unaware where they are, where their location is.
Berî wê kesekî zirar dîtibû?
Had anyone suffered damage before that?
Berî min, pismamê min, Sileyman, lingê wî jî çûbû.
Before me, my cousin, Sileyman, his leg had gone too.
Lingê wî jî çûbû?
His leg had gone too?
Belê.
Yes.
Ew jî sax e?
Is he alive too?
Ew jî sax e.
He is alive too.
Yanî berî te ew jî çûbû?
Meaning before you he had gone [lost his leg]?
Berî min ew çûbû.
Before me he had gone.
Lê belê dîsa jî hûn diçûn wê derê?
But still you went to that place?
Mecbûrî em diçûn, me digot qey cîyê ku pêlepandiye paqij e.
We went out of necessity, we thought the place that was
stepped on was clean.
Me digo qey xelas bû.
We thought it was finished [safe].
Te digo qey xelas bû.
You thought it was finished.
Me digo xelas bû. Derket ne xelas e.
We said it was finished. It turned out it's not finished.
Pê Mihemed, merheba.
Uncle Mihemed, hello.
Mêyît merheba, ehlen we sehlen.
Hello to you, welcome.
Sax bî. Pê Mihemed, gote... tu birîna derman dikî? Nexweşiyê
qulbaşî?
Be healthy. Uncle Mihemed, they said... do you treat wounds?
The Qulbashi illness?
Eywa.
Yes.
Ev çi nexweşî ye? Çawa vê nexweşî çêdibe? Û kê berî te
dikir?
What is this illness? How does this illness happen? And who
did it before you?
Ewa... hîn pita bofkî me rehmetî çêdikir.
That... my late father's aunt used to treat it.
De şîşt? Pita bofkî min.
You washed [massaged] it? My father's aunt.
Û dêka bofkî min, pita me yê ni wê jî dişîştin. Ji pî wê ra,
wê jî dişîşt.
And my father's mother, our aunt who is now [here], she used
to massage too. To her leg, she used to massage too.
Em jî malî, dadê Hecî Mehmûd jî dikin.
We also at home, Mother Hecî Mehmûd also does it.
Bavê te jî dikir?
Did your father do it too?
Bofkî mino, opî min dikirin. Opî min giyo, birakî me yekî
dido dikir.
My father, my uncle used to do it. My uncle and all, one of
our brothers also did it.
Yekî tebeq, Xelîl navê wi qewmezinê me ye. Ew noko tîgum.
One generation, Xelîl is his name, our elder. He is now
gone.
Gund... yanî em berê li Helebê bûn, li Helebê... opê min jî
li vê derê li gund bûn.
The village... meaning we were in Aleppo before, in
Aleppo... my uncle was also here in the village.
Wana li vir dişîşt, min jî li Helebê dişîşt. Opî min didu li
Helebê bûn, wa jî dişîşt.
They used to massage here, I used to massage in Aleppo. My
two uncles were in Aleppo, they used to massage too.
Ya ev nexweşî çawa çêdibe yanî?
So how does this illness happen, meaning?
Ewa welle, î heyî... ekserî ji xweyîbûnê tê, ji qehrê.
That, by God, it exists... mostly it comes from being upset,
from grief.
Pir ji qehrê çêdibe.
It happens mostly from grief.
Ewa. Î linga... î bê, berê bê çî linga qut... qundere teng
be, ling tê dikeve wa dike.
Yes. The legs... look, look at what the legs cut... if the
shoe is tight, the leg falls into it and does that.
Dûbare me.
Repeat for me.
Dûbare me, eywa. Qunderake teng be... ew jî çêdike.
Repeat for me, yes. If a shoe is tight... that also causes
it.
Yo tiş mîştin lî keve, mêxan darin, lî kevin... ew jî wa
dike.
Or if something heavy falls on it, having corns/nails, if
they fall... that also does it.
Berzê jî gişt ji qehrê çêdibe ev nexweşî ye.
The corn/wart is entirely caused by grief, this illness.
Esil ev nexweşî bi xwe ji qehrê çêdibe?
Actually this illness itself happens from grief?
Însanê ku zêde biqehrî jî fe'len pir berxwedide.
A person who grieves too much actually gives up a lot.
Î heyî şeş neqlo tê cem min, dişom. Î heyî pênc neqlo tê, ya
hî neqla kê tê.
It exists, six times they come to me, I massage. It exists,
five times they come, or one time they come.
Ê ewana naçin toxtor?
So do they not go to the doctor?
Darrin.
They run away.
Î?
Really?
Î diçûn toxtor, dilê qutkirin dibî, qutkirin e. Pirr
qutkirin e.
They used to go to the doctor, the heart wants cutting
[surgery], it is cutting. It is much cutting.
Yekê ji ewê... ji gundî... Kûkan e, Kûkan e. Yek ji Kûkanê,
jinek ji Kûkanê hat cem min. Wê sibê da yêkê lê bêçî ma
qutkin.
One of those... from the village... Kukan, Kukan. One from
Kukan, a woman from Kukan came to me. That morning one
[doctor] said let us cut the finger.
Ma wext meke, ma re tixte.
Don't delay, don't be lazy.
Dexlet sote, mi jê ra şûşt, mi heşt neqla jê ra şûşt.
It burned inside, I washed with it, I washed with it eight
times.
Wellehî her neqlek...
I swear, every single time...
Wellehî bile her ser rejîkê sed û pêncî mû jê derdiket.
I swear to God, on every pore, a hundred and fifty hairs
were coming out.
Çû çêbû, ji berê çêtir bû.
It went away and got better, better than before.
Ba rehet te?
Are you comfortable now?
Ebeden, noka jî hîn heye heta noka jî.
Not at all, it is still there even now.
Ez dê bibim nexweşiya qulbşê.
I will call it the scabies/eczema sickness.
Nexweşiya qulbşê...
The scabies sickness...
Na wilo gelek mi jê dîtin ne wilo pîs ti.
No, I saw a lot of it, but not this bad.
Bes ew nexweşiyek teybet... na êşiyaye rastî.
But that is a strange sickness... it doesn't hurt, honestly.
Li kurê ye?
Where is it?
Ew bêçî, ling û destan tê.
That comes to the fingers, the feet and hands.
Ber bêçîyan tê, ber bêçîyan... ya lingan ya yê destan.
It comes to the tips of the fingers... either the feet or
the hands.
Yek diji... cakê li ewê... li...
One stands... a place on the... on...
Qereqûlê... jinikê wî jî dîsa li vî derî hat.
At the outpost... his wife also came to this place.
Mi go çi qasiyê? Hako bibî mi hakim... qasi reş bibû, bî
avakê zer jê dihat.
I said, "What is this?" Look, if you were me... it had
turned black, yellow water was coming from it.
Mi go la sakim, hew le ne hewe?
I said, "Let me see, is it just this or not?"
Welle mi go ew bî salek e.
By God, I said, "That has been a year."
Go wellehî salek e.
He said, "I swear it has been a year."
Bi vî derî girt, mi go pûrikê bixweşe, mi lo nîv... nîv jê
derê maniyan bişom.
He took this part, I said, "Wash the calf," I washed half...
half of it remaining.
Bi vî derî girt, eyar li vî derî sikinî.
It took hold of this place, the skin stopped here.
Eyarê ser ra girt, mîş bû qasi... pir mîş bû, qasi hewtîn...
xerebî.
The skin peeled off, it became like... very eaten away,
like... ruined.
Heft neqla min ew jî şûşt, çû rehet bû, bereket Xwedê kete,
wellehî noka hîn jî heye jinik.
I washed that seven times too, it went away and got better,
God's blessing be upon it, I swear the woman is still
around.
Mêrê jî heye, jinik jî.
Her husband is around, and the woman too.
Ê ev nexweşiya teybet di kîjan mehê de, dema xwe heye, di
kîjan mehê de, di kîjan royê de çê dibe?
So, does this specific sickness have a specific month? Does
it have a time? In which month or day does it happen?
Na... di kîjan royê be...
No... whatever day it is...
Belkî gelek nexweş hebin, dibêjin di çarşemê tewar e, ya înê
tewar e, me hano dikir?
Maybe there are many sick people who say, "Wednesday is the
charm," or "Friday is the charm," did we do that?
Na, na, hewa kîjan royê be, bi şev, bi roj ferq nake. Kîjan
deşû bişon.
No, no, whatever day it is, night or day, it makes no
difference. Whatever time they want, they can wash.
Ferq nake hewa.
It makes no difference.
Dermana xwa çiye? Tu çewa çê dikî?
What is its remedy? How do you prepare it?
Dermana xwe... dema wî nin, werin ava ew bikin.
Its remedy... when they bring it, come and prepare that
water.
Dema avê... avê kef sabûnê çêkin.
When the water... make a soapy foam with the water.
Erê nava avê ye, ne?
Yes, it is inside the water, right?
Hewa av e.
It is water.
Sabûnê jî tekin?
Do they put soap in it too?
Sabûnê jî tekin. Avî sabûnê.
They put soap in too. Soapy water.
Çi kin ebeden.
That's what they do, absolutely.
Dîsa sabûn e? Sabûn e? Te dît na na, em çûbûn cem darê?
Is it soap again? Soap? You saw, didn't you, when we went to
the tree?
Erê.
Yes.
Wan jî dîsa derman da çêkird, dîsa sabûn.
They also prepared the remedy there, again soap.
Erê weleh... heh..
Yes, by God... heh...
Hewa sabûnê kef bidê.
Give it the soap foam.
Bes sabûnê xar... ti zirarê nakê. Karê nakê, zirarê jî nakê.
But eating soap... it does no harm. It doesn't help, but it
doesn't harm either.
Na, ê xurtî çi bûye?
No, what was the strong part [active ingredient]?
Bêjî xurt, qulbşê bila wekî biber e.
Let's say strong, let the scabies be like pepper.
Me bere jî jê ra şûşt.
We washed with it before too.
Ê te rehet bû ye?
So, did you get relief?
Elhemdulillah rehet bû ye.
Praise be to God, it got better.
Çêbû?
It healed?
Ê te jî ew qulbşê çêbû û wa pûrikê werimî û ginê min tî av
girt?
Did your scabies heal, and that swollen calf, and my cheek
that held water?
Û pir dişewitand, işta hono kirin çêbû.
And it burned a lot, look, they did this and it healed.
Erê. Hono kirin rehet bû.
Yes. They did that and it got better.
Hev naba xwe, wekî misşar e. Hev bexwe wekî misşar jî
dikşîne. Mû jî dikşîne, mû.
This pain of his, it is like a saw. It pulls like a saw
itself. It pulls the hair too, the hair.
Ev çi ye?
What is this?
Ev rajî ye, rajî. Rajî... darî ewres e, li çi dibê?
This is the tree root, the root. The root... it is the
Juniper tree, what do you call it?
Darî xwe... wek samxî darî serû ye, serû. Darî serû.
Its tree... is like the gum of the Cypress tree, Cypress.
The Cypress tree.
Ew darê li vir bawer heye?
Are those trees found here, do you believe?
Pir e, pir e, li çî, pir e canim.
There are many, many, on the mountain, there are many, my
dear.
Emê wî bişewitînin, î gendo hişk na, yê hêşîn.
We will burn it, not the dry rotten ones, the green ones.
Dikin tepsika komirê... li mol dini ser, îr bişewitî, we na,
çêbû porîka wî lîke û xelas bîş. Havina jî genda.
Put it on a plate of coal... put it on top of the fire, burn
the fire, like that, it's done, apply the powder and it's
finished. In the summer, it's rotten.
Ê ev bes tenê dermana xwe?
Is this its only remedy?
Erê, erê.
Yes, yes.
Başqa tişt tune?
There is nothing else?
No, no, no, ebeden.
No, no, no, absolutely not.
Bes wextî ma şûşt şûnda...
But after we washed...
Evê pelûlî şîr û sabûnê çêkin.
Make this paste of milk and soap.
Dîsa nexweşî, vê sabûnê, bes milo acer be sabûn, milo ne...
av be.
Again the sickness, [use] this soap, but let the soap be
solid/fresh, don't let it be... water.
Sabûn neyeke şil be.
The soap shouldn't be wet/soggy.
Sabûnî... tikê pî... pelûlê çêke, yake ac... yake pak be.
The soap... a bit of... make the paste, let it be... let it
be clean.
Ma xelas kir şûn, demê win werin, pelûlî şîr û sabûnê çêkin,
amê biserdin, diçikin.
After we finished, when you come, make a paste of milk and
soap, we will cover it, apply it.
Mesele bo derî bêçîya otin. Dînê ser pîç, hono ew bikin.
For example, it came to the toes. Put a bit on it, do it
like that.
Û tî... pûder birijînin û xelas bîç.
And put... pour powder on it and it's finished.
Her du sê saeta... em jêra dibên, yek wî hilke, yek dî
biserde, manî bikşîne, çi tî tê da heye bikşîne.
Every two or three hours... as we say, lift one off, put
another on, so it draws out, whatever is inside, it draws it
out.
Wê nexweşiyê ji kû?
Draws out that sickness?
Êwa. Wî gilgimorê gişî dikişîne.
Yes. It draws out all that itch/infection.
Mû jî tê der, fûr.
The hair comes out too, immediately.
Û çê dibe. Na î heye neqlek tenê em dişon, rehet dibe. Î
heye du neqlo tê, î heye sê neqlo tê, î heye şeş neqlo tê.
And it heals. For some, we wash only once, and they get
relief. For some it takes two times, for some three times,
for some six times.
Însan bes ew nexweşiya vî ket, yekê neqehire, ebeden.
A person, once they catch this sickness, should not worry at
all, absolutely.
Bi çiqo qehri weqû zêde dibe.
As much as they worry, it increases that much.
Ebeden.
Absolutely.
Hate xodxweşû? Keremke.
Are you happy now? Please go ahead.
Nêzî sed û panzdeh xanî û derdora hefsed kes li gund dijîn.
Close to one hundred and fifteen houses and around seven
hundred people live in the village.
Hejayî bîrxistinê ye, koçberiya bandora xwe li ser xelkê
gund kiriye.
It is worth mentioning, migration has had its effect on the
people of the village.
Gundî debar a jiyana xwe bi çandiniyê dikin.
The villagers make their living through agriculture.
Ji baxçeyên zeytûn û rez, û her weha gundî gelek berhemin ji
tirî derdixînin.
From olive orchards and vineyards, and likewise the
villagers extract many products from grapes.
Ji dimis, şerîb, bastîq, û mêwîj, û sinciqan.
Including molasses, syrup, fruit leather, raisins, and
walnut delights.
Digel çandiniyê, gundî dispêrin xwedîkirina sewalan jî.
Along with agriculture, the villagers rely on raising
livestock as well.
Kargeheke dirûnê di gund de heye û nêzî deh karker tê de
dixebitin.
There is a sewing workshop in the village and close to ten
workers work there.
Hinek kes jî di sazî û desteyên rêveberiya xweser da li Reco
û Efrînê kar dikin.
Some people also work in the institutions and boards of the
autonomous administration in Rajo and Afrin.
Her weha fakulteyanek bi navê Şehîd Sefqan ji gund heye û
komîna gund pê hatiye binavkirin.
Furthermore, there is a faculty named Martyr Sefqan in the
village and the village commune has been named after him.
Komîna gund geleki çalak e.
The village commune is very active.
Û yek ji xizmetên ku ji gund re pêşkêş dike, çêkirina riya
di navbera Şingêlê û Panêraka.
And one of the services it provides to the village is the
construction of the road between Shingele and Paneraka.
Û çêkirina meydaneke fereh di nava gund de ji bo komcivîn û
şahiyan.
And the construction of a spacious square inside the village
for gatherings and celebrations.
Û her weha destbikarê sererastkirina hemû rêyên di navbera
gund de kiriye.
And likewise, it has started the repair of all the roads
within the village.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, em ji gundê Şingêlê derketin.
Yes, dear viewers, we have come out of the village of
Shingele.
Me berê xwe daye binê benê.
We have turned towards the bottom of the slope.
Em mane nêzî sînor e. Darek li vir heye, vê re dibên Dara
Şengêlê, pexwa Dare Kewzanê.
We are near the border. There is a tree here, they call it
the Shengel Tree, specifically the Turpentine Tree.
Ez, Apê Xelîl, û Apê Şêxmûs, Apê Remezan va em darbaskirin.
Em spasiya wan dikin, ew hezê jî bire hevin e.
Myself, Uncle Xelîl, Uncle Şêxmûs, and Uncle Remezan have
come here. We thank them, and their affection is mutual.
Saeta we xweş, hûn bi me re derbas bûn.
Bless your hearts, you came along with us.
Ser seran, ser çavan.
You are welcome, with pleasure.
Hun bi xer hatin.
Welcome.
Xwedê ji te razî be.
May God be pleased with you.
Apê Şêxmûs.
Uncle Şêxmûs.
Bêje.
Say it.
We behsa darê kir, em hatin bin darê. Ka keremke, şik kerem,
ba bini wera.
You talked about the tree, we came under the tree. Please,
go ahead, come closer.
Em hinekî bin darê bahs bikin, ji bo temaşevan jî bibînin.
Let's talk a little under the tree, so the viewers can see
too.
We behsa darê kir?
You talked about the tree?
Erê.
Yes.
Xwa dare, Dara Kewzanê?
Is the tree itself a Turpentine Tree?
Erê, Dara Şengêlê, binîş dikan, navê xwe, navê gund bi vê
darê ye.
Yes, the Shengel Tree, it produces gum, its name... the
village's name comes from this tree.
Bi vê darê?
From this tree?
Ez jî çûçik bûm, deh-pênc salî bûm, pazi meydanlixê heft
perçe gund dihatin li virê, dibirin geliyê hecî av didan.
Even when I was small, ten or five years old, after the
square... seven distinct villages used to come here, taking
[livestock] to the Hecî Valley to water them.
Em wiş... meydan a va em dirijin li ava da. Av tune ye.
We... this square, we are pouring into the water. There is
no water.
Av li cema em liqutin e yani.
We have collected the water from the gathering.
Penereke heye, kûso heye, bes Şingêl û Meydanlix, hevalê
hevin e.
Paneraka is there, Kuso is there, but Shingel and Meydanlix
are companions.
Em li avê da hişk in e.
We are dry regarding water.
Dihatin paz li vir maxel dikirin, telma dikirin, pazi xwe...
They used to come, rest the sheep here, fold them, their
sheep...
Î kindî, sibê nîrû dihat, î kindî jî li vir ve, diçûn
meydanlixê. Pazî me û meydanê.
The afternoon, morning and noon would come, the afternoon
too back here, going to Meydanlix. Our sheep and the
square's.
Apê Şêxmûs, te behsa vî kir no? Av li vir tune ye?
Uncle Şêxmûs, you mentioned this, right? There is no water
here?
Av li geliyê hecî heye, li vir. Bes.
There is water in the Hecî Valley, here. Only.
Li bin darê?
Under the tree?
Li bin darê me bî hefte.
Under the tree, we had a week.
Yani... em li avê da rijan e, tişta meydanlix dihat vira,
mesela...
Meaning... we are poured into the water [dependent], the
things of Meydanlix came here, for example...
Hev pez mez û heywan û av dida, de pazê reş bû, xêrî feqara
liqî bû, dinya.
This sheep and livestock and watering... the sheep were
black [numerous], it was the property of the poor, the
world.
Dinya feqara, xêrî pes kes tune bû yani.
The world of the poor, there was no other property for
anyone.
Dû we demê de, ev darê zeytûnê û keraz û dar tune bûn?
In that time, were there no olive trees and cherries and
trees?
No, no, no, tiştek hene bû. Ne keraz, ne zeytûn, ne rez, ne
tiştek.
No, no, no, there was nothing. No cherries, no olives, no
vineyards, nothing.
Tu behsa dikî çend sal in?
How many years ago are you talking about?
Ca... çend sal in... li mêj e... teqrîben... pêncî û pênc
sal, şêst sal heye.
Well... how many years... it's been a long time...
approximately... fifty-five years, sixty years ago.
Emrê me hefte ye.
My age is seventy.
Yani daxwî pazî meydanlixê dahate vira... emrê me deh-deh û
pênc salî bûm.
Meaning, the request of the Meydanlix sheep coming here...
my age was ten, ten-fifteen years old.
Apê Xelîl.
Uncle Xelîl.
Bêje.
Say it.
No ev çend sal in va dar li bave hene? Dara Şengêlê?
So, how many years have these trees been standing? The
Shengel Tree?
Dara Şengêlê bes hebû. Hene çûçik in e.
Only the Shengel Tree was there. These others are small
[young].
Teze ne, çûçik in e. Emrê vê tenê ne.
They are new, they are small. They don't have its age.
Yani ev çend sal in?
Meaning, how many years old is it?
Ev bî... hewa nate bî kesî.
This was... no one remembers it [being young].
Bavê me sed sal bû... gû... gû ten hono ye.
My father was a hundred years old... he said... he said it
was just like that [always].
Apê Remezan, em li gund bûn, te behsa darê kir. Te got... af
dara derman e û gelek çîrok te ji me re gotin.
Uncle Remezan, we were in the village, you talked about the
tree. You said... this tree is medicine and you told us many
stories.
Ka şikerema te, te nîkî vir da were.
Please, if you can come closer here.
Bûr, ehlen wa sehlen.
Come, welcome.
Te gelek çîrok gotin, te got dema...
You told many stories, you said when...
Pez medaniya vira û gur çawa pê digirt, û ma da li vira,
derman çê dikir?
The sheep would come here and the wolf would attack them,
and did they make medicine here?
Çima... Hewa Osmanlî hat, ekê ef daro qut kira.
Why... When the Ottomans came, one of them wanted to cut
this tree.
Ofîkî me hebî hîn eskerê seferberlikê hat.
We had an officer, still the mobilization soldiers came.
Rehmeleq gû ma, gû tû vê darê qut ke, te heyatî dehe gundo
şewitand.
Rehmeleq said to us, he said if you cut this tree, you have
burned the livelihood of ten villages.
Gû xêre, wî jî gotî xêre. Ê gotî gûrb pazî me digire...
He said, "What is the benefit?" He also asked "What is the
benefit?" He said, "The wolf bites our sheep..."
Em tên vê darê birîn, xûyn dikin... û wî benîştî jî em dikin
fetîl, dikin birînî gur.
We come and wound this tree, make it bleed... and that gum,
we make a wick out of it, put it in the wolf's wound.
Gur bi kû derê girtî, em dikin fetîl, bi benîştî benîştkî em
dikin vê birînî, haw birîna çê dibe.
Wherever the wolf bit, we make a wick, with the gum, the
gum, we put it in this wound, and that wound heals.
Heta li mêjro dibese... birîn li mêjro dibet, dîtinin ser,
pak dike.
Even if it reaches the brain... if the wound goes to the
brain, they find it, it cleans/heals it.
Berde... îlacekî girîng e.
Also... it is an important medicine.
Îlacekî degerlî ye. Û pir girîng e.
It is a valuable medicine. And very important.
Tu behsa dikî berî ev sînoran çêbibe, dema Osmanî li vira...
You are talking about before these borders were made, when
the Ottomans were here...
Tu wê demê dikî ne?
You mean that time, right?
Erê, nekê we xo ne qut kirana.
Yes, otherwise they would have cut it.
Wê çaxê.
At that time.
Hoşê nehiştin. Gû ma, gû ti dehe gund... demerandin, te
xerab kirin.
They didn't let them. He said to us, he said "You have
destroyed... ten villages, you ruined them."
Ê gû madem wilo ye, ez qut nakim.
So he said, "Since it is so, I will not cut it."
... w'am qut dikin.
... and we cut it.
Ew çi heng e didotim û vê darê, û didot benîşt ji vê darê
dibere?
What kind of thing is it that comes out, does gum come out
of this tree?
Heft perçem meydan o. Şingêl, Kûsa, Penîrek o.
There are seven types in the field. Shingel, Kusa, and
Penirek.
Deh rojan li ser vê darê bî.
It stays on this tree for ten days.
Dhatin benîşt li vê darê dibirin.
They used to come and take the gum from this tree.
Dikirin devî gur, birînê gur.
They used it for wolf bites, for wolf wounds.
Gur bi pês bigir tosa... êh daynin fatîl kirino...
If a wolf bites the skin... eh, they put a wick [gauze] in
it...
Ê birînê gur kirino, devî bizinê.
They treated wolf wounds, or goat bites.
Birînê bizinê kirino, ê rehet bibo.
They treated goat wounds, and it would heal.
Em teybet ji bo dewarane, wate derman ji bo dewar tenê ye?
Is this specifically for livestock, meaning is it a remedy
only for livestock?
No, li meiro ji... meiro ji, ji dikirin daînan dîdeînan ser
vê birînê.
No, for humans too... humans too, they used to put it on the
wound.
Birîn li kuderê biba, ê daynano ser.
Wherever the wound was, they would put it on.
Ê daynano ser vê birînê, maşallah ê vekirî spî bibo.
They would put it on the wound, and Mashallah, it would open
up and become white [clean].
Birînê pak bibo.
It would be a clean wound.
Hew meiro, hew birînê çêbibo, qene zûniya hew birînê lî
bûye.
That person, that wound would heal, as if there was never a
wound there.
Dazani melek fişek têra derbas bo.
You know, like if a bullet passed through it.
Benîştî... benîştî gelekî pir benîştkî merxûb e.
The gum... the gum is a very desired gum.
Û pir degerli ye, yanî pir girîng e.
And it is very valuable, meaning it is very important.
Û taybet dara Şingêl e?
And it is specifically the Shingel tree?
Û dibên dara Şingêl e. Dara Şingêl e ji qey xoyti ye.
And they call it the Shingel tree. The Shingel tree is also
very distinct.
Yanî emrê xwe çiqo bê lî n... xoyti ye.
Meaning, no matter how old it gets... it is distinct.
Ê di herêmê, wate di milî da, darê din hene? Mesela wek
maidano, ew gundê din...
And in the region, meaning in this area, are there other
trees? For example like in the fields, those other
villages...
Tine, dar li vê heybetê tine ne. Vê qalindbûnê û mezinbûnê,
darê benîştkê tine ne.
None, trees of this majesty do not exist. Of this thickness
and size, gum trees do not exist [elsewhere].
Xo kewsan e?
Is it rocky highland terrain?
Bi xo kewsan e. Kewsanê gundê jor noko zeyber tehl imînim.
It is rocky highland itself. The highlands of the upper
village, now I remain on the bitter slope.
Û em çû, ewkî çêdikin fetîl o. Evê jî pêşkêş kim.
And we went, to make that wick [remedy]. I will present this
too.
Ê kerem ke, çawa çêdikin?
Please go ahead, how do they make it?
Buyrun, he.
Here you go, yes.
Ka wera xeber de, em derman çawa çêdikin. Me'nî...
Come speak, how we make the remedy. Meaning...
Birînê gur, bi bizin o digire.
For wolf wounds, that the goat catches.
Kerem ke.
Go ahead.
Buyrun he.
Here you go, yes.
Haba benîşt e.
This here is the gum.
Haba benîştî, benîştûk e.
This here is the gum, the little gum piece.
Vê darê Şingêl e ye.
It is from this Shingel tree.
Hemû sabûniya rîşken, sabûn...
They grate soap into it, soap...
Ew çi herri ye, te bi herriyê çêkiriye?
What is that mud, have you made it with mud?
Haba herriyê axê gewr, emê bisterin wînî, wextê me dar birîn
kir, nekeve nav erdê axê.
This is white soil mud, we cover it like this, so when we
cut the tree, it doesn't fall into the ground soil.
Yanî rojekê têt birîn dikin darê?
So one day you come and cut [scar] the tree?
Lê, em darê hîlis dikin, ha ha binêre he.
Yes, we strip the tree, look here, yes.
Haba gi benîşt e, he.
This is all gum, yes.
Bi xoy benîşt daderivê?
Does the gum drip out by itself?
Lê, bi xo daderivê, he.
Yes, it drips out by itself, yes.
Sabûn nekaveyî, benîşt naure birînê, birîn kûr e, birînê
gur.
If soap is not put in, the gum won't go into the wound, the
wound is deep, the wolf wound.
Di vê demê da, we dermanê din çêdikir? Yan bes ev derman
çêdikir?
In those times, did you make other remedies? Or did you only
make this remedy?
Bes hav derman, dermanê din hebûn.
Only this remedy, there were other remedies.
Tinebû.
There weren't any.
Derman li seyda... li seydaliyan li ku bûn se waniyan dibîn?
Medicine at the pharma... where were pharmacies back then
for them to see them?
Erê berê de hemû tişt xozayî bû, tebîhet bû ne?
Yes, in the past everything was natural, from nature, right?
Ew çêdikir.
That is what they made.
Lê çawîr e derman çêdikirin?
But how did they make the remedy?
Lê çawîr e derman çêdikirin.
Yes, that is how they made the remedy.
Di vê demê de dîsa sabûn bî?
Was there soap in that time as well?
Lê, di vê demê dîsa sabûn bî.
Yes, there was soap in that time too.
Sabûnê tevî nebe, birîn ew nabê.
If soap isn't mixed in, the wound won't [heal].
Havdin nagire benîşt.
The gum won't stick together.
Emê fetîlê hana bikin.
We will make a wick like this.
Ê hanekî bikin.
We'll do it like this.
Ê gewriya bizinê sa kin. Ê bivî tûnî jî...
They check the goat's throat/infection. And with this
entirely...
... dikin gewriyê.
... they put it in the throat/wound.
Kirin gewriyê se, xelas ê pê çêbibe.
Once put in the throat/wound, that's it, it will heal with
it.
Pê çêbibe, ê de wîrda bizikine, û paşê şer bike tiştekî hana
girêdin.
It will heal with it, it will stick in there, and then later
fight it [the infection] and bind something like this.
Birîn çê nabe, illem bi vî benîştî?
The wound won't heal, unless with this gum?
Lê diranê gur hore qoq o dirêj e, didu sise dikevinê
heywanê.
Yes, the wolf's teeth are hollow and long, two or three
enter the animal.
Ê gur li vir hene?
Are there wolves here?
Hoo ho. Paşê tên.
Oh yes. They come later.
Haya noha hene?
Are there still some until now?
Haya noha hene. Heta nokeno bi pezê me digirin.
There are still some until now. Even right now they catch
our sheep.
Heta nokeno bi pezê me digirin.
Even right now they catch our sheep.
Işta emê werin vî benîştî çêkin, emê werin vê darê birîn
bikin hanekî ye, emê benîşt jê rokin.
So we come and make this gum, we come and cut the tree like
this, and we strip the gum from it.
Û bi fetîl kin, û au bikin.
And make it into a wick, and do that.
Pezê te jî hebî?
Did you have sheep too?
Lê lê lê.
Yes, yes, yes.
Tu çûyi ber pez?
Did you go with the sheep [as a shepherd]?
Erê erê, hoo birîn...
Yes yes, oh the wound...
Çend sal te şivantî kir?
How many years were you a shepherd?
Xalî şivan bî, hew pêncî sal o, bîst sal o pez çêrand.
Use uncle [me] was a shepherd, for fifty years, twenty years
grazing sheep.
Te l'vir diçêrand, diçû der û der?
Did you graze them here, or go far away?
Me l'vir diçêrand.
We grazed them here.
L'vir me diçêrand.
Here?
Here we grazed them.
Tiştek tinebû, ne zeytûn ne dar?
There was nothing, no olives, no trees?
Çiqa heft-heşt perçe meydan gul bide, sêv bide.
However many seven-eight parts of the field give roses, give
apples.
Pezê xelkê re bî, ne yê me bî, pezê xelkê re bî.
Was it other people's sheep, not ours, other people's sheep?
Ê malî Hecî Axa, Gundîbîkê, Şêx Simêlo.
The house of Haji Agha, Gundibik, Sheikh Simelo.
O we pirr...
Oh you [had] many...
Sed û sê bizinê xul jê ambûv kêm bibî.
A hundred and three goats... [unclear] would decrease.
Hef jî diçêrand.
I grazed them too.
E berî bi çend sala?
How many years ago was that?
Berî vê pêncî û pênc sala.
Fifty-five years ago.
Pêncî û pênc sal.
Fifty-five years.
Hef fetîlî ne?
Are these wicks?
Emê meşik biyo, emê çêkin, û paşê emê di birînê gur kin.
We would prepare the skin bag, we make it, and then put it
in the wolf wound.
Û î zêde jî emê hilînin.
And the excess we will save.
Tak ro çê nebe, emê didu din têkin, xelas.
If it doesn't heal in one day, we put two more in, finished.
Ê çêbibe. Birînê gur derhal ê çêbibe.
It will heal. The wolf wound will heal immediately.
Qirtkê bizinê birîn be, bi vî benîştî benîştûk e.
If the goat's throat is wounded, [we treat it] with this
gum, the gum piece.
Vê ra dibên dara Şingêl e.
They call this the Shingel tree.
Vê darê ra dibên dara Şingêl e. Şingêl bi vê darê nav kirin
e.
They call this tree the Shingel tree. Shingel is named after
this tree.
Hicmo gende qalind e. Maşallah.
Its volume is so thick. Mashallah.
Ê wîn tenê l'vir bin danîsê Şingêlî? Li herêmê tenê?
And you only planted Shingel here? Only in this region?
Alem wa dibê.
The world says so.
Dagot dara Şingêl e me'rûf e?
Did they say the Shingel tree is famous?
Ba gundê no zana ye.
Yes, the village knows.
Bes xok kewsan o?
But it is essentially rocky terrain?
Kewsan e, erê kewsanê xwe jî hovo ne, he.
It is rocky, yes its rocks are right here, look.
Kewsanê vê darê hevin e.
The rocks of this tree are these.
Ê li vê darê dibeyî.
Which grow on this tree.
Hev o ye.
This is it.
Û va kewsan o nayê xwarin.
And this rocky [plant/gum] is not eaten.
Î vê darê nayê xwarin. Hişk in e.
The one from this tree is not eaten. It is dry/hard.
Nayê xwarin. Lê kewsaniyan din çoyî me, hevo ye.
It's not eaten. But other mountain gums in our place, there
they are.
Hev kewsan na tê xwarin.
This mountain gum is eaten.
Lê e kask bibin.
But let them become green.
Û tê rîşke, û beharrê hişk bike, û bişo û hişk bike.
And fibers come, and dry it in spring, and wash it and dry
it.
Û paşê zivistanê bixwe.
And then eat it in winter.
Hin bo qehwê çêdikin.
Some make coffee [with it].
Qehwî dibê qehwî kewsan o.
The coffee becomes mountain gum coffee.
Berde xweş e.
It is very good.
Mala we ava be.
Thank you (May your house be prosperous).
Spas wara, saetê we xweş.
Thank you to you, health to you.
Mala we ava be.
Thank you.
Tu jî xweş. Bixêrhatin hatî ser serê me û ser çavê me.
You are welcome too. You are welcome upon our head and our
eyes.
Spas wara jî. Em dîsa vegerin. Kerem ke em dîsa vegerin.
Kerem ke.
Thank you too. We will return again. Please, let's return
again. Please.
Taybetmendiyeke gundê Şingêlê heye, ku hemû pirsgirêkên xwe
bi lêborîn çareser dikin.
The village of Shingele has a characteristic, that they
solve all their problems with forgiveness.
Û gundî hemû di nav ahengî û li hevhatinê dijîn.
And all the villagers live in harmony and agreement.
Û hemû weke yek malbat tevdigerin.
And they all act as one family.
Çar malbat di gund de hene, û hemû malbat ji êla Biyan e.
There are four families in the village, and all families are
from the Biyan tribe.
Silû ango Silêvan, kesê yekemîn e ku di gund de niştecî
bûye.
Silu, or Silevan, is the first person who settled in the
village.
Niştecîbûna wî vedigere zêdeyî sê sed salan.
His settlement dates back to more than three hundred years.
Kesî zanyîngeh dibe jêder ji bo dîroka vî gundî.
An academic person serves as a source for the history of
this village.
Zêdebûna rêjeya koçberiyê xurtbûna gund gelek lawaz kiriye.
The increase in the rate of migration has greatly weakened
the strength of the village.
Di heman demê de, çalakiyên cihereng li dar dixin.
At the same time, they organize various activities.
Yekbûna avakirina tîmeke xortan ya gogapêyan e, bi navê tîma
Şingal.
One is the establishment of a youth football team, named
Team Shingal.
Û bi tîmên navçeyên din re dikevin pêşbirkê.
And they enter competitions with teams from other districts.
Merheba, şer çava?
Hello, how are you?
Merheba serçava.
Hello, you're welcome.
Mamê Hanan.
Uncle Hanan.
Gotin tu strana dibêjî?
They said you sing songs?
Erê.
Yes.
Me jî meraq kir, me jî gazî te kir, û te jî hat, temeşe
kirin.
We were curious too, we called you, and you came, and
watched.
Û gund jî hemî spasya te dikin.
And the whole village thanks you.
Ê kê e stran digotin berî te?
Who used to sing songs before you?
Berî min, apê min hebû didot, hemû ez jê elimîm.
Before me, I had an uncle who sang, I learned it all from
him.
Ez bûm, mesela Şêxû bû, yekî din Hisên, sê heval bûn me.
There was me, for example Sheikhu, another one Hussein, we
were three friends.
Me distira, li daweta.
We used to sing, at weddings.
Galek dawetê gundê me. Paşê lawê birayê min, hunermend Hisên
Mihemed.
Many weddings in our village. Later my brother's son, the
artist Hussein Mohammed.
Ê me silav, klamet giran didanî, paşê jî me yî reqsê didanî.
We greeted, presented heavy [slow/serious] songs, and then
we presented dance [music].
Bes zabe hene dikir de, def tinebûn, tişt tinebûn.
But [unclear], there were no drums, there was nothing.
Def tinebûn, wane bi teştek, bi derbeke me derbas dikir.
There were no drums, so we got by with a basin, with a beat.
Ê jiber şahiya gund tê gîştî strana dibêjî?
And because of the village celebration, do you sing all
songs?
Erê.
Yes.
Wekî dengbêj, wejdar ve nadanî?
Like a bard, you didn't give [perform] that?
No. Em bûn. Ez bûm.
No. It was us. It was me.
We def û zirne jî nadanî?
Did you not use drum and flute either?
No no no, tinebû. Paşê mesele em tivî. Ez bûm, Şêx Mûs bû.
No no no, there wasn't any. Later, for example, we came. It
was me, it was Sheikh Mus.
Û Rehman hewa çûna ka derba.
And Rahman, they have passed away.
Ê ser govendê jî di gunda hene?
Is there head-of-dance [leading dancers] in the village too?
E heye.
Yes, there is.
Ebûl Îş vira dibîn.
They say Abul Ish is here.
Ê berê?
And in the past?
Ê berê, Ebûl Îş diraqisî û me jî çepko dixist me dida
kelama.
In the past, Abul Ish danced and we clapped and presented
the songs.
Û noha tu çi ji mera dibêjî?
And now what will you sing for us?
Emê silav li ser herfê Vêmalê.
We will greet [sing] based on the lyrics of "Vêmalê" [This
House].
Ya'nî Vêmalê, keçik xotina yî.
Meaning "Vêmalê", she is a distinct girl.
Û ba dike.
And she calls out.
Destan ra dike, û difile, ba dike.
She raises her hands, and whistles, she calls out.
Yanî daxwaza ji berê te çawa dawet derbas dikin, noca em
daxwaza tebê strana jî mera bêje.
Meaning the request from the past on how you passed the
weddings, now we request you sing a song for us.
Meşî, erê erê, serçavê min.
Okay, yes yes, upon my eyes [with pleasure].
Spas darêjî.
Thank you.
Ê ka em xatirê xwe bixwazin, li vir jî em bighîjine dawiya
bername...
So let us say our goodbyes, here we have reached the end of
the program...
... bernameya me şevane nêja. Li vir jî emê xatirê xwe jî we
bixwazin.
... our nightly program. Here we will say goodbye to you.
Li vir em gihîştine dawiya bernameya xwe, bernameya Welat,
îro em li gundê Şingêlê bûn.
Here we have reached the end of our program, the program
"Welat" [Country], today we were in the village of Shingele.
Em jî spasiya we dikin, heya neha we li me temaşe dikir.
We thank you too, for watching us until now.
Heta hefteke din emê dîsa we bibînin.
Until another week [next week] we will see you again.
Naha, Mamê Hanan stranekê diyarî ji me ra bêje.
Now, Uncle Hanan will sing a gift song for us.
Û em spasiya Mamê Hanan dikin, û em spasiya gundiyan dikin.
Kerem ke.
And we thank Uncle Hanan, and we thank the villagers. Go
ahead.
Sax be. Em werin ser herfê Vêmalê. Kerem ke.
Be healthy. Let us come to the lyrics of "Vêmalê". Go ahead.
Meke, kul ê... kul ê, meke, meke ooo yoy.
Don't, the sorrow... the sorrow, don't, don't, oh my.
Ka çepke, ka çepke.
Come on clap, come on clap.
Berxê... lê berxê, berxê kul ê vêmale, vêmale, vêmale...
Lamb [Dear]... oh dear, dear, the sorrow of this house, this
house, this house...
Lê vêmale, na şeva ya, xurba dunya şev ale vêmale, vêmale.
Oh this house, it is not night, strange world night
[unclear] this house, this house.
Cemala xelkê min î meqbûl.
The beauty of my people is acceptable.
Li taqê azmên î heftê, li hembera Pêvrûmî jîne.
In the arch of the seventh sky, opposite the Pevrumi life.
Li mabîna ewran, migo belki hebe hoy hebe vêmale, vêmale.
Between the clouds, I said maybe there is, oh there is, this
house, this house.
Oy vêmale, oy kesto xinda mal...
Oh this house, oh [unclear] house...
Lê lê bêmal, cawê te reş e, lê bêmal.
Oh wretched one, your shroud is black, oh wretched one.
Cawê te reş e, lê bêmal.
Your shroud is black, oh wretched one.
Miraz bi dilo, na lê bêmal, lê bêmal, lê bêmal.
The wish remained in the heart, oh no, oh wretched one, oh
wretched one, oh wretched one.
Lê, lê, lê... ooy bêmal, makê vo.
Oh, oh, oh... oh wretched one, oh mother.
Lê bêmal, cawê te reş e, miraz bi dilo.
Oh wretched one, your shroud is black, the wish remained in
the heart.
Na lê bêmal, kulî...
Oh no, oh wretched one, the grief...
Cawê te reş û palak ve, kelmana...
Your shroud is black and tattered, the fever...
Hato nava dilo, kutabû, bo şewitî, lê bêmal, kir ar danî nav
dilî.
It came into the heart, it struck, it burned, oh wretched
one, it set fire inside the heart.
Ooy lê bêmal, cawê te reş e, lê bêmal.
Oh, oh wretched one, your shroud is black, oh wretched one.
Cawê moro, bêmal ooy.
The purple/dark shroud, oh wretched one.
Ax sîngê sîng xorê me, nav kunda me, kurmê reş dano nav
dilo, ooy bêmal, dost û yaro, bêmal ooy.
Ah, I am a chest-beater [mourner], I am inside the ruins,
the black worm has struck inside the heart, oh wretched one,
oh friend and companion, oh wretched one.
Lê lê bêmal, bejna te zirav bû, mîna yayê.
Oh, oh wretched one, your stature was slender, like a bow.
Bejna te zirav bû mîna yayê, li ber deriyê hewşiyê.
Your stature was slender like a bow, at the gate of the
courtyard.
Mala xelkê nazikê, dîwar nekeve kûkakê.
The delicate people's house, may the wall not fall into the
hollow.
Rûniştî ser çawkiyê, ser kursiyê.
Sitting on the stool, on the chair.
Me dengî ban kir, me dengî ban kir...
We called out with a voice, we called out with a voice...
Lê bêmal, lê bêmal, lê bêmal.
Oh wretched one, oh wretched one, oh wretched one.
Melol pîra te werê, kezeb û dilê min qulişî, kir ar, lê
bêmal, li ser kaniyê.
Oh sad one, may your old woman come, my liver and heart are
torn apart, it set fire, oh wretched one, at the spring.
Lê bêmal, li ser kaniyê, ooy bêmal, bêmal, bêmal.
Oh wretched one, at the spring, oh wretched one, wretched
one, wretched one.
Em çûn hecê heyatê, min lêborî te dîtina li ber pîşkafiye.
We went on the pilgrimage of life, I sought you out near the
display/window.
Me go hela hela rindê wara, tûjikanê reş girêda li ber
eniyê.
We said hey, hey, come beauty, she tied the black fringes
over her forehead.
Kulo lawo, ka bi qurban, nîşana me li hena, qewa ser grakê,
beramber deriyê.
Oh grieving boy, come let me be a sacrifice, our sign is
there, the coffee on the hill, opposite the door.
Li ma veger e, saeta dîtina şemreşiyê, ooy bêmal.
Turn back from us, the hour of seeing the black-scarved one,
oh wretched one.
Ooy makê, ax de rabe bêmal ooy.
Oh mother, ah rise up, oh wretched one.
Way lo, way lo, way lo, way lo.
Way lo, way lo, way lo, way lo [Vocables].
Şêrînê xwedê da wo, lo şêrînê xwedê da wo.
The sweet one given by God, oh the sweet one given by God.
Ser kêxê nede xew da wo, lo ser kêxê nede xew da wo.
Do not put her to sleep on the felt rug, oh do not put her
to sleep on the felt rug.
Ser kêxê nede xew da wo, lo ser kêxê nede xew da wo.
Do not put her to sleep on the felt rug, oh do not put her
to sleep on the felt rug.
Min panik pê ve da wo, lo min panik pê ve da wo.
I attached a pin to her, oh I attached a pin to her.
Xewka şêrîn boz da wo, lo xewka şêrîn boz da wo.
She spoiled the sweet sleep, oh she spoiled the sweet sleep.
Xencer li ber şelyo wo, lo xencer li ber şelyo wo.
The dagger at the sash, oh the dagger at the sash.
Ne tu bû, na xencer bû, lo ne tu bû, na xencer bû.
It wasn't you, no it was the dagger, oh it wasn't you, no it
was the dagger.
Ne tu bû, na xencer bû, lo ne tu bû, na xencer bû.
It wasn't you, no it was the dagger, oh it wasn't you, no it
was the dagger.
Xencer gurzkê cewher bû, lo xencer gurzkê cewher bû.
The dagger was a jeweled mace, oh the dagger was a jeweled
mace.
Xencer gurzkê cewher bû, lo xencer gurzkê cewher bû.
The dagger was a jeweled mace, oh the dagger was a jeweled
mace.
Di ser dilî ta werbû, ho di ser dilî ta werbû.
It struck over the heart, oh it struck over the heart.
Fata gewr li hember bû, Fata gewr li hember bû.
The fair Fatma was opposite, the fair Fatma was opposite.
Fata gewr li hember bû, lo Fata gewr li hember bû.
The fair Fatma was opposite, oh the fair Fatma was opposite.
Eşqa Kemo li ser bû, lo eşqa Kemo li ser bû.
Kemo's love was upon her, oh Kemo's love was upon her.
Li heft dêrî no yek der bû, lo li heft dêrî no yek der bû.
Of seven doors, it was one door, oh of seven doors, it was
one door.
Li heft dêrî no yek der bû, lo li heft dêrî no yek der bû.
Of seven doors, it was one door, oh of seven doors, it was
one door.
Ka şivanê pezê yûz, ka şivanê pezê yûz.
Where is the shepherd of the hundred sheep, where is the
shepherd of the hundred sheep.
Ka şivanê pezê yûz, lo ka şivanê pezê yûz.
Where is the shepherd of the hundred sheep, oh where is the
shepherd of the hundred sheep.
Pez berdayî ardê tûz, pez berdayî ardê tûz.
He released the sheep onto the dusty ground, he released the
sheep onto the dusty ground.
Pez berdayî ardê tûz, lo pez berdayî ardê tûz.
He released the sheep onto the dusty ground, oh he released
the sheep onto the dusty ground.
Ez ê îsal a şixulîm, lo...
I will work this year, oh...