(Music starts)
Belê temaşevanên hêja, vê heftê jî emê derbasî gundekî
bibin. Gundek girêdayî bajarê Efrînê be.
Yes, dear viewers, this week we will visit a village. A
village attached to the city of Afrin.
Gundekî nîzî Efrînê be. Dema mirov bibêje biratiya gelan,
yek ji gund ev e.
A village near Afrin. When one speaks of the brotherhood of
peoples, this is one of those villages.
Gundê Bablîtê. Ev gundê Bablîtê, hin Kurd in û hin jî Ereb
in. Bi hevra jiyan dikin.
The village of Bablit. This village of Bablit, some are
Kurds and some are Arabs. They live together.
Me got vê heftê emê derbasî gundê Bablîtê bin. Hinikî emê
gund nas bikin, hinikî urf û adetê vê gundî nas bikin.
We said this week we will visit the village of Bablit. We
will get to know the village a bit, and get to know the
customs and traditions of this village.
Taybetmendiya vê gundî nas bikin. De ka vê carê em bi hevra
derbasî gundê Bablîtê bin.
To know the characteristics of this village. So, let us
visit the village of Bablit together this time.
(Music plays)
Merheba apê Şêro.
Hello Uncle Lion (Term of endearment).
Hûn bi xêr hatin, ehlen we sehlen. Hûn hatin ser serê me û
ser çavê me. Bi qanala Ronahî...
You are welcome, welcome. You came upon our heads and upon
our eyes (warm welcome). With the Ronahî channel...
...û me hêvî dikir ku rûyê wan bibînin.
...and we were hoping to see their faces.
Elhemdulilah ji vê rojê ra. Elhemdulilah.
Praise be to God for this day. Praise be to God.
Elhemdulilah ji vê rojê ra. Em bi halê xwe ne, kerameta xwe
ne, bi şerefa xwe ne.
Praise be to God for this day. We are in our own state, with
our dignity, with our honor.
Û weletê me mefhûz e... Disa nîmetek mezin e ji bo hizbî ra.
And our country is protected... Again, it is a great
blessing thanks to the party.
Ronahî... hev ronahî, rûnek ji Xwedê da hat... ku vê alemê
bisitirîne.
Light... this light, a light came from God... to protect
this world.
Û Xwedê ew bestirînê, Xwedê ew bestirînê.
And God protected them, God protected them.
Û mişkîla, mişkîlek mezin e. Elhemdulilah. Elhemdulilah ji
vê rojê ra. Elhemdulilah.
And the problem, it is a big problem. Praise be to God.
Praise be to God for this day. Praise be to God.
Apê hêja em dixwazin navê te nas bikin, tu xwe bidî
naskirin.
Dear uncle, we want to know your name, please introduce
yourself.
Navê min Şêx Ebdulhenan e.
My name is Sheikh Abdulhanan.
Ser çava mamê Şêx.
You are welcome, Uncle Sheikh.
Apê Şêx, em hatine gundê Bablîtê. Em dixwazin hinekî behsa
gundê xwe bikî.
Uncle Sheikh, we have come to the village of Bablit. We want
you to talk a little about your village.
Ev gundê Bablîtê te behs kir, bi Kurd û Ereb bi hevra
dijîn...
This village of Bablit, as you mentioned, Kurds and Arabs
live together...
Erê.
Yes.
Dema mirov bibêje biratiya gelan, yek ji gund ev e.
When one speaks of the brotherhood of peoples, this is one
such village.
Naam.
Yes.
Gundê Bablîtê.
The village of Bablit.
Ev gundê Bablîtê, hin Kurd in û hin jî Ereb in. Bi hevra
jiyan dikin.
This village of Bablit, some are Kurds and some are Arabs.
They live together.
Me hinek çû serdana wan kir, hinek em neçûn gundê din.
Înşallah emê herin wan gundan jî.
We visited some of them, others we haven't gone to yet. God
willing, we will go to those villages too.
Lê emê navê gundê we ji ku hatiye, navê Bablîtê ji ku
hatiye?
But we [want to know] where the name of your village comes
from, where did the name Bablit come from?
Welle me ji babê xwe bihîst... got, dibêjin "Baba Gît".
Well, we heard from our fathers... he said, they say "Baba
Git".
Baba Gît. Baba mîliyet baba ye yanî. Gît çi? Mêrekî berê
"Egîd" hebû.
Baba Git. Baba is the title Baba. What is Git? There was a
man in the past named "Egid" (Hero).
Egîd... Ereb digotin "Agît"... Baba Gît...
Egid... Arabs used to say "Agit"... Baba Git...
Li hewa peyva çû... Çû Baba Gît.
Through the air/mouth the word went... It went as Baba Git.
Ewa çû... nanê xwe erzan bû û peya bû.
That went... his bread was cheap (generous) and he was a
pedestrian (humble/accessible).
Nanê xwe erzan bû û peya bû. Peyê xwe hebûn, derê xwe hebûn.
His bread was cheap and he was a pedestrian. He had his men,
he had his place.
Û mêrekî... yekî vê hizbê, heqî bû.
And a man... one of this party, he was righteous.
Yekî vê hizbê heqî bû.
One of this party was righteous.
Ê navê gundê we ne ji Ba hatiye? Ba?
Didn't the name of your village come from "Ba" (Wind)? Ba?
Te digot Ba-blît?
You said Ba-blît?
Ba-blît.
Ê gundê we berê li vê derê bû? Yan cîhê wî din bû?
Was your village here before? Or was its place elsewhere?
Na, berê wî li jor bû. Li wî alî.
No, its place was up before. On that side.
Li ku derê?
Where?
Ji kaniya... jor, ser wî sirtî.
From the spring... up, on that ridge.
Çiqas ji vir dûr e?
How far is it from here?
Yanî du kîlometre hene tinin.
Meaning, there are about two kilometers.
Li wir kanî heye?
Is there a spring there?
E, kanî hebû, lê nika hişk bûye.
Yes, there was a spring, but now it has dried up.
Yanî bîr kolan, der kolan... hişk kirin.
Meaning they dug wells, dug places... they dried it up.
Berê na, kanî nika vî derê heye, bîrên kevin vî derê heye.
Before no, there is a spring here now, there are old wells
here.
Û kevirşîlê... berê kî ziftê... bîrek li vî derî heye.
And Kefershil (wet stone)... who formerly paved... there is
a well in this place.
Keferşîlê.
Kefershil.
Ûlî... ûlî... ko kirine, di vir de derket.
First... first... they dug it, it came out here.
Di vir de bîrê jêr de derket.
It came out here in the lower well.
Qena heye?
Is there a canal?
Erê qena heye.
Yes, there is a canal.
Qenaya Romane?
Is it a Roman canal?
Qenaya Romane ye.
It is a Roman canal.
Av tê de heye?
Is there water in it?
Av hebû... bîr kolan, qut kirin.
There was water... they dug wells, they cut it off.
Heta artwazî na kolan... xelkê kola av qut bû. Berê av ber
de jî vedixwar.
Until they dug artesian wells... people dug and the water
was cut off. Before, they even drank water from it.
Tê bîra me, ji vî derî vedixwar. Vî derî qut bû, me ji erqê
vexor.
We remember, they drank from here. This place was cut off,
we drank from the root/channel.
E navê gundê we çiqas sal e ji vir hatiye vir a?
How many years has your village been here (moved here)?
Welle em nizanin.
By God, we don't know.
Zû hatiye?
Did it come a long time ago?
Em dizanin kevn e.
We know it is old.
Jimeje?
From a long time ago?
Jimeje.
From a long time ago.
Yanî dibe dused sal heye. Jimeje.
Meaning it might be two hundred years. From a long time ago.
Gelek e, yanî jimeje.
It's a lot, meaning from a long time ago.
E.
Yes.
E navê gundê we çiqas xanî tê de heye?
How many houses are in your village?
Xanî... sê çelak heye.
Houses... there are about thirty-forty.
Çel xanî heye?
There are forty houses?
Hê, sê çel xanî heye.
Yes, there are thirty-forty houses.
E navê malbatên dêrîn kî ne?
Who are the names of the ancient families?
Malbatên tê de, holê hen tê de...
The families in it, their situation is there in it...
Eh... holê wan... ê Bîdayê dihatî gund de...
Uh... their situation... the Biday (Initial ones) who came
to the village...
Mala Hemdê Elî bûn...
Were the house of Hamdi Ali...
Paşê mala Xezêl...
Then the house of Ghazel...
Şêxê eşîra Amîrat...
The Sheikh of the Amirat tribe...
Paşê ne... ev mernê şêx in.
Then no... these are the men of the Sheikh.
Û ew dê wan hebûn, ew dê me hebûn.
And they had their parents, we had our parents.
Berê de hatin cem hev, civiyan cem hev...
In the past they came together, gathered together...
Silhetî çêdibû, der çêdibû, eydik dibû.
Reconciliation happened, opportunities arose, there was a
feast.
Eydik dibû... Berê du ro... bi eydê piçûkê... li vir...
There was a feast... Before two days... at the small feast
(Eid al-Fitr)... here...
Wekî dawetê bû.
It was like a wedding.
Gişî merî hevin, gişî pismamê hevin, birakê hevin.
All are relatives of each other, all are cousins of each
other, brothers of each other.
Harekî çar pênc... nav gunda dibûn... diman.
A group of four or five... were inside the villages... they
stayed.
Li eydê... dora vî derî... dima,
At the feast... around this place... they stayed,
Direqisîn bi kêf, mesxere û der û paşê diçûn mala xwe.
They danced with joy, joking and [fun], and then went to
their homes.
Di cejna de?
In the feasts?
Erê, cejna. Eydê dihatin... li vî derî... binê gund...
Yes, feasts. They came to the feast... in this place...
below the village...
Ebeden yek navê xwe... hesbanê salim bû... da zemanê...
Never one his name... was accounted safe... giving time...
Û direqisîn heta berê avê. Berê avê berda dibûn.
And they danced until the water released. The water was
released.
Lê her kes diçû cem pismamê xwe, birakê xwe, meriyê xwe.
GUND gî meriyê heve.
But everyone went to their cousin, their brother, their
relative. The VILLAGE is all relatives of each other.
Kesî biyanî tûne. Çend mal Kurmanc hene...
There is no stranger. There are a few Kurmanj (Kurdish)
houses...
Ew jî... wekî wan bûn.
They also... became like them.
Yekî yekî hebûne. Kesî biyanî nebûye.
One by one existed. There was no stranger.
Yanî navê rûniştvanê Kurd û Ereb in?
Meaning the names of the residents are Kurds and Arabs?
Kurd û Ereb in.
They are Kurds and Arabs.
Ez dixwazim hûn kî Kurd in kî Ereb in, wek hev dinalin
giştî?
I want [to know], who are Kurds, who are Arabs, do you all
groan/live the same generally?
Gî wek hev in. Ebeden cema tefrîqe tûne.
All are the same. Never, there is no discrimination among
us.
Na tu jêk dibê, ew dewa sînemayê...
No, you say apart, that claim of cinema (fake)...
Na dewa sînemayê yekî wele bêje em naqesirînin.
No, the claim of cinema, one implies we don't fall short.
Ne dibêjin heva Kurmanc e em naronin cem, ya der, vir da...
They don't say this is a Kurmanj (Kurd), we won't sit with
him, or there, or here...
Wele edeb in û xizmet û der, me hurmet dikirin... em jî wan
hurmet dikirin...
By God, they are polite and service and place, they
respected us... we also respected them...
Têkê behs nîye, got malik e.
There is no need to mention, it is said to be one house.
Wê şo tûne.
That thing does not exist.
Dema şahiyek çêdibê, dema miriyek çêdibê?
When a celebration happens, when a death happens?
Gî, gî, gî bi hevra. Gî bi hevra radibin, bi hevra rûdinên.
All, all, all together. All rise together, sit together.
Welle cema wê îşo tune.
By God, that thing is not among us.
Ew jî daweta didan... ew jî miriya dan... qusûr tûne.
They also gave weddings... they also gave dead (funerals)...
no fault.
Ebeden. Tefrîqe tûne.
Never. No discrimination.
Bi hevra filan, hevra elan... ew şuxul cema tûne.
With so-and-so, with such-and-such... that work is not among
us.
Navê te got malbatên dêrîn kî ne?
You said the names of the ancient families, who are they?
Malbat...
Families...
Berê giya mala Hemdê Elî hene vî derê...
First of all, the house of Hamdi Ali are here...
Aîla... paşê mala Xezêl e...
The family... then the house of Ghazel...
Paşê mala Şêx e...
Then the house of Sheikh...
Paşê mala Birîm Ehmed e...
Then the house of Birim Ahmed...
Paşê mala Hec Sitî ye...
Then the house of Haj Siti...
Paşê mala Hec Ibrahîm e...
Then the house of Haj Ibrahim...
Ê mala Nûrî mala Ehmo, mala Îso, ew jî aîla ne.
And the house of Nuri, house of Ahmo, house of Iso, they are
also families.
Zanî çû?
You know?
A mala aîla Mhemed El Fadil, ew ne jî...
And the house of the family of Mhemed El Fadil, they aren't
also...
Ew jî sê çar mal, ew jî birakê hev in, pismamê hev in...
They are also three four houses, they are also brothers of
each other, cousins of each other...
Gî gundgî meriyê hev e.
All the village are relatives of each other.
Kesê biyanî tûne.
There is no stranger.
Çend malên Kurmanc hene...
There are a few Kurmanj (Kurdish) houses...
Ew jî...
They also...
Elmugrebin yanî.
Meaning they are close (or expatriates/settled).
Û Kurmanc jî...
And the Kurmanj too...
Kurmanc jî...
The Kurmanj too...
Çar pênc mal hene.
There are four or five houses.
Naha ev gundê we nîzî Efrînê, piraniya milletê we derbasî
Efrînê jî bûye?
Now this village of yours is near Afrin, has the majority of
your people moved to Afrin too?
E Efrînê, heye mala Mehmed Leqîf heye.
Yes in Afrin, there is the house of Mehmed Latif.
Mala Birîm Ehmed li wî derê hene.
The house of Birim Ahmed are there.
Mala Şêx li wî derê jî... heç hebe mal hene.
The house of Sheikh are also there... whatever exists, there
are houses.
E... mala Xezêl li wî derê hene.
Yes... the house of Ghazel are there.
E elve hene, gî li Elrîfîn jî hene.
Yes they are there, all are in Afrin (Elrîfîn) too.
Em hatin çel pêncî malê gundê we li vir jî heye.
We came [to know] forty or fifty houses of your village are
here too.
Hê?
Huh?
Çel pêncî mal li vir hene?
Are there forty or fifty houses here?
Ê welle heye, wî derê heye. Em tenê, em li gund in.
Yes by God there are, there are there. We are alone, we are
in the village.
Em li gund in.
We are in the village.
Yanî pêncî mal hene.
Meaning there are fifty houses.
Wî derê...
Over there...
Pêncî mal hene.
There are fifty houses.
Û ciwanên we derbasî gundê din jî bûne?
And have your youth moved to other villages too?
Na, na. E Efrîn û vir, bes.
No, no. Yes Afrin and here, only.
Gundê Bablîtê...
The village of Bablit...
Berê ça bû, cotkarî hebûn.
How was it before, there were farmers.
Cotkarî çû... vî derê sê axa hebûn.
Farming went... there were three Aghas (Landlords) here.
Mala Seydî Memî hebû.
There was the house of Seydi Memi.
Mala Riffet axa hebû.
There was the house of Riffat Agha.
Mala Mistefayê Celemê hebû.
There was the house of Mustafa Celemi.
Ha...
Fellehêd xwe hebûn.
They had their peasants.
Ê fellehêd wan, evna gî çûn.
And their peasants, all of them left.
Fellehêd wan ê vî derê, evna gî çûn.
Their peasants of this place, all of them left.
Old Man: Hinek hebûn, hinek hene ji mala Taha bûn, hemû jî
çûn.
Old Man: There were some, some were from the Taha family,
they all left.
Old Man: Mala Ehmed Naso hebûn.
Old Man: The Ahmed Naso family was there.
Old Man: Mala Berî hebûn.
Old Man: The Beri family was there.
Old Man: Ee pir bûn. Pir bûn, pir bûn.
Old Man: Eh, there were many. There were many, many.
Old Man: Mala Barazî hebûn, hema van, van Barazî.
Old Man: The Barazi family was there, just these, these
Barazis.
Old Man: Bûzikî a.. ji gund in. Mala Ehmed Hesen ji gund in.
Old Man: Buziki... are from the village. The Ahmed Hesen
family are from the village.
Old Man: Ji gund, em gîşk ji gund in. Bes pitêtî qedîmen
çûye, ez pir ha nizanim.
Old Man: From the village, we are all from the village. But
the origins are gone from long ago, I don't know that much.
Host: Êê ew gundî jî cema çûne?
Host: Uh, have those villagers also left completely?
Old Man: Erê, hemû jî çûne. Me ji evan qedîm e.
Old Man: Yes, they have all left. Ours are ancient.
Old Man: Bes hew na tê bîra min, Bûzikî, Mala Ebdê Hesen,
wetan em na çûn.
Old Man: But I don't remember any more than that, Buziki,
Mala Abde Hesen, anyway we didn't leave.
Host: Mala te ava be. Xwedê ji te razî be.
Host: May your home be prosperous. May God be pleased with
you.
Old Man: Ehlen we sehlen.
Old Man: Welcome.
Host: Emê li derbasî gund bin.
Host: We will pass through the village.
Old Man: Pa min di gotin Xwedê qewetek bide we de, we
nexweşiyê me nebînin. Hûn hatin ehlen we sehlen.
Old Man: Then I was saying may God give you strength, may
you not see our troubles. You came, welcome.
Old Man: Hûn hatin ser serê me û ser çavê me.
Old Man: You came upon our heads and upon our eyes (You are
very welcome).
Old Man: Ya mît ehlen we sehlen. Hûn hatin ser serê me û ser
çavê me.
Old Man: A hundred times welcome. You came upon our heads
and upon our eyes.
Narrator: Gundê Bablîtê wekî hemû zayîkek ji her du pêk
hatiye, Kurd û Ereb hatiye hunandin û avakirin.
Narrator: The village of Bablite, like any birth composed of
two parts, has been woven and built by Kurds and Arabs.
Narrator: Nayê zanîn navê gund ji çi hatiye, lê tê texmîn
kirin ku navekî Suryanî ye. Tê wateya Mala Pît.
Narrator: It is not known where the village name comes from,
but it is estimated to be a Syriac name. It means the House
of Pit (Beit Pit).
Narrator: Lê ev agahî nehatiye peyt kirin.
Narrator: But this information has not been confirmed.
Narrator: Yekemîn malbat li gundê niştecî bûye, malbata
Hemdî Elêwî ku ji eşîra Amera ten û ew jî Ereb in.
Narrator: The first family to settle in the village was the
Hemdi Alewi family, who come from the Amera tribe, and they
are Arabs.
Narrator: Piştre malbata Xezal, Şêx Osman, Mamo, û Heskê ji
Ehmed hatin û li gund niştecî bûn.
Narrator: Afterward, the Xezal, Sheikh Osman, Mamo, and
Heske from Ahmed families came and settled in the village.
Narrator: Li rojhilatê gund Deşta Efrînê û Geliyê Heftê
Rişkê. Li başûr gundê Tîtê. Li rojava Qeracêreş û kaniya
Xezalê. Li bakur rêka qaçax, gundê Maratê û Girê Bergirê
dikevin.
Narrator: To the east of the village lies the Afrin Plain
and the Hefte Rishke Valley. To the south is the village of
Tite (Tehtê). To the west is Qeraceresh and the Xezale
Spring. To the north lie the smuggling road, the village of
Marate, and Girê Bergirê.
Narrator: Her wiha, pêncî û pênc malbat li gund hene. Û ew
jî her du ji pêk hatine, Kurd û Ereb pêk tê.
Narrator: Furthermore, there are fifty-five families in the
village. And it is composed of both, consisting of Kurds and
Arabs.
Narrator: Malbata Tofan, Essaf, Fadil Mosa, Xezal, Ebdulla,
Ebdo Ecac, Ehmed Elêwî, Leqaf, û Hec Istîf, hemû malbat Ereb
in û ji eşîra Amera ten.
Narrator: The families Tofan, Essaf, Fadil Mosa, Xezal,
Abdulla, Abdo Ajaj, Ahmed Alewi, Laqaf, and Hajj Istif, are
all Arab families and come from the Amera tribe.
Narrator: Malbata Yaqûb ku ew jî eşîra Şêxîn e. Malbata Mamo
jî Rûbarîn e. Malbata Şêx Osman, Welo, Îso Ehmed, Omer Inco,
gelek xelkên gund jî li bajarê Efrînê niştecî bûn û li wir
dijîn. Ev jî hemû malbatên Kurd in.
Narrator: The Yaqub family belongs to the Sheikhi tribe. The
Mamo family are Rubari. The Sheikh Osman, Welo, Iso Ahmed,
and Omer Inco families; many people from the village also
settled in the city of Afrin and live there. These are all
Kurdish families.
Narrator: Nêzî pêncî û pênc xanî û derdora du hezar kes li
gund dijîn.
Narrator: Close to fifty-five houses and around two thousand
people live in the village.
Host: Ehlê we sehlen.
Host: Welcome.
Host: Destpêkê emê hev nas bikin, navê te çi ye?
Host: First, let's get to know each other, what is your
name?
Mustafa: Mustafa.
Host: Navê te mam?
Host: Your name, uncle?
Old Man: Ebdulla me.
Old Man: I am Abdulla.
Host: Ser çava.
Host: With respect (Upon my eyes).
Mustafa: Îso me.
Mustafa: I am Iso.
Host: Ser çava. Kî xwediyê erdê ye?
Host: With respect. Who is the owner of the land?
Old Man: Ez im.
Old Man: I am.
Host: Tu yî?
Host: It's you?
Host: Ev erdê we ye, milkê we ye?
Host: Is this your land, your property?
Old Man: Erê, em diçînin niha, em dikin nîsk.
Old Man: Yes, we are planting now, we are making lentils.
Host: Ne dema nîska ye hûn diçînin?
Host: Isn't it lentil season that you are planting?
Old Man: Erê wextê nîska ye.
Old Man: Yes, it is the time for lentils.
Host: Berî vê çi hebû?
Host: What was here before this?
Old Man: Berî vê, heta buharê, em paşlê dikin paşê dikin
xudre.
Old Man: Before this, until spring, we fallow it then we
turn it into vegetables.
Old Man: Em dikin bacan, kundir, na.
Old Man: We plant eggplants, squash, no.
Host: Navê erdê zeytûn e?
Host: Is the name of the land "Olive"?
Old Man: Erê.
Old Man: Yes.
Host: Dibe?
Host: Is it possible?
Host: Na, berî vê wa çi çandibû?
Host: No, before this what had you planted?
Old Man: Berî vê tiştek ne çandî bû.
Old Man: Before this, nothing was planted.
Old Man: Zeytûn nebûn, me beref kirin.
Old Man: There were no olives, we cleared them.
Host: Yanî pişta zeytûn xelas dibe, dawî dikin?
Host: So after the olives are finished, you conclude it?
Old Man: Erê, dawî dikin.
Old Man: Yes, we conclude it.
Host: Neha jî meha yekê ye?
Host: And now it is January?
Old Man: Meha yekê ye, erê.
Old Man: It is January, yes.
Host: Hûn dest bi karê nîska dikin?
Host: You are starting the lentil work?
Old Man: Nîska dikin, genim... cîh heye, çi bê em diçînin.
Old Man: We do lentils, wheat... there is space, whatever
comes we plant.
Host: Tu çi karî dikî?
Host: What work do you do?
Mustafa: Wallah ez cotkar im, a.
Mustafa: By God, I am a farmer, yeah.
Mustafa: Cot e.. traktorê me heye.. emê traktorê..
Mustafa: Farming... we have a tractor... we will [use] the
tractor..
Mustafa: Ee emê nîska bajon. Traktora min a, ba'dê
direşînin, traktorê min a, ba'dê direşînin emê cût bajon.
Mustafa: Uh, we will drive [plow] for lentils. It's my
tractor, after scattering, it's my tractor, after scattering
we will drive the plow.
Host: Hûn bi çiqasî dajo?
Host: For how much do you plow?
Mustafa: Dar direşîne, ez jî cût dajom.
Mustafa: He scatters [seeds], and I drive the plow.
Host: Erê ew erdê wî ye, yê xelkê re hûn bi çiqasî dajo?
Host: Yes, that is his land, for other people, for how much
do you plow?
Mustafa: Ew erdê me rind e... av heye, nav de av, lûle bê av
e, ava şîrketê heye.
Mustafa: Our land is good... there is water, in it water,
pipes are without water, there is company water.
Host: Ew av didin, der dikin?
Host: Do they give water, do they extract it?
Mustafa: Wallah her malek traktorekê xwe heye teqrîben.
Mustafa: By God, almost every house has its own tractor.
Host: Her yekî heye?
Host: Everyone has one?
Mustafa: Her malekê teqrîben heye. Eger traktora xwe tune,
bi kirê dajon.
Mustafa: Almost every house has one. If they don't have
their own tractor, they plow for rent.
Host: Tu çi dikî, te jî nîsk destxwe kirine, çi kirine?
Host: What are you doing? Did you prepare the lentils
yourself, what did you do?
Old Man: Erê wallah, em jî.. ew diçînin, bi dêr diçînin.
Old Man: Yes, by God, we also... they plant, they plant with
the harrow.
Old Man: Xwedê ji me razî ye, em ne sêwî ne.
Old Man: God is pleased with us, we are not orphans.
Old Man: Û cînarê hew jî cem me ye.
Old Man: And the neighbor is also with us here.
Old Man: Saeta giya xweş. Xwedê û Pêxember ji giya razî be.
Old Man: The time of the grass/crop is good. May God and the
Prophet be pleased with the grass/crop.
Old Man: Erdê me, biha ye.
Old Man: Our land is valuable.
Old Man: Xwîna xwe, ser êmê erdê xwe emê birjînin.
Old Man: Our blood, upon the fodder of our land we will
spill.
Old Man: Welhemdu lillah serê me jî bilind e. Em karê şêxê
xwe gelek dikin.
Old Man: And praise be to God, our heads are high. We do the
work of our Sheikh a lot.
Old Man: Em ne muhtacî kesekî ne.
Old Man: We are not in need of anyone.
Old Man: Em muhtacî meriyê rind, û xwîna xwe erzan in. Bes.
Old Man: We are in need of good people, and our blood is
cheap [for our land]. That's it.
Old Man: Wekî din, elhemdulillah îşê me gelek rind e, û îşê
me gelek selef e.
Old Man: Otherwise, praise be to God, our work is very good,
and our work is very historically rooted (ancestral).
Host: Di gund da, milkê gund heye?
Host: In the village, is there village [common] property?
Old Man: Wallah hinga heye, hinga tune. Yê me tune ye.
Old Man: By God, some have, some don't. Ours doesn't exist
[we don't have village common land].
Old Man: Ê me tune ye.
Old Man: We don't have it.
Old Man: Tune ye.
Old Man: Doesn't exist.
Old Man: Elhemdulillah ji Xwedê re, em dajişin.
Old Man: Praise be to God, we live.
Host: Hun gîşk Kurd in, yan Ereb in?
Host: Are you all Kurds or Arabs?
Mustafa: Na, ez Ereb im.
Mustafa: No, I am Arab.
Host: Tu Ereb î?
Host: You are Arab?
Mustafa: Ez Ereb im.
Mustafa: I am Arab.
Old Man: Kurmanc im ez.
Host: [And] You?
Old Man: I am Kurmanji [Kurdish].
Mustafa: Ez Ereb im.
Host: You are Kurmanji?
Mustafa: I am Arab.
Host: Tu axaftina te pir baş e.
Host: Your speech is very good.
Mustafa: Ee wallah emê li gund ferq nakin. Em Ereb Kurmanc
gî yek e.
Mustafa: Eh, by God, we don't differentiate in the village.
We Arabs and Kurds are all one.
Mustafa: Kurmancî rind dizanim û Erebî jî pir rind dizanim.
Mustafa: I know Kurmanji well and I know Arabic very well
too.
Mustafa: Û xaltîkê min jî Kurmanc in.
Mustafa: And my aunts are Kurdish.
Host: Xaltîkê te jî Kurmanc in?
Host: Your aunts are Kurdish too?
Mustafa: Ê ji Bablîtê ne.
Mustafa: Yes, they are from Bablite.
Host: Ê noka na, em Ereb in, em Kurmanc in, em gîşk cût jêra
dajon.
Host: It doesn't matter now, we are Arab, we are Kurmanji,
we all plow together.
Host: Cudahiya gund, paşê Ereb û Kurmanc gî jêra dajon.
Host: The diversity of the village, eventually Arabs and
Kurds all plow together.
Host: Kurdî te pir baş e.
Host: Your Kurdish is very good.
Old Man: Erebî te jî baş e.
Old Man: Your Arabic is also good.
Mustafa: Wallah elhemdulillah.
Mustafa: By God, praise be to God.
Mustafa: Erebî me jî pir rind e.
Mustafa: Our Arabic is also very good.
Mustafa: Û Kurmancî me... em ne.. ne bîter dibim.. yanî em
li gund gî, Kurmancî rind dizanim û Erebî jî rind dizanim.
Mustafa: And our Kurmanji... we don't... I won't
exaggerate... meaning all of us in the village, I know
Kurmanji well and Arabic well.
Host: Niha te dest bi karê xwe bike?
Host: Now will you start your work?
Mustafa: A.
Mustafa: Yeah.
Host: Te nîsk reşandin?
Host: Did you scatter the lentils?
Mustafa: Aywa.
Mustafa: Yes.
Host: Te bi tenê xwe reşandin?
Host: Did you scatter them by yourself?
Mustafa: Tenê. Kes din tine.
Mustafa: Alone. There is no one else.
Mustafa: Hinek hatin, ar dikşînin, der dikin, em cût
hevdikin.
Mustafa: Some came, they pull the harrow, they extract, we
plow together.
Host: Te bi şevê cût dajo, yan î?
Host: Do you plow at night, or?
Mustafa: A, ba'dê xelas kir reşandina bi dêr xelas kir, paşê
emê cût bajon.
Mustafa: Yeah, after finishing, finished scattering with the
harrow, then we will drive the plow.
Host: Bi dêr bin erdê dikin?
Host: With the harrow you put them under the soil?
Mustafa: Bi dêr, bin erdê dikin.
Mustafa: With the harrow, we put them under the soil.
Host: Piştî wê, Xwedêyê nan bide, paşê dê... av dikin,
xuşûfê dikin, der dikin û paşê...
Host: After that, God will give bread [sustenance], then...
you water, you level [the soil], you extract and then...
Host: Paşê têne palê û derav û...
Host: Then come the laborers and the harvest and...
Mustafa: Bas av heye elhemdulillah, av...
Mustafa: But there is water, praise be to God, water...
Host: Av ji kuderê tê bo we?
Host: Where does the water come to you from?
Mustafa: Av ji sedê Meydankê tê.
Mustafa: Water comes from the Maydanki Dam.
Host: Ji Meydankê tê?
Host: It comes from Maydanki?
Mustafa: Ji Meydankê tê.
Mustafa: It comes from Maydanki.
Host: Av ji sedê Meydankê tê, û çawa... wek...?
Host: Water comes from Maydanki Dam, and how... like...?
Mustafa: Gî, boro, bin... texzîn, qenalê reîsî hafê gund e.
Mustafa: All [through] pipes, under... storage, the main
canal is at the edge of the village.
Mustafa: Û paşê gî kirina... îçî borî ye.
Mustafa: And then all put into... inside the pipes.
Old Man: Boriyan kê bî, avê daxwaz dike. Boriyan...
Old Man: Whoever opens the pipes, requests water. Pipes...
Host: Hun vedikin, avê berdidinê?
Host: You open them, and release the water into it?
Old Man: Rind be, avê naxwaze.
Old Man: If it [the weather/rain] is good, it doesn't want
water.
Host: Heger baran xweş bû...
Host: If the rain was good...
Old Man: Baş bû, heta buharê bêhna xwe dike, buharî.
Old Man: It was good, until spring it takes a breath, in
spring.
Old Man: Buharê, heta buharê îsa kin, baran rind e. Em av
nadin.
Old Man: Spring, until spring make it like this, the rain is
good. We don't give water.
Old Man: Baran kêm be, emê av bidin.
Old Man: If rain is scarce, we will give water.
Host: Eger av dan...
Host: If you gave water...
Old Man: Na carak av dan.
Old Man: No, gave water once.
Host: Çema nîsk heye bibin, çend meh wext dixwaze?
Host: For the lentils to be ready, how many months of time
does it need?
Old Man: Heta meha...
Old Man: Until the month of...
Old Man: Heta meha pêncê nîsk hene.
Old Man: Lentils are there until May [5th month].
Host: Heta meha pêncê nîsk hene?
Host: Lentils are there until May?
Old Man: Erê, çar meh hene.
Old Man: Yes, there are four months.
Host: Piştî wê hûnê palê bikin?
Host: After that you will do the harvest?
Old Man: Palê dikin.
Old Man: We do the harvest.
Host: Piştî wê jî, hûnê...
Host: And after that, you will...
Old Man: Şixre bikişînin.
Old Man: Pull the harrow/drag.
Old Man: Wê şixre bikişînin, kûm kin, vederê darrast kin.
Old Man: They will pull the harrow, pile it up, straighten
the place/furrows.
Host: Naha tesîra xwe li zeytûna nabe?
Host: Now, does it not have an effect on the olives?
Mustafa: Na.
Mustafa: No.
Host: Av heye.
Host: There is water.
Mustafa: Talama av heye...
Mustafa: As long as there is water...
Mustafa: Tesîra xwe tine ye. Av heye, elhemdulillah û...
fedla Xwedê û av...
Mustafa: It has no effect. There is water, praise be to God
and... grace of God and water...
Mustafa: Û... av nesekne, nesekne, kok nesekne.
Mustafa: And... water doesn't stop, doesn't stop, the root
doesn't stop.
Host: Ez dibînim navbera darê û darê va çandî ye?
Host: I see between the tree and the tree is planted?
Mustafa: Teng e na?
Mustafa: It's narrow, no?
Host: Ewa pir baş e.
Host: That is very good.
Mustafa: Fereh ne.
Old Man: They are wide/spacious.
Mustafa: They are wide.
Host: Na, çiqas navbera dar û darê va çendî ye?
Host: No, how much is planted between tree and tree?
Mustafa: Daw û yek mêtre.
Mustafa: Ten and one meters.
Old Man: Daw û yek mêtre.
Old Man: Ten and one meters.
Host: Yanî gîştî wuna ye, yan bas waha wusa çêkiriye?
Host: Meaning is it all like that, or did he just make it
like that?
Mustafa: Na, me pîva, wexta me çandiye, hisab bû.
Mustafa: No, we measured, when we planted, it was
calculated.
Host: Na, yên din çiqas datînin, darên nîzî hev dikin?
Host: No, how much do others put, do they put trees close to
each other?
Mustafa: Hawna darên xalû ne. Darên xalû, her heft mêtre.
Mustafa: Those are uncle's trees. Uncle's trees, every seven
meters.
Mustafa: Heft mêtre. Mabeyna darê û darê va heft mêtre.
Mustafa: Seven meters. Between tree and tree is seven
meters.
Mustafa: Ew hene hene şeş mêtre ne hîn.
Mustafa: There are those that are even six meters.
Mustafa: Bas ê me yî zeytî, li vederê li deştê, erdê xwe jî
kûr e, erdê xwe sor e, daw û yek mêtre.
Mustafa: But ours, the olives, here in the plain, its soil
is deep, its soil is red, ten and one meters.
Mustafa: Hinek hene daw û du mêtre ne.
Mustafa: Some are ten and two meters.
Host: Mabeyna yanzdeh mêtre?
Host: Between [them] eleven meters?
Mustafa: Ee yanzdeh mêtre, ha. Bûye yanzdeh mêtre.
Mustafa: Yeah eleven meters, ha. It has become eleven
meters.
Host: Tamam ka tu jî kerem ke, tu karê xwe bike, emê te
biawire jî kir.
Host: Okay, please, you do your work, we delayed/bothered
you too.
Old Man: Ê zehmet tine, saeta we xweş. Hûn bi xêr hatin.
Old Man: No trouble, good times to you. You are welcome.
Host: Spas, em jî kêfxweş bûn me dît hûn kar dikin, hemu em
silav dikin li wê.
Host: Thanks, we were also happy we saw you working, we
greet you all.
Old Man: Ee ehlen we sehlen, ehlen we sehlen.
Old Man: Uh, welcome, welcome.
Host: Ka kerem ke karê xwe bike, nîskan... ez jî şarezayî
kar bim.
Host: Please do your work, lentils... so I can be familiar
with the work too.
Old Man: Ya mît ehlen we sehlen.
Old Man: A hundred times welcome.
Host: Te me be elmiye? Te fêr bikî?
Host: Will you teach me? Will you instruct me?
Old Man: Ooo ser serî men.
Old Man: Ooo upon our heads [with pleasure].
Host: Sag be, ka kerem ke.
Host: Be healthy, please go ahead.
Host: Hûn dikarin bera biçin.
Host: You can go forward.
Host: Te ji pişt ve traktorê dajoi?
Host: You drive the tractor from behind?
Mustafa: He?
Mustafa: Huh?
Host: Yallah.
Host: Let's go.
Old Man: Hîç em waha kî, yabo şaş neçe, em wî dajo nîskê
xwe, erd... gi dibe yek.
Old Man: Whatever we do like this, oh father don't go wrong,
we drive it [for] our lentils, earth... all becomes one.
Old Man: Bo vî jî darim, bo vî jî darim, em ortê daren, erd
gi dibe yek. Heblê me fele ne.
Old Man: I have [trees] for this one, I have for this one,
we are in the middle of trees, earth all becomes one. Our
furrow/rope is straight/plowshare.
Old Man: Manê gab yek be.
Old Man: Meaning the path/plowshare should be one.
Host: Noka çend cara tu çûyî hatî ye?
Host: Now how many times have you gone and come back?
Old Man: Dêra çûm... pişta heblê çûm, va pişta hatim, a ka
ortê ji yerim. Manê gab yek be.
Old Man: I went with the harrow... I went behind the furrow,
here behind I came, oh now I take the middle. Meaning the
path should be one.
Host: Ka kerem ke.
Host: Please go ahead.
Old Man: Ee yallah.
Old Man: Uh let's go.
Host: Na te du caran çûyî, carekê çûyî?
Host: No, did you go twice, did you go once?
Old Man: Eywa.
Old Man: Yes.
Host: Te sê caran?
Host: Did you [go] three times?
Old Man: A, cara sî ye ev a.
Old Man: Yeah, this is the third time.
Host: Noka te ber erdê kî biçîne?
Host: Now towards whose land will you plant/go?
Narrator: Xelkê gund dabara jiyana xwe bi çandiniyê dikin.
Narrator: The people of the village make their living
through agriculture.
Narrator: Ji zeviyên zeytûnan, hemû cûreyên dan û gelek
cûreyên sebze.
Narrator: From olive groves, all kinds of grains and many
kinds of vegetables.
Narrator: Û her wiha gelek malbat jî sewalan xwedî dikin, ji
mîh, bizin û çêlek an xwedî dikin.
Narrator: And likewise, many families also raise livestock;
they raise sheep, goats, and cows.
Narrator: Nêzî deh kes di kargehan cûr bi cûr da li bajarê
Efrînê dixebitin.
Narrator: Close to ten people work in various factories in
the city of Afrin.
Narrator: Û behtirî deh kes jî di sazî û desteyên Rêveberiya
Xweser da kar dikin.
Narrator: And more than ten people work in the institutions
and bodies of the Autonomous Administration.
Narrator: Pakrewanek ji gund heye, bi navê Şehîd Şêrzad.
Narrator: There is a martyr from the village, by the name of
Martyr Sherzad.
Narrator: Komîna gund bi navê Şehîd Şêrzad hatiye
binavkirin.
Narrator: The village commune has been named Martyr Sherzad.
Narrator: Û her wiha dibistana gund jî bi navê Şehîd Şêrzad
hatiye binavkirin.
Narrator: And likewise, the village school has also been
named Martyr Sherzad.
Narrator: Şêx Ebdulhenan weke oldarekî di ola Îslamî navdar
bû.
Narrator: Sheikh Abdulhannan was famous as a religious
figure in the Islamic faith.
Narrator: Û yek ji meleyên terîqeta Rifatî bû.
Narrator: And he was one of the mullahs of the Rifa'i order.
Narrator: Gelek mirîdên wî li deverên cûr bi cûr hebûn.
Narrator: He had many disciples in various regions.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, îro jî gera me li gundê Bablîtê ye.
Yes dear viewers, today our tour is in the village of
Bablit.
Em hatin ba zozan malekê bûn, dayika jî xwestin xwarineke ji
me ra çêbikin.
We came to visit a family, and the mother wanted to make a
meal for us.
Hin jin, hin Kurd û hin Ereb in. Li van gunda hin Kurd û
Ereb bi hev ra jiyan dikin.
Some women, some are Kurdish and some are Arab. In these
villages, Kurds and Arabs live together.
Ene kî em ê urf û adetê wan nas bikin. Urf û adetê Kurda,
ene kî Ereba nas bikin.
So, we will get to know their customs and traditions. We
will get to know the customs of the Kurds, and the Arabs.
Em ê hevrêj dayika nas bikin. Merheba ji we ra.
We will also get to know the mother. Hello to you.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Em te nas bikin?
May we know you?
Heval Xedîce.
Friend (Comrade) Khadija.
Ser çava. Tu Kurd î yan Ereb î?
You are welcome. Are you Kurd or Arab?
Ez Kurd im.
I am a Kurd.
Tu Kurd î? Tu?
You are a Kurd? And you?
Ez jî Kurd im.
I am also a Kurd.
Kurd î? Ser çavê min. Hûn kîjan Ereb in?
You are a Kurd? You are welcome. Which of you are Arabs?
Wallah ez Ereb im.
By God, I am an Arab.
Ereb?
Arab?
Ereb im.
I am an Arab.
Ser çava.
You are welcome.
Ez Kurmanc im.
I am Kurmanci (Kurdish).
Yanî hin Kurd in, hin Ereb in?
Meaning some are Kurds, some are Arabs?
Lê em teva hev in.
But we are all together.
Hûn tev hev in?
You are all together?
Ji dê û bava da em cem hev in. Weke ev dem dighîşin, wekî
xwişk û bira kan e.
From our ancestors (mothers and fathers) we have been
together. When these times come, we are like sisters and
brothers.
Û me kêf kirî, em bi hev ra diherine şuxil û bi hev ra têne.
And we enjoy it, we go to work together and come back
together.
Û carê şurek negihîştiye me, û me kêf kiriye, û eyşa
(jiyana) teyîba û derê me elhemdulîlah. Me kêf kirî wallah.
And never has a bad word reached us, and we have enjoyed it,
and our life is good and our situation, praise be to God. We
have enjoyed it, by God.
Eka wê jî bi Erebî bêje. Kurdiya te pir baş e. Ka bi Erebî
jî bibêje.
Please say that in Arabic too. Your Kurdish is very good.
Say it in Arabic as well.
[Arabic] Wallah nihna mkayyifin. W el-hamdulillah kulla mitl
el-ikhwa.
By God, we are happy. And praise be to God, we are all like
siblings.
[Arabic] Wa n'îsh ma' ba'dna, 'al helwa wa 'al murra.
And we live with each other, through the sweet and the
bitter times.
[Arabic] 'Al helwa wa 'al murra. Wa nruh 'al hattab min ji
sawa, nruh 'al zeytun ya ba'dna.
Through the sweet and the bitter. We go to gather firewood
together, we go to the olives with each other.
[Arabic] Nruh 'al bizar wiya ba'dna, nji nitfaddal halna
'ind ba'dna. Ya'ni mitl el-khawat.
We go to the fields together, we come and visit each other.
Meaning, just like sisters.
Û şlona l-'eras 'andkun?
And how are the weddings with you?
[Arabic] El-'eras? El-'eras, ysir el-'ers bil-jarye, wa
tabla, w el-'alam kulla tijina ma'azim.
The weddings? The weddings, the wedding happens in the
village, with drums, and all the people come to us as
guests.
Kî hene? Yanî Kurd û Ereb?
Who is there? Meaning Kurds and Arabs?
[Arabic] Nidhbah, nidhbah 'ala esmut, wa nruh nakhudh nsawwi
lahm 'ajin.
We slaughter (livestock), we slaughter for the feast, and we
go take it to make Lahmacun (meat bread).
[Arabic] Wa tabla heyn tirga', wa nruh njib el-'arus,
nakhudh zaffa ya'ni, Kurd wa 'Arab.
And the drum beats here, and we go get the bride, we have a
wedding procession, Kurds and Arabs.
[Arabic] Kulla truh. Wa njib el-'arus, nji, wa nurgus lal-
maghrib 'ad, wa nkhalliha wa nruh 'ala byutna.
Everyone goes. We bring the bride, we come back, and we
dance until sunset, then we leave her and go to our homes.
[Arabic] E wallah. Wiya ba'dna dom.
Yes, by God. We are always together.
Waxta l-'ers 'andkun, l-'ers shu b-tutbukhu? Win çi xwarinê
çêdikin?
During the wedding with you, what do you cook for the
wedding? What food do you make?
[Arabic] Nutbukh riz, nutbukh hamud fasuliya, ya hamud
batinjan.
We cook rice, we cook sour bean stew, or sour eggplant stew.
[Arabic] Wa riz, wa frike, burghul. Nutbukh, hadha nutbukhu,
shu bidna nutbukh?
And rice, and freekeh, bulgur. We cook, this is what we
cook, what else would we cook?
[Arabic] Wa l-lahme 'ad mu bidna nidhbah? E, wa hadha li
nutbukhu.
And the meat, don't we slaughter? Yes, and that is what we
cook.
Hela wexta çêdibe 'andku l-'ers, intu wek intu l-'Ereb, Kurd
jî tên ba we?
Now when a wedding happens with you, you as Arabs, do the
Kurds come to you?
[Arabic] E! Kurd yiju sa'duna. E yiju sa'duna. E.
Yes! Kurds come and help us. Yes, they come and help us.
Yes.
Yanî dema şahiyekê çêdikin, hûn Kurd û Ereb bi hev ra alîkar
dibin?
So when you hold a celebration, you Kurds and Arabs help
each other?
Erê, erê wallah. Bi hev ra, ebeden. Îna xwandit me ra dikin,
em we xwandina wan ra dikin. Û dinê xerîb e.
Yes, yes by God. Together, absolutely. They attend our
events, we attend their events. And the world is strange
(fleeting).
Te zimanê Kurmancî da pir xweş e.
Your Kurmanji language is very good.
Kurmanciya min xweş e.
My Kurmanji is good.
Tu bi xêr hatî.
Welcome.
Ahlen we sehlen.
Navê xwarinê wek hazir kiriye? Destê we sax bin. Me dixwest
em berî hûn hazir bikin em heba na, em wextê weyî hazir
kiriye.
The name of the food you have prepared? Bless your hands. We
wanted to be here before you prepared it, but you had
already prepared it.
Me hazir kir, me got heta hûn werin xêrê.
We prepared it, we said (it should be ready) by the time you
arrive safely.
Ka navê vê xwarina xwe ji me ra bêje?
Tell us the name of this food of yours?
Xwarina me... hindî ye, navê vê, xwarina hindî.
Our food... it's Indian, the name of this, Indian food
(referring to a specific dish type, possibly 'Hindi' as in
turkey or a specific grain dish, but explains stuffed
veggies).
Hindî ye. Me bacanê reş, ew e bacanê reş me qulandine. Me gi
qewirandine.
It's 'Hindi'. We hollowed out black eggplants, that
represents the black eggplants. We fried them all.
Ew bacan e?
That is eggplant?
Erê. Gi çêkirin, wek meqdûsa, me... û patata jî me
qewirandine.
Yes. Made them all, like Makdous... and we fried potatoes
too.
Me qewirandine, û me qulkirin wek dolma çêkirin.
We fried them, and we hollowed them out and made them like
Dolma.
Na we qewirandin e?
No, you fried them?
Erê, me qewirandine. Û me gi heşwê anîn çêkirin, ke,
bexdûnûsê xwe hûr kirin.
Yes, we fried them. And we prepared all the stuffing,
chopped our parsley.
Û pîvazek xwe hûr kirin, tevhev kirin. Û çêkirin ser zeytê,
hamesandin.
And chopped an onion, mixed it together. And cooked it in
oil, sautéed it.
Û me gi heşwê çêkirin, me heşandin.
And we made all the stuffing, we stuffed them.
Û bacanê xwe jî dîsa me anîn li ber şorê xistin, û me
kelandin.
And our eggplants, we put them in salty water, and we boiled
them.
Û ser pîvazê me tirsandin, û bacanê xwe jî me berdan ser.
And we browned onions on top, and put our eggplants on top
of it.
Û hewa, şîvê me ye. Me çêkirî ji we ra, me hazir kirî.
And there, that is our dinner. We made it for you, we
prepared it.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Me dixwest em berî hûn hazir dikin em hebana...
We wanted to be here before you prepared it...
Erê, em çûbûn. Erê.
Yes, we had gone (ahead). Yes.
Na hûnê çi bikin piştî vê? Dînin ser agir?
So what will you do after this? Put it on the fire?
Em ê naha dînin ser agir ji we ra germ bikin. Gîrmê xwe yê
rizê jî çêkin.
We will put it on the fire now to warm it up for you. We
will also make our rice broth.
Hûn birinc jî çêdikin?
You make rice too?
Erê birinc jî.
Yes, rice too.
Li ber ra?
Alongside it?
Birinc. Ehlen we sehlen.
Rice. Welcome.
Sax be.
Thank you (Long live).
Bû hevalno, wîni bixwin vexwin. Û ehlen we sehlen bi te
selaqa min wa.
It became (ready) friends, so you can eat and drink. And
welcome to you, upon my head (you are welcome).
Sax be. Ka em tiştekî bipirsin ji dayê? Kerem ke, destê xwe
ke.
Thank you. Let us ask mother something? Please, go ahead.
Na, wek te got tu Kurmanc î.
Now, as you said, you are Kurmanci.
Erê.
Yes.
Dayika got yanî got em Ereb in, dema şahiyekê me çêdibê em
hinikî Kurd û Ereb bi hev ra alîkar dibin.
The mother said, meaning she said we are Arab, when we have
a celebration, we Kurds and Arabs help each other a bit.
Hûn jî wek hûn Kurd, dema hûn şahîkê çêdikin Ereb alîkarî
dikin?
You too, as Kurds, when you organize a celebration, do Arabs
help?
Çawa na. Yanî dawetek çêdibe...
Why not. Meaning if a wedding happens...
Yanî ku dawetek çêdibe, ya lahmacûn e, ya tirş û gîrmî rizê
û gîrmî frîkê û gîrmî birxul e, ser gindî jî goştê kelandî
ye.
Meaning if a wedding happens, either it is Lahmacun, or stew
and rice broth, or freekeh broth, or bulgur broth, and on
top of it is boiled meat.
Ya jî sarma, dolme ne, yanî şîvê giran. Ya jî şta bacanê reş
ana, bi kebabê dîsa çêdikin.
Or Sarma, Dolma (stuffed leaves/vegetables), meaning heavy
meals. Or something with these black eggplants, they make
them with kebab again.
Ya jî goşt li sînî rûdixin (datînin). Yanî ştûm-mitûn
çêdikin hana şîva.
Or they put meat on trays. Meaning they make all sorts of
things for these dinners.
Ê daweta xaseten, ê daweta, tirş û gîrmî ye.
But specifically for weddings, for weddings, it is stew and
broth.
Wekî gundî bi hev ra alîkarî dikin, gundanekî?
Do the villagers help each other, as villagers?
Erê. Dê cîran têne, gundî têne, merovê vê kî bin hevdra
xwarê dikin.
Yes. Neighbors come, villagers come, whoever their relatives
are, they cook together.
Û mirîk çêdibe, bêşikê hana be, Xwedê neke mirîk be, dîsa
weha ne. Dîsa bi hev ra xwarê dikin, alîkarî dikin.
And if a death occurs, undoubtedly if it is like that, God
forbid if there is a death, it is the same again. Again they
cook together, they help.
Ka em dîsa vegerin cem dayikê.
Let's go back to the mother again.
Dayê neha emrê te çiqas e?
Mother, how old are you now?
Emrê min, wallah heftê û pênc hene, ne çûçik im.
My age, by God, is seventy-five, I am not small (young).
Te emrê dirêj, Xwedê emrê te xweş bike, dayê.
Long life to you, may God make your life pleasant, mother.
Ne çûçik im, serê bavê xorto.
I am not young, upon the head of the father of the youth.
Heke ez çûçik bim, firotik me bes.
If I were young, I would have been sold (married off)
already, enough.
Tu ji vî gundî bûyî, te bûka vî gundî jî?
Were you from this village, and became a bride in this
village too?
El vê derê me ji vir jî... yanî me mêr kirî. Ji vir jî me
mêr kirî.
In this place we also... meaning we got married. From here
we also got married.
Ez qîçik bûm, paşê el vir zewicîm, manê el vî gundî.
I was little, then I got married here, meaning in this
village.
Û êdî bebê rîj, ê xelkê me ne, ne xerîb e yanî.
And the father of the beard (her husband), is our people,
not a stranger, meaning.
Em merî hev bûn?
We were relatives?
Em merî hev bûn, erê.
We were relatives, yes.
Ew jî wek te zimanê Kurmancî dizanî?
Did he also know the Kurmanji language like you?
Lê ew jî bi Kurmancî zanî û bi Erebî zanî.
Yes, he knew Kurmanji and he knew Arabic.
Erê wallah, em 'alimîn xaye, nav hev da rûniştin, wekî te
gotî.
Yes, by God, we learned it, sitting amongst each other, as
you said.
Ez tiştekî ji te bipirsim dayê.
Let me ask you something, mother.
Hewal de.
Go ahead.
Dema cejn tê, cejn.
When the Eid (holiday) comes, Eid.
Ewa.
Yes.
Hûn çi dikin? Wek hûn gund, hûn çawa bi hev ra alîkar, hûn
xwarinê we bi hev ra ye, ne bi hev ra ye?
What do you do? As a village, how do you help each other? Is
your food together, or not together?
Berê bi hev ra bû wallah ya kurê min.
In the past it was together, by God, oh my son.
Noka ne bi hev ra ye. Noka her kes şîvê xwe yî bike, şqora
jar jê kin, dewarek be, qurbanek be...
Now it is not together. Now everyone makes their own dinner,
they take from the poor/neighbor, if it is a beast
(livestock), if it is a sacrifice...
Qurbana dikin, yanî xêr e. Û ew qurbana jî bela dikin, malim
mal yanî, bela dikin.
They make sacrifices, meaning it is charity. And those
sacrifices are distributed, from house to house, they
distribute it.
Ê berê çûbû?
And how was it in the past?
Berê jî wergî bû.
In the past it was like that too.
Berê we xwarin bi hev ra dixwar?
In the past did you eat food together?
Xwarin berê bi hev ra bû erê.
Food in the past was together, yes.
We kuderê dixwar?
Where did you eat?
Wallah ser xêlê didanîn, xaniyo elçax e.
By God, they put it on the tribe/group, the houses were
low/simple.
Hindik şîn î sîtil danî, ê gîrmî rizê danî, ê nanê bi rûn
danî, û ê ew çiye, ew sembûsek danî, sembûsek.
A few would put out the cauldron (sîtil), put out rice
broth, put out bread with oil/fat, and put out that, what is
it, that Sembûsek, Sembûsek.
Ê dînin rêz dînin. Ê gi bixwin, fatiha xwe bixwînin, û ê
bela bin herin mala xwe.
They put them in a row. They all eat, read their Fatiha
(prayer), and disperse to go to their homes.
Siheta we xweş be, destê te sax be.
Bon appetit (Health to you), bless your hands.
Siheta te xweş, Xwedê te rabike kurê min. Sax bî.
Health to you, may God raise you up my son. Long live.
Naha wînê, we agir... wînê agir hazir bikin?
Now you will, the fire... will you prepare the fire?
Agirê xwe em ê vêxin. Em ê şîvê xwe bixin ser.
We will light our fire. We will put our dinner on it.
Em ê birincê xwe jî wînin.
We will bring our rice too.
Û dînin kêlekê.
And put it on the side.
Belhetkoyî germ bin. Wê sifra xwe dînin.
So that they get warm. We will set our table.
Û wînê bixwin, û sehla we.
And you will eat, and welcome to you.
Ebdulhemîd Xezal wekî şêxê, ango serokê eşîra Amîrat bû.
Abdulhamid Ghazal was the sheikh, meaning the leader of the
Amirat tribe.
Û wî gelek pirsgirêkên xelkê eşîrê çareser dikirin.
And he resolved many problems of the people of the tribe.
Berî heşt salan, Ebdulhemîd Xezal koça dawî kir.
Eight years ago, Abdulhamid Ghazal passed away.
Û kurê wî Ebdulqadir Xezal, şûna bavê xwe girt û ew jî mîna
bavê xwe pirsgirêkan çareser dike û bi mêvanan re rûdine û
deriyê wî ji her kesî re vekiriye, û ew jî xwediyê kerem û
merdemî û serdilovaniya xwe ye.
And his son Abdulqadir Ghazal took his father's place, and
he too, like his father, resolves problems, sits with
guests, and his door is open to everyone, and he is a master
of generosity, humanity, and compassion.
Şêx Ebdulqadir xwedî odayeke, ku mêvan tê de pêşwazî
dikirin.
Sheikh Abdulqadir has a room (Madafe), where guests were
welcomed.
Û bi lavayan, ango bi zikir û Quranê nexweşî derman dikirin.
And through prayers, meaning through Dhikr and Quran, they
treated illnesses.
Odaya mêvanan bi navê medafê di gund de hebû.
The guest room was known as "Madafe" in the village.
Weke cîhê civîna endamên eşîrê bû.
It was like a meeting place for the members of the tribe.
Û tê de hemû pirsgirêk dihatin gotûbêjkirin û çareserkirin.
And in it, all problems were discussed and resolved.
Û xelk ji gund û gundên derdora, lê kom dibûn.
And people from the village and surrounding villages would
gather there.
Em hatin derbasî mala Şêx Ebdulqadir bûn.
We came and entered the house of Sheikh Abdulqadir.
Tu bi xêr hatî, ser seran, ser çavan.
You are welcome, upon heads, upon eyes.
Xwedê ji te razî be, ehlen we sehlen. Bi xêr hatî.
May God be pleased with you, welcome. Welcome.
Sax be. Em te nas bikin?
Thank you. May we know you?
Navê min Şêx Ebdulqadir, mi ra dibêjin.
My name is Sheikh Abdulqadir, they call me.
Ez lawê Şêx Ebdulhemîd im. Şêxlerê di Bablîtê.
I am the son of Sheikh Abdulhamid. The Sheikhs in Bablit.
Em di mantiqê de marûf in bi mala Şêx Ebdulqadir bi me ra
dibêjin.
We are known in the region as the House of Sheikh
Abdulqadir, they call us.
Û ez jî niha li şûna bavikê xwe Şêx Ebdulhemîd, ez şûna wî
şêxliqê dikim yanî.
And I am now in the place of my father Sheikh Abdulhamid, I
perform the Sheikh duties in his place, meaning.
Û em însanê şêx in, terîqeta me Rifaî ye.
And we are Sheikh people, our order (Tariqa) is Rifa'i.
Û ev jî mala min e, tekiya min e.
And this is my house, my Tekkiye (Sufi lodge).
Û win her çi kengî di cive, naha em derbas bûn maşallah
gîştî li vir in?
And you, whenever it gathers... just now we entered and
Mashallah everyone is here?
Ê her pêncşem cem me zikir heye.
Yes, every Thursday we have Dhikr (remembrance ceremony).
Nexweş tên cem me, derd tên, wî tu nîşta... nexweş tên cem
me, xuca dikin, ba wî xwa pê ye yanî.
Sick people come to us, troubles come... sick people come to
us, we treat them, meaning those who have "wind"
(spirits/possession) on them.
Û em ser da dixwînin, banka dikin Xwedê û çako dikin, Rebbê
alemiyan dike tabî.
And we read over them, we call upon God and treat them, the
Lord of the worlds cures them.
Xwedê lê diwa rehmê înşallah.
May God grant mercy upon them, God willing.
Ê heriyê destpêkê Şêx Ebdulqadir e?
And the very beginning was Sheikh Abdulqadir?
Na, kalkê me... Şêx Ebdulqadir bavikê bavikê min e.
No, our grandfather... Sheikh Abdulqadir is my father's
father.
Kalkê me, heka hema heft, şeş-heft navê ji te ra bêjim yanî,
çend bavê ji te ra bêjim ji pîrê min.
Our grandfather, roughly seven, six-seven names I can tell
you, several fathers back I can tell you from my ancestor.
Ê kani suretê kalkê min li vir hene te bibînî.
Look, the photos of my grandfather are here so you can see.
Seke ştêra hewal dim.
Look, I will show you.
Ka ev çiye? Ji me ra li ser vê bêje.
What is this? Tell us about this.
Heva hekîb e, vêra dibên hekîb.
This is a saddlebag, they call this a hekîb.
Ka ev çiye? Ji me ra li ser vê bêje.
What is this? Tell us about this.
Heva hekîb e, vêra dibên hekîb.
This is a saddlebag, they call this a hekîb.
Ka ev çiye? Ji me ra li ser vê bêje.
What is this? Tell us about this.
Heva hekîb e, vêra dibên hekîb.
This is a saddlebag, they call this a hekîb.