Belê temaşevanên hêja.
Yes, dear viewers.
Vê hefteyê jî me berê xwe daye herêma Şêrawa.
This week, we have headed to the Sherawa region.
Vê hefteyê jî em ê gundê Kişte'arê nas bikin.
This week, we will get to know the village of Kishte'ar.
Ev gund tê naskirin bi biratiya gelan.
This village is known for the brotherhood of peoples.
Bi sed sala Kurd û Ereb bi hevra jiyan dikin.
For hundreds of years, Kurds and Arabs have lived together
here.
Em ê vê hefteyê jî gundê Kişte'arê nas bikin, bi hevra
bişopînin.
This week we will get to know the village of Kishte'ar,
let's watch together.
De ka derbas bin, em gundê Kişte'arê nas bikin.
Come on, let's enter and get to know the village of
Kishte'ar.
Belê, em derbasî gundê Kişte'arê bûn.
Yes, we have entered the village of Kishte'ar.
Em hatine mala rûniştinê jî.
We have come to the guest house as well.
Kesêt vê gundê jî hatine derdora me, em spasiya wan dikin.
The people of this village have gathered around us, we thank
them.
Bi Kurd û Erebê xwe.
With their Kurds and their Arabs.
Lê bi rastî jî, dema em berê derbasî vî gundî dibin.
But truly, when we first entered this village.
Qet tu nizanî ferq cûdabûn hene di navbera Kurd û Ereban.
You would never know there is a difference or separation
between Kurds and Arabs.
Meriv nizane kîjan Kurd e, kîjan Ereb e.
One does not know who is Kurdish and who is Arab.
Em spasiya wan dikin hatine derdora me.
We thank them for gathering around us.
Hinekî em ê dîroka vê gundî nas bikin.
We will get to know a bit of the history of this village.
Hinekî biratiya gelan a vê gundî nas bikin.
We will get to know the brotherhood of peoples in this
village a bit.
Hinekî taybetmendiya vê gundî nas bikin.
We will get to know a bit about the characteristics of this
village.
Merheba Hecî.
Hello Hajji.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Ya'tîk el-afiye.
May God give you health.
Allah y'afîk, ehlen we sehlen.
May God give you health, welcome.
Nita'rref 'eleyk?
Can we get to know you?
Mihemed Elî, muxtarê Kişte'ar, ehlen we sehlen fîkum, mît
selamê.
Mohammed Ali, the Mukhtar of Kishte'ar, welcome to you all,
a hundred greetings.
Spas dikim. Apê Mihemed spas bo te jî.
Thank you. Uncle Mohammed, thank you too.
Mît selamê.
A hundred greetings.
Em te jî nas bikin?
Can we get to know you too?
Ez Mihemed Îsa.
I am Mohammed Isa.
Ser çavê min, tu apê Mihemed.
You are welcome [on my eyes], Uncle Mohammed.
Ji Kişte'arê.
From Kishte'ar.
Ser çavê min, ji welatiyê vê derê. Tu Kurd î?
You are welcome, a citizen of this place. Are you Kurdish?
Ez Kurmanc im.
I am Kurmanji [Kurdish].
Tu Kurmanc î?
You are Kurmanji?
Kurd im.
I am Kurdish.
Û Apê Mihemed ev jî Ereb e?
And Uncle Mohammed [referring to the Mukhtar], is he Arab?
Ereb e.
He is Arab.
Bi rastî mirov nizane, ferq nake kîjan Kurd e kîjan Ereb e.
Truly one doesn't know, it makes no difference who is
Kurdish and who is Arab.
Na, yek e.
No, it is one.
Ser çavê min.
You are welcome.
Apê Mihemed destpêkê ji cem te destpê bikin.
Uncle Mohammed, let's start with you first.
Kerem ke.
Go ahead.
Hinekî em gundê we nas bikin.
Let's get to know your village a bit.
Navê gundê we ji ku hatiye? Kesek tê de jiyan dike, ji kîjan
malbatê ne?
Where did your village name come from? Who lives in it,
which families are they from?
Ez nizanim, dibêjin Kişte'ar, zêde wan tişta em nizanin.
I don't know, they call it Kishte'ar, we don't know much
about those things.
Em zanin Kişte'ar e, bes Kişte'ar.
We know it is Kishte'ar, just Kishte'ar.
Hûn nizanin navê wî ji ku hatiye, çi ye, em nizanin?
You don't know where the name comes from, what it is, we
don't know?
Tê bêje gelek caran navên gundê me hatine guhertin.
You could say the names of our village have been changed
many times.
Jiber ku her demekê, hinek tê hukm dikin.
Because in every era, different people ruled here.
Berê Romana hebû, Fransa hebû, Tirkiya hebû, her henekek
zimanekî hat kirin.
Before there were Romans, there was France, there was
Turkey, every group brought a language.
Kişte'ar, deha wilo tê gotin.
Kishte'ar, that's what it is called now.
Lê ew miletê vê derê hêjî hew milet e?
But are the people of this place still the same people?
Hew milet e, hewa. Bes her demekê de hinek kes hatine vira.
It's the same people, yes. Just that in every era some
people came here.
Belê.
Yes.
Na, gundê we wî ji çend malbata têne? Na em bêjin gundê we
Kurd û Ereb in he?
Now, how many families does your village consist of? Or
let's say, your village is Kurds and Arabs, right?
Em cîranê hev in, em û Cilbirê.
We are neighbors to each other, us and Jilbul [neighboring
village].
Wan rûbar in.
They are across the river.
Ji gundê Cilbirê û wî derbasî vir bûne?
Did they cross over here from the village of Jilbul?
Derbasî vir bûn, hatine vir.
They crossed here, they came here.
Wî hatine nav erdê xwe?
Did they come onto their own land?
Erdê xwe.
Their own land.
Na, navbera gundê we û Cilbirê ve çiqas metre heye?
Now, how many meters are there between your village and
Jilbul?
Sê kîlo metre.
Three kilometers.
Sê kîlo metre?
Three kilometers?
Sê kîlo metre.
Three kilometers.
Sê kîlo metre navber a we û Cilbirê?
Three kilometers between you and Jilbul?
Wî hatine nav erdê xwe, wa hatine vira rûniştine, jimeş karê
kîmya û tişta.
They came onto their own land, they came and settled here,
because of the chemical work and things.
Em ê werine cem te jî.
We will come to you as well.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Allah yusellmek ya reb.
God bless you.
Hecî, entum min eyna eşîre?
Hajji, which tribe are you from?
Neḥna eşîret Neîm.
We are the Naim tribe.
Neîm?
Naim?
Ne'em.
Yes.
Walla, bil-qerye entum kem êle fîya? Kem eşîre fîya?
By God, in the village how many families are there? How many
tribes are there?
Neḥna êle weḥde el-qerye, ma fî neḥna.. ma fî 'enna la Kurdî
wala Erebî.
We are one family in the village, we don't have... we don't
have "Kurdish" or "Arab".
Neḥna êle weḥde, wa bêt waḥed.
We are one family, and one house.
Muta'ayişîn ma'a ba'ḍna min mêtên sene, wa ekter min mêtên
sene.
Living together for two hundred years, and more than two
hundred years.
Wa la zilna muta'ayişîn, ehel, wa ixwe...
And we are still living together, family, and brothers...
Wa bêt waḥed, wa mutezewwijîn min ba'ḍna el-ba'ḍ.
And one house, and we are intermarried with one another.
Wa killiyatna qa'dîn ma'a ba'ḍna, wa ma fî şî bênatna el-
ḥemdulillah rebb el-'alemîn.
And we are all sitting together, and there is nothing [bad]
between us, praise be to God, Lord of the worlds.
El-ḥemdulillah. Hela entum Neîm, fî ẍêrkom keman?
Praise be to God. Now you are Naim, are there others too?
Fî Ṭeyy keman hon.
There is [the tribe of] Tayy here as well.
Keman?
As well?
Ê, 'aîlet Ṭeyy.
Yes, the Tayy family.
Mîn îco qebil, entum la hinne?
Who came first, you or them?
Neḥna jîna, el-esas el-ḍê'a, evvel waḥed jiddî îja hûwe
Muṣṭafa.
We came, the foundation of the village, the first one was my
grandfather, he was Mustafa.
Îja Muṣṭafa la hon.
Mustafa came here.
Bi'tibar fî Ekrad ḥewalêna...
Since there were Kurds around us...
Raḥ... ṣaḥûlo Misto, raḥet 'alêna Bêt Misto, wa hella neḥna
Bêt Misto.
They went... they called him Misto, so "House of Misto"
stuck to us, and now we are the House of Misto.
Ê meḍbûḍ, walla Ekrad bisemû Misto.
Yes exactly, by God Kurds call [Mustafa] Misto.
Eymen, Ehmed biqulûlo Êḥo.
Right, Ahmed they call Eho.
Mihemed biqulûlo Meḥme.
Mohammed they call Mehme.
Ê hêk.
Yes, like that.
Wel-ḥemdulillah rebb el-'alemîn, killna muta'ayişîn ma'a
ba'ḍna el-ba'ḍ.
And praise be to God, Lord of the worlds, we are all living
together with one another.
Ma fî tefrîqa bênatna, la fî hada biqûl Kurdî, wa la fî hada
biqûl Erebî.
There is no division between us, no one says "Kurd" and no
one says "Arab".
Wa killiyatna ehel, wa ixwe, wa 'ayşîn ma'a ba'ḍna el-ba'ḍ.
And we are all family, and brothers, and living with one
another.
Şo ṣarlkon, ye'nî ma bita'ref kem sene entum hon?
How long have you been, meaning you don't know how many
years you've been here?
Walla ana ba'ref, ye'nî min mêtên sene ubbehatna byeḥkû...
By God I know, meaning for 200 years our fathers have been
talking...
Min mêtên sene wa hel-ṣob, ma mna'ref.
From 200 years and before that, we don't know.
Minên îju, ma ba'ref.
Where they came from, I don't know.
Byeḥkû inno min mêtên sene qebil...
They say that from 200 years prior...
Eşîret Neîm ketîr.
The Naim tribe is large.
Eşâyir Neîm ktîre, melyane Sûriya killa eşâyir Neîm.
The Naim tribes are many, all of Syria is full of Naim
tribes.
Ḥetta fî bil-Efrîn keman fî kem qerye?
Even in Afrin there are also a few villages?
Fî b'Efrîn, fî...
There are in Afrin, there are...
'En ṭerîq el-Bab fî...
Towards Al-Bab there are...
Fî bi-Ḥeleb, fî 'el-Bab, fî b-Ḥema, fî b-Dêr el-Zûr, fî bi-
Reqa...
There are in Aleppo, in Al-Bab, in Hama, in Deir ez-Zor, in
Raqqa...
Fî eşâyir... eşîre kbîre, ma inno şû ismo...
There are tribes... a big tribe, not just, what's it
called...
Eşâyir Neîm kbîre.
The Naim tribes are big.
Ma inno 'eded mewcûd bi-qerye weḥde, la.
It's not that a number is present in just one village, no.
Mewcûd bi-kill el-muḥafeẓat hay el-eşîre.
This tribe is present in all the governorates.
Ê.
Yes.
Belê, Apê Mihemed dibêje ev jî ji eşîra Neîm e.
Yes, Uncle Mohammed says he is also from the Naim tribe.
Dibêje ew eşîra me jî li piraniya Sûriyê li gund û dera
belav kirî ne.
He says our tribe is scattered across most of Syria in
villages and places.
Li rojhilatê de, em bêjin milê Dêrazorê da, li milê din da,
heta Hemayê...
In the east, let's say towards Deir ez-Zor, in other parts,
up to Hama...
Li Efrînê da, gelek ew eşîre belav kirî ne.
In Afrin, that tribe is very scattered.
Dibêje em nizanin çiqas sal em hatine vira.
He says we don't know how many years ago we came here.
Lê dibêje dema derbasî vir bû, kalikê wan navê wî Mistefa
bû.
But he says when they entered here, their grandfather's name
was Mustafa.
Ew derbasî vir bû.
He entered here.
Ehlen we sehlen fîk.
Welcome to you.
Em bizivirin cem te.
Let's turn back to you.
Ahlen.
Welcome.
Apê Mihemed.
Uncle Mohammed.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Na, me hinekî nas kir gundê we.
Now, we got to know your village a bit.
Hinekî te jî qala wan kir, hinekî Apê Mihemed jî qala wan
kir.
You talked about it a bit, and Uncle Mohammed [referring to
Hajji] talked about it a bit.
Lê em hinekî ser biratiya gelan...
But let's [talk] a bit about the brotherhood of peoples...
Enexwî em bêjin behsa şahiyan.
That is, let's talk about celebrations.
Enexwî miriyan...
That is, funerals [deaths]...
Evîn çawa bi hevra dabeş dikin?
How do you share these together?
Şahiyên wan çawa ne? Şahiyên we çawa ne?
How are their celebrations? How are your celebrations?
Hûn çawa bi hevra dibin alîkar?
How do you help each other?
Wella em efraha me giyek e.
Well, our joys are all one.
Şahîna kê hebe giştî yek e?
Whoever has a celebration, it's all one?
Şabîna kî hebe giştî yek e. Adet û teqalîdê me yek e.
Whoever has a wedding, it's all one. Our customs and
traditions are one.
Neslê me, teqrîben Kurmanc û Ereb giyek e.
Our lineage, almost Kurmanji and Arab, is all one.
Malek, bi hesibîna malek e.
One house, considered as one house.
Efraha, hezana, der e, çi bû...
Joys, sorrows, outside, whatever happens...
Em giyek in.
We are all one.
Em ji hevdû jî zewicîne?
Have we married from each other too?
Em ji hevdû jî zewicîne.
We have married from each other too.
Adet û teqalîd.
Customs and traditions.
Heta cil û bergê we jî teqrîben yek e?
Are even your clothes almost the same?
Giyek e.
All one.
Belê, cilê me yek, lêyê me giyek e.
Yes, our clothes are one, our way is all one.
Erê, wekî me xat kirine, em jî wane wekî wan, em jî wekî wan
e.
Yes, just like we have done, we are like them, and we are
like them.
Malek e, bi hesibîna malekê cem me.
One house, considered as one house among us.
Bes.
Just that.
Belê.
Yes.
Naha em behsa, hinekî debara jiyana xwe.
Now let's talk a bit about making a living.
Gundê we bi çi dijîn?
What does your village live on?
Na em bêjin bi çandinî, me dît ne febrîqe li vira hene,
me'mel li dera hene.
Let's say agriculture, we didn't see factories here, or
workshops around here.
Na, em genim diçînin, ceh diçînin...
No, we plant wheat, we plant barley...
Nok diçînin, nîsk û nok.
We plant chickpeas, lentils and chickpeas.
Wekî din çi heye di gund da?
What else is there in the village?
Tiştek tune wolla, bes zerîat heye.
Nothing by God, there is just agriculture.
Zehmet? Hene?
Is it hard? Is there any?
Ya'nî ma'amil, tiştek tune.
Meaning workshops, there is nothing.
Na na, me'mel tune, tişt tune.
No no, no workshops, nothing.
Tiştekî din tune.
Nothing else.
Û hûn debara xwe giş bi çandiniyê dikin?
And you make your living entirely from agriculture?
Giş bi zîraetê ye.
All by agriculture.
Zeytûn hene?
Are there olives?
Zeytûn hene, deka.
There are olives, sure.
Ya'nî çiqas darê zeytûna heye?
Meaning how many olive trees are there?
Ya'nî sed, sê sed dar têne.
Meaning a hundred, three hundred trees roughly.
Têne? Hinek dikin?
Roughly? Some do?
Hinek dikin.
Some do.
Ew zeytê cem we jî xweş derdikeve wekî yên Efrînê?
Does the oil by you come out good like Afrin's?
Ewa yalla erdn e.
Yes by God, it is our land.
Erdn e.
It is our land.
Erdê we bi xêr û bereket e.
Your land is bountiful.
Belê, em li ba hev ne, zeytûnê cem me wekî yê wan e.
Yes, we are next to each other, our olives are like theirs.
Rind e.
It's good.
Bêhna wan xweş e?
Do they smell good?
Bêhna wan mekin e, zeytûnê cem me yê ewil in.
Their smell is strong, our olives are prime/first-rate.
Kerta zêr tiştekî bibêjî?
Anything golden [valuable] to say?
Wele siheta we xweş.
By God, health to you.
Spas.
Thanks.
Hecî.
Hajji.
Tḥibb tḍîf şî? Teḥkî şî ye'nî?
Would you like to add anything? Say anything?
Teslem, walla mît selamê, ehlen we sehlen fîkum.
Bless you, by God a hundred greetings, welcome to you all.
Mît selamê b-ḍê'etkon, wa bên ahelkon, wa naskon, wa ehlen
we sehlen fîkum.
A hundred greetings in your village, among your family, and
your people, and welcome to you all.
Teslem ya reb.
Bless you, Lord.
Mît selamê.
A hundred greetings.
Allah ya'ṭîk el-afiye.
God give you health.
Mît ehlen we sehlen, ehlen we sehlen, şerreftûna, mît ehlen
we sehlen.
A hundred welcomes, welcome, you honored us, a hundred
welcomes.
Spas. Siheta te jî xweş. Ew jî xweş.
Thanks. Health to you too. That was good.
Û cuma te jî ya xweş, gelekî spas.
And have a good Friday [gathering], thank you very much.
Dema ku mirov derbasî gundê Kişte'arê dibe...
When one enters the village of Kishte'ar...
Çavê nû, seranser li şûnpingul û bumbayan dikeve.
New eyes immediately fall upon the traces of bullets and
bombs.
Xuya dibe ji mirov ra...
It becomes apparent to one...
Gundê Keşta'arê girêdayî navçeya Şêrewa ya kantona Efrînê,
25 kîlometreyî li bakurê rojhilatê bajarokê Basûtê û 30
kîlometreyî li rojhilatê bajarê Efrînê dikeve.
The village of Keşta'ar belongs to the Sherawa district of
the Afrin canton, located 25 kilometers northeast of the
town of Basouta and 30 kilometers east of the city of Afrin.
Û her wiha 6 kîlometreyî li başûrê bajarokê Dêr Cemal e.
And it is also 6 kilometers south of the town of Deir Jamal.
Berê gund girêdayî navçeya Erfadê ya kantona Şehba bû. Lê
piştî şoreşa Rojavayê Kurdistanê, tev li kantona Efrînê hate
kirin.
Previously, the village was attached to the Tel Rifaat
district of the Shahba canton. But after the Rojava
Revolution, it was incorporated into the Afrin canton.
Tê texmîn kirin ku navê gund ji navê Qesr hatiye. Lê di
serdema Fransiyan da tîpa "K" lê hatiye zêde kirin.
It is estimated that the village's name comes from the word
"Qesr" (Castle). But during the French era, the letter "K"
was added to it.
Gelek şûnwarên ji tablo û paykeran li gund û derdora gund
têne dîtin. Ew jî kûrahiya dîroka gund diyar dike.
Many antiquities, such as tablets and statues, are found in
and around the village. This reveals the historical depth of
the village.
Gundê Keşta'arê ji herdu pêkhateyên Kurd û Ereb pêk tê. Û
herdu di navbera ahangiyekê de dijîn.
The village of Keşta'ar consists of both Kurdish and Arab
components. And both live amidst a harmony.
Di şahî û xemgîniyan de wek yek pêkhate tev digerin.
In joy and sorrow, they act as a single component.
Belê, îro jî em li gundê Keşta'arê digerin. Di vê gundî da
emê jî behsa... gotin malek heye, terzî ye, jinek terzî ye.
Yes, today we are visiting the village of Keşta'ar. In this
village, we will mention... they said there is a house here,
a tailor, a female tailor.
Ev mala hanê... ew jinek jî, kesek ji pêkhateya Ereb e. Ka
em herin derbas bin.
This house here... that woman is a person from the Arab
component. Let us go and enter.
Merheba xaltî.
Hello auntie.
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Nata'arraf aleyki? (Bi te nas bin?)
May we know who you are?
Ahlan wa sahlan. Ana el-xeyyata Hamida.
Welcome. I am the seamstress Hamida.
Enti el-xeyyata?
You are the seamstress?
Aywa, tfaddalu.
Yes, please come in.
Ma'arifna el-Kurdi... şlon?
Our Kurdish acquaintances... how are they?
Tfaddalu, ahlan wa sahlan.
Please come in, welcome.
Esselamu Aleykum.
Peace be upon you.
Şar senelik 'am tiştexlî xeyyata?
How many years have you been working as a seamstress?
15 sene walla bexeyyit.
15 years, by God, I have been sewing.
15 sene bedik karî dikî?
You've been doing this work for 15 years?
Ana behkî Kurdî û Erebî, mafî mişkile?
I speak Kurdish and Arabic, is that a problem?
Mafî mişkile, ahlan wa sahlan.
No problem, welcome.
Min weyn t'ellemtî? Şkût ewe fêr bî?
Where did you learn? How did you learn this?
T'ellemt walla... awwal şî immî xeyyata kanet. Btxeyyit, we
ana zxîre t'ellemt.
I learned, by God... first of all, my mother was a
seamstress. She sewed, and I learned when I was young.
Weyn kanet immik? Bi-deiy'a, la bil-medîne?
Where was your mother? In the village or in the city?
Bi-deiy'a walla kanû. Ahli min Hayyan, immî xeyyata bi-
Hayyan kanet.
In the village, honestly. My family is from Hayyan, my
mother was a seamstress in Hayyan.
Wa ana jît tjawwazt 15 sene hon, sar 'am bxeyyit kaman.
Hamatî btxeyyit, jît reht marast nefs el-xyata.
And I came here, got married 15 years ago, and started
sewing too. My mother-in-law sews; I came and practiced the
same sewing.
Hamatik kaman? Immik kaman?
Your mother-in-law too? Your mother too?
Immî kan awwal şî, kint 'indî fikra 'anna. Weqt jît hon
hamatî 'am btxeyyit, nefs eş-şî rji't kemmelt.
My mother was first, I had an idea about it. When I came
here, my mother-in-law was sewing, so I continued the same
thing.
He walê kaman mekînat? Ew mekîne fil-mekînat?
Was it these machines? Or those machines among the machines?
La, kan hadok el-faraşe, er-rijil. 'Ala ijrêna nxeyyit.
No, those were the "Butterfly" ones, the foot [pedal] ones.
We sewed with our feet.
Bedon kahraba?
Without electricity?
Mafî, 'ala hal-qşat we 'ala ijrêna nxeyyit.
None, [we worked] on the belt and sewed with our feet.
Dibêje 15 sal e ez vî karî dikim. Karê terzîtiyê dikim.
She says, "I have been doing this work for 15 years. I do
tailoring work."
Dibêje dema ez li mala bavê xwe, dayika xwe ew terzî bû.
Piştî ew zewicî hat vê gundî, li vir jî ew xwasiya wê, ew jî
terzî bû. Hinekî jî jê fêr bû.
She says when she was at her father's house, her mother was
a tailor. After she married and came to this village, here
her mother-in-law was also a tailor. She learned some from
her as well.
Dibêje berê jî ev makîne tinebûn. Berê makîne hebûn, ew yên
bê kahrabe bûn, bê elektrîk bûn. Li niha jî ev makîne
hatine.
She says previously these machines didn't exist. Before,
there were machines that were non-electric, without
electricity. Now these machines have come.
De se'alek 'al-mekîne. Eyna mekîne kwayse? Hay la hebla?
Just a question about the machine. Which machine is good?
This one or that one?
Walla awwalî kan kways.
Honestly, the first one was good.
Ma biddo kahraba, ma...?
It didn't need electricity, no...?
Ma biddo kahraba, li'anno imta ma biddî abruk axeyyit. Halla
ma bahsin iza mafî kahraba.
It didn't need electricity, because whenever I wanted, I
could sit and sew. Now I can't if there is no electricity.
Ma bahsin iştexil, xalas bestanna.
I can't work, that's it, I wait.
Ya'ni berê ew makînên berê baş bûn, ji ber ku kahraba,
elektrîk nedixwestin. Ji vê baştir bûn.
Meaning, before, those old machines were good because they
didn't require power, electricity. They were better than
this.
Bes hay asra'.
But this is faster.
Eh asra', tab'an, we xyata aqwa sî bat baxeyyit 'aleyha.
Yes faster, of course, and stronger sewing, I sew on it.
Bes mişan kahraba hekî.
But just because of the electricity, it's like this.
Mişan kahraba, li'anno bitfaddil hadîk. Beştexil 'aleyha.
Because of the electricity, because you prefer that one. I
work on it.
Halla awwalî weqt kintî bêt... bêt ehlik. Immik kan btxeyyit
bes la 'arabî? La kaman zeyy Kurdî kan...?
Now, first, when you were at the house... your family's
house. Did your mother sew only for Arabs? Or also Kurdish
fashion was...?
La, kan bes la 'arabî, xeyyitûnî.
No, it was only for Arabs, they sewed for me.
Weqt jîtî hon, sirtî txeyyitî 'arabî we Kurdî?
When you came here, you started sewing Arabic and Kurdish?
Min weyn t'ellemtî? Şlon t'ellemtî?
Where did you learn? How did you learn?
Hamatî kan hon btxeyyit awwalî, la ahl ed-deiy'a. We
t'ellemt... xaleg, xyat Kurdî wa baxeyyit. Tûl 'umrna 'ayşîn
nihna we jíranna dom.
My mother-in-law was sewing here first, for the village
people. And I learned... the creation, Kurdish sewing and I
sew it. All our lives we have been living here, us and our
neighbors, always.
Dibêje piştî hat vira, ew xwasiya wê, ew cilê Kurdî û Erebî
didûrît. Ji ber ku ji wê fêr bûye.
She says after coming here, her mother-in-law sewed Kurdish
and Arabic clothes. Because she learned from her.
Halla bedik teşrahîlna şlon... farq beyn libs Kurdî we libs
'arabî.
Now I want you to explain to us how... the difference
between Kurdish dress and Arab dress.
Bi-saraha ana dexelt 'al-deiy'atkon, ma şift hel-farq.
Honestly, I entered your village, I didn't see that
difference.
Ya'ni bişûf el-niswan, ma bta'rfî eyna Kurdî we eyna 'arabî.
Ma şift fî farq.
Meaning, looking at the women, you don't know which is
Kurdish and which is Arab. I didn't see a difference.
Bes inti şlon el-libskon? Libs 'arabî we libs Kurdî. Na'n
'arif farq ya'ni.
But you, how is your dress? Arab dress and Kurdish dress. We
want to know the difference.
Mafî farq walla. Bil-'aks rob el-cirtik bilbisû ahla
byilbaq, we mni'jibna aktar.
There is no difference really. On the contrary, the "Cirtik"
dress (traditional patchwork style), we wear it, it suits
nicely, and we like it more.
Halla hay... hay libs Efrînî hay bu?
Now this... this is Afrinian dress, is it?
Ê.
Yes.
We libs 'arabî?
And Arab dress?
Libs 'arabî, hay libs 'arabî. Hon.
Arab dress, this is Arab dress. Here.
Libs 'arabî. Hay.
Arab dress. This one.
Fî xêr model?
Are there other models?
Fî hay 'arabî kaman.
There is this Arabic one as well.
Fî hek modelat hadol kaman 'arabî, ya'ni byilbisû.
There are models like this, these are also Arabic, meaning
they wear them.
Ê. Hadol hadîsat hadol.
This one too?
Yes. These are modern ones, these.
Ê. Hek 'am bixeyyitlon min hal-modelat killo byilbisû. Min
awwalî baxeyyit hek.
Yes. Like this, I am sewing for them from all these models
they wear. Since the beginning I sew like this.
Ew yê Kurdî?
And the Kurdish one?
Ê. Efrînî.
Yes. Afrinian.
Û Kurdî hez dikin?
And do they like the Kurdish one?
Ê. Efrînî.
Yes. Afrinian.
Hadûl yên Efrînî.
These are the Afrinian ones.
Fî şî sa'b 'aleykî trik tixeyyitî Kurdî we 'arabî?
Is there anything hard for you, sewing Kurdish and Arabic?
La, mosî, mafî şî sa'b. Killo sahl 'aleyy.
No, not really, nothing is hard. Everything is easy for me.
Btxeyyitî la hon bes la qarye? Inson qarye le bijû kaman min
berra?
Do you sew for here, just for the village? The village
people, or do they come from outside too?
Min berra walla, min Julbon bijû. Walla xyata 'indî min
Julbonko hadol 'am baxeyyito fî bil-hayy mekîne hay min
Julbon bijû la 'indî bxeyyit.
From outside actually, from Julbul they come. Honestly I
have sewing from Julbul, those I am sewing, there is this
machine... they come from Julbul to me to sew.
Ê. Hadîk tenye 'al-habl min Julbon.
Yes. That other one is for the cord/piping, from Julbul.
Tfaddalî la hon, tfaddalî.
Please come here, please.
Ha. Hay la Julbon kaman.
Here. This is for Julbul as well.
Ya'ni bijû min berra we bijû min berra, ê, baxeyyitlon
kaman. Min bas ed-deiy'a, kill el-'alem bijû. Bijî min Ibbîn
la 'indî. Killon baxeyyitlon.
Meaning they come from outside and come from outside, yes, I
sew for them too. From just the village [and] all the people
come. They come from Ibbin to me. I sew for all of them.
Vêca her du tişt têne gotin.
So both things are being said.
Dibêje kesên tên vira, dibêjin ji gundên pir tên.
She says people who come here, she says they come from many
villages.
Dibêje ew ferq cida bûn, ji tîne navbera Kurmancî û Erebî
da, ew cilê wan yane. Dibê qet piskirêk jî nîne. Dema dûrî
yane, piskirêkê wê qet nîne.
She says that difference was distinct, brought between
Kurmanji and Arabic, regarding their clothes. She says there
is no problem at all. When sewing, she has no problem at
all.
Û halla... bes inti 'am tiştexilî?
And now... are you working alone?
Fî hada xêrik bil-qarye la bes inti lihalek?
Is there anyone other than you in the village or just you
alone?
Fî wahde tenye bes ma bta'rif txeyyit cirtik. 'Ayit bes
'arabî btxeyyit.
There is another one, but she doesn't know how to sew
"Cirtik" (traditional patchwork). She sews, she only sews
Arabic [style].
Bes 'arabî btxeyyit?
She only sews Arabic?
Şû isma?
What is her name?
Isma Fatme.
Her name is Fatma.
Ma bta'rif xeyyit hadol?
Fatma.
She doesn't know how to sew these?
La, ma bta'rif.
No, she doesn't know.
Halla, da ma... ma sa'b 'aleykî?
Now, this... isn't it hard for you?
Ê sa'b walla. Beştexlo babrok killo 'ala el-ibre, bxallis
ha-sjef lahatta ba'da axeyyit er-rob, aqiss er-rob we
axeyyto. Şeğle sa'be.
Yes, it is hard, honestly. I work sitting entirely over the
needle, I finish these facings/linings, until after that I
sew the dress, cut the dress and sew it. It's hard work.
Û... Halla şqad, kull fistan şqad btaxdî?
And... Now how much, for every dress how much do you take?
Walla 3000 xyato halla sar.
Honestly, the sewing is 3,000 [Syrian Pounds] now.
3000. Awwalî şkan? Qabil sewre?
3,000. How much was it at first? Before the revolution?
Qabil sewre kan 800 xyato.
Before the revolution the sewing was 800.
800, halla 3000 sar.
800, now it has become 3,000.
3000 sar. Wel-'arabî şqad?
It became 3,000. And the Arabic [dress] how much?
'Arabî awwalî 500 halla sar 1500.
Arabic was 500 at first, now it has become 1,500.
1500. Arxas ya'ni hadîk?
1,500. So that one is cheaper?
Ê arxas he. Mafî sa'b, sahle.
Yes, that is cheaper. There is no difficulty, it's easy.
La xeyyit sjefat hadol, baxeyyit rob 'arabî. We birja' la
xeyyit rob, sar robên.
To sew these facings/linings, I [could] sew an Arabic dress.
And when I go back to sew a [Kurdish] dress, it becomes [the
time of] two dresses.
Halla... bta'rif... bil-bêtkom bes inti bta'rif... bes inti
btxeyyitî? La fî benat ya meselen...?
Now... do you know... in your house only you know... only
you sew? Or are there daughters or for example...?
El-bintî biştexil taht îdî. Bsawî ma'î sjefat, bikwîlî er-
rob, t'alliqlî zrar.
My daughter works under my hand (supervision). She makes the
facings with me, irons the dress for me, attaches buttons
for me.
Ya'ni bes ana baxeyyit 'al-mekîne.
Meaning only I sew on the machine.
Bta'rif txeyyit mitlek? Le lissa ma t'ellemet?
Does she know how to sew like you? Or has she not learned
yet?
La, lissa ma t'ellemet mitlî txeyyit.
No, she hasn't learned to sew like me yet.
Ya'tîk el-'afye, şukran.
May God give you health, thank you.
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Li bakurê gund, gundê Tinebê, li rojhilat gundê Til Ecar,
aşê Feysel û bajarê Erfad, li başûr bajarokê Dêr el-Cemal,
li rojava gundê Cilbirê û Bênê dikevin.
To the north of the village lies the village of Teneb; to
the east, the village of Til Ajar, Faisal Mill, and the city
of Tel Rifaat; to the south, the town of Deir Jamal; and to
the west, the villages of Jelbul and Bene.
Bîra sêvê li bakurê gund e, ta niha ava wê heye. Bîra Pêz di
nîvê gund de ye.
The Apple Well is north of the village, it still has water.
The Sheep Well is in the middle of the village.
Berê pez li ber dihat avdan û niha bûye jêderka avê ji bo
xelkên gund.
Previously, sheep were watered there, and now it has become
a source of water for the people of the village.
Bîra Xerbî ji ava wê hina jî heye.
The Western Well still has some of its water.
Xelkên gund debara jiyana xwe bi çandiniyê dikin. Ji zeviyên
bejî weke ceh, genim, nîsk, di gel wê zeviyên zeytûn û rez
jî diçînin.
The people of the village make their living through
agriculture. From rain-fed fields such as barley, wheat,
lentils, along with that, they also plant olive groves and
vineyards.
Hin malbat jî sewalan xwedî dikin. Ji mîh, bizin û çêlekan û
her wiha mêşên hingiv.
Some families also raise livestock. Including sheep, goats,
and cows, as well as honey bees.
Du kargehên deziyan li gund hene. Nêzî 10 kes lê dixebitin.
Û nêzî 25 kes dezgehên saziyarî yên beriya xwe ser da
dixebitin.
There are two thread workshops in the village. Approximately
10 people work there. And nearly 25 people work on
construction scaffolds outside.
Hêjayî pêşxistinê ye ku gundê Keşta'arê bi Kîlê navdar e.
Berê xelkê ji bo serşûştinê bikar dianî.
It is worth mentioning that the village of Keşta'ar is
famous for the "Kil" (an ancient type of clay/stone).
Previously, people used it for bathing.
Û her wiha ji bo dermankirina hin nexweşiyan jî ta niha
bikar tê. Mîna nexweşiya çerm.
And also, it is still used today for treating some diseases.
Such as skin disease.
Ê dayê merheba, tu bi xêr hatî.
Hello auntie, welcome.
Ehlen û sehlen, ehla û sehla.
Welcome, most welcome.
Em te nospikin, rewşa te baş e?
We won't keep you waiting, how are you doing?
Ayşe.
Ser çavê min.
You are welcome [Upon my eyes].
Ser çav û serî, te xweş be.
You are most welcome, may you be happy.
Fexriye Mirad.
Ser çava.
You are welcome.
Ser çava, tu jî nospikî?
Welcome, and you, we won't keep you waiting?
Nûran Mûsa.
Nuran Musa.
Ser çava. Hûn çi li hev tên?
Welcome. How are you related to each other?
Ev xûşka min e, û ev meta min e.
This is my sister, and this is my aunt.
Em herdu sêwî ne, ev meta me ye xûşka bav e.
We are both orphans, this is our aunt, father's sister.
Yanî du xûşk, danek metik e?
Meaning two sisters and one aunt?
Erê, danek metik e, hewka jî qîzika min e.
Yes, one aunt, and that over there is my daughter.
Keçika te ye?
Is she your daughter?
Keçika min e.
She is my daughter.
E ser çavê min dayê.
You are welcome, auntie.
Çi navê te jî xweş e, navekî Kurdî ye, nake?
Your name is beautiful too, it's a Kurdish name, isn't it?
Ayşe.
Ê dayê, em nêkî berî em spasîya we bikin û emê bimeşin...
Haya berê bîne bîra xwe.
So auntie, before we thank you and leave... recall a bit of
the past life.
Em hatin, dinya ceng hebû, kar hebû, me diçû karê xwe dikir.
We came, there was struggle in the world, there was work, we
went and did our work.
Em dihatin, nanê xwe bi sêlê dikir, hevirê xwe dikir, nanê
xwe dikir.
We came back, made our bread on the griddle, kneaded our
dough, baked our bread.
Me şûştina xwe da serê xwe, em diçûn ser kanîyê.
We put our laundry on our heads, we went to the spring.
Hûn diçûn ser kanîyê?
You went to the spring?
Em diçûn ser kanîyê, me cilê xwe dişûştin.
We went to the spring, washed our clothes.
Sabûna me tunebû, toza me tunebû.
We didn't have soap, we didn't have powder [detergent].
Me bi kopalê li te da, bi avê dişûşt.
We beat it with the wooden paddle, washed it with water.
Teda wê gavê ne kar kîrya, ne meşxûl ceffa dî hebû.
Back then there was no hired work, nor jobs for wages.
Aman hûn nediwestiyan wê gavê bi vê heysê yanî?
But didn't you get tired back then with all that effort?
Me westana xwe ji bîr dikir. Siheta me tima xweş bû. Tim
hîlê me rind bû.
We forgot our tiredness. Our health was always good. Our
strength was always fine.
Yanî em ser hîl û quweta xwe bûn. Em barê wî şuxlî
nediketin.
Meaning we relied on our own strength and power. We didn't
suffer under the burden of work.
Kê em diçûn şûlê, dihatin...
When we went to work, and came back...
We çi kar dikir dayê, wê gavê?
What work did you do back then, auntie?
Me de, me karê me, mesela bêdera me heye, me yê biçûya
bêdera xwe bidûta, me yê pala xwe bikira.
Us, well, our work... for example we have a threshing floor,
we would go gather our harvest, we would hire laborers.
Demek paleyî ji me çûne, me yê taştê jêra bibira.
When the laborers finished, we would take breakfast down to
them.
Me yê taştêya xwe bixwara, demek bêdera xwe şixre xwe
bikşanda, cercerê xwe bikuta.
We would eat our breakfast, then pull our sheaves, pound it
with the threshing sled.
Bêdera Ereba dibat ji me re badida, me yê li ber bayê
bisekinanda.
An Arab thresher would come and winnow it for us, we would
stand it in the wind [to sieve].
Û çu genimê xwe diçalê dikir bo me.
And he would put our wheat into the silos for us.
Me yê genimê xwe bişûşta, têkira halê, daniya xwe bikelanda,
bulxur bikira.
We would wash our wheat, put it in the cauldron, boil our
grain, make bulgur.
Me yê raxista, zuwa bikira, bibira aş.
We would spread it out, dry it, take it to the mill.
Tiriyê xwe biçiniya, bineqanda bidimis kira.
We would pick our grapes, select them and make molasses.
Deh, deh, albidim, bes e me nedikir jî, kulfet pir bû.
Wow, wow, I understand, but we didn't do that much, the
family was large. [Interpreting Ayşe's flow]
Ê noka maşalla xelk diçe... hem reba... hem...
Well now, Mashallah, people go... both jam... and...
Hêjîra... û hem ewa...
Figs... and that...
Yanî tu dibêjî jiyana berê xweş bû?
So you say the life of the past was good?
Xweş! Jiyana berê noka xweştir bû.
Good! The life of the past was better than now.
Heyata noka bi qehr û cefa tê da, bi ye...
The life now comes with grief and suffering, with...
Xelk bi ezabî ye, yanî tu tim diqehirî li ser weterê xwe.
People are in torment, meaning you are always grieving over
your homeland.
Dayê, ew kaniyê avê li ku hene? We dikişiya av ji ku dianî
berê?
Auntie, where are those water springs? Where did you draw
water from before?
Av berê, me ji Totmaraşê, li bin Totmaraşê heye, cem timbê
wî de.
Water, before, we had it from Totmaraş, there is one below
Totmaraş, near that mound.
Û li timbê jî kanî heye.
And at the mound there is also a spring.
Li cem me jî bira Avzê heye.
Near us there is also the Avzê well.
Yanî bîr jî hene?
So there are wells too?
Erê le, bîr, bîst... cem me sed bîrê Avzê nav gund de heye.
Yes indeed, wells, twenty... near us there are a hundred
wells of Avzê in the village.
We ava xwe ji ku dibir, ji bo vexwarinê?
Where did you take your water from, for drinking?
Ji bîra.
From the well.
We diçû ava kincan ji kû dianî?
Where did you go to get water for clothes?
Me ji yek kaniyê, pê dexel dişûştin.
We washed at a spring, beating with paddles.
We kinc dişûşt?
You washed clothes?
Yek kaniya me pê dexel hebû.
We had a spring with paddles [for washing].
Tu çend caran diçûn kanîyê dihatin?
How many times did you go back and forth to the spring?
Bes e... yanî tu kerê dexelê xwe biheri ser, diînî.
Just... you know, you take your donkey with the load, and
bring it back.
Me li haşê dikir, erebana dikir.
We put it on beasts of burden, put it on carts.
Dibirin daniyan û wanan dişûştan, ser cila raxistin şalan.
We took them, put them down and washed them, spread them on
clothes and shawls.
Hişk dikir. Û civandeka dikirin, cûc li pişta xwe dikir.
Dried them. And gathered them into a bundle, put it on our
backs.
Dişanda, êşû dikorand.
Sent them back, and [the men] wore them.
Ê de noka wergî tûnne.
Well now, that doesn't exist anymore.
Na.
No.
Aş li vir hebûn?
Were there mills here?
Na, tûnne bûn.
No, there weren't.
Aşê di berê... berê gihal Basûte wey de diketin.
The mills of the past... fell somewhere near the Basûte
valley.
Li ber avê bûn?
Were they by the water?
Ber avê bûn erê.
By the water, yes.
Paşê eldirjmelê derket. Diçûnê dirjmelê.
Then the diesel mill came out. We went to the diesel mill.
Nêzîk bû?
Was it close?
Tirfê de... dirjmelê, aş hebû. Diçûn Dêron û...
Over there... the diesel mill, there was a mill. They went
to Dêron and...
Salê teye... te ji bo kira...
Your yearly supply... you prepared it...
Hem hêja, mesela tu xwarnê xwe.
And also, for example, you and your food.
Çewalek ard, bîst riyo herre... xelas bû tiyekî didogirî.
A sack of flour, twenty measures go... when it was finished,
you grabbed another.
Dibira nan dikirana.
They took it to make bread.
Me li ser text û tirikê xwe daniya bikirana, nanê xwe
germ...
We would put it on our wooden stand, make our bread hot...
Heft dida bixwara.
And give it to eat.
Erê.
Yes.
Em naha hatine vir, ji bû Kîlê.
We came here now because of the Kîl (clay/bitumen).
Ka em şta pirskin? Li vir we hev Kîlê...
Let's ask about this thing? Here you have this Kîl...
Wa vê Kîlê ji kû derê danî?
Where did you get this Kîl from?
Ardê me ver, ardê Kîlê ye.
Our land here is the Land of Kîl.
Yanî sê-çar metra bikole, gi Kîl e.
Meaning if you dig three or four meters, it's all Kîl.
Û fêdê Kîlê jî pir heye.
And Kîl has many benefits.
Çiye fêdê xwe çiye?
What are its benefits?
Yanî fêdê xwe mesela, berê meserî xaş...
Meaning its benefits, for example, previously for the
head...
Şampo derzemanî berê tûnne bûn. Kîlê dişûştin. Sabûn tûnne
bûn, bi Kîlê dişûştin.
Shampoo didn't exist in the old times. They washed with Kîl.
Soap didn't exist, they washed with Kîl.
Hew pora... nerm dima, dirêj dibû, ziq bû.
The hair... remained soft, grew long, was thick.
Înakê te serê xwe ne dişûşt, hew pora tim bêhna xwe xweş bû.
Dandruff didn't fall from one's head, the smell of the hair
was always pleasant.
Heta ji hesasiyê cismî însên ra pir fêdê xwe hebû.
Even for body allergies of humans, it had many benefits.
Yanî Kîl rind bû, rind bû, ji porê însên ra pir quwet bû.
Meaning Kîl was good, good, it was very strong for human
hair.
Te sa jinê berê te bidîta her pelfikek...
If you saw the women of the past, every braid...
Pişta hebû.
Reached down their backs.
Noka kanî? Noka hev şampoyê, na hev dermanê kîmawî... kîmawî
ne.
Where is it now? Now there are all these shampoos, all these
chemical medicines... they are chemical.
Yanî selbiyetê xwe hene, îjabiyetê xwe jî hene.
Meaning they have their negatives, and they have their
positives.
Bes ê Kîlê giyî îjabiyet e, selbiyetê xwe tûnne bû ji însên
re.
But for Kîl, it was all positive, it had no negatives for
humans.
Hew guvda wextî hew ava Kîlê nerm dikirî, te li ser serê xwe
dikir, hew guvdî însên çiqas nerm dibû.
And the body, when you softened the Kîl in water and applied
it to your head, the human body became so soft.
Rind bû?
Was it good?
Rind bû erê.
It was good, yes.
Yanî ji bû tenduristîya însana baş bû, rind bû?
So for human health it was good, it was fine?
Fêdê xwe jî ji abarê petrolê ra...
Its benefit also comes from the aspect of petroleum...
Yanî gundê me, mintaqaka stratejî pir girîng e.
Meaning our village is a very important strategic area.
Yanî berî vê çend sala, berî hevsewra destpêbikir...
Meaning a few years ago, before the chaos started...
Alem teqrîben vedîtin, teqrîben keşfû xwa xwarin ser erdê
me.
The world almost discovered, almost realized what we have on
our land.
Hatin gelek Kîlê, bişmê abara bikirrin.
They came to buy the Kîl, under the name of wells.
Û metro, metro gihişte deh hezara. Erdê... ya qiraç... ê
yanî koklê nadibûyî.
And a meter, a meter reached ten thousand. The land...
barren land... meaning nothing grew on it.
Bes wûşmê Kîlê der, wûşmê abarê petrolê.
Just because Kîl comes out, because of the oil wells.
Dinya hanekî bûn derbûn û...
The world sort of poured in and...
Valla pirra ji kirî û hîç kî neçûne noka.
By God, many bought it and no one has gone there yet.
Kirrîn, yanî pê disifînin.
They bought it, meaning they are refining it.
Pê disifînin?
They are refining it?
Pê disifînin, bîrin petrolê, pê dilîsin... wûşmê tesrîb
neba, petrol nera.
They are refining it, oil wells, lining them... so that
there is no leakage, so oil doesn't escape.
Fêdê xwe pir heye.
It has many benefits.
Neha tenê li vir cî tê dimîne? Li vê deverê we Kîlê heye?
Now does it only exist in this spot? Do you have Kîl in this
area?
Li vî gundî mexsûs, erdê Kîlê ye.
In this village specifically, it is the Land of Kîl.
Bi Erebî bera dibên "Aradî El-Beylûnê".
In Arabic they call it "Aradi Al-Bayluna" (Land of Fuller's
Earth).
Û biltahdîd şerqî gund.
And specifically, east of the village.
Erdê şerqî... bera dibên erdê Kîlê.
The eastern land... they call it the Land of Kîl.
Erdê Kîlê.
The Land of Kîl.
Erê.
Yes.
Ê noka berê milet pê jiyana dabara xwe dikir, yanî pê
difrotin derdikirin?
So before, did people make their living with it, meaning did
they sell and export it?
Ê lê, difrotin, dibirne Heleb, Etara dikirî.
Yes indeed, they sold it, took it to Aleppo, perfumers
bought it.
Tevle teyrê derî dikir?
[Unclear, possibly asking about transport or mixing]
Nişûştine derî ra. Berî yanî iktîşafê petrolê derî be.
For washing out there. Meaning before the discovery of oil
out there.
Berî şûştina derî ra...
Before washing out there...
Ji dibrine mewad me... deqetir cildîye.
They took it for substances... [treating] skin
doctors/conditions.
Dibirin, pê xelk derman dikirin. Milet.
They took it, people used it for cures. The people.
Î hesasiyê ji guvda dihat.
Also allergies appeared on the body.
Ê purcî ji himêra ra. Berî himêra li guvdî însên dihat.
And also for red rash (Himêr). Before, red rash would appear
on a human body.
Nerm dikirin, teblek uncîya dikutan.
They softened it, pounded a tablet of it.
Û diqewrandin di guvdî însên didan, pê çê dibûn.
And they smeared it on the human body, they were cured by
it.
Ji himêra ra.
For the red rash.
Naha kolanê li vir heye? Hadelekî heye?
Are there excavations here now? Is there a specific spot?
Erê her derekê gundî me da heye, bes... bes kêşê şerqî ji
giyî çêtir e.
Yes, it is in every part of our village, but... but the
eastern side is the best of all.
Heke, benerî li me hesin ku nîzîkî hev, mintaqa ma anî vir,
ji ber ku nîzîk e.
Look, look at the soil, we feel that it's close to each
other, we brought [you] to this area here because it's
close.
Te dîye seke cî Kîlê çûn vir heye? Cî kolanî.
Have you seen the Kîl place over there? The digging place.
Ardê me... yanî giyî teqrîben Kîl têdaye.
Our land... meaning almost all of it has Kîl in it.
Bes aliyê şerqî gund, ji xerbî gund...
But the eastern side of the village, compared to the western
side...
Wir sadeg yanî. Heta lûnî filhanî xwa ne sora.
It's purer there. Even the color of the plowed soil isn't
red.
Yanî tûnî Kîlê te zanî, ne xamiq nabek, lûnî xakêşîf dimîne
hanekî.
Meaning the color of the Kîl, you know, isn't dark... the
color of the soil remains revealed like this.
Rengê axê reş e?
The color of the soil is black?
Ne sora.
It's not red.
Not red.
Na.
No.
Naha gundî we piraniya vê karê dikir, de difrotin
derdikirin?
Now, did the majority of your villagers do this work,
selling and exporting it?
Ê dikirin... erê.
Yes they did... yes.
Yanî hetta...
Meaning even...
Ettar hebûn. Yanî hetta mêrin ji derva gund dihatin pê
dişuxilîn.
There were perfumers. Meaning even men came from outside the
village and worked with it.
Ji derve dihatin dikirîn û dibirin.
From outside they came, bought it and took it.
Dibirin, dihêrandin, ji xwara pê sava blemîş dibûn.
They took it, ground it, and prepared it for themselves [for
washing].
Me îzîno, vêra...
No, listen, for this...
Kîlo mesela çar weraqe, pênc weraqe, teyê pê da...
A kilo for example for four notes, five notes, whatever they
gave...
Kîlo xwe daniya pişta xwe.
They put their kilos on their backs.
Naha kes vê karî dike îna?
Does anyone do this work now?
Ê welle...
Oh, by God...
Na, na, na, ma yekî, yekî, ya ku herîtanî...
No, no, no, maybe one, one... or some peddler...
Na nerman tibbî.
No, [now there is] medical medicine.
Ê, yekî, yekî ku herîtanî me ra bese dibînin, tên, dibirin.
Yes, maybe one, one peddler sees enough for us, comes and
takes it.
Naha derjmelê nîzîkî we hew ji vê karî dikin?
Now, are the diesel mills near you still doing this work?
[Host seems confused or asking about machinery]
Erê.
Yes.
Îsa ti karê derjmelê, awê dikelim dibirin.
Now the work of the diesel mill... they boil the water and
take it.
Wan bi erdê me dişuxilîn.
They work with our land.
Wan bi erdê me dişuxilîn, û derdixistin û difrotin.
They work with our land, extract it and sell it.
Temam, gelekî spasiya we dikim.
Okay, I thank you very much.
Xwedê kîmasiya we nede.
May God not let you lack anything.
Ehlen û sehlen, xwedê te rabike, ew ji me û te ra.
Welcome, welcome, may God raise you up, for us and for you.
Û xwedê rebilalemîn serketa, serketin be. Em bi jor kevin.
And may the Lord of the Worlds grant success, may there be
success. May we rise up.
Û em tim li hev dibin, xweş bin.
And may we always be together, may you be happy.
Û rizq bişînin, û em bidûr nebin ya rebî.
And may He send provision, and may we not be far apart, oh
Lord.
Înşalla, înşalla dayê.
God willing, God willing auntie.
Siheta we xweş e?
Is your health good?
Hûn te jiyan xweş, hatin ehlen û sehlen.
May you have a happy life, welcome, welcome.
Li eynî gundî, odê yek ji kunc û rûspiyên gund heye.
In the same village, there is a guesthouse of one of the
elders and wise men of the village.
Mihu xûbarî yek ji mezin û rûspiyên gund bû.
Mihu Khubari was one of the great and wise men of the
village.
Ew oda damezrand ku ciyê mêvan û rêwiyan bû.
He established that guesthouse which became a place for
guests and travelers.
Û her wiha ciyê civata hemû xelkê gund bû.
And it was also the gathering place for all the people of
the village.
Tê de hemû pirsgirêk, gengeş û çareser dikirin.
In it, they discussed and resolved all problems.
Lê niha ew oda girtî ye û bikar nayê.
But now that guesthouse is closed and not in use.
Mistoyê Kemê kesayetekî gund şeng e.
Mistoye Keme is a prominent figure of the village.
Ew ji eşîra Nêimî ye, Ereb bû.
He was from the Naimi tribe, he was an Arab.
Piştre malbat û rûbarî anku xûbarî ji gundê Cilbirê hat.
Later, the family and Rubari, or Khubari, came from the
village of Jilbire.
Ji ber ku zeviyên xwe li derdora gundê Keştaarê bûn.
Because their lands were around the village of Keshtaar.
Bi hevdû re gund şên kirin.
Together they populated the village.
Hemû malbat û pêkhateyên gund nava têkelî û peywendiyên baş
û xweş dane.
All the families and components of the village have mixed
and have good and pleasant relations.
Ji hevdû zewicîne.
They have intermarried.
Û her wiha girtî... û giş hîn hemûyan bûne Kurda bûn e.
And also generally... and all of them have learned [Kurdish]
and become Kurds.
Nêzî pêncî xanî...
Near fifty houses...
Gundê heye... û derdora hezar û pênc sed kes li gund dijîn.
There is a village... and around one thousand five hundred
people live in the village.
Lê gelek kes koçber bûn ji ber... kêm berhemanîn çandiniyê.
But many people migrated because of... the lack of
agricultural production.
Am ahlam ninzil ‘al bayt.
The sweetest dreams land on the home.
W hadak dar ahlamî.
And that house is my dream.
Ya l-bayt l-fîkî trabbayt... farhit ‘umrî w ayyamî.
Oh, the house where I was raised... the joy of my life and
my days.
Farhit ‘umrî w ayyamî.
The joy of my life and my days.
W ya bay mshtaq ktîr.
And oh father, I miss [you] so much.
L-ahl l-day’a w lammitna... mn l-ghurbî shift l-taqtîr.
[I miss] the people of the village and our gathering... in
exile, I have seen hardship.
W ya ma qsaha ghurbitna.
And oh how harsh is our exile.
W mshtaq lak wallah ya mmî.
And I miss you, by God, oh my mother.
W mshtaq l-hakî dammî... b-‘uyunik asrar l-kown.
And I miss that embrace... in your eyes are the secrets of
the universe.
W min nurik biqtul hammî.
And from your light, I kill my sorrow.
W ya bahr irwî hkayat.
And oh sea, tell the stories.
Dam’atî ‘affu w nhdat... dam’atî mallit kasat.
My tears have dried and sighed... my tears have filled cups.
W qalbî dayib ‘al mina.
And my heart is melting at the port.
W ‘îna ‘al dunya w ‘îna.
And help us with this world, help us.
Ma hada byish’ur fîna... jrahtî qalbî shway shway.
No one feels for us... you wounded my heart little by
little.
Ya ghurbî thinnî ‘alayna.
Oh exile, have mercy on us.
W ya ghurbî thinnî ‘alayna.
And oh exile, have mercy on us.
W ana bitmanna kun ‘asfûr... ruh w daqdaq ‘al ballûr... w
qillik ya immî bonjour.
And I wish I were a bird... to go and tap on the window
glass... and say to you, oh mother, Bonjour.
W tqillî ya ‘aynayya.
And you would say to me, oh my eyes [my dear].
Belê na em derbasî malekê bûn... ew kesê ji... miştexa çêke,
Efrîn bê miştex...
Yes, now we have entered a home... the person who... makes
brooms, Afrin is not without...
Hinek dibêjin sirbiga, hinek dibêjin mikise.
Some call it "sirbiga" (broom), some call it "mikise"
(broom).
Jiber ku ev zimanê Erebî, Tirkî, Kurdî di nav hev da millet
jiyan dike.
Because these languages, Arabic, Turkish, Kurdish, the
people live mixed together here.
Ew kesa jî, ji kesên milletê me yê Ereb e.
This person is also from our Arab people.
Enekî ew bi Erebî biaxife, ez ê enekî vegerînim Kurdî, enekî
emê bi hev re suhbet bikin.
He will speak a bit in Arabic, I will translate a bit to
Kurdish, we will chat together a bit.
Marhaba Hajji.
Hello Hajji.
Ahlan wa sahlan.
Welcome.
Nit'arraf 'alayk?
May we know who you are?
Ali Hamdani.
Ser çavê me Apê Elî.
You are very welcome, Uncle Ali.
Teslam ya 'aynî.
Bless you, my dear.
Sax be... Ah, ta'raf tahkî Kurdî?
Be healthy... Ah, do you know how to speak Kurdish?
La.
No.
Ta'raf tahkî Kurdî? Layn ma ta'raf?
Do you know how to speak Kurdish? Why don't you know?
La.
No.
Ma ta'raf.
You don't know.
Halla antu b-day'a fî l-krad w fî 'arab, ma t'allamtu min
ba'adkom?
Now, in the village there are Kurds and there are Arabs,
didn't you learn from each other?
Fî krad w fî 'arab, bas il-lahje 'arabiyye da'iman baynatna
ya'ni...
There are Kurds and there are Arabs, but the dialect is
always Arabic between us, meaning...
Ah. Halla l-krad killon byi'rafu yahku 'arabî?
Ah. Now, do all the Kurds know how to speak Arabic?
Ee byi'rafu...
Yes, they know...
W l-'arab ta'raf tahkî Kurdî?
And do the Arabs know how to speak Kurdish?
Fî minnon byi'rafu, w minnon ma byi'rafu.
Some of them know, and some of them don't know.
Anta ma ta'raf?
You don't know?
Ana bafham hek shaghlât bas lsênî ma bindar ma'î... ma...
ajawib.
I understand some things, but my tongue doesn't turn with
it... I don't... [can't] answer.
Erê, li gundê wek Kurmanc û Ereb in, hinek vî zimanê hevdû
jî zanin, baş e.
Yes, in the village there are Kurds and Arabs, some know
each other's language too, which is good.
Ee Apê Elî...
Yes, Uncle Ali...
Na'am, na'am.
Yes, yes.
Ya Hajji.
Oh Hajji.
Na'am, na'am.
Yes, yes.
Nahkî hek 'al miknsî.
Let's talk a bit about the broom.
Eewa.
Okay.
Wayn awwal shî wayn b-tizra'û hay?
Where, first of all, where do you plant this?
Hay mnizra'o bayn al-ard... b-ard hamra.
This, we plant it in the land... in red soil.
Tizra'û b-ayy... b-ayy shahr 'am tizra'û?
You plant it in which... in which month are you planting it?
Hay bisîr 'emat wahed b-rabî' iza zara'o bisîr, 'emat man
zara'o ma' l-sayfî bisîr.
This works whenever one plants it in spring it works,
whenever we plant it during the summer it works.
Ya'ni ilo waqt mhaddad kaman, ba'den b-l-akhîr iza l-dinya
sarat... ma bisîr.
Meaning it has a specific time as well, later at the end if
the weather becomes... it won't work.
Bisîr hek... ma b-'arnis... ma bisîr 'arnûs shî.
It becomes like... it doesn't form a cob... it won't form a
cob at all.
Kam shahr biddo hay hatta t-...
How many months does this need until it...
Biddo shahrayn.
It needs two months.
Shahrayn.
Two months.
Ana 'indî ard... ma khallûna nizra'o... ba'den jîit falaht.
I have land... they didn't let us plant it... later I came
and tilled it.
Hatayna flaha, marrtayn tlattî falah'to qilt la sawwî
simsim.
We tilled it, two or three times I tilled it, I said I will
make [plant] sesame.
Jîna sabbayna simsim w khallatna hada bayn l-simsim...
l-bizr taba'o.
We came and poured sesame and mixed this [broom corn] among
the sesame... its seeds.
Zara'na simsim iza sar matar 'aley qabl ma yitla' b-ifqas ma
bitla'.
We planted sesame; if it rains on it before it comes up, it
rots, it won't come up.
Sar matar... tûf sar matar, tili' hek w ma baqa... ynaffid
l-foq l-simsim... mêt. Hada sar.
It rained... a flood of rain happened, it came up like this
and no longer... pushed upwards, the sesame... died. This
[the broom corn] survived.
Ya'ni shakhsiyyan 'am tizra'û aw 'am tishtaghil b-hal
miknsî?
Meaning, personally are you planting it or working with this
broom?
Qadîm an.
Since old times.
Kam sini ya'ni?
How many years, roughly?
Ya'ni min tlatin sini, min arb'in sini bshtaghel b-l-mikn...
ya'ni sawêha.
Meaning for thirty years, for forty years I've been working
with broo... meaning making them.
Min qabl arb'in sine. Mîn kan yishtaghil qablak? Min wayn
t'allamt?
Since forty years ago. Who used to work before you? From
where did you learn?
La ana hiyye 'anna wirasi ya'ni.
No, for me it is with us as a heritage.
Abûk ya'ni?
Your father, you mean?
Fî akwâtî.
There are my brothers.
Ya'ni kill l-'eile btishtighlû?
Meaning the whole family works [in this]?
Mmm.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, dibêje ev... karê bav û kalan e, ew
bi xwe jî ev çil sal e vî karî dike.
Yes dear viewers, he says this is... the work of
forefathers, and he himself has been doing this work for
forty years.
Tê çandin, di gund da tê çandin. Dibêje du meh, heyya du
meha tê xwestin heya çêdibe.
It is planted, planted in the village. He says two months,
up to two months are needed until it is ready.
Ê malbata wî jî hemûya vî karî dikin, bavê wî û... birayê wî
vî karî dikirin. Dibêje ema ji çil salî da em vî karî dikin
yanî.
And his family all do this work, his father and... his
brother used to do this work. He says since forty years ago
we have been doing this work.
Ee Hajji.
Yes, Hajji.
Halla da...
Now...
Btishtaghil?
Do you work [now]?
Haza wahed mu m'allim b-l-maslaha, shayef had... iza b-hitt
l-miknsi bsawwî hek, b-shiddo, bifrumo mitl l-mûs, byiqta'o
min ba'do, taawil.
This [tool], if one isn't a master in the trade, you see
this... if he puts the broom and does this, tightens it, it
will slice it like a razor, it cuts it apart completely.
Halla shû hiyye l-... l-ghrad? Hay?
Now what are the... the tools? This?
Hay shû btsammu hay?
This, what do you call this?
Ha...
Farjînî ya. Shû isma hay?
Show it to me. What is this called?
Mshât hada.
This is a comb [Mshat].
Mshât eh? W had?
A comb, right? And this?
Hay kallabê.
This is pliers [Kallabe].
Kallabê. W had?
Pliers. And this?
Hada kabil.
This is a cable [cord].
Kabil. Btshiddo b-dahrak?
Cable. You tighten it with your back?
Aywa.
Yes.
Hêk ishtaghil shûf hêk m-...
Like that, work so I can see like th-...
Irja' shid.
Go back and tighten.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, Apê Elî çawa çêdike...
Yes dear viewers, how Uncle Ali makes it...
Ev jî qawîşa bi navê xwe girêdide... di pişta xwe girêdide.
This is also the strap, he ties it to his waist... he ties
it around his back.
Hek btishtaghil.
You work like this.
Ba'den nrubto b-l-khayt w mnshid l-khayt mkan 'aley w...
nrakhî zyadi 'aley.
Then we tie it with the thread and tighten the thread firmly
on it and... loosen the excess on it.
Hay shqad bttawwil hay?
How long does this take?
Mmm bttawwil...
Mmm it takes time...
Sawwîna hêk damnak shway.
Make a small bundle for us like that.
Yalla.
Alright.
B-dakhet khayyt Allah.
You have entered God's thread [Working with great
focus/effort].
Halla b-kil yom btsawwî kam wahdi bi-l-yom?
Now, every day, how many do you make in a day?
B-l-yom ma bshtaghel... qolî waqtîn tishtaghil? Bshtaghel
bi-l-sahra l-masa.
In the day I don't work... tell me when do you work? I work
in the evening gathering [Sahra].
Aywa kint shab inta.
Yes, [when] you were young.
Ee kam wahdi kint tsawwî?
Yes, how many used to make?
Hassab il-raghbe, khamse, sitte bi-l-sahra.
According to the desire, five, six in the evening.
B-qaddêsh 'am tbî'a?
For how much are you selling it?
Ishqad dawlah'ne? B-jîbû qash... w ntlâda nshiddo bi-l-ujra.
How much do they pay us? They bring the straw... and we meet
to tighten [make] it for a wage.
Ya'ni hinne bjîbûlak yah anta btshiddo bas.
Meaning they bring it to you, you just tighten it.
Ana bshiddo bas.
I just tighten it.
Hadol mu ilak halla?
These aren't yours now?
Ilî ilî hadol.
Mine, these are mine.
Hadol ilak.
These are yours.
Bas mîn biddo miknsi bjîblak yah? Btshiddillû yah?
But whoever wants a broom brings it [the straw] to you? You
tighten it for him?
Eewa.
Exactly.
B-qaddêsh 'am tshiddillû yah?
For how much are you tightening it for him?
Wallah halla ghalî sayir shaddo.
By God, now the tightening has become expensive.
Awwal êsh kan l-shad?
At first, what was the [price of] tightening?
Awwal kinna nshidda b-... khams lirat, b-'ashr lirat, sarit
ba'den...
At first we used to tighten it for... five liras, for ten
liras, it became later...
Halla sayir...
And now?
Now it has become...
Waa yê. Bi qedê çi?
That is it. For how much?
Em... sê sed wereqe, çar sed wereqe, şeş sed û pêncî.
We... three hundred notes, four hundred notes, six hundred
and fifty.
Li cem me ewilî hey ye, çiqas kîloya titûnê bû hey? Kîloya
titûnê bi heft heşt wereqan bû. Niha çiqas heqê wê ye?
Back with us in the beginning, look at this, how much was a
kilo of tobacco, this? A kilo of tobacco was seven or eight
notes. Now how much is its price?
Heqê wê heştsed wereqe.
Its price is eight hundred notes.
Hela bi sûq, heştsed e hey?
Even in the market, is this eight hundred?
Ee, mû hedîk la, hedîk la.
Yes, not that one no, not that one.
Bi çendê ye li sûq?
How much is it in the market?
Ee bes mîna wê ye, bi heştsed wereqe heqê wê ye.
Yes, but it is like it, its price is eight hundred notes.
Dibêje berê, dema destpêka ma kar dikir, dibêje em bi pênc
wereqan kar dikir. Lê niha dibêje em pir baha bûne niha.
Belkî bi sê sed wereqî firotan yanî.
He says before, when we started working, he says we worked
for five notes. But now he says we have become very
expensive. Maybe selling for three hundred notes.
Ya Hecî, Allah, bi pênc lîran, tu bi çend sala hey?
Oh Hajji, Allah, with five liras, how many years were you
[working] with that?
Min zeman.
Since a long time.
Yanî bi çend sal yanî?
Meaning how many years?
Bi pêncazdeh salan yanî, bîst salan taqîben.
For fifteen years roughly, twenty years approximately.
Dibêje berê bi bîst sala da bi pênc wereqa kar dikir. Niha
jî bi sê sed wereq.
He says twenty years ago he worked for five notes. Now for
three hundred notes.
Xilas bû hey ne?
Is this one finished?
Ee xilas.
Yes, finished.
Meşkur.
Thank you.
Berê te maşallah nifêjê xwe jî dawî kirî. Em ê niha veda
bikin.
Before this, Mashallah, you also finished your prayers. We
will now take our leave.
Hela yek sar cahiz, yîk la dol.
Now a cold one [drink] is ready, bring that one.
Hela cahiz. Hela tu sewêt ilna yanî?
Now it's ready. So you made it for us?
Ee ehlen we sehlen, mûqedeme.
Yes, welcome, it is offered [to you].
Xwedê weke te.
May God keep you.
Mûqedeme welle.
It is offered, by God.
Ene te'elemit minnek meslehe.
I learned the trade from you.
Yû.
Oh.
We ene bedelak biştexil mitlak.
And I will work like you instead of you.
Ee kwayîs.
Yes, good.
Kwayîs?
Good?
Ma bide şî?
Doesn't it need anything?
La ma bide şî.
No, it doesn't need anything.
Bide xeyt û heda.
It needs thread and that.
Mesela el xeyt bi hedde zade, hade xeyt hade.
For example, the thread is to this limit too, this thread is
this.
Lê?
Why?
Do xeyt qewî ye beda, xeyt qewî ye bade bi file şûf le halo
bi file.
This is strong thread it needs, strong thread, look
afterwards it unravels on its own, it unravels.
Hecî, ye'tîk el afiye, elf şukr.
Hajji, may He give you health, a thousand thanks.
Allah ya'fîk, ehla we sehla.
God give you health, welcome.
Te'ebnak me'ana.
We tired you with us.
Ee afwan, afwan. E'le rasi, e'le rasi.
Yes, you're welcome, you're welcome. On my head, on my head
[my pleasure].
Belê îro jî em li gundê Keştaarê digerin. Berê di her
gundekî de ode û dav mêvan hebû. Di vê gundî de jî, jiyîna
oda mêvan heye. Xwediyê odê derbasî vir bûn, em ê pirsa xwe
ji wan pirs kin. Merheba ji we re.
Yes, today we are visiting the village of Keshtaar. In the
past, every village had a room ("Oda") and a guesthouse. In
this village too, the life of the guest room exists. The
owners of the room passed by here, we will ask them our
questions. Hello to you.
Ehlen we sehlen, ser çava.
Welcome, upon my eyes [you are welcome].
Em nav nas bikin?
May we know the names?
Imadedîn Mihemed Elî, ez Rûbarî me.
Imad al-Din Muhammad Ali, I am a Rubari.
Ser çavê min.
Upon my eyes [pleased to meet you].
Elî Behrî.
Ali Bahri.
Ser çava. Tu bi xwe jî ji malê Rûbarî yî?
Upon my eyes. Are you also from the Rubari family yourself?
Nefs el aîle, ne, yek e.
The same family, no, it is one.
Ser çavê min. Ehlen we sehlen, ser çava.
Upon my eyes. Welcome, upon my eyes.
Em destpêkê ji odê bipirsin. Piraniya gunda, di her gundekî
de ode û mêvan hebû. Di vê odê de ew mêvan pêşwazî dikir,
şevbêrkê xwe derbas dikirin, şahiya xwe, çi piskirêkê gund
heba, giştî di vê odê da bûn. Neha ev oda we kê girt?
Let us first ask about the Oda (Guest Room). In most
villages, in every village, there was an Oda and guests. In
this Oda, they welcomed those guests, spent their evenings,
held their celebrations, whatever problem the village had,
everything happened in this Oda. Now, who established this
Oda of yours?
Oda me, kalkê me girtiye, kalkê min Hec Mehmûd el Xubarî ye.
Our Oda, our grandfather established it, my grandfather is
Hajj Mahmoud al-Ghubari.
Li vê derê hatiye, ev gundîya, eslê xwe ji Cibrê hatiye vir,
ji sed salî de.
He came to this place, this village, his origin came here
from Jibra, a hundred years ago.
Tarîxa odê teben ser odayê yo zmiş kirî ye.
The history of the Oda, naturally, on top of the room he
has... [unintelligible - implied: inscribed/built it solid].
Va ev odê, oda mêvana ye.
This Oda here, it is the guests' Oda.
Têda rûdiniştin, qehwa tehl têda çêdikirin.
They used to sit in it, they made bitter coffee in it.
Û xelkê mêvan dihat berî gi li vê odê, mezinê gund, gişt
civat bûn, hevar bi hevar li vê derê rûdiniştin.
And the guest people would come before all to this Oda, the
elders of the village, all gathered, neighbor by neighbor
sat here.
Şêwr dikirin, mesele hewal didan. Çi mişkîlek gund hebu,
dihatin...
They consulted, discussed issues. Whatever problem the
village had, they came...
Muxtarekî gund jî hebu, mezin bû bi emr, hew jî...
There was also a Mukhtar of the village, he was old in age,
he also...
Doxê kalkê min da, bi hevdura dimeşiyan ten, bi hevdura li
vê derê rûdiniştin.
In the time of my grandfather, they walked together, they
sat together here.
Qehwê xwe çêdikirin, li vir rûdiniştin, fravîn dixwarin,
mêvan dihatin, li vir rûdiniştin. Hêvarî dseherin, meselê
hewal didan.
They made their coffee, sat here, ate lunch, guests came,
sat here. In the evening they stayed up, discussed issues.
Hinek stranekê xwe hebu dikirin, hinek...
They had some of their songs they would sing, some...
Şevbêrkê xwe herû li vir derbas dikirin?
Did they always spend their evenings here?
Herro kî li vir derbas dikirin, yewmî yen, tim.
Every day they spent it here, daily, always.
Ê pişti wî... kî ev oda bi dest kê da ma?
And after him... who did this Oda remain with/who took
charge?
Destê lê û da ma.
It remained in his hand/from him.
Navê xwe çî ye?
What is his name?
Navê xwe Ibrahîm Mehemed Elî, rûyê Hec Mehmûd.
His name is Ibrahim Muhammad Ali, the face [son/descendant]
of Hajj Mahmoud.
Xwaş e, ew jî wefat kir?
[Host asks: Is he well?] He also passed away.
Ew jî wefat bû, teqrîben sala nodî da wefat kir.
He also passed away, approximately in the year ninety he
passed away.
Baş e jî, hêşta... hew domand...
It is good, still... he continued...
Berê noka, fetrekê tedî... wextê ke hicûma me kirin, vê derê
hêşta hew şewitîn, hew yên xwo derbê li me xistin.
Before now, a period... when they attacked us, this place
was still... they burned it, they struck us with their
blows.
Ev kengî ev oda xera bû?
When was this Oda destroyed?
Yanî kîjan demê da bû?
Meaning in which time was it?
Di vê demê da... Cebhet el Nusra... Cebhet el Nusra di vê
derê bû.
In this time... Jabhat al-Nusra... Jabhat al-Nusra was in
this place.
Ji du sala da. Cebhet el Nusra li vê derê bû, hicûmek li ser
bû. Teyare jî hatin...
Two years ago. Jabhat al-Nusra was here, there was an attack
on it. Planes also came...
Teyareyê Rûsî hatin... gund qasifandin.
Russian planes came... they shelled the village.
Oda wêra xera bû. Noka em termîma wê dikin, oda mêvana ye
yanî.
The Oda was destroyed then. Now we are renovating it, it is
a guest room, you know.
Em çêdikin noka, termîmê çêdikin. Me dîwar ji erdê hildan va
girtin.
We are fixing it now, doing renovations. We raised the walls
from the ground and closed them.
Û em kê hindir çêkin û wec hetadiye çawa dikiya, we çêkin.
And we will fix the interior and the face [facade] etc.,
however it was, we will fix it.
Belê.
Yes.
Na bela firê li vir xist?
Now, did the calamity [planes] strike here?
Li vir xist?
Yes.
Did it strike here?
Ew hemû?
That whole thing?
Erê... Cebhet el Nusra li vê derê bû, daîxê li xist.
Yes... Jabhat al-Nusra was here, the blow struck it.
Hatin têda rûniştin?
Did they come and sit inside it?
Li cema pir man, Cebhet el Nusra li vir pir man. Wekî bîst
meha... wî wekî... li vê derê man.
They stayed with us a lot, Jabhat al-Nusra stayed here a
lot. Like twenty months... something like that... they
stayed here.
Paşê derketin... Daîş gîşta vir.
Then they left... ISIS reached here.
Berê Daîş... heyşt mehan cem me man.
Before ISIS... they stayed with us for eight months.
Daîş.
ISIS.
Daîş berê tiheng ne kirin li gundî me.
ISIS at first didn't do anything annoying to our village.
Bes paşê Cebhet el Ekrad hicûmek anîne Daîş...
But then Jabhat al-Akrad [Kurdish Front] brought an attack
on ISIS...
Hinek laşê... qulbetê gund... nehe laş ketin, û serê jî qut
kirin, Daîş qut kirin.
Some bodies... at the edge of the village... nine bodies
fell, and they cut the heads too, ISIS cut them.
Wekî dehek, dehyek meriyê keso jî girtin.
Like about ten, eleven people of [our] folks they also
captured.
Xora birin Ezazê, li Ezazê şerjêkirin.
Took them along to Azaz, in Azaz they slaughtered them.
Yanî ew jî meriyê we bûn?
Meaning they were also your people/relatives?
Ew jî meriyê me bûn.
They were also our people.
Û yekî ji gundê me birin. Heta noka ew meriya hinda ye.
And they took one from our village. Until now that person is
lost/missing.
Em nizanin, mirî ye, sax e, em nizanin.
We don't know, is he dead, is he alive, we don't know.
Em zivir bikin ser odê.
Let's turn back to the Oda.
Neha di gund da... piranî di her odêkî da, piranî çîrokvan
hebûn.
Now in the village... usually in every Oda, usually there
were storytellers.
Çîrokvanê gundê we jî hebûn?
Were there storytellers in your village too?
Çîrokvan...
Storytellers...
Yanî hikayetî yanî?
Meaning, [tellers of] tales?
Wellehî teqrîben hebûn, Silê Carke... Gundekî heye li bal
Silê Carke dihatin... qiset Zîr û Zenetî û Ebû Hîlal û
nizanim çi...
By God, there were approximately, Silê Jarke... There is a
village near Silê Jarke, they came... [telling] the story of
Zir and Zanati and Abu Hilal and I don't know what...
Rûdiniştin, deng dikirin, hewal didan, yanî mewcûd bû hewa.
Bes gindî Silê Carke bû, wefat kir.
They sat, made noise [spoke], told stories, meaning this
existed. But he was from the village of Silê Jarke, he
passed away.
Navê xwe Ismaîl Hec Ehmed bû. Hîç Silê Carke bû.
His name was Ismail Hajj Ahmed. His nickname was Silê Jarke.
Ne Kurmanc bû?
Wasn't he a Kurmanj [Kurd]?
Ne Kurmanc bû, Ereb bû, ji Silê Carke bû.
He wasn't Kurmanj, he was Arab, from Silê Jarke.
Neha berî rispiyê we... li gunda kî bû? Mesela em bêjin
bîvirê dihatin li vir rûdiniştin. Neha te behsa muxtêr kir.
Now before your elders... in the village who was it? For
example, let's say the brave/leaders came and sat here. You
mentioned the Mukhtar.
Erê muxtarê, kalkê min navê wî Şînî Gundin, yekî jî mezin
hebu, navê xwe Ebû Zîr bû.
Yes the Mukhtar, my grandfather his name was Shini Gundin
[Head of the village], there was also an elder, his name was
Abu Zir.
Û Berberiyê... Ehmed Qiblewî. Berberiyê gund bû jî.
And the Barber... Ahmed Qiblewi. He was also the village
barber [or leader].
Û hew jî dihat li vê derê, û çîrok hewal didan û distira jî.
And he also came to this place, and told stories and sang
too.
Kurmancî jî distira û Erebî.
He sang in Kurmanji and Arabic.
Ne Ereb bûn, Ereb?
Weren't they Arab, Arab?
Ereb bû, bes bi Erebî distira û bi Kurmancî jî distira.
He was Arab, but he sang in Arabic and sang in Kurmanji too.
Hîvarî distira û rûdiniştin.
In the evenings he sang and they sat.
Hada pir aîle hebûn zeman, pir aîle hebûn...
There were many families back then, many families...
Je hadibûn je... hirh je ber ve... t... ma'rat... ma'rat el
artîq hebûn... hebûn le ji Qiblê wîq hebûn, mala Brîmo hebu,
Ehmed Brîmo, ew jî şûna Heleb... Pir aîle hebûn, gîş vir...
gîş yani çûn.
They had come from... um from... Ma'rat... Ma'rat al-Artiq
were there... there were from Qiblewiq, the Brimo family was
there, Ahmed Brimo, he is also from Aleppo place... Many
families were there, all here... all, meaning, left.
Ji mêj, ji çel pêncî salî de çûne. Ne, ne li zemana noka na.
Kes nema.
Long ago, forty or fifty years ago they left. No, not in the
current times. No one remained.
Neha di gund da, çi pirsgirêkê gund hebana... Kurd bû, Ereb
bû wîn dihatin vê odê?
Now in the village, whatever problems the village had... be
it Kurd, be it Arab, did you come to this Oda?
Erê, gî... nav Kurda û Ereba jî... wekî bira, bi hevdura
dijiyan.
Yes, all... among Kurds and Arabs too... like brothers, they
lived together.
Gî dihatin di vê odê de rûdiniştin.
All came and sat in this Oda.
Çi mişkîlek heba, çi derd bû, gî hel dikirin li vê derê.
Whatever problem there was, whatever trouble, they solved it
all here.
Û mişkîla ne wekî noka, êkê helbiyo yanî.
And the problem was not like now, [where] one would flare
up, you know.
Nebên welle mişkîlek bû û nikanî hel krana. Ka çi ba, êkê
hel krana yanî.
They wouldn't say "by God there was a problem and it
couldn't be solved." Whatever it was, one would solve it.
Tim helê xwe diçî odê da bû. Û hew mered mezin, rûdiniştin û
hew mişkla hel dikirin.
Always its solution went into the Oda. And those great men
sat and solved that problem.
Neha komîn ava bûye?
Now has the Commune been established?
Noka komîn, eslen em teqlîdê... ewê xoyê berê dikin.
Now the Commune, actually we imitate... those ones of the
past.
Çawa meziniyê gund heba mesele... ê gund... li hev
rûdinin...
Just as there was a village elder for example... of the
village... sitting together...
Çi mişkîlek gund e, çi xedemetî gund gerekin...
Whatever problem is the village's, whatever services the
village needs...
Çi lijne de komînê da hene...
Whatever committees are in the Commune...
Ez jî serokê komînê me, ê gundim. Û ez xu danê vê kolkê min,
xu danê vê odê ne.
I am also the head of the Commune, of the village. And I am
the owner of this gate [house] of mine, owners of this Oda.
Û yanî teqrîben karê komînê me, wekî şe'bê me yê berê, çû
dikir, eslen wê tenzîmê em dimeşînin di gund da.
And meaning roughly the work of our Commune, is like our
people of the past, what they did, actually that
organization we are running in the village.
Em li adet û teqalîdê berê çû dimeşiyon...
We [follow] the customs and traditions of the past, how they
walked [functioned]...
Çû mirova tiştek bibûya, em derin li hevdû dipirsin.
If something happened to a person, we go and ask after each
other.
Çi mişkîlek li gund hebe, em dipirsin.
Whatever problem is in the village, we ask.
Kîşkê, heq di heqê wî da xwar be, em derin malat...
Whoever, if a right was eaten against his right [if he was
wronged], we go to the families...
Berê jî wa bû teb'en. Berê jî wergî dikirin.
Before it was like that too, naturally. Before they did
exactly that.
Û em noka jî nefsi wî mebde'î dimeşin.
And we now also walk on that same principle.
Çi mişkîlek di kuder malê da heye, em derin wê mişklê sed
dikin.
Whatever problem exists in whichever house, we go and block
[fix] that problem.
Efrahe di nav gund, em sê taîfe ne, Rûbarî, ê Kurmanc û...
[In] celebrations in the village, we are three sects/groups,
Rubari, the Kurmanj and...
Hinko malê Hemdê ne, eslê xweş Hiyaniyê ne, hew jî di gund
da rûniştine.
Some are the Hamde family, their origin is from Hiyan, they
also settled in the village.
Û malê Misto jî, hew no... ew...
And the Misto family too, those... those...
Na mîratî ye.
No, it is a tradition (inheritance).
Heke kaptan N'êmî ne.
Even if they are Captain Naimi.
Em gi bi hevdira dijîn, em gi bi hevdira destbira ne.
We all live together, we are all sworn brothers to each
other.
Ahzanê me, dawetê me muxtelêt in, gi bi hevdra.
Our sorrows, our weddings are mixed, all together.
Adî, adî. Wekî...
Normal, normal. Like...
Çawa virtual, nefsî şî ye.
Just like virtual, it is the same thing.
Yanî adetê me gi yek in.
Meaning our customs are all the same.
Heta ew jî wekî adetê me, cilê xwe, denqê xwe, elaqetê xwe,
iştîmaeta xwe...
Even they are like our customs, their clothes, their style,
their relations, their social life...
Wekî me ne, bidebt.
They are like us, exactly.
Gelek spasî we dikin, sehet xweş.
We thank you very much, bless you.
Ser çava, ser sera, bixêr hatin, ser çava.
You are welcome, upon my head, welcome, you are welcome.
Selamet, spas.
Safety to you, thanks.
Way lo, way lo, way lo, way lo.
Oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my.
Way lo, way lo, way lo wa.
Oh my, oh my, oh my.
Şêrînê Xwedê da wa lo, şêrînê Xwedê da wa.
The sweet one given by God, the sweet one given by God.
Ser textê xînê d'xew da wa lo, ser textê xînê d'xew da wa.
On the henna bed while sleeping, on the henna bed while
sleeping.
Min panîk pê va da wa lo, min panîk pê va da wa.
I kicked it with my heel, I kicked it with my heel.
Mişte re tûrek ke wa lo, mişte re tûrek ke wa.
Filled a bag with a handful of it, filled a bag with a
handful of it.
Way lo, way lo, way lo wa.
Oh my, oh my, oh my.
Tel vî girî li wî ristî lê, tel vî girî li wî ristî.
Tied a knot in that spun thread, tied a knot in that spun
thread.
Rindê bilxarê xistî lê, rindê bilxarê xistî.
The beauty put on the jewelry, the beauty put on the
jewelry.
Liv meryê xirapo lo, dil ket qîska b'dergistî.
Oh bad man, the heart fell for the engaged girl.
Lo way lo, way lo wa lo, way lo, way lo, way lo wa.
Oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my, oh my.
Şêrînê Xwedê da wa lo, şêrînê Xwedê da wa.
The sweet one given by God, the sweet one given by God.
Belê temaşevanên hêja.
Yes, dear viewers.
Li vir jî em dighêne dawiya xeleka xwe, dawiya bernameya
xwe.
Here we reach the end of our episode, the end of our
program.
Îro jî em li gundê Keştê bûn.
Today we were in the village of Keshte.
Me bi hevra vê gundî naskir, me bi hevra şûpan.
We got to know this village together, we tracked it
together.
Heya hefteyek din, emê dîsa bera bin.
Until another week, we will be together again.
Li benda me bin, lê vê carê li gundekî din. Bi xatira we.
Wait for us, but this time in another village. Goodbye.
[Music]