Serkanî ye da spî ye, heya Hemamê tûm rêk e.
It is white at the fountain, the road is straight all the
way to Hemamê.
Ciyê zeytûn, kelem û merx, bayê jê tê tûm hênik e.
The place of olives, thorns, and junipers, the wind blowing
from there is always cool.
Belê, vê hefteyê me berê xwe da navçeya Cindirêsê.
Yes, this week we turned our direction to the district of
Jindires.
Em derbasî gundê Hemamê bûn.
We entered the village of Hemamê.
Di sala 1939'an da, li vir sînor çêbû.
In the year 1939, a border was created here.
Li vir xetek çêkirin, têlek çêkirin, gund bi du alî.
They drew a line here, built a fence, [splitting] the
village into two sides.
Hinek li Rojavayê Kurdistanê ket, enî jî li Bakurê
Kurdistanê ket.
Some of it fell into Western Kurdistan (Rojava), and the
other into Northern Kurdistan (Bakur).
Berî vê gundê, navê xwe Qişla Omer Axa bû.
Before this, the name of the village was Qişla Omer Axa
(Omer Agha's Barracks).
Lê di vir da avek heye, ji bo nexweşiyê.
But there is a water source here, for sicknesses [healing].
Piştî wî nav lêkirin gundê Hemamê. De ka vê hefteyê em hev
re derbas bin, em vî gundî nas bikin.
Afterwards, they named it the village of Hemamê (Bath). So,
this week let us go together and get to know this village.
Gundê Qişla Omer Axa, yan girêdayî Cindirêsê, ku niha wekî
Hemamê tê bi nav kirin.
The village of Qişla Omer Axa, or connected to Jindires,
which is now known as Hemamê.
Deh kîlometreyan Rojavayê navçeya Cindirêsê dikeve.
It is located ten kilometers west of the Jindires district.
Gevirên malan, dar û berên gundê ku li ser sînor e, di
navbera Rojava û Bakurê Kurdistanê de ye.
The ruins of homes, the trees and surroundings of the
village located on the border, is between Rojava and
Northern Kurdistan.
Di nava dîrokê de, şahidî li jiyana Kurdewarî û civaka
Xoybûnê ra kiriye.
Throughout history, it has borne witness to the Kurdish way
of life and the Xoybûn society.
Û gelek serpêhatiyên jiyanî borandiye.
And it has passed through many life experiences.
Dema Fransa, Sûriye û Rojavayê Kurdistanê dagir kiribû, di
herêma gund de nahiyek çêkiribû.
When France occupied Syria and Western Kurdistan, a district
center (nahiye) was established in the village region.
Û wekî navenda bazirganiyê bikar dianî.
And it was used as a center for trade.
Ji ber ku li vir navendeke bazirganiyê hebû, besedan
bazirgan û rêwî serî li herêmê didan.
Because there was a trade center here, hundreds of merchants
and travelers would visit the region.
Û pêdiviyên xwe peyda dikirin.
And they would procure their necessities.
Bi vê sedemê jî ji ber xwesteka gund, av û hewa herêm geş bû
û wekî navendeke sereke dihat bikaranîn.
For this reason, and due to the appeal of the village, the
region's climate and atmosphere thrived, and it was used as
a main center.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, em derbasî gundê Hemamê bûn.
Yes, dear viewers, we entered the village of Hemamê.
Ev dîmenê we dîtin, ev dîmenê gundê Hemamê bûn.
These scenes you saw, these were scenes of the village of
Hemamê.
Em derbasî mala Apê Evdo Roşo bûn, bavê Celal.
We entered the home of Uncle Evdo Roşo, father of Jalal.
Li gundî jî hemî hatin derdora me, em spasîya wan dikin.
In the village, everyone gathered around us, we thank them.
Emê silav bikin li Apê Evdo.
We will greet Uncle Evdo.
Ya ehlen û sehlen, ehlen û sehlen, hatin xêr, bi silametî
hevalno.
Oh welcome, welcome, welcome in peace, safely friends.
Sax be. Apê Evd, ev gundê we kengî ava bû?
Bless you. Uncle Evd, when was your village built?
Gundê me, tê bîra min, hîn berî hezar û neh sed û sî û nehan
da (1939).
Our village, as I recall, even before nineteen hundred and
thirty-nine (1939).
Te bîst? Li vanderê Axler hatine. Berê hatine, hîn berê.
Did you hear? The Aghas (lords) came here. They came before,
even earlier.
Gund tune bû li vir. Axler hatin li vira, gund çêkirin.
There was no village here. The Aghas came here, built the
village.
Milk li hevdu pay kirin.
They divided the property among themselves.
Vade re Şêx Mihemed Axa ketê.
This place here fell to Sheikh Muhammad Agha.
Xerbî vir, Arif Axa ketê. Xerbî, Silêman Axa ketê. Evna sê
bira bûn.
West of here, Arif Agha took it. West [of that], Suleiman
Agha took it. These were three brothers.
Te bîst? Paşê li vanderê bazar çêbû. Nahiye çêbû. Esas
nahiya me li Mabatê bû.
Did you hear? Then a bazaar was created here. A district
center (nahiye) was created. Originally, our district center
was in Mabeta.
Dapîra me li Mabatê bûn. Dapîra Axleran yani.
Our grandmothers were in Mabeta. The grandmothers of the
Aghas, that is.
Mabeta da ket urfî, vadere çêbû.
Mabeta fell under martial law/customary rule, and this place
was built up.
Li vanderê Axlera hikum kir.
The Aghas ruled here.
Çarşî çêbû, bazar çêbû, otêl hebû.
A market was built, a bazaar was built, there was a hotel.
Gi hebû, Ermenî sirgûn bibûn hatibûn, Ermenî tijî bûn li
vanderê.
Everything existed. Armenians had been exiled and came here;
it was full of Armenians here.
Cem me pir bûn.
There were many with us.
Paşê nahiye çêbû.
Then the district center was established.
Û nahiyê, va milletan gi li dor Axleran kom bûn.
And the district... all these people gathered around the
Aghas.
E kengî nahiye çêbû?
So when was the district center established?
Nahiye, bi hîn berî 39'an da çêbibû. Ez gîştimeyê nahiye ye.
The district center was established even before '39. I
reached [was alive during] the district era.
Hîn berî wê, ez waye jê mezin dibîsim.
Even before that, I seem to be older than it.
Girêdayî Qirixxanê bûn, ne ne?
You were connected to Kirikhan, no?
Em girêdayî Rihanî bûn berê.
We were connected to Reyhanli before.
Berî Cindirêsê. Heta Cindirêsê tune bû.
Before Jindires. Back when Jindires didn't even exist.
Vadere nahiye bû.
This place was the district center.
Efrîn?
What about Afrin?
Efrîn heta tune bû tê bîra min.
Afrin didn't even exist back then, in my memory.
Bes Mabeta hebû. Efrîn heta tune bû tê bîra min.
Only Mabeta existed. Afrin didn't even exist in my memory.
Piştî nahiye ji vir rabû, bi çû Cindirêsê?
After the district center left here, did it go to Jindires?
Nahiye ji vanderê rabû, nahiye heta hidûd daket.
The district center left here, the district went down until
the border was placed.
Di 39'an da hidûd danîn. Hîn bazara me li yêjî Tirkî bû.
In '39 they set the border. Our bazaar was still on the
Turkish side.
Na dibêjin berî ev sînora da keve, gundê we li jêr bû. Li
cîkî din bû.
No, they say before this border was placed, your village was
lower down. It was in another place.
Çarşî hebû.
There was a market/downtown.
Hewna Axler li der... li jêr bûn. Paşê hatin vira.
Those Aghas were out... were down there. Then they came
here.
Payî kirin, vanderê noke, tabî'î Şêx Mihemed Axa ye.
They divided it. Here now, naturally, belongs to Sheikh
Muhammad Agha.
E orte, tabî'î Birekê Axa ye. Xerbî jî tabî'î Silêman Axa
ye. Evna sê bira bûn.
The middle naturally belongs to Birek Agha. The west
naturally belongs to Suleiman Agha. These were three
brothers.
Na na, ez serxetê man, e yalî sînor din kî ye? Kî li wir
man?
No no, I mean those who stayed 'above the line' (in Turkey),
who is on the other side of the border? Who stayed there?
Li wir? Gundî vî gundî, gund hebû. Di ortê ra hidûd lêket.
Over there? The villagers of this village, there was a
village. The border cut right through the middle.
Mirovê te li wir hene, merî we?
Are your people there, your relatives?
Pirr in meriyê me.
Our relatives are many [there].
Hemî meriyê we ne.
All of them are our relatives.
Em tê bîra min, me işta em gî li vanderê me baxçe dikirin.
Me banador manador diçandin.
I remember, we used to make gardens all over here. We
planted tomatoes and such.
Me baxçe diçand. Li wî deştê vanderê.
We planted gardens. On that plain over there.
Yanî piştî ev sînora da ket, hûn parçe bûn. Gund bû du
parçe.
So after this border was placed, you were separated. The
village became two pieces.
Em parçe bûn, em fel... em li vira man. Em li hikumeta Ereba
re man, ê din jî çûn hikumeta Tirka re çûn.
We were separated... we stayed here. We stayed with the Arab
government, and the others went with the Turkish government.
Pismamê bavkê min, wana gî çûn waderê.
My father's cousins, they all went over there.
E haya we ji hev heye?
Do you have news of each other / stay in touch?
Erê, ya em haydar in teca me.
Yes, we are aware of our interactions.
Hûn di cejna de diçin ba hevdu?
Do you go to each other during the holidays (Eid)?
Di eîda da...
During the Eids...
Di eîda da jî wek din pasaporta jî, berê, berê hidûd felt
bû, em diçûn dihatin, tişt tunne bû.
During the Eids, like with passports... before, when the
border was loose, we used to go and come, there was nothing
[stopping us].
Na, ev gundê we, berê navê xwe din hebû? Berî gundê Hemamê?
No, this village of yours, did it have another name before?
Before "Village of Hemamê"?
Qişlet Omer Axa bû berê.
It was "Qişlet Omer Axa" (Omer Agha's Barracks) before.
Noka nifûsê dume tê da hene, dibê Qişlet Omer Axa.
Even now, in the ID records we have, it says Qişlet Omer
Axa.
Qeyda nifîsê hîn li ser Qişla Omer Axa ye?
Is the civil registry record still listed as Qişla Omer Axa?
Qişlet Omer Axa ye, erê.
It is Qişlet Omer Axa, yes.
Omer Axa bavkê waş sê na bû.
Omer Agha was the father of those three [brothers].
Qişlet Omer Axa ye.
It is Qişlet Omer Axa.
Waxtê li vir qişla çêkirin, millet gî hatin. Hatin cem, li
vira çarşî çêbû, bazar çêbû, nahiye çêbû.
When they built the barracks here, all the people came. They
gathered, a market was built here, a bazaar was built, a
district center was built.
Piştî ev sînora da ket, tiştek nema?
After this border was placed, nothing remained?
Tiştek nema, hidûd derket. Îçî wî, wacî çû. Paşê lora milk
belakirin.
Nothing remained, the border appeared. This one went here,
that one went there. Then they divided the property there.
Qandî vî gundî, gund hebû li xerbî vir.
As big as this village, there was a village to the west of
here.
Tirka milk belakir, av hişk kirin. Millet kişandin, milk
danê.
The Turks distributed the property, dried up the water. They
pulled the people [away] and gave them property.
Vadera boş ma, xêrî malikî... melekîyê xa bû, vira erdê xa
bû, hew ma.
This place remained empty, except for a house... it was his
own property, this was his own land, it just remained.
Bes hew ma.
It just remained.
Wek din gî boş bû vira.
Otherwise, it became completely empty here.
Ya cî xerbî.
On the western side.
Cem me, em li halî xa man.
With us, we stayed in our own situation.
Na jî gund mezin bû ye? Ev gund?
Is the village big now? This village?
Gund mezin bû ye, aîle pir bûn e. Her yekî meselen her aîlek
bûye çar pênc parçe.
The village has grown, the families have become many. For
example, every family has become four or five parts
[households].
Ev navê Hemam ji kû hat?
Where did this name "Hemam" (Bath) come from?
Navê Hemamê li cem me ava qudretê heye, ji erdê da, avê germ
dertê.
The name Hemam... near us there is "power water" (natural
spring), from the ground, hot water comes out.
Vê ra digotin Hemam.
They called this Hemam (Bath).
Û navê gund jî Hemam lêkirin.
And they named the village Hemam too.
Heta li yêjî Tirkiyê heye, dibên Hemamê Ereba, gundek jî li
wir heye, dibên Ereb lê pir bûn. Digot Hemamê Ereba.
Even on the Turkey side there is one, they call it "Arab's
Hammam", there is a village there too, they say there were
many Arabs. They called it Arab's Hammam.
Yanî av li gundî we hebû, ji bo nexweşiyê bû?
So there was water in your village, was it for sickness?
Bû nexweşiyê, merî gureba sedat dikete, ra şamê dihatin, ji
Guder dihatin... li vir otêl hebû. Otêlê xew dikirin, xwe
dişûştin, derdikirin. Diçûn.
It was for sickness, people with scabies/skin diseases would
come... they came from Damascus, from Guder... there was a
hotel here. They slept in the hotel, washed themselves, and
got out. They would go.
E milet ji kû der dihat vira?
Where did the people come from to here?
Ji Idlibê dihatin, ji Helebê dihatin, ji Hemê, ji Humsê, ra
Şamê dihatin. Dengî... avê vê, avê bîstik dihatin vira, li
otêlê xew dikirin.
They came from Idlib, from Aleppo, from Hama, from Homs,
they came from Damascus. The fame... of this water, this
[healing] water, they came here and slept in the hotel.
Haya naha tên?
Do they still come now?
Na, noka nayên. Ji ber ku hidûd daketî nayên.
No, now they don't come. Because the border was placed, they
don't come.
Di 39'an û vir da dan, nayên pir.
From '39 onwards, they don't come much.
Paşê di du 39'an ra heval, di du 39'an ra, hikumeta Tirka û
Sûriyê ittîfaq kirin bi hev ra. Mileti va derê diçû xal
Hemamê dişûşt.
Then after '39 friend, after '39, the Turkish and Syrian
governments made an agreement together. The people here used
to go to the Hammam and wash.
Apê Evd, haya naha ew av li vir heye? Avek...
Uncle Evd, is that water still here now? A water...
Li yêjî Sûriyê tunne ye heval. Yêjî Tirkiyê ma ew ava.
On the Syria side there isn't any, friend. That water
remained on the Turkey side.
Heman e vira, lê xistine çîçik germ e, yanî germ e, ne wek
wê Hemamê ye.
Right here, they tapped into a little bit of warm [water],
meaning it is warm, but not like that Hammam.
Ne wek wê ye. Ew Hemam a, tu têkevî setik, cismî te paf da
germ dibe.
It's not like that one. That Hammam, if you enter for an
hour, your body immediately gets hot.
Hewa bînê kurkûkê jê tê, germ e, ne pir germ e.
A sulfur smell comes from it, it is hot, but not too hot.
Ne pir germ e.
Not too hot.
Yanî Adem baştir, ji vê baştir e?
Meaning man [feels] better, better than this one?
Erê, hawa. Li vira otêl hebû, xelk dihat bi mehan tê da xew
dikirin. Xwe li wir dişûştin, nexweş bûn, çê dibûn, diçûn.
Yes, exactly. There was a hotel here, people came and slept
in it for months. They washed themselves there, they were
sick, they got better, and left.
Du hemam bûn, ne yek.
There were two hammams (baths), not one.
Yek e beleş bû, millet diketê. Yek jî bi pera, beledîye
bir... da bû.
One was free, the people entered it. The other was for
money, the municipality took... gave it.
Bi pera diketine, li otêlê xew dikirin. Otêl li vira hebû.
They entered with money, they slept in the hotel. There was
a hotel here.
Nana, li vê milî me ne heye?
No no, on our side is there none?
Ne ma, ne otêl, ne av heye.
None remained, neither hotel nor water exists.
Bes mexferê Tirka li wir e. Kes naçe nayê. Bes milletî wa
doriyê, xwa diçin.
Only the Turkish outpost is there. No one goes or comes.
Only the people of that surrounding area go themselves.
...şûn derdiketin û esker hatin şûn, eskerê tirka.
...they were leaving and soldiers took their place, Turkish
soldiers.
Ope Evdo, gundê we debara xwe bi çi dike?
Uncle Avdo, how does your village make a living?
Debara me, em berê milkê me tinenebû, giş axlera bû. Îslah
ziraat hat milk bela kir, em bi milkê xwe dijîn.
Our livelihood, before we didn't have property, it all
belonged to the landlords. Agricultural reform came and
distributed property, we live off our property.
E wext çi cew heye?
So what kind of crops are there?
Zeytûn hene. Meselen xudra giş heye. Bes darê fêkî di
hewşada hene yanê, baxçe wekî din tinene.
There are olives. For example, there are all kinds of
vegetables. But fruit trees are only in the courtyards,
there are no orchards otherwise.
Mala te ava be.
Thank you.
Ser te ta xweş be.
You are welcome.
Li seranserî kantonê, Efrînê têne li gundê Hemamê ava
kibrîtî weke derman tê bikaranîn heye.
Across the canton, only in Afrin, in the village of Hamam,
sulfur water is used as medicine.
Berîya sînûr bi têlan rêsa yî bê tê girtin...
Before the border was closed with wire fences...
Gundîyan û hemû xelkê herêmê serî li vî ragihiştin a Bakurê
Kurdistanê didan û ava wê wekî derman bikar dianîn.
The villagers and all the people of the region used to visit
this spring in Northern Kurdistan and used its water as
medicine.
Piştî sînûr hate girtin, gundî ketin nava lêgerînê û dema
bîrek dikolan, di alîyê Rojavayê da jî heman ava wê alî
derket.
After the border was closed, the villagers started searching
and while digging a well, on the Rojava side the same water
as that side came out.
Noha jî xelkê herêmê û bajar û hemû gundên herêmê serî lê
didin...
Now the people of the region and the city and all the
villages of the region visit it...
...û laşê xwe bi vê ava bîrê dişûn.
...and wash their bodies with this well water.
Belê noha em derbasî nava zevîkî bûn, nava darên zeytûnan
bûn.
Yes, now we have entered a field, among the olive trees.
Ev gundê Hemamê bi vê avê tê naskirin.
This village of Hamam is known for this water.
Berê ev av li vî alîyê sînûr bu, piştî wî ev têl hat vêr
çêbûn, sînûr qut da ket.
Before, this water was on this side of the border, after
that this wire was built here, the border cut through.
Gund ji vê avê qut bû. Lê ber vê bi çend sala bîrek li vir
kolandin, dîsa av derket.
The village was cut off from this water. But a few years ago
they dug a well here, and water came out again.
Ev ava ji bo nexweşîyê jî ye. Em hatine cem Birêz Mihemed
Elî, emê bipirsin. Merheba ji te ra.
This water is also for illnesses. We have come to Mr.
Muhammad Ali, we will ask. Hello to you.
Ya ehlen we sehlen, ser dil û çava. Ehlen we sehlen bi
hatina we kanala Rûnahî, ser ser û ser çava.
Oh welcome, upon my heart and eyes. Welcome to the arrival
of your Ronahi channel, upon my head and eyes.
Çavê te sax bin. Ava te jî, av jî pir germ e av.
May your eyes be healthy. Your water, the water is also very
hot.
Av germ e, av herareta avê 41 e. 41 e heraret.
The water is hot, the water temperature is 41. 41 is the
temperature.
Ev kengî te ev bîra koland?
When did you dig this well?
Va bîra me kola sala hezar nehsed û heftê da.
We dug this well in the year nineteen seventy.
Me kola serê vê em darê avdin. Me kola maşallah av derket,
av pir derket.
We dug it initially to water the trees. We dug and mashallah
water came out, a lot of water came out.
Me rabû trompa daxistê, çar înc em jê dikişînin. Me rabû ava
wî me bir çû Helebê tehlîl kir.
We lowered a pump into it, we are drawing four inches from
it. We took its water and went to Aleppo to analyze it.
Yanî dema we kolan av germ derket?
Meaning when you dug, hot water came out?
Av germ derket, me zanî ava Hemamê ye. Wa ava ku li hêlê
sînûr mayî. Me sehkir hew av e.
Hot water came out, we knew it was the Hamam water. That
water that remained on the border side. We realized it is
that same water.
Ew ava jî em berê da zanin, xelk dihat, nexweşîyê gurr vira
heba, şebab, xort, ser çavî wana, ew bana, çêdibûn hebe sale
çêdibûn.
We knew that water from before, people used to come, if
there was scabies disease here, youth, young men, on their
faces, pimples, they would get better, Aleppo boil would get
better.
Nexweşîyê kaba, vira heba na çêdibû. Pora wî diweşîya,
meletê nexweş vira heye çêdibû. Hew av va derket.
Knee diseases, if it was here, it would get better. Their
hair was falling out, a sick person was here, they would get
better. That same water came out here.
Me rabû me xwest em li ser wî luqente çêkin. Em çûn Helebê,
merago tê herî ava wî nîwarî, emê ava wî tehlîl kin.
We stood up and wanted to build a facility on it. We went to
Aleppo, they told us you go and bring its water, we will
analyze its water.
Geger sefî nexweşîyê derket emê ji te ra semah kin tê
bişuxulî, tê çêkî luqente.
If it turns out to be for healing diseases, we will permit
you to work, you will build the facility.
Me hat ava wî bir çû Heleb Kulîyet el-'Ulûm. Ji me re av
tehlîl kirin, netîcê tehlîlê avê derket...
We came and took its water to Aleppo, Faculty of Sciences.
They analyzed the water for us, the result of the water
analysis came out...
...ku va ava, ava nexweşîyê romatîzm, û hebet şebab, û hebet
sale, û nexweşîyê cild, û men' teqelus el-şe'r, û va tiştî
ra çêbû.
...that this water, is water for rheumatism disease, and
acne, and Aleppo boil, and skin diseases, and prevents hair
loss, and was good for these things.
Ji me re gotin ok herre luqente çêke. Em hatin me ev luqente
ra bû me çêkir.
They told us okay, go build the facility. We came and built
this facility.
Hîn luqente naha kêmasîya xwe jî heye gerek otêl hebe. Sevi
nexweşek werê têda mualace be nexweşîyê wekî nexweşîyê disq.
Still, the facility currently has its shortcomings, there
needs to be a hotel. Because if a patient comes to be
treated for a disease like disc disease.
Vêra yê werê mualace be. Lazim e ev a rakeve. Ewa li cîyê
xwe nelive.
They will come here to be treated. It is necessary for them
to lie down. They shouldn't move from their place.
Dr. mualace fîzaîye werê wî mualace ke, rok, dudu, heft,
deh, pazdeh, bîst ro da ji wan nexweşîyê xelas dibe.
A physical therapy doctor should come and treat them, one
day, two, seven, ten, fifteen, twenty days, they will be
cured of those diseases.
Ne nexweşke rabe û herre mal û sê roj çar rojan şûnda were û
hana va tûnî feydê nabîne.
Not a patient who gets up and goes home and comes back three
or four days later, like that they won't see any benefit.
Ile nexweş ji bo va avê rakeve, her rokê du car sê caran
masaj ke diktorê mualace fîzaîye, gi van nexweşa feydê
bibîne.
Unless the patient lies down for this water, gets massaged
two or three times every day by a physical therapy doctor,
then these patients will see benefit.
Ew tişta jî me nikanî bikira, qudretê me negiştê.
That thing we couldn't do, our means didn't reach it.
Me rabû kanî, hîç kanî me kir, me nikanî otêl çêkira. Me
nikanî, wa otêl ji wa tûnî ma.
We built the spring, we just made the spring, we couldn't
build a hotel. We couldn't, that hotel just remained
unbuilt.
Ava, ava kuda dihere ev ava?
The water, where does this water go?
Va ava dihere luqentê.
This water goes to the facility.
Na yanî ava ku zêde dibe diherike kuda?
No, meaning the water that overflows, where does it flow to?
Ava zêde dihere, meşa gund heye, dihere nav meşa gund dihere
ciyêkî nizim dihere.
The excess water goes, there is a village drain, it goes
into the village drain, goes to a low place.
Sînûr çiqas dûrî vê ye?
How far is the border from here?
Sînûr va ye, hezar metron, pênc sed metron dûr e.
The border is right there, a thousand meters, five hundred
meters away.
Emê niha herin wê derê jî.
We will now go there as well.
Emê herin wê derê, ez ji te ra xeber dim.
We will go there, I will talk to you there.
Belê niha em giştine ciyê, ev kesê nexweş tên vêr xwe dikin
avê. Niha ew li kuda ye ciyê xwe dikin avê li kuda ye?
Yes, now we have reached the place where these sick people
come here and bathe in the water. Now where is it, where is
the place they bathe?
Ciyê xwe dikin avê ha li vê derê hanê ye. Deh dudu odene,
şeş xurfe, ê aîlet dikevinê.
The place they bathe is right here. There are twelve rooms,
six rooms, that families enter.
Her yekî nexweş, nexweşî tu bitûn e, nexweşîyê cild dihatin,
nexweşîyê romatîzm, êşekê kaba, dera dihatin, ê habê sale
dihatin, ê porê xwe diweşê dihatin.
Every sick person, whatever sickness there is, skin diseases
came, rheumatism diseases, pain in the knees, those with
Aleppo boil came, those whose hair was falling out came.
Û gîşî şîfa dibûn yanî, feyde didîn. Diçûn vedigerîyan.
And all found healing, it gave benefit. They left and
returned.
Carekê ez hatim luqentê vira, min dî kalek û pîrekî va
hatine vira. Min go çî ye pîrê?
Once I came to the facility here, I saw an old man and an
old woman came here. I said what is it auntie?
Go wala kalî min hekê davê kevê. Min go çima? Go wala kabê
xwe dêşin, nikanê xav ke, da kal emrê xwe heftê heştê sal e
yanî.
She said well, my old man will fall if I let him go. I said
why? She said well his knees hurt, he can't walk, the old
man was seventy-eighty years old.
Ê min go ehlen we sehlen, de hat kalê rehet bibe inşallah.
Min go bes rehet bû, tê kê miron, mrîşkî minî werî ha,
mrîşkik sipî têkê minî werî. Bi pîrê ra.
So I said welcome, come, may the old man get relief
inshallah. I said but if he gets relief, you will make me a
dish, bring me my chicken, bring me a white chicken. To the
old woman.
Wala go temam. Rabû ketinê çûn. Rojê din saet heft û nîv ez
hatim vira tên paqiş dikin, zariyê me tên.
Well she said okay. They got up, entered, and went. The next
day at seven thirty I came here, they come to clean, our
children come.
Min hatim min dî kal û pîrê berqê pida hatin, li salonê
ratin e.
I came and saw the old man and woman walking briskly,
resting in the salon.
Tu çikirin?
What did you do?
Ji xwedê berşî ye bûn. Min go hun çi digerin, vê sibê zû
hatine çi? Go yaro saetê te xweş. Go ya qurban va ocaxî bim.
They were awake early by God. I said what are you looking
for, why did you come this early morning? She said oh man,
health to your hours. She said oh sacrifice, may I be this
hearth.
Go kalî min heşev têr xav kir go. Kalê rehet xav kir go,
derê xwe nêşîyan.
She said my old man slept fully tonight. The old man slept
comfortably, his places didn't hurt.
Ê min go ehlen we sehlen. Wala kal jî ji nava jî kirê û ji
nava jî çûn.
So I said welcome. Well the old man also did the bath from
inside and they went from inside.
Ev çend sal e te evir çêkirî?
How many years has it been since you built this place?
Vira wala sala du hezar û sissyê da me xelas kir. Bes sala
du hezar a da em pê belişîyan. Du sal du sal nîva min ra
dirêj kir. Heya me xelas kir.
Here, well in the year two thousand and three we finished
it. But in the year two thousand we started struggling with
it. It took me two years, two and a half years. Until we
finished it.
Vira jî hîn ji me, qudretê me têr nekir em vira çêkin.
Here too, still from us, our means were not enough to build
fully here.
Hukimetê jî alîkarîya me nekir, ne qertek da me, ne tiştek
da me. Me gîş bi hesabê xwe, bi kîsê xwe me çêkir.
The government also didn't help us, didn't give us a loan,
didn't give us anything. We built it all on our own account,
out of our own pocket.
Me xwest em vira mezbut kin, otêla çêkin, tişta çêkin, me
nikanî.
We wanted to make this place solid, build hotels, build
things, we couldn't.
Yanî niha tu dixwazî ku vira çêkî, yanî avadankî?
So now you want to build here, meaning to develop it?
Ez dixwazim vira avadankim, eger emkanîyet hebe, destek
hebe, ezê vira bikim cinet.
I want to develop here, if there is possibility, if there is
support, I will make this place a paradise.
Ezê ximê vira rakim, oda lêkim. Ximê me çadirin, naylonin,
zivistanê sar e, nexweş nikanin werin. Tên dicemidin, diçin
nexweş dikevin.
I will remove the tents here, build rooms. Our tents are
canvas, nylon, in winter it is cold, patients cannot come.
They come and freeze, go and get sick.
Ez dixwazim vira ximê rakim, oda lêkim, vira bikim, bi Erebî
jêra dibêjin 'Merkez sihî lil mualace fîzaîye'.
I want to remove the tents here, build rooms, make this
place, in Arabic they call it 'Health Center for Physical
Therapy'.
Temam. Te spas dikim. Serkeftin ji te ra. Bişalla tu ji
otêla jî bigrê.
Okay. I thank you. Success to you. Inshallah you will also
build the hotel.
Ya ehlen we sehlen. Bi hatina we, bi kanala Rûnahî. Ser ser
û ser çava. Û ehlen we sehlen ji we ra.
Oh welcome. With your arrival, with Ronahi channel. Upon
head and upon eyes. And welcome to you.
Mîna hemû gundên ser sînûrê di navbera Rojavayê û Bakurê
Kurdistanê de, gundîyên Hemamê jî ziyanek mezin ji ber xeta
sînûr dîtin.
Like all the villages on the border between Rojava and
Northern Kurdistan, the villagers of Hamam also suffered
great damage due to the border line.
Û malbatên gund ji hev perçe bûn. Beşek e gundîyan ji li
Rojavayê û beşê din jî li Bakurê Kurdistanê man.
And the village families were torn apart. A part of the
villagers remained in Rojava and the other part in Northern
Kurdistan.
Ji ber vê yekê civak û kûn, goşîn û şahîyên xwe bi hevre
jîyan dikirin...
Because of this, they lived their social gatherings and
weddings and celebrations together...
Ji hevkutbûn û nemanê, karîbûn hevdû bibînin.
From separation and absence, they were able to see each
other.
Dema Fransa ji Sûriyê vekişiya, di gundê Hemamê de deriyekî
sînor, ku wekî fermî hate avakirin.
When France withdrew from Syria, an official border gate was
established in the village of Hemamê.
Rêjîma Baas şibû ku herêmên kurdan bi pêş nekeve, derî girt
û li şûna wî derî, navçeya Ezaz a Atmayê vekirin.
The Baath regime, wanting the Kurdish regions not to
develop, closed the gate and opened the Azaz district of
Atma instead of that gate.
Gundiyên Hemamê yên ku bi xwezaya xwe ra bûn yek, li benda
wê rojê ne ku careke din dixwazin xwara yên Bakur re jiyana
bê tîl bijîn.
The villagers of Hemamê, who are one with their nature, are
waiting for the day when they want to live a life without
wire [fences] with those in the North again.
Karibin careke din bi hêsanî serdana hevdû bikin û jiyana
civakî ya berê bijîn.
To be able to visit each other easily once again and live
the social life of the past.
Belê, em derbasî mala axê bûn. Ev pişta me xuya ye qişla axê
bû.
Yes, we moved to the Agha's house. What is visible behind us
was the Agha's barracks [mansion].
Navê Apê Mistefa me re hat, bû alîkar, em spasîya wî dikin.
We were given Uncle Mustafa's name, he helped us, we thank
him.
Apê Mistefa, destpêkê kijan axa di vî gundî... navê xwe çi
bû?
Uncle Mustafa, initially which Agha was in this village...
what was his name?
Golkê bûn, Omer Axa. Omer Axa.
They were Golkê [family name], Omar Agha. Omar Agha.
Paşê qîçik jê gence... pêda bûn... Silêman Axa pêda bû.
Then children... were born from him... Suleiman Agha was
born.
Arif Axa pêda bû. Şêx Mihemed Axa pêda bû.
Arif Agha was born. Sheikh Muhammad Agha was born.
Sê lawê xwe bûn?
Were they his three sons?
Ji yek kalî da.
From one grandfather.
Paşê ji koliye da jî, ew... ji Arif Axa da ew çêbûn.
Then from the lineage as well, they... from Arif Agha they
were born.
Ehmed Axa çêbû. Izzet Axa çêbû.
Ahmed Agha was born. Izzet Agha was born.
Arif Axa çêbû. Hema qonaxa Arif Axa, yê esasî maye li vêra,
niha hema ye.
Arif Agha was born. The mansion of Arif Agha, the main one,
remains here, it is still here now.
Ê din xanî ne... qişla din?
Are the others houses... the other barracks?
Ê din... ê Ehmed Axa jî, ha va, ew li hember me ye. Ê berî
van, yek hebû xera bû.
The other... Ahmed Agha's is also, look there, it is
opposite us. The one before these, there was one, it was
destroyed.
Apê Mistefa heya kîngê axa hebûn li vir?
Uncle Mustafa, until when were there Aghas here?
Heya... pêncî... şêst û pêncî da axler hebûn cem me hêj.
Until... fifty... in '65 and '50 there were still Aghas with
us.
Heta islah hat, şêst û heftê da. Şêst û duduya da hat.
Until the [agrarian] reform came, in '67 [sic]. It came in
'62.
Emlek dôle bela bû, şêst û heftê da jî islah bela bû.
State property was distributed, and in '70 the reform was
distributed [implemented].
Ê çaxê axler neman. Ferq tîn... her kes çû... çû.
At that time Aghas didn't remain. It made no difference...
everyone went... went.
Niha zarokê xwe kî mane?
Who of their children remain now?
Zarokê xwe yek wa ye kelêk me, Enwer Axa ye, lawê Enwer Axa
ye... Enwer Axa lawê Izzet Axa ye.
One of their children is right next to us, Anwar Agha, Anwar
Agha's son... Anwar Agha is Izzet Agha's son.
Ser çava, te spas dikim. Spas.
You're welcome [on my eyes], I thank you. Thanks.
Xwedê sehetê te xweş ke.
May God give you good health.
Hemamê bi ava xwe dewlemend e.
Hemamê is rich with its water.
Di gund de sê bîrên bi destên mirovan hatine kolan hene.
In the village, there are three wells that have been dug by
human hands.
Kevirên bîrên ku di nava gund de belav bûne, rojane li
sitran û serbêhatiyên gundiyan ku bêdiliya xwe ya avê
dikişînin, guhdar dikin.
The stones of the wells scattered within the village listen
daily to the songs and stories of the villagers who draw
their water unwillingly [laboriously].
Kevirên bîran bi gundiyan şîn dikin.
The stones of the wells mourn with the villagers.
Û di heman demê de şahiya wan jî, jiyan dikin.
And at the same time, they live out their joy as well.
Her sê bîr, jêdera tekane ya av a vexwarinê û kar, ya
şêniyên gund e.
All three wells are the sole source of drinking water and
work for the village residents.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, em gihîştin ber sînor. Sînor li pişta
me ye, 20 metro em jê va nêzîk in.
Yes dear viewers, we reached the border. The border is
behind us, we are 20 meters close to it.
Berekî gund li ber gund li vir jî bû. Niha mevanê me li ser
bîrekê, ez û Apê Evdo va.
A part of the village was here in front of the village too.
Now our guest is at a well, me and Uncle Abdo here.
Apê Evdo çend bîr li gundê we hene?
Uncle Abdo, how many wells are there in your village?
Heval, sê bîr li gundê me hene.
Friend, there are three wells in our village.
Yek bîra Firfirkê jê re dibêjin.
One, they call it the Firfirk well.
Li binî çarşî dikeve. Li ser hudûd dikeve, tirka teslîm bir.
It is located below the marketplace. It is located on the
border, the Turks took it over.
Wextê tirk hatin, tirka teslîm bir.
When the Turks came, the Turks took it over.
Vê dera... qurbeta diha lê dîdina, va bîra tina bû.
This place... the nomads would see [settle] here, this well
didn't exist [then].
Va bîra tina bû. Qurbeta temam li vir didîdina. Bazar temam
li Hemamê dibû.
This well didn't exist. The nomads would fully settle here.
The entire market was in Hemamê.
Bazar bû.
It was a market.
Dihatin bi hefta li vira rûdiniştin qurbet. Rabû Xatûnê jê
ra ev bîra kola.
They used to come and sit here for a week, the nomads. So
Khatun dug this well for them.
Va bîra... bîra Xatûnê ye.
This well... is Khatun's well.
Ê din jî Firfirk e. Em vêra dibêjin bîra Firfirkê. Yek jî li
cem me li gund e, gund paş de li ser wê bîrê bû.
The other one is Firfirk. We call it the Firfirk well. And
one is with us in the village, the village was based on that
well back then.
Ê çima dibên Firfirk?
Why do they say Firfirk?
Firfirk... teke ew rêt kiribûne. Wek Firfirka difitilî, av
çêdikir hewz û jor.
Firfirk... just that they had poured [built] it. It spun
like a whirligig (firfirk), making water into the upper
pool.
Jor hewz û dida nehiyê, dida cendirmê, dida êd malê xalê
jêr, gi hewzê wî hebû.
The upper pool gave to the district center, gave to the
gendarmerie, gave to the uncles' houses below, it all had
its pool.
Av didayê.
It gave water.
Ew tişta tê bîra te?
Do you remember those things?
Gî tê bîra min. Rind... heta niha hewzê wî di tehmînim. Rind
tê bîra min.
I remember it all. Well... even now I can estimate [see] its
pool. I remember it well.
Ev jî Xatûnê girtiye kîngê?
And when did Khatun take [dig] this one?
Hewa jî Xatûnê girtî... ji ûştê qurbetê. Bazar ji vê derê
da, wextê cem me bazar, roja duşemê bû.
Khatun took [dug] this one too... because of the nomads. The
market started from here, when the market was with us, it
was on Monday.
Seke, ji şemiyê da bazar bû. Ehedê, duşemê, sêşemê... çar
roja bazar bû. Bazar ji vir da digihîşt kaniya reş.
Look, the market was from Saturday. Sunday, Monday,
Tuesday... the market was for four days. The market reached
from here to Kaniya Reş (Black Spring).
Mirov bazar bû? Berê vir bazar bû?
Was it a human market? Was here a market before?
Bazar li derxan bû, ciyê bazarê eşkere, cem Firfirkê.
The market was outside, the place of the market is obvious,
near Firfirk.
Bazar li wir bû.
The market was there.
Wira ciyê wehesî bû, melet dihatin wir mehesî...
That place was a resting place, people came there to rest...
Wira... bes qurbet lê bûn. hewa qurbeta çadirê xwe didîdan.
There... only nomads were there. The nomads would pitch
their tents there.
Ji wir da, heta kaniya reş, hewa gî bazar bû. Çar ro.
From there, up to Kaniya Reş, it was all a market. Four
days.
Ji Hemê dihatin, ji Humsê, ji Helebê, ji Idlibê, ji
Iskenderûnê, ji guderê... va gî, va bazara çêdibû.
They came from Hama, from Homs, from Aleppo, from Idlib,
from Iskenderun, from everywhere... all of this, this market
was happening.
Ev berê sînor da dikeve?
Does this fall before the border [time]?
Berê sînor da dikeve. Sînor da ket hat... dîsa bazara me li
yê ciyê xerbî bû, li yê ciyê tirka bû.
It falls before the border. The border came down... still
our market was on the western side, on the Turks' side.
Bes hadisek bû, merikekî merik kuşt. Rabû hanîn şerqî
mexferê. Bazar hanîn şerqî mexferê.
But an incident happened, a man killed a man. So they
brought it east of the outpost. They brought the market east
of the outpost.
Şerqî mexferê, çend bazara, wek salekê bazar kirin şerqî
mexferê. Paşê midûr nehiyê rabû Cindirêsê, bazar rakir
Cindirêsê.
East of the outpost, for a few markets, like for a year they
held the market east of the outpost. Then the district
director stood up in Jindires, and moved the market to
Jindires.
Hawa di sî û neha da.
That was in '39.
Naha tê got... ev mala jî berê millet li vir a bû?
Now it is said... were there people in these houses here
before?
Hev na... millet li vir bû, vir a mehellê Ebdîn Axa vêra
digotin. Wira jî malê Şêx Mihemed Axa wan in.
This... no... the people were here, here they called it
Abdin Agha's neighborhood. And there are Sheikh Muhammad
Agha's family's houses.
Ev milleta naha kuderê çûye li vira?
Where have these people gone from here now?
Hev milletê... Tirka, Dêngiz, berê Dêngiz nêzîk bû ji vir
da.
This people... The Turks, the Sea [Lake Amik], before the
Sea was close to here.
Dêngiz hişk kirin. Erd dan va milleti. Millet gî di pêncî û
heyştan da çûn.
They dried up the Sea. They gave land to these people. The
people all left in '58.
Heta pêncî û heyştan, vira gî gund bûn.
Until '58, this was all villages here.
Gund bûn, millet bûn, xanî bûn...
There were villages, there were people, there were houses...
Ya milleta kuderê çû? Ew mirovê we?
So where did the people go? Those relatives of yours?
Gî... gî çûn işte çûn li wir, milk dayê, tirka milk dayê,
erd danê.
All... all went, you know, went there, they gave them
property, the Turks gave them property, gave them land.
Li kîjan gundî rûniştine?
In which village did they settle?
Li Hemam iskanê rûniştine. Li avê... li ewê rûniştine... li
Pircê...
They settled in Hemam Iskan. At the water... they settled at
that... at Pircê...
Pircê rûniştine, ber Dêngizê.
They settled in Pircê, near the Sea [Lake Amik].
Ev gundê Hemamê din li kuderê dikeve?
Where is this other Hemamê village located?
Ê li bakurê Kurdistanê?
The one in North Kurdistan?
Li bakur, li vir dikeve. Li şimal dikeve... Hemamê dikeve.
In the North, it is located here. It is located in the
North... Hemamê is located.
Hemwa... Ereb lê bûn... Ereb... gund gî ê, ê... ê ewê bû.
Those... Arabs were there... Arabs... the village was
entirely, uh... uh... belonged to that.
Ê Axê bû.
It belonged to the Agha.
Ê Eẍe bû. Ereb dihewan... cotarlixê ereba dikir, vêra
lêkirin Hemamê Ereba.
It belonged to the Agha. Arabs stayed... he did farming with
Arabs, so they named it Arab Hemamê.
Ev li Bakurê Kurdistanê dikeve?
Does this fall in North Kurdistan?
Li Bakur, li vir dikeve, li şimal, li vir dikeve. Li şimal,
li vir dikeve. Hemamê dikeve. Hemamek di arleqê me, wî gundî
daye. Û Hemamek jî, ê vir da ye.
In the North, it falls here, in the North, it falls here. In
the North, it falls here. Hemamê falls. There is a Hemamê in
our rear, in that village. And there is a Hemamê here too.
Ê vir da, belaş bû. Millet kî bahata se belaş dikete. Ê wê
da jî, otêl motêl girtibûn. Ê nexweş, ji Şamê, ji Hemê, ji
Humsê dihatin se.
The one here was free. Whoever came could enter for free.
The one over there, they had booked hotels and motels. The
sick used to come from Damascus, from Hama, from Homs.
Bi hefta, bi meha rûdiniştin. Xwe dişûştin.
They would stay for weeks, for months. They would wash
themselves.
Ê gurr dibûn, ê çi, heb meb lê hebûn, se diketine, çêdibûn.
Those who had scabies, or whatever, pills or mills [skin
issues], they would enter and get cured.
Germ bû ava xwe. Ava xwe tunkanî pirtêketa. Yanî germ bû.
Its water was hot. Its water would burst out powerfully.
meaning it was hot.
Nana Apê Evdo...
Now Uncle Abdo...
Ev piştî vî sînor da ket.
This was after this border fell [was established].
Ev mirovê we li wî alî man. Hûn li vî alî man.
These relatives of yours remained on that side. You remained
on this side.
Ê wa.
Like that.
Û ev parçe bûn?
And this was divided?
Erê.
Yes.
Ê we çawa hev didît?
So how did you see each other?
Me... hudûd tina bû. Em saet yekî du şev diçûn, dihatin.
We... there was no border. We used to go and come at one or
two o'clock at night.
Di pêncî û heyştan da, wextê Cemal Ebdilnasir hukim kir, va
hudûda mekin kirin.
In '58, when Gamal Abdel Nasser ruled, they strengthened
these borders.
Pêncî û heyştan.
Fifty-eight.
Axlerê î milkî xwe li wayê jî heye, î li vir heye, bi qeçaxî
diçûn bi pasawana.
The Aghas who had property on that side too, and here too,
used to go illegally with passavants [passes].
Digot pasawan in ev.
He said these are passavants.
Pasawana. Tu axa yî mesela, te erdî te li wir e. Te kîş...
dîlîk... çend merivê te hene, te delîlê xwe xwest, te
pasawanî çêdikir, di qepiro diçûn dihatin.
Not passports?
Pasawana. Tu axa yî mesela, te erdî te li wir e. Te kîş...
dîlîk... çend merivê te hene, te delîlê xwe xwest, te
pasawanî çêdikir, di qepiro diçûn dihatin.
Passavants. You are an Agha for example, your land is there.
You... [stutter]... how many people you have, you asked for
your proof, you made a passavant, they went and came through
the gate.
Heya kîngê ev qapî hat girtin? Vê deriyê hat girtin?
Until when was this gate closed? Was this gate closed?
Hev qapîa... teqrîben di pêncî û heyştan da hat girtin.
Wextê Cemal Ebdilnasir hukim kirî, hat girtin.
This gate... was closed approximately in '58. When Gamal
Abdel Nasser ruled, it was closed.
Ew derî jî girtin?
Did they close that door too?
Wira jî girtin. Paşê vekirin. Vekirin, şêniyê Sûriyê jî
diçû, diket wê Hemamê. Bi pera diketine.
They closed there too. Then they opened it. They opened it,
the residents of Syria also used to go, entered that Hemamê
[bath]. They entered for money.
Belediyê Rihaniyê, îcare dida xelkê. Elî Krêt bire bû.
The municipality of Reyhanli leased it to people. Ali Kret
had taken it.
Elî Krêt li ber rûnişt, qîçkê gund rûdiniştin, bi pera em gî
diçûn diketine.
Ali Kret sat in front of it, the village children sat there,
we all went and entered for money.
Felk bû yanê. Em diçûn... di or de diketine.
It was open [public] essentially. We went... entered there.
Nana, û ew bîra, mirovê xwe nekolane?
Now, and those wells, didn't your people dig them?
Wî bîra hevdû nagirin?
Do those wells not connect to each other?
Em derîntênin, bi pasaporta derîntênin.
We bring them out, we bring them out with passports.
[Speaker misunderstands question or speaks metaphorically
about crossing].
E na... ewê niha... wind kirin?
No... did they now... lose them?
Em... ew... bîlbew... ew di bin hewa ra derînin, ya di esasê
ra derin.
We... that... unknown... they bring it out from under the
air/sky, or they go through the foundation.
Dûr dikevin?
Are they far apart?
Ê dûr dikeve, em bêjin çi... esas gerek qapî li Hemamê ba.
It falls far, let's say what... essentially the gate should
have been at Hemamê.
Spas, sehet xweş.
Thanks, good health.
Ehlen, sehet a te jî xweş.
Welcome, good health to you too.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, em derbasî mizgeftê bûn.
Yes, dear viewers, we have entered the mosque.
Nah, dibêjin kevirekî pir kevn li vir heye, me jî meraq kir
em derbasî mizgeftê bin.
Now, they say there is a very old stone here, we were
curious so we entered the mosque.
Ez û Apê Reşad, û Mele jî li vir bû, spas ji te ra jî.
Myself and Uncle Rashad, and the Mullah was here too, thank
you as well.
Ka ji me ra çîroka vî kevirî bêje.
Tell us the story of this stone.
Wele, va kevra, em gîhiştinê, li hewşa camiyê bû.
Well, this stone, when we arrived [grew up], it was in the
courtyard of the mosque.
Îmamê camiyê hildikişiya ser, li ser jî azan dida.
The Imam of the mosque would climb onto it, and call the
adhan (call to prayer) from atop it.
Li ku derê bû ev kevir?
Where was this stone located?
Li va derê bû. Li pêşiya camiyê bû.
It was right here. It was in front of the mosque.
Hewşa camiyê tinebû, minare tinebû.
There was no mosque courtyard, there was no minaret.
Ev kevra jê gî bilindtir bû, hildikişiya ser azan dida.
This stone was higher than the ground, he would climb up and
call the adhan.
Ev kevra wextîna ji banî ketiye xwarê, em nizanin.
This stone fell down from the top at some point, we don't
know [when].
Bes, Melik el-Eşref li ser nivîsiliye.
But, "Melik el-Eşref" (King Al-Ashraf) is written on it.
Melik el-Eşref melikê Şamê bû.
Melik el-Eşref was the King of Sham (Damascus).
Qçkê Sêfedîn, Ebûbekir el-Eyûbî ye.
He is the son of Saif al-Din, Abu Bakr al-Ayyubi.
Yek melik bû li ser Misrê, navê xwe Melik el-Kamil bû.
One was king over Egypt, his name was Melik el-Kamil.
Yek li ser Şamê bû, navê xwe Melik el-Eşref bû.
One was over Damascus, his name was Melik el-Eşref.
Yek li ser Cizîrê bû, navê xwe Melik el-Salih bû.
One was over Jazira, his name was Melik el-Salih.
Yek li ser Urfayê bû, navê xwe Melik el-Muzeffer bû.
One was over Urfa, his name was Melik el-Muzeffer.
Yek li ser Ce'ber bû, navê xwe... nizanim Melik çi bû, mi ji
bîr kiriye navê wî.
One was over Ja'bar, his name was... I don't know what Melik
he was, I have forgotten his name.
Qçkê xwe, deh û heft qçkê xwe bûn. Vana pêjna ez zanim.
His children, he had seventeen children. These represent the
ones I know.
Eva div a hedê da, Eyûbiya hukim dikir li... li Watan el-
Erebî, li dewleta Îslamiyê.
This was during that era, when the Ayyubids ruled in... in
the Arab Homeland, in the Islamic State.
Sala çendê nivîsandine?
What year was it written?
Sala çarsed û heştê û heşta.
The year four hundred and eighty-eight.
Nah, ev çi nivîsandine?
Now, what is written on it?
Dibê: "Enşe'ehû Sultan el-Melik el-Eşref".
It says: "Established by Sultan Melik el-Eşref".
Ê... î... vaye çêkirî, navê xwe...
Uh... he... the one who made it, his name...
De hewa ji kuderê helbî em nizanin. Merkezê xwe Şam bû.
Though where he originated from [exactly], we don't know.
His center was Damascus.
Gelo heva ji kuderê bû, ji ko hatiye?
I wonder where this [stone] was from, where did it come
from?
Dibê: "Enşe'ehû Sultan el-Melik el-Eşref".
It says: "Established by Sultan Melik el-Eşref".
Melik el-Eşref, melikê Şamê bû.
Melik el-Eşref was the King of Damascus.
Di vî hedî da jî, di çarsed û heştê û heşta da, Eyûbiya
hukim dikir.
And in this era, in four hundred and eighty-eight, the
Ayyubids were ruling.
Ev ne Erebî ye?
Isn't this Arabic?
Eskî Tirk e, bi Tirkî kevn e.
It is Old Turkish, in ancient Turkish.
Eskî Tirk yanê... bi Tirkî kevn e. Paşê rabûn kirin... bi ya
jî rast yazmîş dikirin eski kevn.
Old Turkish means... in ancient Turkish. Later they
started... they used to write from right to left in the old
days.
Paşê rabûn bi Ecnebqî, ya jî çepê da yazmîş dikirin.
Later they started with the foreign [Latin script], writing
from the left.
Nah, ev çend sale wanî li vir xistî?
Now, how many years has it been placed here like this?
Hema teqrîben ji şêstî da, ji vî derî da ye. Şêst... pênc û
heştê da hene.
Well, roughly since the sixties, it has been in this spot.
Sixty... since eighty-five, it is there.
Li va derî da, bes berê li vir bû. Ciyê xwe li vir bû.
In this spot, but before it was over here. Its place was
here.
Ev çend metre ye ev kevir?
How many meters is this stone?
Metre rûbek heye. Qalinbûna ginde jî wekî sê rûb metre heye.
It is a meter and a quarter. Its thickness is also about
three-quarters of a meter.
Erdê xwe.
Its width.
Çima Mele hildikişiya jor, azan dida, ser vî kevirî?
Why did the Mullah climb up to call the adhan atop this
stone?
Belê, di ciyê xwe zêde herî. Hema î tewrî bilind bû.
Yes, in its place it was very... it was just this high.
Minare tinebû, di hewşa camiyê da bû.
There was no minaret, it was in the mosque courtyard.
Şêx hildikişiya ser, azan dida. Kevrekî xwe biçûk jî dîna
bûn kelhekî, wekî derece pêledana, diçû ser.
The Sheikh would climb up and call the adhan. They had put a
small stone next to it, like a step for a staircase, to go
up.
Tê bîra te?
Do you remember it?
Tê bîra min, rint tê bîra min.
I remember, I remember it well.
Ev xaniyên berê tinebûn? Vê xaniyê...
Were these old houses not here? This house...
Hef hewşa tinebû.
This courtyard wasn't here.
Wextê hewa, li... li va cî, heva hewşa tinebû.
At that time, in... in this place, this courtyard didn't
exist.
Wextê va hewşa çêkirin, kevir aniyan guherandin, daniyan
piyê ken.
When they built this courtyard, they brought the stone and
moved it, placing it at the foot of the wall.
Û bervî ginde jî oda bidin.
And they built the room on that side.
Vê yazî kesk, ne kesk bû, gî reş bû. Paşê...
This green writing, it wasn't green, it was all black.
Later...
Hinik hatin boyax tê dan.
Some came and added paint to it.
Hane bû.
That's how it was.
Em mizgefta kingê ava bû cemaet? Kengê çêbû mizgeft?
When was this mosque built, folks? When was the mosque
constructed?
Came?
The mosque?
De pênc û şeşa, pênc û hefta da tejdîd bû. Li çel yeka hat
girtin.
In '56 or '57 it was renovated. In '41 it was closed.
Îselef çel yeka.
The predecessor [old mosque] was from '41.
Tejdîda ginde, û va minara, de pênc û şeşa, pênc û hefta da
bû.
Its renovation, and this minaret, was in '56 or '57.
Em silav kin Mele da jî. Merheba mamosta.
Let's greet the Mullah too. Hello teacher.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Kêfxweşbûn bi dîtina te.
Pleased to see you.
Haya naha çend Mele di vê mizgeftê da bûn?
Up until now, how many Mullahs have been in this mosque?
Teqrîben heşt Mele em di vê mizgeftê da bûn.
Approximately eight Mullahs, we have been in this mosque.
Mele Tewer (?), silav... Dela Elî bû (?). Delê Xoca.
Mullah Tewer (?), greetings... It was Dela Ali (?). Dela
Khoja.
Li deşt Tirkî bû, ji kuderê bû, li vî derî ew dikir.
He was from the Turkish plain, wherever he was from, he did
[served] here.
Ba'dî wînî, Şêx Osman hat. Şêx... piş wînî Şêx Osman jî ji
nefs vî gundî bû.
After him, Sheikh Osman came. Sheikh... after him, Sheikh
Osman was also from this very village.
Xoca, Mele dikir li vî derî.
Being the Khoja, the Mullah here.
Piştî Şêx Osman, Şêx Kemal hat. Ew jî ji vî gundî bû.
After Sheikh Osman, Sheikh Kemal came. He was also from this
village.
Wî jî fetrok radikir li ser camiyê bû, xizmet dikir.
He also spent a period at the mosque, serving.
Piştî wînî, Şêx Arif anîn li vî derî, û li ser camiya me
teqrîben.
After him, they brought Sheikh Arif here, and [he was] at
our mosque approximately.
Û piştî Şêx Arif jî, Şêx Reşîd hat vî derî.
And after Sheikh Arif too, Sheikh Rashid came here.
Û Şêx Reşîd jî li vî derî ma. Û piştî wînî jî teqri...
Şêx... teqrîben Şêx Reşîd hat vî derî.
And Sheikh Rashid also stayed here. And after him roughly...
Sheikh... roughly Sheikh Rashid came here. [repeating
slightly]
Û piştî Şêx Reşîd jî, Şêx Mistefa hat vî derî.
And after Sheikh Rashid, Sheikh Mustafa came here.
Û piştî Şêx Mistefa jî, Şêx Hesen hat.
And after Sheikh Mustafa, Sheikh Hassan came.
Û piştî Şêx Hesen, Şêx Mihemed hat, û ez jî ê nehem e
teqrîben.
And after Sheikh Hassan, Sheikh Mohammed came, and I am
roughly the ninth one.
Wînî hemo Mele li vir bûn?
All these Mullahs were here?
Tu ji kuderê yî?
Where are you from?
Ez ji... Rubalqî me... ji Xurkêkê (?).
I am from... Rubalqi... from Xurkeke (?).
Tu ji Xurkêkê yî? Tu çend sal in li vê gundî yî?
You are from Xurkeke? How many years have you been in this
village?
Bû du sal teqrîben li vî gundî me.
It has been about two years I am in this village.
Du sal e.
Two years.
De spas dikim.
Well, I thank you.
Mala te ava be.
May your home be prosperous (Thank you).
Belê temaşevanên hêja, nah em derbasî vir bûnê.
Yes, dear viewers, now we have moved over here.
Sînor ava, sînor bekî deh metre ji me va naki... nîzîk e.
The border is there, the border is barely ten meters away
from us... it is close.
Pişt me jî, ev mala xuya dike, berê ev navenda Fransa bû.
And behind us, this house that is visible, formerly this was
a French center.
Berê leşkerê Fransa li vir bû.
The French army used to be here.
Lê niha jî maleke têda ye, kesek ji vî gundî têda ye.
But now there is a home inside, a person from this village
lives in it.
De kes kîlek me nîne. Emê navê wan bipirsin.
There is no one beside us [from the house]. We will ask
their [the men sitting there] names.
Emê dîroka vê mexferê bipirsin.
We will ask about the history of this outpost.
Merhaba ji we ra.
Hello to you.
Merhaba, elîn (ehlen).
Hello, welcome.
Navî te bi xêr?
Your name, please?
Nûrî Aze.
Nuri Aze.
Ser çava. Navî we?
You're welcome (lit: upon my eyes). Your name?
Ehmedê Biş.
Ahmed Bish.
Ser çava.
You're welcome.
Ciyê te xweş be.
May your place be pleasant.
Apê î bêje, ka ji me ra bêje, dîroka vê mexferê bêje.
Uncle, tell us, tell us about the history of this outpost.
Çi tê bîra te?
What do you remember?
Dîroka vê mexferê...
The history of this outpost...
Di tarîxa kevn da, vira bajar bû.
In ancient history, this place was a city.
Vira kî... met'am, loqente, firne, meselen qesab, filan
bêvan bûn.
Here there were... restaurants, diners, bakeries, for
example butchers, and so on were here.
Û îçê di wan da jî miletê Ermeniyî hebûn.
And inside those [businesses], there were also Armenian
people.
Fe ba'dî fetrokî, nav şûna vê zeytûna berê vir çarşî bû.
So after a period, in the place of these olives, formerly
here was a market.
Çarşî bû.
It was a market.
Vira bû.
It was here.
Û va dera jî bazar bû. Ba'dî poppora wana bazar bû.
And this place was a bazaar. Behind their hustle and bustle,
it was a bazaar.
Di wî demî da sînor tinebû li vir?
At that time, there was no border here?
Sînor tinebû.
There was no border.
Tinebû.
None.
Ba'dî ku sînor hat, şerek li vî derî çêbû.
After the border came, a war happened in this place.
Alaqê milet xop xil (?), gel da.
The people related to... (?) fought.
Li vî derî gelek hat kuştin.
Many were killed in this place.
Me'ne wayî, ji vo derê rabûn bazara kinfêrê (?), piş vî
bînayê me.
Meaning, from here they rose up, the market of... (?),
behind this building of ours.
Vayînoka piş me, di sewrîne.
The things behind us, looking over.
Ê Fransa, demakê... mehekê, salekê û şeş mehama.
Uh, France, for a time... a month, [actually] they stayed
for a year and six months.
Paşîngê Înglîs dehm kir.
Afterward, the English took over.
Tê bîra te, dema Fransa da?
Do you remember the time of the French?
Na, na. Bavkê min, kalkê min ji min ra hewal didan.
No, no. My father, my grandfather used to tell me.
Dê dûra Înglîs hukim kir.
Then afterwards, the English ruled.
Ba'dî Înglîs, Alman li Helebê bû.
After the English, the Germans were in Aleppo.
Alman vî derî weftek xoşand vî derî.
The Germans... this place... a delegation... [unclear] this
place.
Ji vo derê Fransa revî dexlî çi bû?
From here France ran away, where did they enter?
Çûn, revîn çûn mintaqa Ezazê û çûn ê zêde çû Beyrûtê.
They went, they fled and went to the Azaz region, and most
went to Beirut.
Didûwê ra, neqla çarê, tekrek fitilî, Fransa tekrek hat.
Secondly, the fourth time, they turned around again, France
came back again.
Ji kuda hat? Ji qirxanê da hat.
Where did they come from? They came from Kirikhan.
Hat ku? Hat ser hevala.
Came where? Came upon the friends [locals].
Hevalit me, ê silahradikirin yanê medenî, ya sîlahradikirin
didî Fransa.
Our friends, the ones taking up arms, meaning civilians,
taking up arms against France.
Ji welatê xwe daf'i dikirin.
They were defending their country.
Hawa di salê sî û hefta da, sî û şeşa da, sî û pênca da, sî
û çara da, sî û siya da...
That was in the year '37, '36, '35, '34, '33...
Çimkî pir dirêjeda. Şeş heft joq bûn yanê.
Because it lasted a long time. There were six or seven
groups [waves], that is.
Tekbiyiq, Mistefa Çolaq, Muhî Îbşeş...
Tekbiyiq, Mustafa Cholak, Muhi Ibshesh...
Hesenê Elî...
Hassan Ali...
Havna gî, gî mêrê bûn, sîlah radikirin, payê xwe hebûn,
dihatin fîda dikirin...
All of them, all were men, they took up arms, they had their
status, they came and sacrificed...
Meselen vî erdî ava kin.
For example, to build up/protect this land.
Ê paşîngê rabû Fransa hat vî dera dehm kir.
Uh, afterwards, France rose up, came and bombarded this
place.
Ma'ne wana.
Their meaning [intention].
Ba'dî dehm kir şunda, milet reviya.
After they bombarded it, the people fled.
Gund, vira, gel reviya.
The village, here, the people fled.
Î kût ma, î qçik ma, ê din reviyan.
The lame stayed, the small stayed, the others fled.
Li vo derê eskerê Emîr Ebdullah vêra bû, Îslam bû, li meriya
ne dixistin.
In this place, Emir Abdullah's army was here, it was Islam
[Muslim army], they didn't attack the people.
Ê Fransa li vî derê, daw û heft mer o li vira pêşiya me
kuştin.
Uh, France, in this place, killed seventeen men right here
in front of us.
Kî bûn ew daw û heft mer, ne kî bûn?
Who were those seventeen men, who were they?
Ji va gundî me bûn.
They were from this village of ours.
Jê, yek... xeyo îşte zemanê kevn revînek kuştine...
From it, one... well, in the old times, they killed a
fugitive...
Tê fehm kir?
Did you understand?
Ba'dî va... awa darbaz bû şûnda, va...
After this... passed, this...
Awa darbaz bû, sînor virdane mekine.
It passed, don't make the border over here.
Deqqa sînor virdane mekine, vo derê... nehî ye bû.
The moment... don't make the border here... this place...
was a district/sub-district (nahiye).
Nehiyek li vir bû. Firne li vir bûn. Mat'am li vir bûn.
Loqente li vir bûn.
There was a district here. Bakeries were here. Restaurants
were here. Diners were here.
Helajê pênbê... havna gî li cem me hebûn yanê.
Cotton carders... all of these existed among us, that is.
...je hidûd hatî ta em nê... Sinûr da ket... revîn çûn belav
bûn, hin çûn Heleb, hin çûn Efrîn, hin çûn cire se...
...came from the border until we... The border fell... they
fled and scattered, some went to Aleppo, some went to Afrin,
some went to [unclear place]...
Va sê mal va derê rûniştin. Heta niha rokê îro jî mesela
îşte emê erdê xwe sê dikin, miqaweme dikin.
These three families settled here. Up until this very day,
for example, we are [securing] our land, we are resisting.
Em kê ku derê herin? Çêtir mal tune ye. Emê li ser erdê xwe
em bimînin.
Where would we go? There is no better home. We will stay on
our land.
Ji welat şêrîntir tune ye.
There is nothing sweeter than the homeland.
Te spas dikim. Kanê vê mêrîjê bipirsin? No, Apo nêzî çend
sal e li vir rûniştin e?
I thank you. Let's ask this gentleman? Uncle, approximately
how many years have you been residing here?
Hezar neh sed û heftê û heftan da qurban.
Since nineteen seventy-seven, my dear.
Ya ne ê Fransa bû?
Wasn't it [from the time of] the French?
Ez zanim ne ê Fransa bû... eno xêrê me hat û derê berê
hewarê me kirrî vî derî.
I know it wasn't French... well, our good fortune came and
previously... we bought this place.
Me bi pera kirrî qurban.
We bought it with money, my dear.
Bes kê kirrî ev?
But who bought it?
Me ji layê Memed Genc... nazê(?) Genc me ji wî kirrî. Belê.
We bought it from Memed Genc... [unclear name] Genc, we
bought it from him. Yes.
Me berwan... nuqut ver da man e qurban.
We [paid] in cash... we gave cash/points remaining there, my
dear.
Te tînim berê xwe de bawkurekî Kurdistan. Erê. Ev pişta te
têla, ev leşkerê Tirka li pişta te ne.
I am bringing you to face Northern Kurdistan [Turkey]. Yes.
This wire is behind you, these Turkish soldiers are behind
you.
Na, ev leşkerê Tirka tora gotin çi waha?
No, did these Turkish soldiers say anything like that to
you?
Ha, noka miraz bînçî... va miletê ma çi digerî?
Ha, now [unclear phrasing]... what are these people of ours
looking for?
Me go va miletê revî hatine ji kora tefsîrê bikşînin û
esaretê ka bikşînin.
I said these fleeing people have come to endure the
interpretation [of their situation] and to endure captivity.
Bes hewa tiştek din tune ez fenim me go.
But there is nothing else, sir, I said.
Go teşekur ederim. Rabû bere xwe da milê xwe xistin çûn
qeyta dî.
He said "Thank you" [in Turkish]. He got up, turned around,
slung [their guns] over their shoulders and went to the
other side.
Heye wekî din çiye?
Is there anything else?
Te spas dikim. Saeta te xweş.
I thank you. Bless you.
Çi çîrok bi ser te re derbas bûn e? Jiyekî ta dûr û dirêj?
What stories have passed over you? Through such a long life?
Çîrok wekî ef tarîbêm. Berî vî... quwet hat. Ji ku derê? Ê
Tirka.
A story as I tell you. Before this... a force came. From
where? The Turks.
Hat, yanê berî vê... Go acele go, reîs mexfer tê da xwazê.
Came, meaning before this... Said "Hurry," said, "The
outpost chief wants you."
La bipîceme go, bipîceme wallah.
Man, in pajamas he said, in pajamas, by God.
Ê mexferê ku derê? Ê Tirka? Ê vira?
Which outpost? The Turkish one? The one here?
Mexferê me. Ê Sûriyê, na. Ê nizamî.
Our outpost. The Syrian one, no. The regular [army].
Rabû, daxwaza go bankir, hekî mexû(?) yarim pîceme go pîceme
teke ware. We lêxistin taxa tum keko.
He stood up, the request was called out... help/friend,
pajamas, he said come in just pajamas. We went up to the
neighborhood, brother.
Daxa me go selamun aleykum, go aleykum selam.
Then I said "Peace be upon you," he said "And upon you
peace."
Go Nûrûzayê, me go buyur efendim.
He said "Nuruzaye" [Name/Title?], I said "Yes sir" [in
Turkish].
Go sen bana diyorsun, burda pekkeke yok go. Tu miradî bê PKK
li vir tune ye.
He said "You tell me, there is no PKK here" [in Turkish].
You mean to say there is no PKK here.
Opo gendi burda efendim. Opo bi xwe li vir e. Wallah ji
Xwedê ra wildim.
"Apo himself is here, sir" [in Turkish mix]. Apo himself is
here. By God I was stunned.
Me go sayîniz başim, ez kani m? Daxwaza go Opo li vir e, ez
kani m?
I said "My dear sir," where am I? He claims Apo is here,
where am I?
Lê yarim, me go Opo Xwedê zane li ku derê ye... li kû je
memleketî ye... la sukûcan çoyî dane...
Oh friend, I said God knows where Apo is... in which country
he is... man, in the streets or tea pots...
La yarim Opo li vir çi dike? Wallah hoha.
Oh friend, what is Apo doing here? By God, like that.
Me dî... per nemaze te... Meryemê me yî benzemîşî Opo dike,
hat ma beynî me herdu qest dikin. Wallah hana.
I saw... not long after... Our Maryam resembles Apo
[Öcalan], she came and stood between the two of us making
[gestures]. By God, like that.
Daxa sekinî, hekî çi bikim? Ez zanim serwîs dindikin, bi
dest li pişta xis.
Then he stood, what to do? I know they are doing a patrol,
with hands clasped behind the back.
Me go sayîniz başim. Sen Opo didîn budir me go. Ê te digot
Opo ev e?
I said "My dear sir." You said "This is Apo" [in Turkish].
Is this the one you said was Apo?
Sed vira qinaet çêbû. Rasin la silkiyê xo derxist telefon
quwetê kir.
A hundred times conviction happened [he was finally
convinced]. Immediately he took out his radio, he phoned the
force.
Çi qas leşker hatin vira?
How many soldiers came here?
Pir hatin. Belkî sed jê hatin.
Many came. Maybe a hundred of them came.
Tengo me dît... babo dî.
It was tight [tense], we saw... father saw.
Hema bes bîstin, navê bavê Celal. Ehmed bûk. Temam.
Just twenty [years old], father's name Jalal. Ahmed Buk.
Okay.
Bîstin gene Ebû Celal. Ciwanek Ebdullah Ebû Celal hatî.
Twenty again, Abu Jalal. A young man, Abdullah Abu Jalal
came.
Rabû bere xwe da teqrîrê xwe... telefonê xwe derxist, quwet
telefonê quwetê kir.
He stood up, turned to his report... took out his phone, the
force phoned the force.
Wallahî di nîv saetê da, te ne zanî hav quwata firî, te ne
zanî ev quwata heli.
By God, within half an hour, you wouldn't know if this force
flew away, or if this force melted away.
Derbike. Em jî xelas bûn qurban.
Get out. We were saved, my dear.
Mala te ava, spas. Saetê te xweş.
May your home be prosperous, thanks. Bless you.
Spas.
Thanks.
Belê em li vir jî gihîştin dawiya bernameya Ax û Welat.
Yes, here we have reached the end of the program "Ax û
Welat" (Land and Homeland).
Emê xatira xwe ji we bixwazin, ji Deşta Hemqê, li ber Sinûr,
ji gundê Hemamê.
We will bid you farewell, from the Hemq Plain, by the
Border, from the village of Hemam.
A şevana pêşî tê... Merheba şivanê.
Ah, the shepherd is coming forward... Hello shepherd.
Spas. Ka heywanên me... li gundî... emê dîsa hewa rabin, li
benda me bin.
Thanks. Let our animals... in the village... we will rise
[appear] again, wait for us.