[Music]
Afrîn soza min bi te re, te nahêlim nare.
Afrin, my promise is to you, I won't leave you, no way.
Bimirin û mandinê, te re hevalim.
Through death and exhaustion, I am a companion to you.
Afrîn soza min bi te re, te nahêlim nare.
Afrin, my promise is to you, I won't leave you, no way.
Bimirin û mandinê, te re hevalim.
Through death and exhaustion, I am a companion to you.
Afrîn bûka Kurda ye, serê me pê hildaye.
Afrin is the bride of the Kurds, we hold our heads high
because of her.
Afrîn welatê me ye, serê me pê hildaye.
Afrin is our homeland, we hold our heads high because of
her.
Bixwîn û vîna xwe, gelê me parastiye.
With their blood and their will, our people have protected
her.
Bixwîn û vîna xwe, gelê me parastiye.
With their blood and their will, our people have protected
her.
Afrîn soza min bi te re, te nahêlim nare.
Afrin, my promise is to you, I won't leave you, no way.
Bimirin û mandinê, te re hevalim.
Through death and exhaustion, I am a companion to you.
Qamişlo û Kobanê, Afrîn wargehê me ye.
Qamishlo and Kobane, Afrin is our sanctuary.
Dêrîk û Kobanê, Afrîn wargehê me ye.
Derik and Kobane, Afrin is our sanctuary.
Pîroz û bimbarek be, azadî doza me ye.
May it be blessed and congratulated, freedom is our cause.
Afrîn soza min bi te re, te nahêlim nare.
Afrin, my promise is to you, I won't leave you, no way.
Bimirin û mandinê, te re hevalim.
Through death and exhaustion, I am a companion to you.
Xweseriya Dîmoqrat, diyariya gelê me ye.
Democratic Autonomy is the gift of our people.
Asayîş û YPG, Gerîla pişta me ye.
Asayish and YPG, the Guerrilla is our support.
Afrîn soza min bi te re, te nahêlim nare.
Afrin, my promise is to you, I won't leave you, no way.
Bimirin û mandinê, te re hevalim.
Through death and exhaustion, I am a companion to you.
Wey dengê te sax be, wey dengê te sax be.
May your voice be healthy, may your voice be healthy.
Belê temaşevanên hêja, îro jî me berê Xwedê, navçeya Recû...
Yes, dear viewers, today, by God, in the district of Raju...
Îro jî em derbasî gundê Hecîka bûne.
Today we have entered the village of Hecîka.
Dê di destpêkê de em silavekê bidin mêvanê xwe yê hêja.
In the beginning, we will give a greeting to our dear guest.
Emê bixwazin hunermend Selah Berîm bikine, ji begustranek
pir xweş û mergûb, em hatin li ser Efrînê.
We would like to introduce the artist Salah Berîm, with a
very beautiful and desirable song, we came regarding Afrin.
Mamoste, car din dengê te sax be.
Master, once again, may your voice be healthy.
Tu sax bî mamoste.
May you be healthy, master.
Mamoste, hûn kîngê û behsa Selah Berîm bikin, ji çend salan
e strana tu dibêjî?
Master, when... and if you talk about Salah Berîm, for how
many years have you been singing?
Weleh strana jî biçûkî ya xwe de ez dibêjim, lê...
By God, I have been singing songs since my childhood, but...
We karê hunerî ye, teqrîben... deh, daw dozdeh, daw sêzdeh
sal hene ez dikim, resmî yanî.
As for artistic work, roughly... ten, or twelve, or thirteen
years I have been doing it, officially that is.
Yanî ji kîngê, pazdeh salan tu wek hunermend derdikevî,
strana dibêjî?
So since when, since fifteen years old you've been coming
out as an artist, singing songs?
Tu, yanî wek dibêjin tu li mal da, berê strana li mal digot?
Yes.
You, as they say, at home... did you sing at home before?
Erê, ez zarok bûm, biçûk bûm, di sitra...
Yes, I was a child, I was small, I sang...
Ema li vê gundê tu dimeşî te strana ji xwe re digot?
But in this village while you walked, did you sing to
yourself?
Erê, li vê çiya û çem na, li vê gundan û, erê.
Yes, in these mountains and rivers, in these villages, yes.
Ema navê dîwana zeytûnan...
But the name of the Olive Gathering (Diwan)...
Ciyê rûniştina me, ez çeqel li vê derê rûniştim, yanî ez
biçûk bûm, dihatim vê derê, li ser benê.
Our sitting place, I sat right here as a kid, I mean I was
small, I used to come here, on the dam.
Ê na çawa di bîra te da ma, ma hûn derbasî dîsa vê ciyê bûn,
ciyê herî bilind jî ye ne?
So how did it stay in your memory? Did you pass by this
place again? It is the highest place too, isn't it?
Erê, zarokiya min... di xewna xwe da, zarok hat bîra min.
Yes, my childhood... in my dream, the child came to my
memory.
Dema tu zarok, tu derbasî vir dibû?
When you were a child, did you pass by here?
Belkî min, şeş-heft salî min dihatim vê derê.
Maybe I, at six or seven years old, I used to come here.
Heta mamoste... ne... em bêjin, di malbata te da kes dengbêj
hebû, strana digotin berê?
So master... no... let's say, in your family, was there any
bard (dengbêj), did they sing songs before?
Ê bavê min ne dengbêj e, strana li oda-moda distirê.
Well, my father isn't a bard, he sings songs in
rooms/gatherings.
Xalê min dengbêj in, hene...
My uncles are bards, there are some...
Ew ji kîjan alî ne?
From which side are they?
Ew ne ji gundê Kêlî bûn e. Ehmedê Kêlî bû, xalê bavê min e,
strana digotin.
They were from the village of Kêlî. It was Ehmedê Kêlî, my
father's uncle, they sang songs.
Sidqî bavê Şêhan, ew jî gundî ye, mamoste Sidqî.
Sidqî, father of Şêhan, he is also a villager, Master Sidqî.
Ê xalên bavê min in, strana digotin.
Well, they are my father's uncles, they sang songs.
De ji ber wê da jî dibê qeçik li xalê tê, naha wisa dibêjin,
erê. Me das jî wergirtiye.
So because of that, they say "the boy takes after the
uncle," that's what they say now, yes. We took the sickle
[trait] too.
Temam mamoste, naha ema... em... te strana yekemîn di jiyana
xwe da...
Okay master, now but... we... the first song in your life...
Te guhdar kir, û bala te kişand, çi bû ew strana?
That you listened to, and it caught your attention, what was
that song?
Xwedê mamoste stranên Efrînê folklor, yanî hemû stranên min
guhdar dikirin.
By God, master, Afrin's folklore songs, I mean I listened to
all the songs.
Mamoste Cemîl Horo... nemir Cemîl Horo, Elî Tijo, Hesen
Nazî, Ebdê Şehriyê, stranên kevin...
Master Jamil Horo... the immortal Jamil Horo, Ali Tijo,
Hasan Nazi, Abde Shahriye, the old songs...
Stranên kevin, min pir guhdar dikirin ew du stran yanî.
The old songs, I listened to them a lot, those two songs
specifically.
Ê herî destpêkê bala te kişandî çi bû? Kîjan strana bû?
So at the very beginning, what caught your attention? Which
song was it?
Strana... Hesenê Dêmlez min pir jê hez dikir.
The song... "Hesenê Dêmlez," I liked it a lot.
Ê Hesenê Dêmlez, lawik pir xweş bûm jê hez dikir dhistra.
Yes "Hesenê Dêmlez," I was very fond of the ballad, I liked
it, he sang it.
Ew qisate li kuderê çêbûye?
That story, where did it take place?
Na ne li vir e. Ne li... ne li Efrînê, na.
No, it's not here. Not in... not in Afrin, no.
Tê naha ji me ra wê stranê bêje?
Will you sing that song for us now?
Ez bêjim meqtekê jê, were bêjim.
I will sing a segment of it, come let me sing.
Kerem ke.
Please, go ahead.
[Music]
Law delal, law, law delal, law, law delal, law, law delal,
loy...
Oh dear boy, oh, oh dear boy, oh, oh dear boy, oh, oh dear
boy, loy...
Emrê min telef kir, law, law meqeda bera pismam, bela vê ra,
delal, law delal, law delal, law delal, loy loy.
You wasted my life, oh, oh the fate given to the cousin, the
trouble with this, dear, oh dear, oh dear, oh dear, loy loy.
Lo, la pismam dilê min dêşe, carî dêr e, oy...
Lo, oh cousin my heart hurts, it is the time of the
church/convent, oy...
La hise, law dilê min dêşe, carî dêr e, qurban se carî dêr
e, ay.
Don't make a sound, oh my heart hurts, it is the time of the
church, my sacrifice, three times the church, ay.
Dilê min dêşe, se carî dêr e, temam dilê minî ji kulanî, bi
kul e, ji birîna, bi birîn e, qurban bi birîn e.
My heart hurts, three times the church, my whole heart is
full of sores, full of sores, from wounds, it is wounded, my
sacrifice, it is wounded.
Kêla xwediyê îmanê şewitî, tevdab ser kul û birînê min da,
na kewîne, qurban na kewîne, lo heyran na kewîne.
The pillar of the faithful one burned, putting salt on my
sores and wounds, it won't heal, my sacrifice, it won't
heal, oh amazing one, it won't heal.
[Music]
Her du gundên Hecîka jêrîn û jorîn, girêdayî navçeya Recû ya
kantona Efrînê ne.
Both villages, Lower Hecika and Upper Hecika, are connected
to the Raju district of the Afrin canton.
Çar kîlometre li rojavayê bajarê Recû, û sîh û pênc
kîlometre li bakurê bajarê Efrînê dikevin.
They are located four kilometers west of the town of Raju,
and thirty-five kilometers north of the city of Afrin.
Hecîka peyvek e Kurdî ye, tê wateya "Hemo da viran".
Hecika is a Kurdish word, it means "Hemo gave [it] here".
Ji ber ku xelkên gund, li gelek gundan niştecih bûn e, û
piştre hatine cihê gundê niha, û ji xwe re gundek ava
kirine.
Because the people of the village were settled in many
villages, and afterwards they came to the site of the
current village, and built a village for themselves.
Yekemîn kesê...
The first person who...
Piştî çîbûyê, Hecî Birîm bû, bi serî da Hecîka Jêrîn hata
avakirin.
After the incident, it was Hecî Birîm, initially Lower
Hecika was built.
Piştra kesek bi navê Hiso derket û gundekî din bi heman navî
Hecîka Jêrîn avakir.
Later, a person named Hiso appeared and built another
village with the same name, Lower Hecika.
(Music)
Mamê Omer merheba ji te ra.
Uncle Omer, hello to you.
Merheba ehlen.
Hello, welcome.
Em îro derbasî gundê we bûn, me xwest hinekî dîroka gundê
Hecîka jî nas bikin.
We passed through your village today, we wanted to learn a
bit about the history of Hecika village.
Ehlen we sehlen.
You are most welcome.
Sax be. Lê di destpêkê, em dixwazin nav bipirsin. Navê gundê
we çiko hatiye?
Thank you. But in the beginning, we want to ask about the
name. How did your village's name come about?
Wela, çend cîyên tim... bor kirin ji dîroka, ji dedebên, hem
Hecîka wa dibên... hemû cîya yanî... hemû cîya rûniştin e.
Well, several places... migrated from history, from
ancestors, they call it Hecika... all places... all places
are settlements.
Yanî pir bûn.
Meaning they were many.
Yanî ew kîda rûniştin destpêkê?
So who settled there first?
Selef şivan bûn, paşê li vî deran rûniştin... Paşê li vî
derî... berê wek gundê Hesen bû, paşê... borkirin hatin vir.
The ancestors were shepherds, then they settled in these
places... Then here... before it was like Hesen village,
then... they migrated and came here.
Em îro kî hevin bi Xwedê yanî. Hecîkê Jêr, Jor merivê hevin
yanî.
Today we are together, by God. Lower and Upper Hecika are
relatives.
Yanî kîjan gundê berî kîjan avabû?
So which village was built before which?
Ema em ê jêr berî vir... çêbû, paşê vir hat. Ewa selef gundê
Hesen bû paşê hat.
But we the lower ones were built before here, then here
came. That ancestor was Hesen village then came.
Ema selef em ê jêr... ê Hebeş... ser benê... Hebeş, Hecîkê
Jêr e. Hebeşê Birîm.
But our ancestor the lower... Hebeş... on the roof... Hebeş
is Lower Hecika. Hebeşê Birîm.
Na, di destpêkê gundê jêr ava kir navê wî kî bû?
No, who was the name of the one who first built the lower
village?
Navê wî xuyaye Hebeşê Birîm bû. Û ê viro jî Hisê Birîm.
Apparently his name was Hebeşê Birîm. And the one here was
Hisê Birîm.
Evê jî dawad bû... Silêmanê Birîm bû... işte pismamê hevin.
This one was also... Silêmanê Birîm... they are cousins.
Yanî gîştî malbat in, pismamê hevin?
So it's all one family, they are cousins?
Pismamê hevin, gişt... Pêşiyê bavê hevin... kes xerîb tine.
Ayla xerîb gund da tine. Ne jêr ne jor.
They are cousins, all... Ancestors are the same father...
there are no strangers. There is no strange family in the
village. Neither lower nor upper.
Apê Omer hun bi kîjan eşîrê tên naskirin? Hun ji kîjan eşîrê
ne?
Uncle Omer, which tribe are you known by? Which tribe are
you from?
Eşîra Şêxan e.
Sheikhan tribe.
Hun Şêxî ne?
Are you Sheikhi?
Ha, Şêxî ne.
Yes, we are Sheikhi.
Gundê we çiqas xane tê da heye?
How many houses are in your village?
Wela, jêr jor, heftê û pênc hene.
Well, lower and upper, there are seventy-five.
Yanî heftê û pênc xane?
So seventy-five houses?
Gerek hebin erê... Ne ya kêm zêde, hom hene.
Should be, yes... Not less or more, all are there.
Wek pazdeh bîst a koçî işte li derva... Efrînê, Reco, Heleb
hene, işte wano.
Like fifteen, twenty migrated outside... Afrin, Rajo,
Aleppo, like that.
Yanî milletê we bar kiriye ji Reco jî, Efrîn jî û li Heleb
jî rûniştine?
So your people moved to Rajo, Afrin, and settled in Aleppo
too?
Erê işte çar mal vir, pênc vir, mihim deh pazdok hene. Deh û
pênc hene.
Yes, four houses here, five here, important is there are
ten-fifteen. There are ten-fifteen.
Apê Omer ez tiştekî jî bipirsim, ji ber ku gundê we pir
bilind e.
Uncle Omer, let me ask something else, because your village
is very high.
Erê.
Yes.
Çiqas bilindbûna wî heye?
How much is its elevation?
Wela bilindbûn... bilind e dayê... heş sed metre heye.
Well elevation... it's high dear... it's eight hundred
meters.
Bi vê çiyayî va dibên çi, navê wî çi ye?
What do they call this mountain, what is its name?
Dibên Çiyayê Emînê, mero.
They call it Emine's Mountain, man.
Ji ku hatiye vê navî?
Where did this name come from?
Dibên Çiyayê Emînê... da wextîn aş... Hisê Birîm li vir
bû... Da gotin hewa kî li vir rakeziye?
They call it Emine's Mountain... once... Hisê Birîm was
here... They said who is settled here?
Gotin Hisê Birîm. Gotin hewa çakê Emînê... yanî... ta
pêşiyên me wa... mezbûte ne yanî.
They said Hisê Birîm. They said this is Emine's place...
so... our ancestors said so... it's confirmed.
Gotin ba'd çoyê Emînê, da dibên Çoyê Emînê heta noka.
They said after Emine's mountain, so they call it Emine's
Mountain until now.
Apê Omer, naha çiqas gund li ser vê çiyayî hene?
Uncle Omer, how many villages are on this mountain now?
Gund wela pir in lê... Gund... Sê sê gund hene.
Villages are many but... Villages... There are three
villages.
Da Çiyayê Emînê vî pî da heye... gundê Bilko, pîro
virdahona... Kumraş e, gundê Hesen e, Kurrê ye... gund hene
yanî.
On this side of Emine's Mountain... Bilko village, on that
side... Kumraş, Hesen village, Kurrê... there are villages.
Şadiya ye... el-muhim.
Şadiya... anyway.
Yanî bi vê çiyayî gîştî va dibêjin... navek e?
So do they call this whole mountain... one name?
E da ê bi vî pî Reco ket dibên Çiyayê Emînê işte... Vê geçê
xerb da. Da wey da ber rojhilat ka nizanim.
The part falling to Rajo side is called Emine's Mountain...
On this west side. I don't know about the east side.
Ji ber ku gundê we pir bilind e jî, naha em behsa berfê
bikin.
Since your village is very high too, let's talk about snow.
Erê.
Yes.
Naha ta dîsa berf baş barî ba we?
Did snow fall well for you again recently?
Erê barî.
Yes it fell.
Naha em behsa berfê bikin, ji çiqas salan da berf nebarî
yanî? Ew berfa weke salên bihorî yanî?
Let's talk about snow, in how many years did snow not fall?
That snow like past years?
Wela... heye deh panzdeh sal hene... berê rind ket. Deh
panzdeh sal, bîst sal hene, jor û vir da hêsa li rind ket.
Well... it's been ten-fifteen years... before it fell well.
Ten-fifteen years, twenty years, up and here it fell well.
Di kîjan salê da berf zêde barî?
In which year did it snow a lot?
Salên gozan da... mêj e... ha? Heştê û heştê da... o da no
da çokê me ket bori...
In the years of 'gozan' [maybe 80s]... long ago... huh? In
eighty and eighty [1980]... oh it fell to our knees...
qederê girt... mekîn bû. Û îsal li rind bû.
about a meter... it was strong. And this year was good.
Dibêjin demên berê da, tedî... em diçûn gunda behsa we
dikin, dibêjin... dema berf dibarî, dibê deriyê me mal
venebûn? Hinkî berf dibarî...?
They say in old times... we went to villages talking about
you, saying... when it snowed, our house doors wouldn't
open? It snowed a little...?
Wela wena pir zêde negihiştime, hewa pêşda ye. Yanî wena...
Tebîan wa digotin, digo gava venebûn, heta bi zorê bêra,
dera ve dikirin, diçûn cîrana der dikirin...
Well I didn't catch that much, that's from before. So...
Naturally they said so, said when they wouldn't open, until
with force shovels, they opened doors, went and dug out
neighbors...
Mekin bû berê. Bes dema vê salan we bû, ne wena berê... dema
kevn disa rind bû yanî.
It was strong before. But in these years it was like that,
not like before... old times were good.
Naha behsa avê bikim. Naha di gundê we da kanî hene?
Now let's talk about water. Are there springs in your
village?
Hene.
There are.
Li kuderê ne? Navê kaniyê we çi ne û li kuderê ne?
Where are they? What are the names of your springs and where
are they?
Kanî... ew bîr heye, Hecîkê Jêr e. Li viro bîrek heye, kanîk
heye, avê hindik e, ne pir e.
Spring... there is that well, Lower Hecika. Here too there
is a well, a spring, water is little, not much.
Wa de kanî zivistanê der, hew no... yanî ê tebî... havîn
mivînê bişixulin tinne.
That spring comes out in winter, not now... so naturally...
in summer and such working is not there.
Tinne bes bîrê me işte av zê ye. Ya Hecîkê Jêr. Û yek li vir
heye, piçik tê da heye, baş e.
None, but our well has much water. The one in Lower Hecika.
And there is one here, has a little in it, it's good.
Apê Omer, wek gundê Hecîka hun debara xwe bi çi dikin?
Uncle Omer, as Hecika village, how do you make a living?
Wela berê berê ji mêj, ga û kûmbar dikir, pez xwedî dikir...
her malekê sed dewar, dused dewar xwedî dikir pez.
Well long long ago, we used oxen and plowing, raised
sheep... every house raised hundred, two hundred animals
sheep.
Û kûmbar jî ne qeysax bû dikirin... Ziraat, genim, ceh e...
filan e, baqil e, rez in... Paşê darên zeytûn çandin. Zeytûn
ne ji mêj e yanî.
And plowing was not easy they did... Agriculture, wheat,
barley... so on, legumes, vineyards... Then they planted
olive trees. Olives are not from long ago.
Yanî paşê, nuka jî işte ser zeytûna ye... darê behîva heye,
mişmişê hene, mişmişxane heye, rind e maşallah.
So later, now too it's on olives... there are almond trees,
apricots, apricot orchards, it's good mashallah.
Axê me yanî lê dibe... ha çi çand dibe.
Our soil allows it... whatever you plant grows.
Deşt tune ji ber ku hemû çiya ye?
No plains because it's all mountains?
Deşt tune he... ê me deşt tune. Ê me giş çiya ye. Deşt heye
ji Atmana wê da... vir da ê me deşta me tune.
No plains huh... ours has no plains. Ours is all mountains.
There is plain from Atmana over there... over here we don't
have plains.
Mala te ava be. Xwedê kêmasiya we nede.
May your house be prosperous. May God not give you lack.
Te xweş... Ehlen we sehlen.
You too... Welcome.
(Music)
Li bakurê gund, gundê Atmana, kûrtahîra li rojhilat, Xirabê
Îbî kaniya şûrkê, Reco gundê Mûskê,
To the north of the village, Atmana village, the short
distance to the east, Xirabê Îbî spring of Şûrk, Rajo
village of Mûsk,
û erdê kûrtê li ba Şûrçiyayê Kaşê Eniya Hizir, Geliyê
Kêmiriyê û gundê Dêrwîş,
and the land of Kûrt near Şûr Mountain, slope of Eniya
Hizir, Valley of Kêmiriyê and Dêrwîş village,
û li rojava bînayê kir, û her du ziyaretgehên Sêbikê û Sêbê
Quncik.
and to the west built buildings, and the two shrines Sêbikê
and Sêbê Quncik.
Her wiha sê şikeftin kevnar di serdema Romaniyan de hatibûn
vekirin hene.
Also three ancient caves opened in the Roman era exist.
Gundiyan da nezanîn ku kozik bi qyasî heft şimilan genim lê
hatiye dîtin, lê pişta kûriya gund hate zevt kirin, di bine
erdê de man.
Villagers did not know that a silo with about seven measures
of wheat was found there, but after the depth of the village
was seized, they remained underground.
Her wiha pakrewanek di gund de heye bi navê Şehîd Celal ku
yekemîn ji şehîdên destpêkê ye di salên nodî de şehîd bûye.
Also there is a martyr in the village named Martyr Celal who
is one of the first martyrs, martyred in the nineties.
Komîna gundê jêrîn bi navê Şehîd Celal e û komîna gundê
jorîn jî bi navê Şehîd Melsa ye.
The commune of the lower village is named Martyr Celal and
the commune of the upper village is named Martyr Melsa.
(Music)
Merheba ji we ra.
Hello to you.
Merheba ehlen.
Hello welcome.
Em îro derbasî gundê we bûn, me xwest hinekî dîroka gundê
Hecîka jî nas bikin.
We passed through your village today, we wanted to learn a
bit about Hecika village's history.
Ahlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Sax be. Lê ewilî destpêkê em ê navan bipirsin, navê we?
Thanks. But first we will ask names, your name?
Navê min Seîd e. Ji gundê Hecîka.
My name is Seîd. From Hecika village.
Ser çava.
Upon my eyes [You're welcome].
Navê min Sebrî ye.
My name is Sebrî.
Ser çava Sebrî.
Upon my eyes Sebrî.
Xêr û selamî hatin, ser çava, ser seran.
Good and peaceful coming, upon eyes, upon heads.
Sax be. Navê dayikê?
Thanks. Mother's name?
Navê min Fîdan e. Ji Hecîka me. Ehlen we sehlen hatina we.
Ser çava ser sera.
My name is Fîdan. I am from Hecika. Welcome to your coming.
Upon eyes upon heads.
Sax be. Dayê navê te?
Thanks. Mother your name?
Ehlen we sehlen, heval. Em Hecîka ne, bi mal in, em li vir
in.
Welcome, friend. We are Hecika, with home, we are here.
Sax be. Belê me xwest îro em derbasî gundê Hecîka bûn, lê em
ê dema me ra behsa gundê Hecîka dikê, em ê behsa darê dikin,
behsa bîrê dikin.
Thanks. Yes we wanted today as we passed Hecika village, but
when talking about Hecika village to us, we will talk about
the tree, talk about the well.
Me xwest hinekî dîroka vê bîrê û vê darê nas bikin.
We wanted to learn a bit about the history of this well and
this tree.
Em spasiya gundiyan jî dikin bi me ra derbas bûn. Lê naha,
nekê em ê bipirsin, ev dara kê çand? Kengî çand? Û çawa hat
çand? Yanî ev çend sal in?
We thank the villagers too for passing with us. But now,
first we will ask, who planted this tree? When? And how was
it planted? I mean how many years is it?
Ev dara, emrê xwe dused û pêncî sal in.
This tree, its age is two hundred and fifty years.
Kalkê me Hisê Birîm navê Hisê Birîm bû, wî şitil, wextê ku
mehsar çêkirî, kevirê mehsarê anî ye ji Kilis... buxara
şitil ra ji Kilis anî hat çand.
Our grandfather Hisê Birîm, his name was Hisê Birîm, he
brought the sapling, when he built the press, he brought the
press stone from Kilis... brought the sapling root from
Kilis and it was planted.
Emrê xwe dused û pêncî sal in.
Its age is two hundred and fifty years.
Navê xwe çi bû?
What was his name?
Kalkê me Hisê Birîm bû.
Our grandfather was Hisê Birîm.
Hisê Birîm.
Yanî ev dar a ji Kilis anî vir?
So he brought this tree from Kilis to here?
Ev şitil ji Kilis anî hatiye vir. Li vir çand. Û emrê xwe
dused û pêncî sal in.
This sapling was brought from Kilis to here. Planted here.
And its age is two hundred and fifty years.
Û mehsere jî çêkir. Mehsere jî çêkir, divê esta da. Wextê
mehsere çêkirî, kevirê mehsere ji jûr da anîn... hat... wa
şitla zeytûna jî bi xwe ra anî hat li vî derî çand.
And he built the press too. He built the press, in that
time. When he built the press, they brought the press stone
from up there... came... he brought olive saplings with him
too and planted here.
E mehsere li kuderê ye?
And where is the press?
Mehsere ew e li cem me ye. Li vî derî.
The press is that one near us. At this place.
Nêzîk e?
Is it close?
Nêzîk e.
It's close.
E mehsere çi ye?
And what is the press?
Mehsere zeyt e. Ê zeytê. Wê şitlê zeytûna jî ra jûr derê
anîn, wek hezar şitlî şitil zeytûn li vê mentiqê tinebûn.
Press is oil. Of oil. They brought those olive saplings from
up there too, like a thousand saplings, olive saplings
weren't in this region.
Şitlê zeytûna jî bi xwe ra anî hat, zeytûn jî... li hafê wa
rê... rêyê Reco, şitil hezar dar girt û bi derê da çand.
He brought olive saplings with him too, olives too... on the
side of that road... road to Rajo, he took a thousand
sapling trees and planted in the place.
Û mehsar jî girt, teb'en caiz kir yanî. Ji wê, emrê dused û
pêncî salî hetanî naha.
And he took the press too, naturally made it ready. Since
then, age of 250 years until now.
Ev dar a navê xwe Çinar e?
This tree's name is Plane tree?
Çinar e.
It is Plane tree.
Naha em behsa mehsere bikin, işte tiştekî bipirsim,
mehsere... mehsere kevir e?
Now let's talk about the press, just ask something, the
press... is the press stone?
Mehsere kevir e. Hisê Birîm pêşbavê me ayle bû...
The press is stone. Hisê Birîm was our ancestor family...
Gundî Golsan û vî gundê me, gundê me lê Husê Brim...
The villager Golsan and this village of ours, our village
where Husê Brim...
Ma'ser girt di sê sala da.
Built the press (olive press) in three years.
Rabi kevirê ma'serê, kevirê raş ji Kilis anîn.
He stood up and brought the press stone, the black stone
from Kilis.
Nîrê di stê dega kirin û bi meriya, bi ga ew kevirê gandin
heya vê derê.
They put the yoke on the necks of oxen, and with men and
oxen, they rolled that stone up to here.
Raş Kilis?
Black Kilis?
Raş Kilis.
Black Kilis.
Û bira... weşê tlî darê çinarê jî li xwar anîn.
And brother... they also brought that plane tree sapling
down there.
Heta emarê, girtina dîroka ma'serê Husê Brim...
As for the age, the history of the construction of Husê
Brim's press...
Girtî, teqrîben mabeyna 200 heta 250 salî, ez texmîn dikim.
It was built approximately between 200 to 250 years ago, I
estimate.
Li vê şwînê da, ma'ser girt, wî dorê jî dîroka salê ma'serê
di wê tê çandin?
In this place, he built the press; was the date of the press
year planted (inscribed) in that era?
Wî dorê çinarê?
In that era of the plane tree?
Na ez pirsa dikim, ma'ser hîn heye?
No, I am asking, does the press still exist?
Ma'ser heye.
The press exists.
Ew kevirê wê tivê gi heye?
Is its stone and all its equipment there?
Kevrê xwe heye, êçigê nîzamî mayî.
Its stone is there, the orderly grinding wheel remains.
Noka jî em herin êçigê, mihemê her derê ku çiyê emê hewldin.
Even now if we go to the grinder, the important parts of it
everywhere, we will try [to show/preserve it].
Na a berî bi 250 salî li vir zeytûn he bûn?
Now, 250 years ago, were there olives here?
Zeytûn tüne bûn, kevir bûn.
There were no olives, there were rocks.
Tebe'an li kirdaxê hebûn, bes li vira, di wê salê bi ma'ser
girtî da...
Of course, in Kurd-Dagh (Kurdish Mountain) there were some,
but here, in that year when the press was built...
Hezar darê zeytûnê, pişta rêya Reco û wa li ser erdê gi
çand.
He planted a thousand olive trees behind the Rajo road and
on all this land.
Di hewşê wa wekî hezar mêwî çand, rezê hejîro binê gund jî
ew jî tabi'ê rez e.
In its courtyard, he planted about a thousand vines, and the
fig orchard below the village is also part of the orchard.
Wê çaxê ew milkê, bi destê xwe bi ma'serê ra çand û hata
noka.
At that time, that property, he planted it with his own
hands along with the press, until now.
Ez tiştekî dî jite pirskim.
Let me ask you something else.
Na ev riya...
Now this road...
Ev riya diçê kûderê?
Where does this road go?
Na ev riya ku li vira?
Now this road that is here?
Ev riya, derê gundê Qude ye.
This road goes to Qude village.
Û derê 'Umera û derê Me'mela ye.
And goes to 'Umera and goes to Me'mela.
Le'in bi e'tîbar berê makîne tune bûn.
Because, considering that in the past there were no machines
(cars).
Ew bi meşê bûn, dewar bûn, nahiyA me nahiya Reco bû.
They were on foot, there were pack animals, our district was
the Rajo district.
Ji Me'mela da, 'Umera da, gundê Qude da, gi di vê riya me ra
dişuxulin, diçûn û dihatin.
From Me'mela, from 'Umera, from Qude village, everyone used
this road of ours to work, going and coming.
Heye noka diçûn tê?
Do they still go on it now?
Hata noka hîn darin.
Until now, they still go.
Û noka 'ecer, jelk û makîne û dinya hedîs bûye, darin gundê
Xelîl ra darin, darên nû ra darin.
And now, lately, since rags (old ways) are gone and machines
and the world have become modern, they go via Xelîl village,
they go via the new roads.
Û exlebiyet ji vê rû darin tên.
But the majority go and come via this way.
Ka em zayîkê pirsin tişkî?
Let's ask the young man something?
Dayê... na bîr li vir heye?
Mother... now is there a well here?
Mm.
Na ev bîra... Wa çend gunda dihat ji vê bîrê av dibir?
Now this well... How many villages used to come to fetch
water from this well?
Wele pênc şeş gunda dihatin ser.
By God, five or six villages came to it.
Kûderê?
Where (which ones)?
Her Hecîk dihatin ser, Hecîkê Jûr û Jêr.
Hecîk always came to it, Upper and Lower Hecîk.
Û Atmana, gundê Qude, gundê Dewrîş, gundê Mîske.
And Atmana, Qude village, Dewrîş village, Mîske village.
Hat gundê Hesen, hata Banîkê Dana dihatin av dibirin, bi
dewar.
Up to Hesen village, even Banîkê Dana came to fetch water,
with pack animals.
Gundê Qude?
Qude village?
Gundê Qude, Kumreş.
Qude village, Kumreş.
Ew jî dihatin vir?
Did they also come here?
Wele Kumreş... ez nizanim.
By God, Kumreş... I don't know.
Yanê nêzîk deha gunda dihatin vir?
So nearly ten villages came here?
Ee, nêzîk deha gunda.
Yes, nearly ten villages.
Dihatin bi dewar av dibirin, me'nê male, sehnîş tüne bûn.
They came with animals to take water, meaning for the house,
there were no cisterns.
Û dihatin kinc dişûştin li vira? Nav vê ardê ne, kî kelem
bûn?
And did they come to wash clothes here? Inside this land,
were they crowded?
Kincê xwe dişûştin, serê xwe dişûştin, û tişta diçûn.
They washed their clothes, washed their heads (bathed), and
took things and left.
Dayê ez tiştekî jite pirskim.
Mother, let me ask you something.
E berî vê bi çend sala hûn dihatin ser vê bîrê?
How many years ago did you come to this well?
Wele aqê bim, pêncî sal ne hatime vir.
By God, as far as I remember, I haven't come here for fifty
years.
Pêncî salî em dihatin vir avê.
Fifty years ago we came here for water.
Li viderê me av bi kera, heywan dibir, me bi pişta dibir.
Here we took water with donkeys, animals, we carried it on
our backs.
Me kinc dişûşt, me serê xwe dişûşt, me sitlê xwe...
We washed clothes, we washed our heads, our buckets...
Me mesk dibir, me çota dibir.
We took the butter churns, we took the large sacks.
Rê tune bû, kelem bû, siq bû, tiştê re ne diçûn ne dihat.
There was no road, it was crowded, it was steep, things
couldn't go or come easily.
Ma em yane waneta re diçûn dihatin.
We used to go and come on those paths anyway.
De di gundê me ra... yar manok nî bû.
So for our village... there was no other helper/option.
Em kanê biçin ser bîrê jî, em binêrin bîra wa çiqas metru
kûre.
Let's actually go to the well too, let's see how many meters
deep your well is.
Wala bîra... dorik yerek me'rûf e, ji liva mentîqê.
By God, the well... around here is a known place, in this
region.
Le'nû dar huna, bavo mezinbînê tune ne, heta li mentîqê hebe
jî.
Because trees are here, man, there are no big ones, even if
they exist in the region.
Yanî hene kêm in?
So there are some, but they are few?
Kêm in, û yumkin hîç tüne bin.
Few, and possibly there are none at all.
Û dar xetê... divê em herin bin darê çinarê rûnin, me'rûf e,
hênik e.
And the tree line... we must go sit under the plane tree,
it's famous, it's cool.
Xweşiya avî bîrê jî, xweş e ava bîrê.
The pleasantness of the well water too, the well water is
good.
Ava vê bîrê jî avek pir xweş e li mentîqê, yanê yumkin kêm
avê waha hebin.
The water of this well is very good water in the region,
meaning possibly few waters like this exist.
Ev avê baranê ye lê avzê ye ev bîrê?
Is this rainwater or is it spring water (groundwater), this
well?
Avzê ye, avzê ye.
It's groundwater, it's groundwater.
Ev çend metru heye?
How many meters deep is it?
Ewa teqrîben... deh yanzdeh metru hebin.
That is approximately... ten or eleven meters.
Lê bes silef ne ava bîrê tebe'an, bîr qedîm e em nizanin
kinga ye.
But naturally it's not [just] surface water, the well is
ancient, we don't know when it's from.
Tarîxê xwe kevn e.
It's old?
Its history is old.
Romanî ye çiye em nizanin.
Whether it's Roman or what, we don't know.
Eme çavê xwe girtî yanê.
We opened our eyes [and it was here], meaning.
Bes... hesebî demê re çêkirin, çikê bilind kirin, mese
çêkirin çikê bilind kir.
But... according to the time they fixed the path, raised the
level a bit, fixed the area and raised it.
Da me hane çêkirin me rehet av jê kişand.
So we fixed it like this so we could draw water from it
comfortably.
Yanî wa hinek wa girtî?
So you closed/built up some of it?
Ee me hinek qijik tê wernebin, ewa berê neha bî, berê fere
bî.
Yes, so that little kids wouldn't fall in, it wasn't like
this before, before it was wide.
Deriyê wa fere bî.
Its opening was wide.
Biçûk dertê werdibûn.
Small ones (kids/animals) would fall in.
Û yek şitê werbî jî jê derkeve.
And if something fell in, to be able to get it out.
Na di gundê we da çend bîr hene?
Now in your village, how many wells are there?
E neha... çend bîr di gundê we da hene?
Like this... how many wells are there in your village?
Dido ne.
There are two.
Yek ev e, yek jî li geliyê jûr mefreqê Hecîkê jûr e lina.
One is this one, one is in the upper valley at the fork of
Upper Hecîk there.
Û herdû jî qedîm in e.
And both are ancient.
Si'netê kûderê ye em nizanin?
Whose craftsmanship (origin) it is, we don't know?
Yanê kevn e, qedîm e.
Meaning it's old, it's ancient.
Lê di vê bîrê da berbeq heye, de re nav...
But in this well there is a conduit (aqueduct pipe), going
into...
Nav erd erd dikeve daharike.
Going into the earth, it runs underground.
Wa zemanî, pê erd avdan, veda xwarin, mihim berbeqê mecro
heye, hata derê jêr.
In that time, they irrigated the land with it, ate from it;
essentially there is a conduit channel, all the way down.
Mala wa ava be.
May your home be prosperous (Thank you).
Spas ji were.
Thanks to you.
Saetê we xweş.
Health to you.
Spas.
Thanks.
Li başûrê gund dareke çinarê kevnar heye.
To the south of the village, there is an ancient plane tree.
Dîroka wê dikişê ta 250 salî.
Its history stretches back to 250 years.
Ev dar bi destê Husê Brim hatibû çandin.
This tree was planted by the hand of Husê Brim.
Li şitê darê zeytûna anîbû û li derdora wê çandibûn.
He brought olive saplings and planted them around it.
Riyek di kêleka wê re derbas dibû.
A road used to pass by its side.
Ev riya diçû Kilisê.
This road went to Kilis.
Tevlî kevirê delûbê bi tolkirina û bi meşê...
Including the Delube stone, by rolling and walking...
Haniya gund û çand.
They brought it to the village and planted [the press
stone/tree].
Li bin darê bîreke kevnar heye.
Under the tree, there is an ancient well.
Dîroka bîrê nayê zanîn.
The history of the well is unknown.
Lê heyan niha ava wê heye.
But until now, it has water.
Di dema bûrî de...
In the past time...
Gundên derdora Atmana, Hecîka, Banîkê...
The surrounding villages of Atmana, Hecîka, Banîkê...
Hesen, Qude, Derwîş...
Mûske û Hec Xelîl û Reco.
Mûske and Hec Xelîl and Rajo.
Av ji bîrê dibirin û şivanên jî pezê xwe ji av didan.
They took water from the well and shepherds watered their
flocks from it.
Me ne bêrîkerê nane sêlê...
We are not missers of the griddle bread... (implied:
actually, we are)
Fera bîna li ber palê...
Wide vision on the hillside...
Şabirûka me darbestê bûn...
Our playful ones were [on] wooden biers...
Bice rûka kal û pîrê...
With the faces of the old men and women...
Ho ez xerîbê... welatê me...
Oh, I am a stranger... my homeland...
Ho ez xerîbê welatê me.
Oh, I am a stranger to my homeland.
Bêno gulo çelmisiyame...
Without scent, the flower has withered...
Gul ketime bextê yame...
The flower has fallen to my luck...
Ez xerîbê welatê me.
I am a stranger to my homeland.
Wespas.
Thanks.
Dengê te sax be.
May your voice be healthy.
Dayê quwat be jibo ra.
Mother, strength to you (greeting).
Spas, ehle w sehlen.
Thanks, welcome.
Dayê na, demê berê şahîk li cem we çêdibû...
Mother, now, in the past when you had a celebration...
We çi xwarin çêdikir?
What food did you make?
Me çi xwarin dikir? Me dawe rja jî dikir.
What food did we make? We made wedding rice (bulgur/pilaf).
Me germ dikir, me germê rizê, î bilxurê.
We made soup, rice soup, or bulgur soup.
Me dew çêdikir, me şurbe dikirin, me şurbê rizê dikir.
We made yogurt drink (ayran), we made soups, we made rice
soup.
Lebenî dikirin, tişta çi hebî me gi dikir.
We made yogurt stew, whatever there was, we did it all.
Davê me're mir me gi dikir yanê bi jerwa.
For our guests, we did it all together.
Xewra dikirin, kufte dikirin, sermisok dikir, beluh dikir,
tişta vê tiştina me gi dikirin.
We made braised meat, we made meatballs (kufte), we made
Sermisok (dumplings), we made Baluh, we made all these
things.
E dayê na, jiberê da gundê we usa ye? Wî li hev dicivin?
So mother, now, has your village been like this since the
past? Do they gather together?
Ee, em civîna me heye.
Yes, we have our gathering.
Demê mîvanekî we tê?
When a guest comes to you?
Na evro em bînim mîvanê we, em hatin ji wî xwarinê kê
çêdike?
Now today, let's say your guests, we came, who is making
that food?
Eywa, em xo nika çêdikin.
Yes, we are making it ourselves right now.
Wî jiberê da hanane?
Has it been like this since the past?
Ee, em jiberê da hanane, kî hat, hat cimet hat bixwe.
Yes, we've been like this since the past, whoever came,
came, the community came to eat.
Kesî nabêjê neyê.
No one says "don't come".
Dayê na, berê digutin, ser kincê jina, cilê jina.
Mother, now, they used to say, regarding women's clothes,
women's dress.
Berê digutin destmalê eniya, berê jina ber hembiya dikirin.
In the past they spoke of forehead scarves, in the past
women wore aprons/vests.
Destmalê çiçik didan eniyê xwe diştandin, flaz wekî jina
sewi...
They tied flower-patterned scarves on their foreheads, loose
cloth like women...
Ew destmala hîna bal te hene?
Do you still have those scarves?
Ew destmal no wele me davêtine dayê, eniyê xwe nalcamîne,
jiberê da.
Those scarves, no by God we threw them away mother, we don't
bind our foreheads anymore, since a while ago.
Ena 'alimim, me caran we nekirî.
I am not aware/used to it, we never did that (lately).
Dayê heye we dike, ê heye jî we nake, tişta herim tûnîkîne
ez nizanim.
Mother, there are those who do it, and there are those who
don't, things are forbidden or not, I don't know.
Dayê... destê we sax bin.
Mother... may your hands be healthy.
Ehle w sehlen, tuji.
Welcome, you too.
Ka ji mera ser xwarina xwe dehange.
Talk to us about your food.
Em xwarina xwe... mesle ev em germê xwe dikin, em rizê xwe
dikelînin...
Our food... for example, this, we make our soup, we boil our
rice...
Cî... takra, em germê xwe didinên, em goştê xwe û pîvazê xwe
jî be hevda ditirsinin, dirca xwe dikine û em li germê xwe
dikin.
Place... then, we put our soup on, we fry our meat and
onions together, we put our spices and we put it in our
soup.
Takra, em hevîrê xwe distirên û em nanê xwe pehn dikin û em
dikin sermisok.
Then, we knead our dough and flatten our bread and we make
Sermisok (dumplings).
Dikin şamburek?
You make Samburek?
Mm.
E, de hişta berê me pahn dikir, me... me bi destê ra
dikirin, ew roke ew işa gi çû.
Yes, so back then we flattened it, we... we did it by hand,
those days and that work is all gone.
Na hûn navî sêlê dikin?
Now do you make griddle bread?
Mm, em nanê sêlê jî me bare dikir.
Mm, we also made griddle bread in the past.
Na hûn nakin?
You don't do it now?
Na, noka em noke. Nan tüne be em dikin, nan hebe em nakin.
No, now we don't. If there is no bread we do it, if there is
bread we don't.
Qut qut qut be em dikin, qut nebe em nakin.
If it's scarce we do it, if it's not scarce we don't.
Çar nû'ane zanin?
Do you know four types?
Na şamburek hûn dibên...
Now the Samburek you say...
Em bi şîşburek... ê şurbara dibên şîşburek, em bi Kurdî
dibên sermisok.
We say Shishbarak... the soup people say Shishbarak, in
Kurdish we say Sermisok.
Çend no'ê wî heye?
How many types of it are there?
Çend no'ê wî dikin, yê lorqokê dikin, masikê dikin.
We make several types, we make the rolled ones, we make the
small ones.
Ê lûrkê em dikin, emê mastî kemadî dikin, emê ispanaxê
dikin, amê goşt û rizê dikin.
We make the Lûrk type, we make the yogurt one completely, we
make the spinach one, we make the meat and rice one.
Ê nîskê?
The lentil one?
Ê nîskê jî em dikin.
We make the lentil one too.
We destê wa sax be.
May your hands be healthy.
Saxbî.
Be healthy.
Her wiha rêjeya xwendinê di gund de bilind e.
Likewise, the rate of education/literacy in the village is
high.
Û bêhtirî sed kesî zanîngeh qedandine.
And more than one hundred people have graduated from
university.
Û gelek bijîşk...
And many doctors...
Eşk û evîna diyarê Parêzer Mamuste.
The love and passion of the land of Lawyer Mamuste.
Û karwanê payabilind, jigurd hane.
And the high-status caravan, are jigurd (brave/alert).
Û sê Mihemed Muxtarê sê gunda bûn û hemû pirsgirêkên wan
çareser dikirin.
And there were three Mihemed Mukhtars of three villages, and
they solved all their problems.
Hesen Mihemed Hiso, di serdema Fransiyan de, dema balafira
Fransiyan herêm keşf dikir...
Hesen Mihemed Hiso, during the French era, when the French
airplane was scouting the region...
Wî bi qelêşa xwe avêtê û balafir anî xwarê.
He shot at it with his rifle and brought the airplane down.
Hêjayî birxistinê ye ku di gund de xanîyek bi herîya şîr
hatîye avakirin û tana ha jî ew xanî heye.
It is worth mentioning that in the village, a house was
built using mud mixed with milk, and that house still exists
to this day.
Merheba.
Hello.
Merheba te.
Hello to you.
Merheba.
Hello.
Emano sipî ke.
Make it peaceful/safe.
Tu remezan î, ne?
You are Remezan, right?
Serçava, Hecîkê.
You're welcome, (I'm from) Hecîka.
Şikirî?
Are you thankful (good)?
Serçava.
You're welcome.
Spasxweş.
Thank you.
Spas.
Thanks.
Serçava.
You're welcome.
Hûn çi karî dikin li vir?
What work are you doing here?
Em kevrên reş derdixin...
We extract black stones...
Na berî vî, kevrê da, şerek derketîye, hûn şerê dikin, hûn
çi dikin?
No, before that, in the stone, a fight has broken out, are
you fighting, what are you doing?
Ha, vaye kesere li ber heye, em kevir tînin, dişkênin,
çêdikin, keserê pê de'inin.
Ah, here is the cutter in front of it, we bring the stone,
break it, fix it, and apply the cutter to it.
Wa çend sal e ev kesere li vir hatiye danîn?
How many years has this cutter been placed here?
Ha vaye 20 sal hene.
Ah, it has been 20 years.
20 sal hene?
It has been 20 years?
20 sal hene.
It has been 20 years.
Ê kî xwedan e?
And who is the owner?
Ez xwedanê xwe me, Remezan.
I am my own owner, Remezan.
20 sal e tu vî karî dikî li vir?
You have been doing this work here for 20 years?
Erê.
Yes.
Jiber ku cewê hemû zinar e?
Because the geography is all cliffs/rocks?
Erê.
Yes.
Erê?
Yes?
Wê keviran ji vî zinarî radikin?
Do they take the stones from this cliff?
Erê.
Yes.
Hûn çi dikin pê?
What do you do with it?
Em pê... de'inin, caîz dikin... dikin bexsî belata. Bexsî
belata em pê çêdikin.
We... put it, prepare it... we make it into blocks for
tiles. We make blocks for tiles with it.
Ê nasê betûnê çêdibin... Tiştê hewa pê îşare derdikevin.
And concrete people are made... Things like that come out of
it.
Yanî hûn belata çêdikin?
So you make tiles?
Na em ne belata, em caîz dikin bexsa, nasê me'mela, nasê
me'mela caîz dikin, dikin belata.
No, we don't make tiles, we prepare the blocks, the factory
people, the factory people prepare it and make it into
tiles.
Li kuderê ne me'mel?
Where are the factories?
Li Efrînê ne.
They are in Afrin.
Hewna belata ji we çêdikin?
They make tiles from you (your stones)?
Hewna jê belata çê... Em bexsa jê bar dikin, dişkênin bexsa,
jivir caîz dikin, dişkênin û didin wan, hewna li wirê dikin
belata.
They make tiles from it... We load the blocks from it, break
the blocks, prepare it here, break it and give it to them,
and they make tiles there.
Hûn vî kevirî ji vî zinarî jêdikin?
You cut this stone from this cliff?
Erê, ji wir tînin tînin. Erê.
Yes, we bring it from there. Yes.
Na ji kuderê? jivir?
No, from where? From here?
Na, ji derve, nav zeytûna tînin.
No, from outside, we bring it from among the olive trees.
Yanî ne ne livir e?
So it's not here?
Na.
No.
Hûn çawa jêdikin tînin vir?
How do you cut it and bring it here?
Zinar diçûlê, nav zeytûnan derdixînin, bar dikin, tînin tên
viderê dişkênin.
We extract the rocks in the countryside, among the olive
trees, load them, bring them here, and break them.
Û çêdikin di keserê, kesera dêrê... caîz dikî bexsa...
bêjing heye li jêr.
And we process it in the cutter, the cutter puts it...
prepares the blocks... there is a sieve underneath.
Bêjing heye têda dikî haryekî... ewî gîndî başqa çêdikî,
nimrê xwa başqa çêdikî.
There is a sieve, you put a mesh in it... it separates the
coarse one separately, it makes its number (size)
separately.
Î girsî hûr ser hev ra darbask dikî.
It passes the large and small ones over each other.
Hewa we daxê... paşê caîz bû, barî qelaba caîz bû, em bar
dikin di şînin me'mela ra.
Like that time... then when it's ready, when the dump truck
load is ready, we load it and send it to the factory.
Yanî hefte çend caran hûn dişînin?
Meaning, how many times a week do you send it?
E hesb şixul... yani heseb şixul caîz bû em dişînin.
It depends on the work... meaning depending on the work,
when it's ready, we send it.
Ne ne muhadad e?
No, it's not specific?
Ne, ne belî ye.
No, it's not clear.
Yanî rojê carekê, hefteyê carekê?
I mean once a day, once a week?
Na, na, na. Hewa hefteyê carekê wano.
No, no, no. Like once a week or so.
Teqrîben?
Approximately?
Teqrîben, he.
Approximately, yes.
Karê we baş e?
Is your business good?
Karê me henû ye, erê.
Our business is so-so, yes.
Yanî debara we jê tê?
I mean, does your livelihood come from it?
E bereket versin, debara me.
Let there be blessings (Thank God), our livelihood.
Ka emê binêrin hûn çawa kar dikin? Ka kerem kin kar bikin.
Let's see how you work? Please go ahead and work.
Yalla, heya... bişkênin...
Yalla, come on... break it...
Win destpêkê vî kevirî dişkînin?
You break this stone at the beginning?
E, kevir dişkênin... caîz dibe...
Yes, we break the stone... it gets prepared...
Em bidere kar bikin.
Let's work outside (continue working).
Kerem kin.
Go ahead.
Yanî bes vî mezin tê de hûr dikin?
So you only crush this big one in it?
Erê vî mezin tê de hûr dikin.
Yes, we crush this big one in it.
Mane, wekî vayê mezin hûn çawa dikin vay?
I mean, like this big one, how do you do this one?
Vî mezin dişkênin, hûr dikin.
We break this big one, crush it.
Têkarnabe?
It doesn't fit in?
E ka em binêrin?
No, no.
Can we see?
Ê ka bîne.
Hey bring it.
Ev çi kevir e reş e bira?
What kind of black stone is this, brother?
Kevrê me ne bes reş e. Kevrê me reş heye, sipî heye, xwêgir,
bi Erebî dibêjin Aselî, kesk heye.
Our stone isn't only black. We have black stone, white,
xwêgir (beige/salt-colored), in Arabic they say Aselî
(Honey), there is green.
Yanî her new'ek ji maddê ruxam luba me tê dîtin.
I mean, every type of marble material can be found with us.
Gîş ji bilata ra? yanî karên din jî jê çêdibin?
Is it all for tiles? Or are other works made from it too?
E na, ev belata... ev şekirine, ev kevrî sax be, girin be,
dibin menşera, qut dikin, dikin lowh.
Eh no, this tile... this is sugar (crushed/granular), (but)
if this stone is whole, is heavy (large block), they take it
to the sawmills, cut it, make slabs.
Jê mejla çêdikin, dîkora jê çêdikin, xetê Erebî têra divîn.
They make sinks/tables from it, make decor from it, write
Arabic calligraphy in it.
Xetê Erebî jê çêdikin. Ewe, cama û îmkanyat tinen e, yanî
menşera ba me wano na şuxilin.
They make Arabic calligraphy from it. It's that, we don't
have the glass (machinery) and possibilities, meaning
sawmills don't work like that with us.
Wî difroşin kuderê?
Where do you sell it?
Berê me dibir Şamê, dibir Himsê, dibir heta Libnan diçû ba
me dibir, Latqiyê.
Before, we used to take it to Damascus, take it to Homs, it
used to go even to Lebanon, we took it, Latakia.
Teb'en wana jî tesdîr dibin, diçûne Siûdiyê, diçûne Iraq,
diçûne her welatekî diçûne.
Of course, those would be exported too, they went to Saudi
Arabia, went to Iraq, went to every country.
Û elhemdulellah cem me, yanî îmkanyatê ruxam pir û pir heye.
And praise be to God, with us, I mean the possibilities
(reserves) of marble are very plentiful.
Em dixwazin, yanî miletê me îtîmad kir ser ruxam, teb'en ew
jî serwetek ji miletê me ra ye.
We want, I mean our people relied on marble, of course that
is also a wealth for our people.
Wal bira karê xwe bidomînin ha?
Well brother, continue your work, okay?
Hevo uzir bû, ortox, motora bişxulînin, wa me binerin.
There was an excuse/issue, friend, start the engine, let's
look at it.
Şixulînin?
Should we turn it on?
Bişixulînin.
Turn it on.
Roja te bi xêr dayê.
Good day to you, mother.
Roja te xwaş.
Good day to you.
Em te nasbikin?
May we know you?
Ez... navê min Meqbûle ye.
I... my name is Meqbûle.
Serçavê min dayê.
You're welcome (on my eyes), mother.
Serê çavê te sax be.
May your eyes be safe (Thank you).
Tu gundo, behsa te kir got tu bena çêdikî?
You villager, they talked about you saying you make threads?
Ez bena çêdikim, urxana girê didim...
I make threads, I tie heavy blankets (quilts)...
Ez nexwaşî heye pirko(?), ez çêdikim.
I have an illness/hardship..., I make them.
O tu gelek kar ba evro dikî?
And do you do a lot of work today?
E dikim, ma ez çi bikim? Zarokê min hene, heft zarokê min
hene, mêrê min miriye.
Yes I do, what else should I do? I have children, I have
seven children, my husband is dead.
Dayê na te hazir kindir jî te bidarê xistî, te kar dikir
naha?
Mother, no, you had prepared the skein/rope and put it on
the wood, were you working just now?
Ez karî îşta ban... karê min ban in. Ez urxana girê didim.
I... the work of thread... my work is threads. I tie heavy
blankets.
Hewa, yanî qusûrî se mekanî dikim, hefsar hînî, em pê qişkê
xwe tînin.
Just like that, I mean I do the shortcomings of the
place(?), halters and such, we make our living with it.
Em hînî pê, ava sarincê hildikşînin.
We pull up cistern water with it.
Pê tîşkî derdixin ser xanî.
They pull up things to the roof of the house with it.
Tu çend sal e tu bena çêdikî?
For how many years have you been making threads?
Çend sal no? Welle emrê min dehe salî bû, mala bavkê min,
dêkê min, bavkê min ser dehekim zewicî bû, em 'alîm bûn karî
wana, qusrê semekan. Ji dil hewa dibêm.
How many years? Well, my age was ten years old, my father's
house, my mother, my father... I was married over ten(?), we
learned their work, Qesra Semekan (Village name). I say it
from the heart like that.
Tu xwe ji vî gundî ye?
Are you from this village yourself?
No, ez ji gundê Wilîlê me.
No, I am from the village of Wilîlê.
Tu bûka gundê Hecîka ye?
You are a bride of the village Hecîka?
Bûka Hecîka me.
I am a bride of Hecîka.
Tu çend sal e tî vî gundî?
How many years have you been in this village?
Welle 40 sal nav de me.
Well, I have been in it for 40 years.
40 sal.
40 years.
Oîna tû mala bavî xo bûyî te çêdikir vî bena?
And when you were at your father's house, did you make this
thread?
E min mala bavî xo, min ben çêdikirin, micil çêdikirin.
Yes, at my father's house, I made threads, made sitting
mattresses.
Min mû dişkînî.
I spun hair/wool.
Yanî şaiyê gundê xisûsî heye hîro?
Meaning, is there a specific joy/celebration of the village
today?
Korê dêkê mi bû, 'elî 'alimîm.
It was my mother's son(?), Ali taught me.
Keçkê te jî hene?
Do you have daughters too?
Keçkê min, Xwedê we ji we ra bihêlin, ê d singî şebabina
Xwedê bidin, me çara dane, yek minê mayî ye, hew çûye,
cemberek Tirkê ye.
My daughters, may God keep yours for you, those in the prime
of youth may God give them, we gave away four, one of mine
remains, she has just gone, she is near Turkey(?).
No keçkê te ji vî karî zanin?
No, do your daughters know this work?
Bes qîzik min, urxana girêde.
Only my little girl, she ties blankets.
Ê dî te ne 'almandin?
And the others you didn't teach?
Kes ne 'alimî.
No one learned.
Çima te ne 'almandin?
Why didn't you teach them?
Na, diyata, te 'almand vî karî. Te çima keçkê xwe ne
'almand?
No, look, you learned this work. Why didn't you teach your
daughter?
Ê dibê jîr da mezin bûn.
Eh, they say they grew up under it.
Em ne 'acer hatine viderê.
We didn't come here as strangers/refugees(?).
Win berê li Helebê bûn?
Were you in Aleppo before?
Em li Heleb rûniştim, li Reqa rûniştim, li Efrînê rûniştim,
li Şamê rûniştim. Xêr e, ma'neyî, ewê zirûf wano îcab kir,
ez hatim viderê geriyam.
We lived in Aleppo, lived in Raqqa, lived in Afrin, lived in
Damascus. It's good, meaning, the circumstances required it
like that, I came here and wandered.
Tu pir geriya ye.
You have wandered a lot.
Ez pir geriya me.
I have wandered a lot.
Yanî Qusrê Semekan, hîn pir pir, ez têrêkî meriyê xwe livir
nas nakim.
I mean Qesra Semekan, still very very much, I don't know
enough of my own people here.
Tu çend sal e tî gun?
How many years have you been in the village?
Welle heye, heft sal heye.
Well there is, there is seven years.
Heft sal nû de tu hatiye?
Have you come in the last seven years?
E hewa.
Yes, like that.
Destpêka şoreşê te hatiye?
Did you come at the beginning of the revolution?
Ah.
Yeah.
Ka da, em binêrin tu çawa kar dikî?
Look mother, can we see how you work?
Na, te vî benî çidike? Tu çawa çêdikî?
No, what do you do with this thread? How do you make it?
Vayî 'ilm e, seh bike, hewa.
This is science/skill, look, like this.
Kê, ez kê je serî kerrê raçêkim?
Who, should I weave the donkey [load] from the start?
Na, destpêkê, tu çawa çêdikî? Em bi destpêkê da…
No, at the beginning, how do you do it? Let's start with the
beginning...
Ez darrisim.
I am spinning it.
No, ev pembû ye?
No, is this cotton?
Na, ev lastîk e.
No, this is nylon (synthetic).
Naqete?
It doesn't break?
Na qet naqete. Tu çi qasî.. av bikî, bayê li ber bidî, ew
rizîbûnê nake.
No, it never breaks. No matter how much... you put water on
it, or expose it to wind, it does not rot.
Tu ji ku tînî vê?
Where do you get this from?
Em dikiirin, cûta dikiirin.
We buy it, we buy the pair.
Hûn dikiirin?
You buy it?
Kîlo pêncî dînar dikiirin.
We buy the kilo for fifty [thousand] dinars.
Paşê tînî dirisî, çêdikî?
Then you bring it, spin it, and make it?
Tînim dirisim û çêdikim.
I bring it, spin it, and make it.
Ê ev jî çi jê tê?
And what comes out of this?
Wele darê xwe heye.
Well, it has its own wood/spindle.
Darê xwe heye.
Huh?
It has its own wood/spindle.
Dar?
Wood?
Darê ye, hewa jî darê çêdibe.
It's wood, this is also made via the wood.
Çawa ji darê çêdibe?
How is it made from wood?
Heva, tenê ji ku darê... wele nizanim darê... hewa...
This, just from where the wood... well I don't know the
wood... this...
Ne pembû ye?
Is it not cotton?
Na.
No.
Ne pembû ye ev.
This isn't cotton.
Eva, vê ra dibêjin lastîk. Kûk naqete.
This, they call this nylon. It absolutely does not break.
Erebî dibêjin jî kû...
In Arabic they also say...
Bes Kurmancî em dibêjin lastîk.
But in Kurmanji we say "lastîk" (nylon/rubber).
Ka, fanekî bixe şê da hinekî were, ji kerema xwe te be.
Here, put a spool on so it comes a bit, if you please.
Ez ê hena birisim. Ez ê hena çêdikim.
I will spin it like this. I make it like this.
Di rojekê da çend danê xilas dikî?
How many pieces do you finish in one day?
Wele, rojekê yekî dirisim, û rojekê jî didûnim.
Well, one day I spin one, and one day I wind it.
Dirrî yo. Dirrî yo benikê çêdikim.
It's a thorn [metaphor for difficult work]. I make the
string like a thorn.
Û ebena jî difroşim.
And I sell these strings too.
Tu bi çendê difroşî?
For how much do you sell it?
Hezar pênc sedî.
One thousand five hundred.
Hezar û pênc sed. Çend metre tê de?
One thousand five hundred. How many meters are in it?
Heft metre.
Seven meters.
Di rojekê yekî xilas dikî?
You finish one in a day?
Na. Dirrî yo.
No. It is thorny [hard work].
Her dirrî yo?
Always hard work?
Mm. Her dirrî yo yekî xelas dikim. Îşta meriv feqîr ekê,
kuryana bikem çikum.
Mm. With hard work, I finish one. Look, one is poor, what
else should I do for the boys?
Ê kîjan derê tebat dikî? Bîne...
And where do you secure it? Bring...
Hewe? Benê te yê hazir kiri hewe?
This? Is this your ready-made string?
Erê.
Yes.
Heva min hazir kiriye.
This, I have prepared.
Naqete jî?
And it doesn't break?
Qetandin tê tuneye.
There is no breaking in it.
Ê naxwe heyalek çend sal e pêk anaye harê...
So, a family has been doing this for how many years now...
Ya, dendana te tunebû ya!
Oh, you don't have teeth!
Ê hey, me kin e.
Hey, we pulled them out.
[Laughs]
Me o kin e, lo yê mi pê kişand.
We pulled them out, my son pulled them out.
Teş na bê?
Isn't it painful/bad?
Teş nebî, neqetî.
Let it not be bad, let it not break.
Em pê teşta, derdixin ser xaniyê.
With this, we carry basins up to the roof.
Bilxurê xwe pê bikşînin ser xaniyê, hişk bikin.
We pull our bulgur up to the roof with it, to dry it.
Meselen, satilê xwe avê pê bibin ser xaniyê, tîk avê tiştin,
gelekî tadê dibe.
For example, we carry our buckets of water up to the roof
with it, a drop of water... it withstands a lot of pressure.
Wekî xizîna em derdixin ser xaniyê.
Like the pantry goods we carry up to the roof.
Tiştê hana em pê derdixin ser xaniyê.
Things like that, we carry up to the roof with it.
Em darên qişka pê derdixin ser xaniyê.
We carry the winter wood up to the roof with it.
Em serşoyê xwe pê dişon.
We wash our heads/bodies with it.
Ê ji bo hindê hûn wer saxlem in maşellah?
Is that why you are so healthy, mashallah?
Em saxlem in. Werzîş ev e.
We are healthy. This is the exercise.
Werzîşa we ev e.
This is your exercise.
Werzîşa me ev e.
This is our exercise.
Em saet nehê şevê radikevin.
We go to sleep at nine o'clock at night.
Em saet çara şevê şiyar dibin.
We wake up at four in the morning.
Heta roj diçe ava, em li ser lingan e.
Until the sun sets, we are on our feet.
Em rûnanin.
We do not sit down.
Ne hewce ya hûn biçin qaca sporê û dietê bikin.
It's not necessary for you to go to a sports gym and go on a
diet.
Diet ev e. Spor ev e.
This is the diet. This is the sport.
Spor ev e, şixul e.
This is the sport, the work.
Xwarina me mast e.
Our food is yogurt.
Mast e.
It's yogurt.
Nanê me tîr e.
Our bread is tîr (flatbread).
Savara me, savara sor e.
Our bulgur, is red bulgur.
Rûnê me, rûnê nîvişk e. Rûnê kerrê ye.
Our oil is butter/ghee. It's donkey [churned] butter.
Yanî vê ba... vê xuzayiya, ev çiya, bes hena bef li ba we
heye.
I mean, with this air... this nature, these mountains, but
there is snow here with you.
Demê li bajarî ev tişta... tenê ma tu televîzyona didî? Ne,
sîreta didî me didî?
When in the city, these things... are you just watching
television? No, are you giving us advice?
Erê. No, qisûra se mêke, hewa boyê gû derman e.
Yes. No, excuse me, looking at this (nature/lifestyle) is
medicine.
Derman e.
It is medicine.
Derman e. Sibê rabibî, sibê zû qapî aze vekir, oçix bikim.
It is medicine. To wake up in the morning, early morning I
open the door, to open it wide.
Boyê li hindirî mexînê, maney bînî der, nexweşiyê dero
derkeve.
So that the smell inside the house, the smell goes out, the
illness goes out.
Rizqê jî eysî ro tê.
And sustenance comes with the morning light.
Dibê qapî rizqê timî vekirî. Kî sibê zû şefaqê rabû, qapî
xwe oçix bike.
They say the door of sustenance is always open. Whoever
wakes up early at dawn, should open their door wide.
Belê, raste.
Yes, that's true.
Ê qapiyê xwe sibê oçix dikim.
So, I open my door wide in the morning.
Û azaw dikim.
And I pray/call out.
No do.. te got difroşî, kû derê vê bena?
Now then... you said you sell, where (do you sell) this
string?
Cîranê mi dikirrin.
My neighbors buy it.
Tu naçî bazara?
You don't go to the market?
Na. Ez naçim bazara. Gund gidi bena...
No. I don't go to the market. The village comes for the
string...
El mal dat...
At home...
El mal dat. Gundî qesta tên dibin. Hecîkê me giya rom e...
çêl banê min çêkirî min dayî gund.
At home. Villagers come intentionally and take it. Our
Hacîka is mostly... I made forty strings and gave them to
the village.
Çêl ber... bes te ji gund ra?
Forty... only for the village?
Bes gund ra.
Only for the village.
Û ji dervey gund ra?
And for outside the village?
Ê da, ê g... bi... dibîsetin tê. Ê g... bîstin tên dikirin
dibin.
Well yes, those... who hear about it come. Those... twenty
come, buy, and take.
Wî nebîstin jî, il mal o min çewextî gerek bîne bibin.
Even those who don't hear, my home is there whenever they
need to come and take.
Ê dayê, tu terhetî vê kariyê dikî di vî gundî da?
So mother, are you comfortable doing this work in this
village?
Wele va gundî, noka ezî pênas dikim. Kesî kef min tînî
nemaye.
Well, these villagers, now I know them. There is no one left
who brings me joy (peers might be gone).
Ê kef min ezî mame.
Well, my joy, I remain.
Ê berê kesî dikir?
Did anyone do it before?
Ê wele nete.. eh.. jin.. jina pîrekê Ebû Omer dikir. Xwedê
rehma xwe lê ke.
Well, not you... uh... the wife... the old wife of Abu Omer
used to do it. May God have mercy on her.
Wê şuxulî wana dikir.
She used to do that work.
Yanî hebûn li gunda kar dikirin?
Meaning there were people in the village who did the work?
Ah, dikirin. Kar dikirin.
Ah, they did. They worked.
Bes ê wekî me jî, yanî.. te iştan bêjer derbûbîn.
But those like us too, mean... you look, we have become worn
out.
Aho tu binêrî, rind kes min nas nake.
Now if you look, no one knows me well anymore.
Tu karî dî jî dikî?
Do you do other work too?
Karî çû?
What work?
Yane karî, tu diçî...
Meaning work, do you go...
Adem qişkê zingû dikim.
I pickle the winter vegetables.
Karî min. Û em dambê kulfetî xwar-xwarê dikin. Em dar û ber
dikin.
My work. And we feed the family. We deal with the trees and
surroundings.
Em çêl û ça dikin, vî kurî ana mezin dikin.
We deal with cows and such, we raise these boys.
Gipehlok tiştek le were, em vî ro xwarê dikin.
If a scuffle or something happens, we feed them today.
Dayê, ez tiştekî ji te bipirsim. No, dayikê berê hemî karî
diket.
Mother, let me ask you something. Now, the mothers of the
past did all the work.
Keçkê noha, vê karan nakin. Çima?
The girls of today do not do these jobs. Why?
Dimsê şêrîn me çêdikir.
We used to make sweet molasses.
Me mîş çêdikirin.
We used to keep bees/make honey.
Me mastî hemû dî çêdikir, me penêr çêdikir. Hav tişta giş
bin destî mi ra derbas dibiye.
We made all the yogurt, we made cheese. All these things
passed through my hands.
Keçik ji vê karî dikin?
Do the girls do this work?
Keçikê min nakin.
My girls don't do it.
Ê keçikê gund?
And the village girls?
Keçikê gundî... ê no, no vî cîlî noko nakin.
The village girls... well now, no, this generation now
doesn't do it.
Ê çima?
And why?
Me ne alîmon, sîjê wane, sîwana.
We are not educated, it's their nature/style, their style.
Cîlî noka çû bajarê. Ê çû ket bajar. Alimî zet û zantera.
The generation now went to the city. They went and fell into
the city. They got used to oil and fake stuff.
Tiştî nebatî bixon.
To eat vegetable (industrial) products.
Yarê zeytê eslî jî bixwin, hingî vî zeytî nebatî.
I wish they would eat real oil/butter, instead of this
vegetable oil.
Noko lawkê min heye mezin, şîrî bizina qismis naxwe.
Now I have an older son, he won't eat goat's milk at all.
Wî me jî, rûnê eslî... ê rûbirû naxim sa, sorke bê rû kûk
min naxwariya.
But as for us, real butter... I don't put it face to face
(directly), if I don't fry it with butter, I haven't eaten
at all.
Ê rûn dirûmikî xwana, vî rûnî bati ezê çêkem. Û ez kê
bixwim.
The oil/butter of the churn, I will make this 'bati' oil.
And I will eat it.
Rûbirû xwedê. Du kîlo sê kîlo rûn min çêkiribî.
Before God. I had made two kilos, three kilos of butter.
Hava am kê rûbirû bixwin.
Like this, we will eat it directly.
Mala te ava be.
May your home be prosperous.
Ê te jî ava be. Ê lawo xwedê.
And yours be prosperous. Oh son of God.
Ser û çava.
Upon my head and eyes (You are welcome).
Zor spas dayê.
Thank you very much, mother.
Ehlen we sehlen.
Welcome.
Zor spas dayê.
Thank you very much, mother.
[Traditional Kurdish Folk Song Starts]
Kaniyê, boka Diyana min
Spring, my bride of Diyana
Jiyê Mêranî, şerê giran e
Life of Merani, is a heavy war
Eskerê stana, boka Diyana min
The soldiers of the land, my bride of Diyana
Jiyê Mêranî, şerê giran e
Life of Merani, is a heavy war
Kaniya zînet, walê avûne
The spring of ornaments, oh the water
Dê û bav neman, birê şetî ne
Mother and father remain no more, brothers represent the
river
Kaniya zînet, walê avûne
The spring of ornaments, oh the water
Dê û bav neman, birê şetî ne
Mother and father remain no more, brothers represent the
river
Xwe li ser û ku, walo bar sîme
Himself on the head and where, oh load of silver
Hemiye bit rûne, ji rûze bîme
All with butter, from daily existence I became
Xwe li ser û ku, walo bar sîme
Himself on the head and where, oh load of silver
Hemiye bit rûne
All with butter
Ji rûze bîme
From daily existence I became
Hat kaloz me bû, xeman xeyrîne
The old hat became ours, worries changed
Leşkerê romê, li xwedê diyar e
The soldiers of Rome (Turkey/Ottoman), are visible to God
Eskerê stana, boka Diyana min
The soldiers of the land, my bride of Diyana
Jiyê Mêranî...
Life of Merani...
Belê temaşevanên hêja.
Yes, dear viewers.
Em spasiya we dikin. Wîn hatin, neha we li ber ekranê bûn û
we li me temaşe dikir.
We thank you. You came, now you were in front of the screen
and you watched us.
Me bi hevra ev gunda nas kir. Gundê Hacîka.
Together we got to know this village. The village of Hacîka.
Hacîka jêr û Hacîka jor. Me bi hevra nas kir, me bi hevra
şopand.
Lower Hacîka and Upper Hacîka. We got to know it together,
we explored it together.
Emê xatira xwe ji we bixwazin. Vê heftê jî em li navçeya
Recû bûn.
We will bid you farewell. This week we were in the district
of Rajo.
Haya hefteyekî din, li gundekî din, em ê dîsa berê bin. Bi
xatira we.
Until another week, in another village, we will be together
again. Goodbye.
[End Credits Music Instrumental]
End of Video