şerrefûna ehbabîna, ehlen we sehlen...
Our loved ones have honored us, welcome...
şerrefûna ehbabîna...
Our loved ones have honored us...
Ehlen we sehlen bi ustaz şerîf, îzaeit Ronahî.
Welcome Mr. Sherif, Ronahi TV.
Şerretûna bi hudûrkum.
You honored us with your presence.
Allah ya'tîkum el-afiye, we yahmîkum inşallah we yiba'id el-
da'eş wel du'eş kile 'ankum.
May God give you health, protect you, God willing, and keep
ISIS and the likes of them away from you.
Allah yahmî ceîş el-Kurdî kile.
May God protect the entire Kurdish army.
Şukran.
Thank you.
Saet xweş.
You are welcome (Happy hour).
Belê temaşevanên hêja...
Yes, dear viewers...
Îro jî em li gundê Şurbê ne.
Today, we are in the village of Shurba.
Li vê mexist, xwarinek çêkin, ji ber ku ev gunda bi navê
xwarina şurbe tê nas kirin.
In this place, (we will) make a dish, because this village
is known by the name of the "soup" dish (Shurba means soup).
Îro jî dayika... ew xwarina amade kirine.
Today, the mother... has prepared that food.
Lê em spasiya dayikê dikin, dayik jî xelqê Lubnanê ye.
But we thank the mother, the mother is actually from
Lebanon.
Bûka vê gundî ye. Xweş e destpêkê da... bi Kurdî, bi
Erebî... bi zimanê Erebî ji me ra bêje.
She is a bride (daughter-in-law) of this village. It would
be good at the start... in Kurdish, in Arabic... tell us in
the Arabic language.
Spas ji bo te...
Thank you...
Ez nizanim... lazim biftil ya'nî.
I don't know... I need to switch (translate).
Tu dizanî?
You know (how to speak)?
Salik çend sal bûn?
It's been a year... how many years?
Sar lî şî... tlatîn hek.
It's been about... thirty, like that.
Tlatîn sene.
Thirty years.
Ya'nî kinna bi Hims, we jîna la hon, sar lî hella deh snîn
hon.
Meaning we were in Homs, and we came here, I've been here
for ten years now.
Minêm Lubnan?
Where from in Lebanon?
Min B'albek. Bi qe' B'albek.
From Baalbek. The Baalbek distinct.
Bi medîne?
From the city?
La, bil medîne, bil medîne. Lekan.
No (yes), in the city, in the city. Of course.
Wa sarlik xamsa we tlatîn sene hawn?
And you've been here for thirty-five years?
Eh hek... qadna bi Hims hunîk we jîna la hon.
Yes, like that... we stayed in Homs over there and came
here.
Ma t'allemtî Kurdî?
You didn't learn Kurdish?
Ya'nî şway... hindik.
Meaning a little... a tiny bit.
Hindik?
A tiny bit?
Eh... şway, hindik ya'nî mitil ma btqûlû.
Yes... a little, a tiny bit, as you say.
Belê, dayik jî xelqê Lubnanê ye.
Yes, the mother is from Lebanon.
Dibêje ev sî sal, sî û pênc sale bûka vê gundî ye.
She says for thirty, thirty-five years she has been a bride
of this village.
Lê hêna Kurdî rind fêr nebûye, ji bajarê B'albekê ye.
But she hasn't learned Kurdish well yet, she is from the
city of Baalbek.
Şû btqûlî la ehlik?
What do you say to your family?
Ehli... bib'atlon tehiye, we bselim 'ala kil el-cemî'.
My family... I send them greetings, and I say hello to
everyone.
We Allah ywafeqhon we yahmîhon, we Allah ya'tîkum el-afiye,
Allah ywafeqkum. Ahla we sahla fîkum.
And may God grant them success and protect them, and may God
give you health, God grant you success. Welcome to you all.
Malbata... silav dikî? Malbata xwa li B'albekê, Lubnanê
silav dike.
The family... you greet them? She greets her family in
Baalbek, Lebanon.
Nehna kaman mnsellim 'ala ehlik. Beyt Zi'ayter?
We also send greetings to your family. The Zeaiter family?
Beyt Zi'ayter, eh.
The Zeaiter family, yes.
Emê werin ba dayika... Dayê destpêkê destê we sax bin.
We will come to the mother (elder)... Mother, firstly,
health to your hands.
Destê we ji sax bin.
Health to your hands too.
Gundê Şurba ye.
It is Shurba village.
Erê.
Yes.
Wa jî xwarina şurba amade kiriye.
And you have prepared the soup dish.
Erê.
Yes.
Emê hinekî... destpêkê navê xwarinê we bi giştî bipirsim.
We will... first ask about the names of your foods in
general.
Yanî çi cure xwarin we çêdikirin? Xwarinê berê û yên niha.
Meaning what types of food did you used to make? The foods
of the past and those of now.
Piştî emê derbasî xwarina we niha bin.
After that we will move on to the food you have now.
Oo, na... berê çi qas xwarin cewa hebû... berê we çi xwarin
çêdikir?
Oh, no... in the past how much variety of food there was...
what food did we use to make before?
Me kufte çêdikirin, me sarmîsok dikirin, me hûrmane dikir...
We used to make meatball (kufte), we made garlic-yogurt
pasta (sarmîsok), we made pear stew (hûrmane)...
Me şurbe donî dikir... tişta... hunukî... şîvê zemanê berê,
sorma, dolma...
We made yogurt soup (shurbe doni)... things... simple
ones... dinners of the past times, sarma (stuffed leaves),
dolma (stuffed vegetables)...
Sarmîsok, kufte, şîşpere, kuftê bêz, ê qewurandî.
Sarmisok, kufte, shishbarak, meatless kufte, the fried
confit meat (qewurandî).
Me şîvê do nuh dikirin.
We used to make dinners like that back then.
Munasibet xwa, dawetê xwa çikê me... em diçûn miriya...
tişta me şîvê do nuh dikirin.
For our occasions, our weddings... when we went to
funerals... we made dinners/meals like that.
Em kî... merû kî çûk... çi bike?
What... what can a small person (humble person)... do?
Ê de tişta em nokû jî, awa şîvê me hevene. Kurd û Kurmancî
hevene.
Well, even now, those are our dinners/meals. Kurds and
Kurmanji people have these.
Zêde em nizanin.
We don't know much else.
Hev.
That's it.
Tu xelqê vê gundî, tu...
You are from this village, you...
Na ez xelqê vê gundî me, û dê û bavê min ji vê gundî ne, û
ez ji vê gundî me.
No (Yes), I am from this village, and my mother and father
are from this village, and I am from this village.
Tu ji malbata mala Şurba yî?
You are from the Shurba family?
Malbata mala Şurba me. Erê.
I am from the Shurba family. Yes.
De em tişta bipirsin.
Let us ask something.
Ehlen we sehlen bi hatina we. Ehlen we sehlen bi hatina we
be.
Welcome to your arrival. Welcome to your arrival.
Sax bî.
Be healthy.
De em dixwazin... em vê xwarinê nas bikin.
So we want... to get to know this food.
Êwa.
Yes.
Ne tenê dibêjin şurbe... nizanim, dewî heye, ê nîskê heye,
nizanim çi heye.
They don't just say soup... I don't know, there is yogurt
one, lentil one, I don't know what implies.
Ê vî kîjan şurbê çêdikin? Û çi dikeviyê?
So which soup do they make here? And what goes into it?
Wele em şurbê donî çêdikin.
Well, we make yogurt soup (Shurbe Doni).
Û nok dikevinê, û dan dikeviyê, û mast e.
And chickpeas go into it, and wheat goes into it, and
yogurt.
Û ji gundê bav û pîrê me da va şurba kirine.
And from the village of our forefathers and ancestors, they
have made this soup.
Û da hişta... gû mala şurba va şurba kirine.
And still... they say the Shurba family made this soup.
Û li xelqê waze... handin û bi xwe jî xwarin.
And they served it to the people... and ate it themselves
too.
Û ehlen we sehlen ji hatina we ra, û ji hevalat ra, û ser
serê me û ser çavê me hatin.
And welcome to your arrival, and to the friends, you are on
our heads and on our eyes (most welcome).
Sax bî. Na destpêkê we çi kirî?
Be healthy. So firstly what did you do?
Me dan... dan kiriye û nok kiriniyê.
We put wheat... put wheat and put chickpeas in it.
Û da wa, mast e.
And that's it, it's yogurt.
Mastê xweş, qa rohn dibe, kelkel... tiştê xwe kirine.
The yogurt is good, when it gets liquidy, boiled... you did
your thing.
Lê? Hewa, me wa nekiriye hişta. Şurbê donî haniye.
What? Yes, we haven't done that yet. We brought the yogurt
soup (Shurbe Doni).
Ê çi qas... tê xwestin heta li ser agir... çêbibe xwarin?
So how much... is required until it is on the fire... for
the food to be ready?
Ê da wekî... saetkê heye dixwaze.
Well like... it needs an hour.
Na temam e ava?
So this is finished?
Ee, le.
Yes, indeed.
Hema temam e.
Just finished.
Temam bû, xelas.
It finished, done.
Ka wîn e?
Where is it?
Her bibîne, sar bibe, kî çiçikî tî bibe.
Let look at it, let it cool down, let it get a bit thicker.
Na... ev xwarina çi ye? Ev... şurba?
Now... what is this food? This... soup?
Eva Lebeniye.
This is Labaniyeh (Yogurt stew).
Ev jî Lebeniye?
This is also Labaniyeh?
Û ava şurbe donî ye.
And that is Shurbe Doni (Wheat Yogurt Soup).
Ava?
That one?
Lebeniye, ya'nî berkufto.
Labaniyeh, meaning "Berkufto" (With meatballs).
Me'ne berkufta. Û ava jî şurbe donî ye.
Meaning with meatballs. And that one is Shurbe Doni.
Û awa jî sorma. Awa jî sormê qernebiyê û sormê çilû ne.
And that is Sarma (Stuffed leaves). That is cabbage sarma
and grape leaf sarma.
Û ji wê da... germê firîke.
And over there... Freekeh soup (roasted green wheat).
Û goşt li ser e, be'îv li ser in. Emê niha dînin, bi xêr,
emê li wê gotinê jî dankin.
And meat is on it, almonds are on it. We will serve it now,
with goodness, we will attend to that conversation too.
Nirca' la 'indik keman.
We return to you as well.
Tfezzal.
Go ahead.
Bes se'lek sual. Êş fî ferq beyn adet we teqalîd el-Ekrad,
we adet we teqalîd Lubnaniye?
Just asking you a question. What is the difference between
the customs and traditions of the Kurds, and the Lebanese
customs and traditions?
Mm...
Meselen bil a'ras?
For example in weddings?
Bil kil şî.
In everything.
Bi kil şî.
Bil a'ras întû adetkun... geyr adetna keman.
In weddings your custom... is different from our custom too.
Êş fî ferq?
What is the difference?
Êş fî ferq? Bta'mlû cehaz întû, bitfercû lal 'alem killa.
Nihna adetna mû hek.
What is the difference? You do a trousseau (show), you show
it to all the people. Our custom isn't like that.
Ma 'indkun cehaz?
You don't have a trousseau?
Ya'nî biya'mlû cehaz lal 'arûs...
Meaning they make a trousseau for the bride...
We adetkum bitcîbû el-mehbes lal 'arîs întû.
And your custom is that you bring the ring to the groom.
Nihna ma bincîbû. El-'arîs bicîb lal 'arûs we hay bas.
We don't bring it. The groom brings (it) to the bride and
that's it.
We 'al tebix?
And regarding cooking?
'Al tebix keman... biya'mlû ekil...
Regarding cooking also... they make food...
Yella, mesela...
Come on, for example...
Hakîna 'an şurba, hakîna...
We talked about soup, we talked...
Bita'mlû şorba, bita'mlû kufte, kil şî, şişberak... Şakriye.
You make soup, you make kofta, everything, shishbarak...
Shakriye.
We germî riz, we germî frîkî, kil... nefs el-ade.
And rice soup, and freekeh soup, all... the same custom.
Şû btqûlû la el-germe? Întû şû btqûlû?
What do you call "germe" (soup/stew)? What do you call it?
Kay? Burgul 'a şa'rîye. Burgul... ya'nî frîket... keman
burgul ya'nî.
How? Bulgur with vermicelli. Bulgur... meaning freekeh...
also bulgur I mean.
Ya'nî ma fî ferq beyn... ktîr beyn hon we beyn hon?
Meaning there isn't a difference between... much between
here and there?
Fî fî, haseb el-hakî keman.
There is, there is, depending on the speech (dialect) too.
Ma bnihkî 'al lehce.
We aren't talking about the dialect.
Bnihkî 'al tebix.
Yes.
We are talking about the cooking.
'Al tebix keman nefso, 'am qillak.
About cooking it's also the same, I'm telling you.
Bes innû fî...
But that there are...
Fî întû btitbuxû, qiltillak... Boranîye.
There are (things) you cook, I told you... Borani.
Nihna Boranîye ma bna'mil. Hay t'allemta 'indkun ya'nî.
We don't make Borani. That, I learned at your place.
Fî tebxa tanîye bes...
There is another dish but...
Danik?
Ê, hay el-Danik keman ma mna'rifa.
Yes, that "Danik", we also don't know it.
Hay el-done şuxl Efrîniye?
This "Done" is Afrini work?
Sarma, dolma, kil hay bna'mila. Hay şuxl ehl... Efrîn ya'nî.
Sarma, dolma, all this we make. This is the work of the
people of... Afrin I mean.
Şlon leqeytî hûn Efrîn?
How did you find it here, Afrin?
El... şû ismo...
The... what is its name...
Walla, mnîha. Hilwe.
Honestly, good. Beautiful.
'Acebetnî, Allah yahmîkum.
I liked it, may God protect you.
We Allah ya'tîkum el-afiye.
And may God give you health.
We habeytkum ktîr enî ya'nî.
And I loved you all a lot, truly.
Şukran.
Thank you.
Allah yqawîkum, we yahmîkum inşallah.
May God strengthen you, and protect you, God willing.
Belê.
Yes.
Me xwest hinekî ji dayikê bipirsin, ser urf û adetên Efrînê
û Lubnanê.
We wanted to ask the mother a little about the customs and
traditions of Afrin and Lebanon.
Bi rastî jî, ema behsê kir jî, tu ferq cuda bûn pir tûne ye.
Truly, although she discussed it, there isn't much
difference.
Ema navên xwarina, gotin, dibêje ev xwarina nek cem me tune,
Danik e.
But the names of the foods, she said, she says "this food
doesn't exist at our place, Danik."
Ev kî şu, kî hemen... l'ekil tanîye?
This one... what... is there another food?
L-Boranîye... boranîye.
The Borani... Borani.
Dibêje ev du xwarina li ba me tûne ne, ew Danik e.
She says these two foods don't exist at our place, that
Danik.
Ji ber ku ev jî xwarinek Efrînî, taybetmendiya Efrînê ye.
Because this is an Afrini food, a specialty of Afrin.
Û dibêje ew li Lubnanê tûne ye.
And she says that doesn't exist in Lebanon.
Yanî pir ferq cuda bûn tûne ye, dibêje behsê dike.
Meaning there isn't much difference, she says, discussing
it.
Ji navbera Efrînê û Lubnanê va.
Between Afrin and Lebanon here.
Dayê em dîsa vegerin cem te.
Mother, let's return to you again.
Niha xwarina we li ser agir e.
Now your food is on the fire.
Mm.
Niha kîjan xwarin xweş e? Li ser agir xweş e, li ser gazê
xweş e?
Now which food is good? Is it good on fire, is it good on
gas?
Na, ser agir xweş e.
No, on fire is good.
Yanî tama wê... cudabûn heye?
Meaning its taste... is there a difference?
Ê... tama wê... tikanê... kel ket, agirê xwe mîna bikşîne,
yavaş bikele... erê, xwarina ser agir xweş e.
Yes... its taste... the pot... when it boils, if it draws
its fire slowly, boils slowly... yes, food on fire is good.
Ê da nokû jî tişta ser gaza... xureat nokin, ser gaza.
Well now, things are on gas... they make it quickly
(rushed), on gas.
Mala wa ava be, Xwedê kêmasiya wa nede.
May your home be prosperous, may God not give you lack.
O te jî ava be. Û saeta we xweş. Aqûbet ser keftina mezin
be.
And may you be prosperous too. And good health/times to you.
May the outcome be great success.
Û em pir xweş kefin jiyana we ra.
And we are very happy with your life/living.
Sax bin. Sax bin.
Be healthy. Be healthy.
[Music]